<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2001-01-23</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — January 23, 2001</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2001-01-23</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2001-01-23</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2001-01-25</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — January 23, 2001

## Introduction


## Hawaii and Puerto Rico
Little or no precipitation fell on Hawaii last week, with even the climatologically-wettest areas on the Big Island reporting a few tenths of an inch at most. Recent dryness, in addition to the multi-year drought from with much of the state has yet to fully recover, led to the introduction of D1(A,F) for southern Kauai and western sections of Maui. Other areas remained unchanged.
Scattered light to moderate rains left the D0 areas of Puerto Rico unchanged, though totals of 1 or 2 inches were noted at a few sites on the northern and eastern fringes of the eastern D0 region.

## The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region
A large area from the northern half of the Ohio Valley westward through the central and northern High Plains received little or no precipitation for the past 7 days. As a result, most of last weeks D0 and D0(W) areas remained unchanged, and some slight expansion of D1 and D2 occurred near the Kansas/Nebraska border.
Last weeks dryness, combined with substandard precipitation for at least the last 30 days, led to the introduction of D0 into a broad area from southern Iowa southward through most of Missouri and southeastern Kansas, and southeastward across the middle Mississippi and lower Ohio Valleys. Most of these areas are at least 1 inch below normal for the last 3 months, with 4- to 7-inch deficits reported in parts of central and southeastern Missouri. 30-day precipitation totaled 2 to 4 inches below normal throughout the central and lower Ohio Valley, prompting the introduction of D0 in central and northern Kentucky despite 0.2 to 1.0 inch of precipitation last week.

## The South
Unseasonably heavy precipitation fell on much of the region, resulting in little dryness elimination but substantial areas of decreased drought severity. The heaviest precipitation (over 5 inches) soaked central and northeastern Mississippi and part of south-central Louisiana while 2 to 5 inches were widespread from eastern Texas eastward through most of Alabama and northeastward into southern West Virginia. This led to the elimination of dryness and drought in all but the southeastern and northeastern fringes of the lower Mississippi Valley, and a reduction to D0(W) in adjacent former D1(W) areas to the east.
Farther north, generally 1 to 3 inches of precipitation eliminated D3(W) conditions that had affected western North Carolina and nearby areas. However, most of the D0(W) to D2(W) areas did not demonstrate enough improvement to warrant classification decreases.
In addition, 1 to 3 inches of precipitation induced a 1 step reduction to D0(W) or D1(W) for central and southern Alabama, and the western Florida Panhandle.
In Florida, a week of light to locally moderate rains kept most dryness and drought regions unchanged. Only a slight expansion of D1 into southwestern Florida and a small northward expansion of D2 into the southeastern Florida Panhandle were identified.
The only other area of deterioration noted was in the Tennessee Valley and adjacent sections of the Mississippi Valley, where most locations recorded less than 1 inch of precipitation. For the last 90 days, precipitation anomalies of -4 to -7 inches are common, prompting a northward expansion of D1 and D2 toward the Ohio/Mississippi confluence.

## The West
Parts of the Pacific Northwest and northern Intermountain West recorded up to an inch of precipitation in the last 7 days, but most areas received less.
On January 23, snowpack water content was below 80% of normal from the central Rockies and the Sierra Nevada northward, and less than half of normal in northwestern Montana, the Idaho Panhandle, northwestern and northeastern Washington, southern Oregon, and the Sierra Nevada. In much of the Pacific Northwest, water-year precipitation (since October 1), expressed as a percent of normal, is below corresponding snowpack water content percentages. Many areas have had only about half their normal to date. This is climatologically the wettest time of the year for the West Coast and the higher elevations of the western United States, so by late January precipitation and snowpack water content deficits cause increasingly significant concern with each passing day about the region's water supplies for the ensuing spring-autumn period. The unprecedented California power crisis, and concerns about the Pacific Northwest's power supplies, have rapidly risen to prominence as a consequence of the extended period of dry weather.
Given these considerations, D0(W) has been expanded to cover much of Oregon, all of Washington, most of Idaho, southwestern Montana, parts of Nevada, northern California, the Sierra Nevada, and a large part of Wyoming.

## The Western Mid-Atlantic
Between 0.6 and 2.0 inches of precipitation fell on West Virginia. This was sufficient to eliminate D1(W) conditions in the southern part of the state, but not enough to change the D0(W) areas.
Farther north, 0.2 to 0.6 inch of precipitation fell on central and western Pennsylvania and southwestern New York. These areas recorded totals among the lowest 5% of the historical distribution for the last 30 days, and 90-day anomalies of -4 to -7 inches have developed in parts of the region. Furthermore, streamflows were in the lowest 25th percentile at most gauges on January 22, and a few were below the 10th percentile threshold, while modeled soil moisture dropped below the 20th percentile threshold in most areas. All these factors led to the introduction of D0 into western and central Pennsylvania, and southwestern New York.

## Forecast
Anticipated occurrences which may impact current areas of dryness and drought over the next 10 days include: (1) Fairly extensive light to moderate precipitation across central and northern California and the Intermountain West January 23 - 24; (2) Additional light to moderate precipitation in northwestern California and the southern Sierra Nevada January 24 - 29; (3) Moderate to locally heavy precipitation in parts of the southern half of the Rockies January 24 - 29; (4) Moderate to locally heavy precipitation in the southern half of the Plains (except southern Texas) January 24 - 29; (5) Enhanced likelihood of a return to subnormal precipitation in most of the southern Rockies, Nevada, and California January 30 - February 3; (6) A dry January 24 - 29 followed by an increased probability of surplus precipitation in much of the South, the Ohio Valley, the Great Lakes, the Appalachians, and the middle and northern Atlantic states January 30 - February 3, especially in the interior central Gulf Coast region and the northern half of the Atlantic Seaboard; and (7) Suppressed precipitation throughout the next 10 days in much of drought-stricken Florida.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.7864828</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.5382825</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.9309052</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0035991</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:52:49-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 