<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2014-09-02</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Heim</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Simeral</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Western Regional Climate Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — September 02, 2014</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2014-09-02</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2014-09-02</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2014-09-04</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — September 02, 2014

## Introduction
This U.S. Drought Monitor week saw heavy showers and thunderstorms across the Central Plains and portions of the Upper Midwest as well as along the central and western Gulf Coast. Rainfall accumulations in the Central Plains and Upper Midwest were heaviest across Iowa, Kansas, and Nebraska with some areas receiving in excess of six inches. The combination of above-average summer rainfall accumulations in many areas and short-term gains (seven-day accumulations) led to improvements in drought-affected areas of Kansas and Nebraska. Along the central and western Gulf Coast, locally heavy rainfall fell across coastal areas of Louisiana and Texas with some areas receiving five-to-ten inches helping to improve drought conditions in southeastern Texas. Meanwhile, much of the Northeast, Mid-Atlantic, and Southeast remained relatively dry with the exception of some isolated showers and thunderstorms across portions of Florida and Georgia. Temperatures were well above average for the week across Texas, the Southern Plains, Midwest, and portions of the Mid-Atlantic and New England. Out West, light rainfall accumulations were observed in the Central Rockies, New Mexico, and Wyoming. In the Southwest, monsoonal rains began to taper off across the region. West of the Continental Divide, dry conditions dominated.

## Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico
On this week’s map, conditions in these regions remained status quo. In Alaska, temperatures were below normal across the Interior while the rest of the state hovered near normal. According to the NWS in Juneau, record wet summer conditions (June-August) were reported in southeastern Alaska at several stations in Juneau and Haines. In the Hawaiian Islands, average temperatures were slightly below normal except for the northern part of the Big Island where temperatures were three-to-five degrees (F) above normal.

## Mid-Atlantic
The Mid-Atlantic remained drought free on this week’s map. Short-term precipitation deficits led to the introduction of areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) in Delmarva Peninsula and east-central Virginia. Overall, conditions were dry across the region during the past week with well above average temperatures early in the week. According to the NWS, record high temperatures were reported earlier this week at Wallops Islands, Virginia (94° F) and New Bern, North Carolina (96° F).

## Midwest
Significant rainfall accumulations (ranging from three-to-seven inches) were observed across portions of Iowa, central Illinois, southern Minnesota, and northwestern Wisconsin. This week’s rains led to one-category improvements in areas of Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormally Dry (D0) in southwestern and central Missouri as well as reductions in areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) in northeastern Iowa, northwestern Illinois, northern Wisconsin, and southeastern Michigan. According to the NWS in Sioux Falls, Iowa, rainfall records were broken at the Sioux Falls Airport for the summer months (30.38 inches from June through August; breaking the previous record of 20.13 inches set in 2010) as well as for the month of August (10.12 inches). Temperatures across the region were above normal during the past week except for extreme northern portions of the Midwest.

## The Northeast
The Northeast remained drought-free, and no changes were made on the map this week. Across the region, dry conditions generally prevailed except for some isolated, light shower activity (one-to-two inches). Despite a dry week, a monthly total rainfall record (14.07 inches) for August was broken at Islip Macarthur Airport on Long Island, according to the NWS. Temperatures were one-to-four degrees (F) above normal across the region for the week.

## The Plains
Drought conditions continued to improve across portions of Kansas and Nebraska this week as heavy rains increased soil moisture conditions and streamflows. Rainfall amounts were highest across eastern Kansas and southeastern Nebraska where accumulations ranged from three-to-six inches leading to one-category improvements in areas of Severe Drought (D2) and Moderate Drought (D1). In southwestern Nebraska and southeastern South Dakota, summer rains have brought conditions back to normal. In west-central Oklahoma, above-average temperatures and short-term precipitation deficits led to expansion in areas of Extreme Drought (D3) and Severe Drought (D2) while rainfall this week helped to slightly improve areas of Extreme Drought (D3) and Severe Drought (D2) in the Panhandle. During the past week, temperatures were above normal in the Southern Plains while Northern Plains temperatures were below normal.

## The South
During the past week, locally heavy precipitation (three-to-eight inches) fell across southern Louisiana, while Mississippi and Alabama received lower accumulations ranging from one-to-three inches in Mississippi and one-to-two in northern Alabama. Along parts of the western Gulf Coast of Texas, significant rainfall accumulations (four-to-ten inches) helped to improve drought conditions in areas of Extreme Drought (D3), Severe Drought (D2), and Moderate Drought (D1). In south-central Texas, on August 12, 2014, the Edwards Aquifer Authority (serving nearly 2 million south-central residents) declared Stage 4 pumping reductions for users in the San Antonio Pool as groundwater levels dropped below threshold levels. Across most of Texas, temperatures were well above average especially in the Big Bend region of southwestern Texas where temperatures were six-to-ten degrees (F) above normal. Record daily high temperatures were set at Amarillo (104° F), Borger (106°), and El Paso (100° F), according to the NWS. In Lake Charles, Louisiana, a summer rainfall record was broken with 36.90 inches reported by the NWS in Lake Charles.

## The Southeast
The Southeast received some isolated shower activity during the past week with the heaviest rainfall accumulations (one-to-three inches) observed across parts of Florida while the rest of the region remained generally dry. A continued hot and dry pattern across the region led to further deterioration in conditions across southern and eastern portions of Georgia as well as South Carolina and the Florida Panhandle. In southern Georgia, short-term precipitation deficits (30–90 days) continued to mount leading to expansion of areas of Severe Drought (D2) and Moderate Drought (D1). In the Florida Panhandle and South Carolina, low streamflows and short-term precipitation deficits led to expansion of areas of Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormally Dry (D0). In west-central Florida this week, the NWS in Tampa Bay reported record daily high temperatures at Sarasota-Bradenton (96° F) and Ft. Meyers (96° F).

## The West
During the past week, conditions were generally dry across most of the West with the exception of some light, isolated shower activity (&amp;lt;2 inches) in portions of Arizona, New Mexico, Colorado, Wyoming, and Montana. The Far West, Great Basin, and Intermountain West were dry, however. Improvements were made on the map in parts of the eastern Great Basin including one-category improvements in areas of Severe Drought (D2) in northwestern and west-central Utah, as well as northeastern Nevada where springtime and monsoon-season rains helped improve rangeland conditions, soil moisture, and streamflows. In the mountains of northeastern Nevada and south-central Idaho, snowpacks were below normal for the Water Year (since October 1st); but total precipitation amounts at Natural Resource Conservation Service (NRCS) SNOTEL sites (observational stations that measure snow water content, snow depth, accumulated precipitation, soil moisture, and air temperature) in these areas show that Water-Year-To-Date accumulated precipitation is near normal or normal. In this region, lingering hydrologic impacts persist as reservoirs remain well below normal. In northwestern, west central, and southwestern Utah, monsoon rains improved soil moisture and rangeland conditions according to the August 25, 2014, U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) Utah Crop Progress and Conditions Report. In northeastern Utah, northwestern Colorado, and southwestern Wyoming, summer rains helped to improve conditions leading to one-category improvements in areas of Extreme Drought (D2) and Severe Drought (D1). During the past week, temperatures were above normal in the Far West and below normal across the eastern half of the West.

## Forecast
The NWS WPC 7-Day Quantitative Precipitation Forecast (QPF) calls for moderate-to-heavy rainfall accumulations (two-to-five inches) across the Desert Southwest, Southern Rockies, Central Plains, Upper Midwest, Southeast, and lower Mid-Atlantic regions. Late in the period, a plume of subtropical moisture is forecasted to move into the Southwest bringing potentially heavy rains. In the Far West, dry conditions are forecasted to persist across California, the Great Basin, and most of the Pacific Northwest. The 6–10 day outlooks call for a high probability of above-normal temperatures across the Far West, Southern Plains, South, Southeast, and Mid-Atlantic while below-normal temperatures are forecasted across the Central Rockies, Northern Plains, Upper Midwest, and New England. Temperatures across much of Alaska, including western, south-central, and southeastern regions are forecasted to be above normal. Regarding precipitation across the conterminous U.S., a high probability of above-normal precipitation is expect across the Southwest and the eastern half of the U.S. Below-normal precipitation is expected across the Pacific Northwest and western Alaska while precipitation in southeastern Alaska and the eastern half of Interior Alaska is forecasted to be above normal for the period.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-158.224206008432</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.6909313727242</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.9284123273676</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0010753952739</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:36:54-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 