<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2000-08-22</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Staff </gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — August 22, 2000</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2000-08-22</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2000-08-22</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2000-08-24</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — August 22, 2000

## Introduction


## Hawaii, and Puerto Rico
Locally heavy showers at windward and higher-elevation sites fell during August 20-21, enhanced by moisture and energy from the remnants of Hurricane Hector. Between 3 and 7 inches of rain drenched eastern portions of Oahu and the Big Island, with slightly lesser amounts (1 to 3 inches) observed on windward sides of Kauai, Maui, and Molokai. Although the drought-affected leeward side of the islands received much less rain (less than an inch), a few leeward locations measured significant totals, namely south-central Oahu (2-4 inches) and the southern Big Island (2 inches), slightly reducing D1 drought in those two areas.
In Puerto Rico, generally light and scattered showers prevailed across the island through 12Z August 22. The greatest totals (1 to 2 inches) fell on northwestern areas, with slightly lower amounts (0.5 to 1.5 inch) measured across east-central and northeastern sections. It remained relatively dry (less than 0.5 inches) across central parts of the island. With Hurricane Debby tracking just north of the island, heavy rains from feeder bands (up to 15 inches in orographically-favored sites) fell across Puerto Rico during late Tuesday and Wednesday.

## The Great Lakes Region:
Abnormal dryness (D0) expanded in northern lower Michigan and the eastern Upper Peninsula of Michigan, and first-stage drought (D1) appeared in the latter area due to another rainless week, near-record low streamflows, subnormal July 1-August 22 rain (e.g. Sault Ste. Marie: 1.91", 37% of normal; Alpena: 2.60", 49% of normal; and Marquette: 4.65", 87% of normal), and increasingly dry soil moisture indices. Impacts, however, have been minimal as below normal summer temperatures have kept evaporative demands low.

## The Northern and Central Plains
Showers and thunderstorms developed across the central Rockies and moved eastward, dropping light to moderate rains on parts of the central Great Plains and western Corn Belt. After a cold front moved southeastward across the northern Plains and western Corn Belt, August 15-21 temperatures averaged 2F to 6F below normal. With 1 to 3 inches of rain in central and eastern Colorado, the fifth successive week of light to moderate rain, abnormal dryness was partially alleviated in portions of the state. Farther east, 1 to 5 inches of rain in southeastern Nebraska, northwestern Missouri, and northern Iowa, plus moderating temperatures, eased dryness in southeastern Nebraska, northwestern Missouri, and parts of western Iowa. Farther north, however, cold front passages failed to bring any appreciable rains to Montana, although cooler weather aided wildfires. Still, the NIFC reported that 31 large wildfires were active across the state through August 21, affecting over 646,000 acres.

## The South
A second consecutive week of above normal temperatures (highs near 100F, and departures between +2F and +5F) and little or no rainfall was observed in most of the Southeast, intensifying drought conditions. The heat and lack of rain decreased topsoil moisture in the Southeast, with 93% of Alabama, 76% of Georgia, 65% of Tennessee, and 45% of South Carolina rated short or very short by NASS, while record or near-record low streamflow levels for USGS reporting sites slightly increased in the same states. The exceptions were along the South Carolina and Georgia coasts, in northern Georgia, and parts of Florida. With 1 to 3 inches of rain and temperatures close to normal, dryness slightly diminished along coastal South Carolina and Georgia, and in northeastern and southeastern Florida. Farther west, hot, dry, and windy weather in the Delta and southern Plains (temperatures averaged more than 4F above normal, readings routinely soared into the triple-digits, winds typically gusted 20-30 mph in the Plains) expanded dryness (D0) or intensified existing drought (D1-D4). Rapid moisture degradations were common; for example, 84% of the Mississippi streamflow levels for reporting sites were in the lower tenth percentile on August 22, an increase from 63% a week ago; in Oklahoma, 85% of the topsoil moisture was rated short or very short, compared to 68% last week; and Dallas, TX last measured rain on June 30 (0.03"). Southern wildfires, though not even close to the severity of ones in the West, have recently developed in Texas and Oklahoma as fire indices are rated very high to extreme, according to NIFC.

## The West
Some slight improvement occurred in southern sections as continued monsoonal showers dampened eastern parts of Arizona and Utah, most of New Mexico and Colorado, and south of the Las Vegas, NV area. Between 1.5 and 2.5 inches of rain fell on scattered locations in east-central Arizona, northern New Mexico, and southwestern Colorado. As a result, a further reduction in dryness and drought was made in these areas. Monsoonal showers also reached most of Utah this week, but amounts were generally light (0.1 to 0.5 inches) and temperatures still averaged above normal, thus keeping D1(A,F) drought intact. Hydrological drought was added to western Arizona and southeastern California as long-term warmth and dryness (e.g. dry 12 and 24-month SPIs) have begun impacting the regions ground water supplies. Farther north, another dry week in Nevada, Oregon, and Idaho, plus very dry (&amp;lt;5%) 10-, 100-, and even 1000-hour fuel moisture contents, expanded first-stage drought (D1(A,F)) in some areas, but its increase was kept to a minimum as much cooler air pushed into the Northwest (departures between -2F and -7F). 27 and 6 large wildfires blazed across Idaho and Nevada through Monday, charring nearly 600,000 and 73,000 acres, respectively.

## Forecast
Weather events that may influence some of the Nations dry or drought areas are: 1) Tropical Storm Debby (if it survives), is expected to move into the Gulf of Mexico by this weekend, and then the track is uncertain; 2) A persistent upper-air pattern over the lower 48 states (similar to a week ago) should feature troughing over the Northwest and Northeast, and ridging over the central U.S., producing: 3) More scattered showers and thunderstorms across the eastern portions of the Southeast and Tennessee Valley in association with a stalled cold front; 4) High pressure over the central Rockies/Plains should continue through Tuesday, keeping most of the West, Rockies, and Plains dry and warm and fire danger high, although some monsoonal moisture should generate widely-scattered showers along the western edge of the ridge (e.g. Arizona northeastward); 5) A weak frontal system dropping southeastward from Canada may trigger scattered light thundershowers to the north-central Plains, western Corn Belt, and Great Lakes region; 6) The ridge should also keep the southern Plains and Delta warm and mostly dry again, although some scattered showers may occur along the western Gulf Coast.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.7600917</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.971253</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.001624</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T00:53:23-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 