<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-05-24</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brad Rippey</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>U.S. Department of Agriculture</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — May 24, 2005</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-05-24</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-05-24</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-05-26</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — May 24, 2005

## Introduction


## Alaska
Although no abnormal dryness was introduced, short-term precipitation deficits continued to gradually mount in parts of southern Alaska. From April 1 - May 24, precipitation totaled 0.38 inch (38 percent of normal) in Anchorage and 7.68 inches (41 percent) in Yakutat. Juneau netted only 0.45 inch (17 percent of normal) during the first 24 days of May, threatening its May 2004 record-low total of 0.84 inch.

## Hawaii
Warm, mostly dry weather persisted in Hawaii, where daily average temperatures were above normal on each of the months first 24 days in locations such as Lihue, Kauai, and Hilo, on the Big Island. May 1-24 temperatures averaged 2.6 degrees F above normal in Lihue and Hilo, and 4.3 degrees F above normal in Honolulu, Oahu. In a 20-day period from May 4-23, Honolulu set or tied twelve daily-record highs and reached the 90-degree mark five times. In addition, April 1 - May 24 rainfall totaled just 0.51 inch (22 percent of normal) in Kahului, Maui; 0.84 inch (48 percent) in Honolulu; and 9.04 inches (47 percent) in Hilo. Due to concerns about wildfire activity and water supplies for those reliant upon rain-fed catchment systems, moderate drought (D1) was expanded across all of the Big Island.

## Puerto Rico
Rain intensified across Puerto Rico in mid-May, eliminating vestiges of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) along the south coast. For the week ending May 20, south coast totals ranged from 6.42 to 8.64 inches. Farther north, May 1-24 rainfall in San Juan reached 7.82 inches (187 percent of normal), following an April-record total of 15.00 inches (404 percent).

## The Northeast
As recently as early April, major flooding struck parts of the Northeast. On the Pennsylvania-New Jersey border, early-April water levels at several gauging locations along the Delaware River surpassed those observed following the September 2004 passage of former Hurricane Ivan and were the highest since the August 1955 record flooding associated with Hurricanes Connie and Diane. Farther west, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, experienced its wettest year on record in 2004, with an annual total of 57.43 inches (152 percent of normal). More recently, however, streamflows have fallen sharply in parts of the Northeast, especially across Pennsylvania and New York. In addition, topsoil moisture on May 22 was rated 36 percent very short to short in Pennsylvania and 35 percent in New York, according to USDA. Through May 24, month-to-date rainfall totals in or near a gradually expanding area of abnormal dryness (D0) included 0.47 inch (17 percent of normal) in Scranton, Pennsylvania, and 0.45 inch (17 percent) in Syracuse, New York.

## The Plains and Midwest
A new area of abnormal agricultural dryness (D0) was introduced on the central High Plains. Rainfall totaled just 0.04 inch in Dodge City, Kansas, from May 1-23, although 0.68 inch fell on May 24. By May 22, winter wheat was rated 20 percent very poor to poor in Kansas, Oklahoma, and Texas, while statewide topsoil moisture was rated 65 percent very short to short in Oklahoma and 42 percent in Kansas. Abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) continued to expand in areas from the southern Plains northeastward into the Great Lakes region, while hot, mostly dry weather maintained severe drought (D2) in parts of southern Oklahoma and northern Texas. For many locations, May 21 was the hottest of several stifling days on the central and southern Plains, where highs soared to 102 degrees F in Russell, Kansas, and 101 degrees F in Cherokee, Oklahoma.
Selected season-to-date precipitation totals for March 1 - May 24 included 2.04 inches (20 percent of normal) in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma; 3.90 inches (35 percent) in Tyler, Texas; 4.10 inches (42 percent) in Peoria, Illinois; 4.20 inches (49 percent) in Grand Rapids, Michigan; 4.25 inches (46 percent) in South Bend, Indiana; and 4.31 inches (41 percent) in St. Louis, Missouri. Farther north and west, heavy rain resulted in a reconfiguration of the dryness/drought situation in parts of the Dakotas. Although there were continuing hydrological effects from dryness and drought in North Dakota, May 1-24 totals such as 4.21 inches (260 percent of normal) in Jamestown and 4.18 inches (253 percent) in Dickinson largely eliminated agricultural concerns. Some dryness (D0) lingered farther south, however, especially in northeastern South Dakota. March 1 - May 24 precipitation in eastern South Dakota totaled 2.44 inches (47 percent of normal) in Aberdeen and 3.12 inches (50 percent) in Huron.

## The South
A small pocket of abnormal dryness (D0) lingered in the southern Mid-Atlantic piedmont, where May 1-24 rainfall totaled just 1.08 inches in Fayetteville, North Carolina. Farther west, however, much more serious short-term dryness expanded eastward from the lower Mississippi Valley, reaching as far east as western Tennessee. On May 22, Louisiana reported topsoil moisture 84 percent very short to short, along with 78 percent in Arkansas and 56 percent in Mississippi. In Louisiana, May 1-24 rainfall totals were as low as 0.14 inch (3 percent of normal) in Alexandria and 0.18 inch (4 percent) in Lafayette. Louisiana crop conditions continued to decline sharply and by May 22 USDA rated the following amounts very poor to poor: range/pastureland, 44 percent; soybeans, 32 percent; and corn, 26 percent. Farther north, May 1-24 rainfall amounts of 0.42 inch in Jackson, Tennessee, 0.28 inch in Tupelo, Mississippi, and 0.22 inch in Jonesboro, Arkansas, were all less than 10 percent of normal and a threat to record-low May totals (Jackson: 0.49 inch in 1951; Tupelo: 0.85 inch in 1941; and Jonesboro: 0.45 inch in 1911). In parts of the South, dryness was also becoming more apparent at longer time scales, with March 1 - May 24 Louisiana totals as low as 3.11 inches (23 percent of normal) in Lafayette and 4.72 inches (40 percent) in Lake Charles. Meanwhile, year-to-date rainfall deficits continued to mount in much of the lower Rio Grande Valley, where January 1 - May 24 totals included 2.41 inches (37 percent of normal) in McAllen and 2.43 inches (33 percent) in Brownsville. Heat aggravated the effects of dryness throughout the region, with record warmth reaching the South by May 20. Temperatures approached or reached monthly record-high levels in several locations, including New Iberia, Louisiana, where maxima of 98 degrees F on May 21 and 22 tied its record established on May 31, 1951.

## The West
Hot, dry weather expanded across much of the West, bringing a long-awaited period of rapidly melting snow. By May 24, preliminary information from USGS indicated that Western river gauges were at their highest levels on record for the date in dozens of locations, including the Humboldt River at Battle Mountain and Elko, Nevada; the Sacramento River at Colusa, Grimes, and Verona, California; the Virgin River at Virgin, Utah; the Sevier River at Hatch, Utah; the Verde River at Paulden, Arizona; the Animas River at Cedar Hill and Farmington, New Mexico; and the San Juan River at Pagosa Springs and Carracas, Colorado. In northeastern Nevada, a lingering ribbon of abnormal dryness (D0) was removed due to additional heavy precipitation and the response of reservoirs to rapidly melting snow. Hundreds of daily-record high temperatures were set or tied across the Southwest starting May 19. In Colorado, Grand Junction notched five consecutive daily-record highs (94, 92, 94, 95, and 94 degrees F) from May 20-24. On May 22, Tucson, Arizona, posted a high of 109 degrees F, just 2 degrees shy of its monthly record established on May 29, 1910. Meanwhile in the Northwest, some ranges and pastures continued to reflect the effects of long-term drought, despite a wet spring. On May 22, USDA rated 24 percent of Wyomings and 23 percent of Washingtons range and pastureland in very poor to poor condition.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (May 26 - 30), below-normal temperatures are expected in most areas east of the Rockies. Cool weather will be especially beneficial in areas of the Plains and South affected by the recent heat wave. In addition, widespread showers and thunderstorms are forecast to develop across the southern Rockies and southern High Plains on May 26-27, followed by an eastward expansion of much-needed rain across the South during the weekend and early next week. Only scattered showers are expected, however, across the Midwest and the Northeast. Meanwhile in the West, hot, mostly dry conditions will continue for a few more days before heat gradually subsides by early next week. The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for May 31 - June 4 calls for near- to below normal temperatures nationwide. Cool weather is most likely across the Great Basin, the Midwest, and the East. Meanwhile, wetter-than-normal conditions are expected in a broad area stretching from the Northwest into the Southeast, including parts of the Plains. Below-normal precipitation is forecast in the middle and lower Rio Grande Valley, along with much of the Midwest and Northeast.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-77.3094955</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.3784715</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:49:34-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 