<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-07-22</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brad Rippey</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>U.S. Department of Agriculture</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — July 22, 2008</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-07-22</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-07-22</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-07-24</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — July 22, 2008

## Introduction


## Hawaii
Drought persisted in more than two-thirds of Hawaii, despite a few showers.  Through July 22, year-to-date rainfall totals stood at just 2.86 inches (30% of normal) in Honolulu, Oahu; 2.98 inches (26%) in Kahului, Maui; and 8.22 inches (40%) in Lihue, Kauai.  On the Big Island, Hilo's January 1 - July 22 rainfall totaled 74.66 inches (109% of normal), although more than half (39.08 inches) of that amount fell during the first half of February.  According to the latest agricultural report from USDA, drought on parts of the Big Island has dried up stock water ponds normally supplied by runoff.  Despite some beneficial showers on Maui, all previously issued water conservation notices, both voluntary and mandatory, remained in effect.  On Oahu, the mandatory 30% reduction in water use remained in effect for the Waimanalo irrigation system users.

## Puerto Rico
On time scales ranging from 1 to 6 months, a similar pattern of below-normal rainfall has prevailed across the southern and eastern portions of the island.  Moderate drought (D1) persisted and expanded slightly across interior eastern southeastern Puerto Rico, where only light rain fell during the past week.

## The Central and Southern Plains
Dolly made landfall on South Padre Island, Texas, during the early afternoon of July 23 as a low-end Category 2 hurricane with maximum sustained winds near 100 m.p.h.  Dolly was the strongest hurricane to strike the U.S. since Category 3 Wilma tore across southern Florida on October 24, 2005.  By 4 a.m. CDT on July 24, Dolly was an inland tropical storm, centered about 95 miles northwest of Brownsville, Texas.  As with many landfalling tropical storms, Dolly's passage across Deep South Texas has been accompanied by both drought relief and significant flooding.  More details on Dolly's rainfall will be provided in next week's summary.  Meanwhile, there was limited relief from severe to exceptional drought (D2 to D4) in the region centered on the Oklahoma panhandle, and some modest increase in moderate to severe (D1 to D2) drought coverage on the central High Plains, including eastern Colorado and western Nebraska.  On July 20, Colorado's rangeland and pastures were rated 52% very poor to poor.  Although highly variable conditions existed in Texas, with a range from no drought to exceptional drought (D4) across the Lone Star State, rangeland and pastures were rated 48% very poor to poor.

## The Northeast
Locally heavy showers swept across interior sections of the Northeast, but largely bypassed areas closer to the Atlantic Coast.  As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) expanded into a continuous region stretching from Delaware to southern New England.  For the week ending July 20, USDA rated 30% of Rhode Island's pastures in poor condition.

## The Northern Plains and Upper Midwest
Conditions were mixed across the northern Plains and the upper Midwest, with some areas seeing expansion of dryness or drought and other areas experiencing significant rainfall.  Short-term dryness (D0) expanded to include much of Montana, while areas of abnormal dryness in the Dakotas and Minnesota were joined into one area.  The percentage of Montana's spring wheat rated in good to excellent condition stood at 53% good to excellent on July 20, down from 70% at the end of June.  There was a general expansion of dryness and drought in North Dakota, with D3 (extreme drought) returning to the state for the first time since June 10.  North Dakota's rangeland and pastures were rated 38% very poor to poor for the week ending July 20.

## The Southeast
From July 15-21, much of the Southeast turned hot and dry.  As a result, there were several expansions of dryness (D0) and various drought intensities (D1 to D4).  Hydrological and agricultural impacts remained widespread in the Southeast and became more apparent in the western and central Gulf Coast States and the lower Mississippi Valley.  By July 20, according to USDA, 31% of the cotton in South Carolina was rated in very poor to poor condition.  The portion of rangeland and pastures rated very poor to poor included 56% in South Carolina, 42% in North Carolina, 36% in Georgia, 33% in Mississippi, and 30% in Alabama.  In contrast, heavy rain continued for several more days across Florida's peninsula, eliminating much of the remaining dryness (D0).  Vero Beach (2.99 inches), netted a daily-record total for July 15, followed two days later by a daily record of 2.63 inches in Daytona Beach.  On July 19, Tropical Storm Cristobal formed about 100 miles east of Charleston, South Carolina.  The following day, Cristobal moved parallel to the North Carolina coast, with the center passing a few miles offshore from Cape Lookout and Cape Hatteras.  Most of the heavy rain and gusty winds associated with Cristobal stayed offshore, although Wilmington, North Carolina (3.43 inches), measured a daily-record rainfall for July 19.  On the morning of July 20, a wind gust to 45 mph was clocked on Wrightsville Beach, North Carolina.

## The West
Once again, little or no rain fell in the West Coast states and the northern Rockies, while locally heavy monsoon showers dotted the Southwest.  Further reductions in the coverage and intensity of drought, some significant, were introduced across Arizona and New Mexico.  During the first 21 days of July, rainfall totals in southern New Mexico included 6.39 inches in Deming, 4.57 inches in Silver City, and 3.87 in Truth or Consequences.  Deming is within reach of its wettest month on record, which occurred in July 1911 when 7.13 inches fell.  Farther north, however, dry weather continued to stress some Western pastures, rangeland, and spring-sown crops.  In California, 100% of pastures and rangeland remained in very poor to poor condition for the week ending July 20.  In Washington, one-quarter of the spring wheat was rated very poor to poor.  There was a slight expansion of abnormal dryness (D0) in the Northwest, and a modest increase of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) in the Great Basin.   In northern California, more than a dozen large wildfires continued to burn, nearly a month after the June 20-21 lightning storms that ignited most of the blazes.  By July 22, northern California's year-to-date charred area topped 600,000 acres, with the largest active fire (109,000 acres; 65 percent contained) west of Hayfork in the Shasta-Trinity National Forest.  In total, northern California's active wildfires were responsible for the loss of more than 100 structures, including homes, cabins, sheds, and outbuildings.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (July 24-28), rain will fall in several areas experiencing dryness or drought.  The remnants of Hurricane Dolly will continue to produce torrential rainfall across southern Texas, where storm-total rainfall could reach 8 to 12 inches.  Isolated amounts near 20 inches may occur.  It is possible that Dolly's rainfall could further tighten the gradient between no drought in Deep South Texas and extreme to exceptional drought (D3 to D4) in south-central Texas.  Toward week's end, remnant moisture associated with Dolly's remnants may become embedded in the monsoon circulation, which could boost rainfall totals in parts of the central and southern Rockies and the Southwest.  Meanwhile, locally heavy showers will linger through July 24 in abnormally dry areas of the Northeast.  Farther west, a cold front will produce scattered showers in the north-central U.S., including the Dakotas.  Beneficial showers will also return to the lower Southeast, including parts of Florida.  Elsewhere, mostly dry weather will prevail into early next week in the West, excluding the Four Corners states.  The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for July 29 - August 2 calls for above-normal rainfall across the lower Southeast, the Atlantic coastal plain, the southern Rockies, and the upper Midwest, while drier-than-normal conditions will prevail from the southern Plains to the Great Lakes region and in most areas west of the Rockies.  Meanwhile, below-normal temperatures in the southeastern and Mid-Atlantic states will contrast with near- to above-normal readings elsewhere.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083017126</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.7471188704016</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.9005689769644</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0018155336346</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:45:32-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 