<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2011-03-01</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Laura Edwards</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Western Regional Climate Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — March 01, 2011</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2011-03-01</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2011-03-01</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2011-03-03</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — March 01, 2011

## Introduction
A strong storm system passed through the central United States this week, bringing heavy rainfall from Missouri to Ohio, alleviating drought conditions in the Ohio River Valley.  Drought intensified in parts of the southern states of Texas, Louisiana, Alabama and Florida.

## Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico
In Hawaii, rainfall is benefitting primarily the western half of the state, leaving the Big Island in deteriorating conditions.  Agricultural impacts are being reported to warrant expansion of moderate drought on the eastern half of the island, and D0 in the west.  Some of these include the need to haul water for livestock and general water use for residents, and reduced yields of some crops.  On the islands of Lanai and Maui, pasture conditions have improved and a one-category change was made to moderate drought status this week.
There were no changes made in Alaska or Puerto Rico.

## High Plains
An area of improvement is reflected in eastern Kansas as a result of the storm system that moved through the area last week.  Local amounts ranged from 2 to 3 inches for the Drought Monitor period.  A reduced drought area is now depicted on the map, with only abnormally dry conditions.

## Midwest
Significant improvements in drought conditions are reflected on this week’s map.  A large area of one-category improvement in drought severity was made in the Ohio River Valley, from Missouri to the Ohio-Kentucky border.  The core of precipitation fell fortuitously on the previous severe drought area in the 4-state region of Missouri, Arkansas, Kentucky and Tennessee. Rainfall totals for the week amounted to seven inches or more in the heart of this rain band, resulting in flooding across the area.  US Geological Survey data show continued high streamflow in the area.  The northern reaches of this band of precipitation improved drought in west central Indiana as well, with one-category improvements made there, resulting in removal of moderate drought (D1).  Some local totals were greater than five inches.  Illinois is now entirely drought-free on the map.

## Northeast and Mid-Atlantic
No changes are made in the drought depiction for this region.  Lighter precipitation of less than an inch fell over the current D0 area in northern New York, Vermont and New Hampshire during this Drought Monitor period.  Higher total rainfalls for the week were in Connecticut, Rhode Island and Massachusetts.  Along the coastal states, rain primarily fell along the shores as snow dominated inland areas.

## South
Areas of Louisiana and Texas are shown this week to have more severe drought.  Louisiana continues to experience severe rainfall shortages as compared to normal.  A one-category deterioration was made in central Louisiana, and also in the southeast to expand the reach of severe and extreme drought areas.  New Orleans is in its driest 6 month period on record, with just 11.72 inches of precipitation.  In the central and western part of the state, deficits are mounting, with the last similar period occurring in 2004-05.
A number of climate data sources supported expansion of severe drought (D2) in southern Texas counties from Zapata to Hidalgo along the Mexican border.  Worsening conditions in the Houston area and along the Gulf coast warranted degradation from D0 to moderate drought.  Recent data show the last 6 months to be the 15th driest on record, about a 1 in 10 year event.

## Southeast
Drought has been intensifying in this region as a typical La Nina pattern is settling in place.  Areas with worsening conditions include southern Florida and much of Alabama.  In Florida, D2 is expanded to include reflect significant rainfall deficits since October 1.  For the last 90 days, a large portion of south Florida has received just 25 to 50 percent of normal precipitation.  Fire danger is high for this time of year as well, as seen in some fire danger indices.  Additionally, soil moisture is at or below 20 percent of capacity, with some exceptions in the Miami-Dade and surrounding areas where it is a bit higher.  Hence, a hydrological impact label is given to this newly expanded D2 and D3 area.  D1 now also covers the area from Tampa to Fort Myers along the Gulf coast.
In Alabama, substantial rainfall deficits are accruing quickly across the state.  The hardest hit areas include Tallapoosa and Chambers counties, where extreme drought (D3) is re-introduced this week.  The region of severe drought is expanded in southwestern Alabama, and similarly D2 conditions now exist over Jackson and DeKalb counties in the northeast.  The previous area of D0 in central Alabama is downgraded to moderate drought in this week’s depiction.  Significant rainfall deficits over the last 30 to 90 days in addition to very low streamflow values were factors in these areas.   Since December 1, many locations are reporting precipitation totals of 6 to 10 inches or more across the middle of the state.

## West
Drought severity is increasing in the plains of eastern Colorado.  The Standardized Precipitation Index for this region varies from -1 to -3, for various periods of 120 days to 12 months.  Poor soil moisture conditions and increased wildfire threat are also apparent.
A new area of abnormally dry conditions is introduced in central Washington.  Precipitation deficits are accumulating in what is normally the wet season.  For the last 60 days, some locations have received less than 50 percent of their normal precipitation.
Hydrological conditions in Wyoming have been improving of late due to recent snowfall in the mountains, resulting in removal of D0 in west central Wyoming.  Abnormally dry conditions persist in the northwest and southwest.
Elsewhere in the West, no changes are made.

## Forecast
In the early part of the next Drought Monitor period, widespread precipitation is forecast for northern California and the Pacific Northwest, and the Great Lakes states and south into the Mississippi and Ohio River Valleys.  Precipitation amounts are not as considerable as those of last week in the Ohio River Valley, but could be enough to bring this region out of drought conditions.  Temperatures in the West will initially be warm bringing high-elevation rain.  The Great Lakes region could be particularly cold, resulting in snow or freezing rain.
A frontal passage over Hawaii could bring some much-needed precipitation to the state, relieving some drought concerns for a short while.
In the six to ten day outlook, below normal temperatures are projected to dominate the northern states in the lower 48.  Warmer than normal temperatures are likely to cover most of western and northern Alaska, and the Southeastern US, from Virginia to Florida.  Above average precipitation is the current forecast for most of the northern states from northern California to Maine, with less rainfall in the desert Southwest and Florida.  These conditions could exacerbate current severe drought in these areas.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-165.1264349</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-71.4568446</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>65.2266376</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:54:51-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 