<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-05-10</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Mark Svoboda</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — May 10, 2005</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-05-10</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-05-10</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-05-12</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — May 10, 2005

## Introduction


## Hawaii
Conditions remain the same this week, with most of the archipelago showing abnormally dry (D0) conditions due to unseasonably dry weather.

## Puerto Rico
The depiction across the island remains unchanged from last week.

## The Great Lakes and Midwest
Dryness continues its advance across the region as abnormally dry (D0) conditions have spread across all of Michigan, extreme northwestern Ohio, northern Indiana and most of Illinois and Missouri. New this week is the addition of a small area of moderate drought (D1) in extreme southwestern Michigan and extreme northwestern Indiana. With each week that passes, the 90-day deficits are mounting rapidly as we enter the warm season. Many areas within this region are commonly seeing 4 to 6 inch (25-50% of normal) deficits over this time frame, with most of that accruing only since March 1. Top soil moisture is taking a beating as USDA short-very short reports in Wisconsin, Michigan, Indiana, Illinois and Missouri are all running well above the 10-year mean. As of May 8, statewide reports of short-very short top soil levels showed Illinois (39% vs. 12% 10-yr mean), Michigan (45% vs. 18% mean), and Wisconsin (36% vs. 15% mean) are experiencing the worst statewide averages. Modest scattered precipitation across northern Minnesota and southern Wisconsin was only enough to maintain the D0 status quo.

## The Northern and Central Plains
The past week brought some modest precipitation to the northern Plains and parts of the eastern Dakotas but wasnt nearly enough to offset substantial deficits that have been mounting both recently (90 days) and over the longer haul (water year--since October 1, 2004) where totals are still coming in at around 30-60% of normal for both time frames. The rains have proven to be enough, however, in holding off the advancement of dryness in the region. As such, conditions remain unchanged this week across Nebraska, South Dakota and North Dakota.

## The Rockies and Western States
The big story in the West can be found in some modest improvements within the long-running epicenter of this drought across parts of Idaho, Montana and Wyoming (details below). For the first time since April 2002, there is no exceptional drought (D4) depicted on the Drought Monitor in the West. There are still large areas under severe (D2) and extreme (D3) drought, however, and summer streamflow forecasts from USDA/NRCS are still calling for 25-50% of average flows in the coming months across many basins in Wyoming, Montana, Idaho, Oregon and Washington.
A very fortuitous late-season moisture push (coupled with the recent coolness) continues to help in the short term, and some of these totals are really starting to have an impact on the water year and longer time frames as well. Additionally, the persistent cooler temperatures have delayed both the snowmelt and early irrigation demands across most of the West to date. As a result, there are a lot of changes to note this week, all of them positive in nature for a change.
The abnormally dry (D0) tongue in west central Colorado has been pushed back to the west because of solid year-to-date and water year precipitation totals. In addition, the moderate drought (D1) tongue along the Upper Colorado River basin along the Colorado/Utah border has also receded a bit to the north as some positive flows are being reported, resulting in some gains to reservoirs down stream, most notably Lake Powell and Lake Mead. While it is impossible to say whether or not this is simply a wet year embedded within an overall dry 10-year period, we wont know if the recovery is sustainable until we make it through the next water year in as good as fashion as this year. What took a long time to take hold will take a long time in coming out.
Abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) areas in Arizona have continued to see improvement this water year and have also seen resulting long-term precipitation deficits dwindle or reverse into 12 to 24-month positive anomalies for the first time in years, leading to a slight pushing eastward of D0 and D1 boundaries in central and northern parts of the state.
Farther north, the bountiful water year (150-200% + of normal precipitation) has led to more shrinking of the D0 and D1 in northwestern Nevada. The recent wetness has also brought about the reduction of moderate drought (D2) in southeastern Oregon, still leaving D1 in its wake.
To the east across Idaho, Montana and Wyoming, all areas of exceptional drought (D4) have been removed. Impressive late-season precipitation and cooler weather compared to the balmy winter temperatures have done wonders in salvaging what could have been yet another below-average water year. As it stands now, the long-term cumulative deficits and impacts will still take a long time to overcome and even this water years improvements have been spotty at best and not very widespread. The remaining extreme hydrological drought (D3) is still firmly entrenched because of this long-term temporal factor and resultant lagging surface and groundwater recharge. Fortunately, though, the former D4 areas fell within the pockets of good water year totals, leading to their removal. Although the gains are indeed modest, it is good to see improvements relative to some of the poor winters of the past seven years. Many basins in these states are still only expecting 25-50% of average summer streamflows according to the USDA/NRCS forecast issued on May 1. In addition, the large D3 area that had previously covered most of northern Wyoming and southern Montana has been reduced and pushed to the east due to the late-season surge (3 inch positive departures/130-200% of average) of precipitation over the past 90 days.

## The Southern Plains
Intensification was seen this past week over central Oklahoma and extreme north central Texas while central, south central, and southeastern coastal Texas saw marked improvement and removal of D0 due to some late-period heavy rains (2 to 4 inches). The same doesnt hold true for extreme southern Texas where the moderate drought (D1) has begun to push slowly north following the D0 up the Rio Grande river basin.
Oklahoma hasnt had much good fortune either as D1 has now spread across all of central Oklahoma. This week also brings the introduction of severe drought (D2) across south central Oklahoma, where 90-day departures run 4 to 7 inches or more. For the Central and South Central climate divisions, it is the driest such period on record, while the Southwest comes in as the second driest, resulting in a second driest statewide value. Not to be outdone, the North Central, Northeast, East Central and the Southeast divisions all ranked in the top 5 driest 90-day periods (going back to 1921) ending May 9. Following suit was the reported statewide USDA Topsoil Moisture value of 72% short-very short, which is an amazing 53% more than the 10-year mean for the May 8 date. Topsoil reports for Arkansas (36% vs. 15% 10-year mean) and Louisiana (67% vs. 25% 10-year mean) paint a very similar picture. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions have spread across more of southeastern Arkansas, northeastern Louisiana and extreme western Mississippi mainly due to this same three-month dry pattern in the region. Extreme southwestern Kansas has also seen a slight extension of D0. Winter wheat concerns grow across the southern Plains with each passing week of little or no moisture .

## Forecast
For the areas showing dryness/drought conditions during May 12  May 16, more late-season improvement is on tap for parts of northeastern Oregon, parts of Idaho, southern Montana, northern Wyoming and most of South Dakota as yet another fruitful system moves through, bringing with it the potential for 1.5 to 2 inches of precipitation. This is good news for the Missouri River basin lakes, rivers and tributaries. A wet spring would be welcomed given yet another relatively benign snow season in the headwaters region. The central and southern Plains states could see anywhere from 1 to 5 inches or more, with northern Oklahoma, eastern Kansas, eastern Nebraska, Iowa and northern Missouri seeing the potential for 3 to 5 inches or more as a result of a large spring storm tracking out of the Rockies, which should have a nice source of Gulf of Mexico moisture to tap into. The system will then proceed to move into the Great Lakes region and could bring with it 1 to 3 inches or more across southern Wisconsin, northern Illinois, extreme northern Indiana and southern Michigan, right where it is needed, given the spring dryness in these parts. Following in the storms path, temperatures are expected to be unseasonably cool (3 to 12 degrees below-normal) across most of the central and northern Plains and the Upper Midwest as Canadian air follows the rain and fills in behind it.
Looking out at the ensuing 5 days (May 17  21), precipitation is expected to be above normal in the Pacific NW and the northern reaches of the Great Basin and into western Montana. Cool temperatures are also expected across most of Washington and western Oregon. Another region seeing the potential for above-normal precipitation is the Upper Great Lakes, including most of Wisconsin, northeastern Minnesota and the Upper Peninsula of Michigan. Above-normal temperatures are more likely across the Southwest and the western areas of the central and southern Plains. Below-normal precipitation is also forecasted for most of the central and southern Plains and the Mississippi River basin.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.6591475</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.9284123</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.3383223</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:49:27-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 