<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-03-09</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — March 09, 2010</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-03-09</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-03-09</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-03-11</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — March 09, 2010

## Introduction
During the past 7 days, dryness generally increased between the Appalachians and the Mississippi River and across the northwestern quadrant of the country, but decreased through the southwestern one-quarter of the contiguous 48 states. On Hawaii, windward locations improved but dryness and drought persisted or intensified elsewhere.

## East of the Mississippi River
Between the Mississippi River and the Appalachians, only a few tenths of an inch of precipitation fell, if any. This allowed dryness and drought across Minnesota and the western Great Lakes region to persist. Farther east and south, growing short-term precipitation deficits led to D0 introductions across much of the northern half of Michigan as well as through much of the southern half of Kentucky, Tennessee, northern Alabama, and adjacent Mississippi. Since early December 2009, precipitation in most of northern and central Michigan totaled 2 to 4 inches below normal, with some reports of 4 to 6 inches below normal in northwestern lower Michigan. Farther south, the new D0 area coincides with areas that received 4 to 8 inches below normal precipitation during this period, and streamflows at many sites in the area were among the lowest 5 to 20 percent of values observed at this time of year.

## Hawaii and Alaska
The worst drought in the nation continues impacting the state of Hawaii. Fortunately, heavy precipitation on many windward locations and a few other scattered areas led to improvements across eastern sections of Molokai, Maui, and Hawaii Island. In contrast, reports of increasing agricultural impacts led to D2 and D3 expansion on the western half of the Big Island. The last 90 days brought 1.5 to 3.0 inches of rain to Lihue, Kauai; Honolulu, Oahu; and Kahului, Maui. These amounts were about 6 to 9 inches below normal.
In Alaska, little or no precipitation fell across much of the state, with greater amounts along the far southern tier, as usual. As a result, abnormal dryness was unchanged from last week

## Texas
The areas of abnormal dryness in southern and western Texas persisted, with little precipitation reported in these regions during the past 7 days.

## The West
Weekly precipitation totals of 0.6 to 3.0 inches were fairly common in several areas, most notably in parts of the Sierra Nevada and western California that are no longer experiencing significant abnormal dryness. However, similar amounts fell on numerous locations from southeastern Nevada through southeastern Arizona, part of the dry area in the central California valleys, andportions of southern Oregon, and the western slopes of the Washington Cascades, along with scattered to isolated locations through the rest of the Rockies, Intermountain West, and interior Pacific Northwest coastal plains.
This precipitation, in conjunction with a series of relatively wet weeks, led to the elimination of D0AH in central and southeastern New Mexico, and some reduction in northwestern parts of the state as well. Farther west, D1 and D2 conditions across southern Nevada and Arizona were reduced due to the recent precipitation and a re-assessment of conditions. Moderate drought was eliminated across southern and northwestern Arizona where significant moisture surpluses have been established over the last 90 days and 12-month totals were within 4 inches of normal. Meanwhile, essentially the middle of the severe drought region in northeast Arizona and the southern reaches of the region in southern Nevada were removed. In the remaining areas of severe drought across Arizona, 24-month precipitation amounts were still only 50 to 70 percent of normal, and 36-month totals ranged from 60 to 80 percent of normal.
Other areas of improvement in the western half of the country included part of north-central Colorado east of the continental divide, where abnormal dryness was trimmed, and north-central Washington, where little rain fell last week but where year-to-date precipitation amounts were significantly above normal. The moderate to severe drought in this region improved one category, to range from abnormally dry to moderate drought.
The wet week led to the removal of abnormal dryness in part of the central California Valleys, but for the remainder of the contiguous United States from the Rockies westward, dryness and drought either persisted or intensified relative to last week. Abnormally dry conditions were extended westward in Oregon and Washington as 90-day precipitation amounts declined toward 75 percent of normal. Meanwhile, moderate to severe drought expanded in northeastern and north-central California, southern Oregon, and northwestern Nevada where precipitation has consistently come up short of normal since early in the water year, and where some locations are experiencing their fourth consecutive drier than normal year so far. Conditions in the Klamath Basin have become particularly severe of late, prompting the Governor of Oregon to announce plans to sign a state drought declaration for the region in the near future.
Finally, precipitation and snowpack have been below average for a while across Idaho, Montana, and western Wyoming, and have declined to seriously low levels recently. As a result, D1 and D2 conditions expanded significantly across these regions and adjacent eastern Washington and Oregon. In the western half of Wyoming, snowpack water content was generally below 70 percent of average for the date, and surface water supply indices (SWSI’s) were among the lowest 5 to 20 percent of expected values for this time of year. In areas of western Wyoming and adjacent Utah where snowpack water content was below 55 percent of normal for the date, D2 was introduced. Farther north, significant D1 and D2 expansion took place across central and northern Idaho and, to a lesser extent, western Wyoming as seasonal precipitation totals and snowpack water content continued to decline relative to average conditions for early March. During the last 60 days, less than half of normal precipitation fell on northwestern Montana and essentially the northern half of Idaho.

## Forecast
Moderate to isolated heavy precipitation is anticipated during March 10 – 15, 2010 for northern California, interior western sections of Washington and Oregon, parts of the northern Intermountain West, central New Mexico, the Big Bend of Texas, the new dry area in the interior Southeast, central and northern Michigan, and northern Wisconsin. Light precipitation should fall on most other current areas of dryness and drought, with little or none expected in southern Texas, the desert Southwest, southern California, western Nevada, Wyoming, and north-central Montana. For the ensuing 5 days (March 16 – 20, 2010), the odds favor wetter than normal conditions in southern Texas, and closer to normal precipitation in Washington, northwestern Oregon, and the southern Big Bend of Texas. All other current areas of dryness and drought should receive below-normal precipitation, including much of Alaska.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-83.1908845</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>68.3169483</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:49:47-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 