<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2000-02-29</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Staff </gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — February 29, 2000</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2000-02-29</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2000-02-29</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2000-03-02</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — February 29, 2000

## Introduction


## Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico
February was very dry across the state of Hawaii. Most locations across the central and eastern sections normally record anywhere from 2 to 12 inches for the month, but less than an inch fell during February 2000 and many locations received little or no rain. As a result, D1 agricultural drought persisted along leeward sections of central and eastern Hawaii.

## The Plains and Midwest
Moderate to locally heavy precipitation brought welcome though incomplete relief to much of the region. February 22 - 29 featured 2 to locally 4 inches of precipitation in portions of central and eastern Kansas and Oklahoma while totals exceeding 1 inch covered most of the remainders of Kansas and Oklahoma, central and northeastern Missouri, a broad area from southeastern Missouri through much of Indiana, northwestern Illinois, and scattered sites across the northeastern Great Plains. Totals exceeding 0.5 inch were at least scattered across other areas, except for the High Plains, the northernmost reaches of the Great Plains and Great Lakes regions, southwest Wisconsin, and northeastern Iowa. But despite the beneficial rains, drought classifications remained the same in most areas, and some worsening was noted in southwestern Wisconsin (D0 to D1), part of east-central Missouri (D0 to D1), and interior eastern Iowa (D1 to D2).

## The South-Central and Southeastern States
Light to moderate precipitation fell on most of the region during the last 7 days, with heavier amounts (2 to 4 inches) measured in parts of northeast Texas, central and southwestern Arkansas, and a small part of the lower Ohio Valley. These were the first substantial rains in central and eastern Texas for several weeks, so the region's drought classification remained severe (D2). However, the rains did reduce drought severity to first-stage (D1) drought from D2 in parts of northern Mississippi and western Tennessee. Farther south, conditions worsened from D1 to D2 in southern Texas, part of western Georgia, and northern Florida while D1 conditions expanded to cover the Texas Panhandle. Across central and southern Florida, dryness that began in early December continued through late February. Much of this region recorded less than half of normal precipitation during the past 90 days, with anomalies of -4 to -7 inches measured in the upper Peninsula. These factors led to the southward expansion of abnormal dryness (D0) and D1 drought from central sections of the state through the Keys. The continuing dryness and generally above-normal temperatures have enhanced wildfires along the southern tier of states through January and February 2000. More than 206,000 acres of land were scorched from Arizona eastward to the Carolinas and Florida, compared to a national average of less than 58,000 acres for the period during 1997 - 1999.

## The West
Generally 1 to 4 inches of precipitation doused coastal southern California, bringing an end to abnormal dryness, while amounts of 0.5 to 2.0 inches were measured in portions of eastern Nevada, northwestern Arizona, southwestern Utah, southwestern Colorado, and north-central New Mexico during February 22 - 29. Other areas from western Nevada and the California deserts eastward through southern Colorado and New Mexico reported only isolated totals above 0.5 inch. Despite an increase in rainfall during the last few weeks, part of southeastern California, most of central and southern Arizona, and the southern tier of New Mexico recorded less than 25% of normal precipitation since late November. In the lower Colorado hydrologic region, 42% of monitored sites reported streamflows in the lower 25th percentile of observed occurrences for February 28, up from 27% on January 12.

## Forecast
There appears to be hope for at least some relief in most areas during the next 10 days. Unseasonably mild weather will dominate the next 5 days (March 1 - 6), and some areas should receive substantial precipitation. At least 0.25 inch of rain is anticipated in central and southern South Carolina, as well as the Tennessee and northern lower Mississippi Valleys and most of the southern Plains. Heavy rains are possible in drought-affected regions of central and northern Texas and across Oklahoma, where 1 to nearly 4 inches are expected to fall. Meanwhile, daily highs should average 4F to 8F above normal east of the Mississippi River, allowing unseasonably high evaporation rates and increasing crop moisture demands that could reduce the benefits of any rain that falls. The ensuing 10 days should bring normal to above-normal temperatures and heavy precipitation to most of the region, with only southwestern Texas and southern Florida anticipating no rainfall.
Southern parts of the region may experience significant relief during the next 10 days while conditions remain intact or worsen farther to the north. March 1 - 6 is expected to feature unseasonably warm weather, with significant precipitation anticipated in the central and upper southern Great Plains. Highs should average from about 4F along the southern fringes of the region, to more than 20F above normal in northeastern North Dakota and adjacent Minnesota. Most areas from far southern Nebraska and central Missouri southward are expected to receive over 0.5 inch of precipitation during the period, with totals exceeding 1 inch in central and southern Kansas. During the ensuing 5 days (March 7 - 11) above-normal precipitation is anticipated for all areas south of southern South Dakota, central Iowa, and northern Indiana while near- to below-normal precipitation falls farther north. Temperatures should average near normal in the central Plains, above normal farther to the north and east, and much above normal in the southern Great Lakes region.
The next 10 days hold the potential for significant relief in many of the dry areas. Ample precipitation (over 0.5 inch) is possible during March 1 - 6 in the dry areas of central and northern Arizona, west-central Nevada, the northern half of New Mexico, and parts of southern Utah and Colorado. Between 1 and 3 inches may fall in southwestern Colorado and central Arizona, which would be the heaviest precipitation since the end of the 1999 monsoon season in the latter region. Meanwhile, temperatures should average below normal in western parts of the region, and near or slightly above normal from central Arizona eastward. The following 5 days should bring abnormally cool weather to areas west of eastern New Mexico, and widespread above-normal precipitation except in parts of the desert.
As the wet season winds down, there is little prospect for substantial relief in the near future. Normal or above-normal rainfall is expected during the next few months, but this is a relatively dry time of year, and even surplus rains would do little to alleviate the continuing long-term dryness.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.3062736</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-77.8696472</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.3856286</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T00:51:46-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 