<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2011-07-19</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Matthew Rosencrans</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — July 19, 2011</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2011-07-19</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2011-07-19</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2011-07-21</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — July 19, 2011

## Introduction
The overall weather pattern for this past week featured a trough near the west coast, a strong ridge across the central portions of the contiguous 48 states, and a trough across the northeast.  The trough near the west coast contributed to below-normal temperatures west of the Continental Divide while the ridge across the middle of the lower 48 contributed to temperatures well above normal from Texas to Minnesota. This week featured a return of wet weather to the Gulf Coast region, with rains spreading from southeast Georgia to southeast Texas and temperatures near normal across the region.  Rainfall associated with the North American monsoon was largely focused across New Mexico and sparse in coverage.  The northern Great Plains and Pacific Northwest also experienced significant rains.

## Great Lakes
Continued dryness that began about 60 days ago prompted the introduction of an area of abnormal dryness (D0) to the map across the lower Great Lakes region.  Farmers have reported cracking ground and up-turned leaves on corn plants across northern Indiana.  Precipitation during the last 30 days has been less than 50% of normal for many portions of eastern Iowa, northern Illinois, and Indiana.
Across western New York and Pennsylvania, continued dry conditions lead to an expansion of the recently introduced D0 area.  Local National Weather Service offices reported that after one of wettest springs ever across western New York and northwestern Pennsylvania, rainfall totals across the region since June 1 are only about half of normal.  Additionally, the airport at Buffalo New York has received less than 2 hours of rainfall during the past 18 days.

## Great Plains
The drought conditions across the Southern Great Plains persisted, and worsened across most areas, with localized improvements due to isolated rain events.  AHPS precipitation estimates in excess of 5 inches prompted the improvement across southeastern Texas while sparse rainfall just east of El Paso also allowed for minor improvement.  The rest of the southern Great Plains experienced continued hot (2 – 8 degrees F above normal) and dry weather.  Exception drought (D4) coverage was expanded in coverage across portions of Texas, including Erath, Hood, Somervell, Comanche, Jim Wells, and Duval counties.  Additional expansion and intensification of the less severe drought conditions was included in the latest analysis across central Texas.  Range and pastureland across Texas and Oklahoma continued to deteriorate.  Across Texas, 94% of the range and pastureland was described as being in poor or very poor condition.  This is a record weekly value, although measurements of this kind only extend back to 1995.  Across Oklahoma, 78% of the range and pastureland described as poor or very poor, tied for the fifth highest percentage (August 6, 2006).  The rest of August 2006 saw statewide poor and very poor conditions expand to over 80% of all range and pasturelands.

## Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico
: Rainfall across Puerto Rico was significant so no dryness is depicted.
Windward areas of Hawaii have been receiving rainfall so D0 on the northeast-facing slopes of Maui and the Big Island was scaled back.  Afternoon upslope showers over the NW portion of the Big Island contributed to some improvement in the moderate drought (D1) area.  Across the Kona District, rainfall has been below normal so abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded across the western portions of the Big Island.  On the south side of the Big Island (Kau District), the United States Department of Agriculture field agents indicated that pastures have been deteriorating, so D1 was expanded.
The depiction across Alaska was modified to match the driest areas for the most recent 30 and 90 day periods, with a small reduction in coverage to reflect rains during the last week.  Rainfall totals were between 0.5 and 1.5 inches across southern interior portions of Alaska.  The panhandle of Alaska remained dry, and should be monitored closely for deteriorating conditions.

## Rockies and Southwest
Rainfall (approximately 0.5 inch) associated with monsoonal moisture contributed to a small improvement across northwest New Mexico (McKinley County).  The central portions of New Mexico remained dry while some portions across the south received nearly 6 inches of rainfall.  Even with 4-6 inches falling in the Cloudcroft region, improvement could not be pursued as average rainfall is 5.2 inches.  Within the same climate division, most other stations reported less than 1 inch of total rainfall during July.  Minor changes were made in the drought depiction across southeastern Colorado.  Radar estimated rainfall indicates higher amounts as much of the rain has been evaporating before reaching the ground (as is the case across much of western Oklahoma and New Mexico).  Impacts from the drought continue to linger across the southernmost portions of Colorado, while the improvements were made across central Colorado to reflect the rains this week (0.5 – 2.7 inches.

## Southeast and mid-Atlantic
A dry pattern persisted for the Carolinas, prompting a slight expansion in coverage of all the drought categories.  Some stations in the area reported rainfall totals near 1 inch but that amount is right near, or slightly below the 7-day average (1.0 – 2.0 inches) for many stations across the Carolinas for the past calendar week.   Many of the higher rainfall totals were measured near the Charlotte, NC metro area, with little impact across the driest coastal regions.
Farther southwest, significant rains (0.5 – 11.0 inches) fell across the Gulf Coast region (Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, and the Florida Panhandle).  Significant improvements in the drought designation were made across this region as a result of the rains.   A two category improvement was not pursued due to longer term (6-24 months) deficits in the region.  Twelve month rainfall deficits range from 16 inches to more than 20 inches below average across the region, despite the recent above-average rains. Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI) values from 3-24 months continued to indicate at least severe drought the region.
Improvements were made across Florida, due to recent rains (0.5 – 3.7 inches across southern Florida) and an improving hydrological situation (some wells have recovered by 50 percent and the South Florida Water Management District (SFWMD) reports an excess of water groundwater supply in some water conservation areas).  Improvements were tempered by the continued low levels in Lake Okeechobee. At just over 10 feet, Lake Okeechobee is not expected to exceed minimum water management levels by the end of the year even with near average rainy season inputs.

## Forecast
July 20 - 26, 2011 – The atmospheric flow pattern is expected to bring significant precipitation to the northern Great Plains and middle Mississippi River Valley. Moisture associated with the North American monsoon is expected to bring rainfall to much of Arizona and Colorado.  Afternoon thunderstorms are likely across most of the southeast, with a focus across central Alabama, Georgia, and Florida.  Dry conditions are expected to continue across Texas and Oklahoma, with little relief forecast.  Temperatures are expected to remain above normal for the central portions of the contiguous 48 states and below-normal along the Pacific Coast.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.3062736</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-74.8921568</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>64.8287345</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:57:04-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 