<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2003-06-17</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — June 17, 2003</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2003-06-17</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2003-06-17</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2003-06-19</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — June 17, 2003

## Introduction


## Alaska
Scattered showers and thundershowers crossed the D0AH region last week, but rainfall totals were too small to have a significant effect on the low streamflows and surface moisture depletion that have affected the area for the past few months. In fact, some D0AH expansion into nearby areas of southwestern and northeastern Alaska was introduced in response to an increase in certain fire danger indices that reflect surface moisture conditions.

## Hawaii
Scattered showers and thundershowers, particularly on some windward northeastern-facing slopes, produced some beneficial rain last week, but amounts were too small and localized to provide any tangible relief for those areas entrenched in dryness or drought. Over an inch of precipitation fell on parts of Kauai while 2.0 to 4.5 inches were measured at some sites in eastern Hawaii Island, but these latter amounts were measured in areas with some of the highest normals in the country. Since the start of the calendar year, Much of Hawaii and Molokai Islands have received only 25% to 50% of normal rainfall, and amounts greater than 80% of normal have been restricted to most of Kauai and small parts of northwestern Maui, south-central Molokai, and west-central Hawaii Islands. For some sections of southeastern Oahu and Maui, as well as eastern and southern Hawaii Island, these totals represent 20 to nearly 50 inches less than normal rainfall.

## The Northeast
Between 2 and 4 inches of rain fell on northern New Hampshire, ending D0H conditions. Farther north and east, Totals of 1 to locally 3 inches in much of Maine led to the elimination of D0H along the southeastern tier, and some reductions to D0H and D1H farther to the north and west.

## The northern and central Plains and upper Midwest
Light rain was the rule for much of this region, with a few noteworthy exceptions. Scattered totals of 1 to 3 inches were reported across northern and western Kansas, eastern Colorado, southern and western Nebraska, lower northern Missouri, and parts of the Dakotas, especially around the Black Hills. As a result, D0 categorizations were removed from northeast Colorado and adjacent Kansas, and conditions improved to D0H in and near the Black Hills, in portions of southwestern and southeastern Nebraska, and in part of southeast Colorado. In addition, D1 to D2 conditions improved by one category in part of west-central Nebraska and a small area near the Arkansas River in central Colorado. In contrast, little or no precipitation fell on eastern South Dakota, far northern Missouri, most of Iowa, northern Illinois, southern Wisconsin, and far southwestern Michigan, keeping prior areas of D0 to D2 intact, and allowing for the expansion of D0AH conditions into eastern South Dakota, southwestern Minnesota, central and eastern Iowa, northeastern Missouri, northern Illinois, southern Wisconsin, southwestern Michigan, and adjacent Indiana. For many of these areas, this marks a return to dryness that had been eliminated by heavy rainfall during the first half of May. For the last 30 days, rainfall totals ranging from 1 to locally 4 inches below normal have been measured.

## The Rockies and Far West
It was another dry week for most areas from the Big Bend of Texas northwestward through central and western New Mexico, Arizona, Nevada, Utah, western Colorado, southwestern Wyoming, central and southern Idaho, and central and eastern Oregon, where only scattered sites reported a few tenths of an inch of precipitation. Light to locally moderate rainfall was a bit more widespread to the north and east of these areas, specifically along the eastern tier of the Rockies, across central Colorado, through most of Montana and Wyoming, and in western Washington, but only isolated sites in the southeastern Rockies and near the High Plains recorded more than one inch. This left drought and dryness essentially unchanged from last week, with a few exceptions. Primarily, the A qualifier was extended to cover a broad portion of the central and southern interior West where short-term precipitation deficits, temperatures, and other surface moisture indicators pointed toward deteriorating conditions. In terms of drought categorizations, the eastward extent of D1 and D2 conditions in central Colorado declined slightly, as did the southward extent of D0A conditions in western Washington. Meanwhile, conditions deteriorated to D3AH in part of central New Mexico and across northeastern Nevada, where water supply projections through the end of summer were recently downgraded by some local authorities.

## The southern Plains
Last week's areas of dryness and drought in Oklahoma, central and eastern Texas, Arkansas, Louisiana, and adjacent Mississippi benefitted from copious rainfall. Totals exceeded 1 inch through most of these areas, with reports of 4 to 10 inches scattered across interior southwestern Oklahoma, northeastern Texas, central and southern Louisiana, central and southern Arkansas, and west-central Mississippi. With these rains came the removal of the A impact indicator from west-central Texas east-northeastward to the Mississippi River, where a broad one category improvement and small areas of two-category improvement were identified. Still, a large area of D0H remains across much of Louisiana, central and north Texas, and eastern Oklahoma, with D1H hanging on in the Red River Valley near the Oklahoma/Texas/Arkansas triple point, and in southwestern Louisiana, where 90-day rainfall totals are still a few inches below normal. According to the National Agricultural Statistics Service, some crops remain affected by the past few months of dryness despite improvements in surface moisture conditions during the last few weeks. Across Texas, 35% of pastures and rangelands, 34% of corn, 40% of cotton, and 50% of winter wheat crops were in poor or very poor condition, as were 25% of pastures and rangelands in Louisiana, on June 15. Farther south, along the Gulf Coast and in the southern reaches of Texas, heavy rainfall was not as abundant nor widespread as it was farther north, thus D0A to D2AH conditions were essentially unchanged in these regions. Three-month rainfall totals are still more than 7 inches below normal in a band from Houston, TX southwestward to near Victoria, TX.

## Forecast
June 19 - 23 is expected to bring moderate precipitation to many areas now experiencing dryness and drought. Specifically, 1 to locally 3 inches are forecast in Maine while 0.5 to 1.5 inches are predicted for central and northeastern New Mexico, southeastern Colorado, the Oklahoma and northern Texas Panhandles, western Kansas, southeastern Nebraska, northern Missouri, Iowa, the Black Hills, western and north-central Wyoming, southeasternmost Idaho, and a broad area in central and southern Montana. In contrast, less than 0.1 inch is forecast in central and southwestern Nebraska, northeasternmost Colorado, much of central and southwestern Texas as far north as the Red River, Arizona and adjacent New Mexico, western Colorado, southwestern Wyoming, much of Utah, and central and southeastern Nevada. During the ensuing 5 days (June 24 - 28), odds favor above-normal precipitation across Maine, the Corn Belt, northeastern Minnesota, the southwestern half of Texas, and most of New Mexico. Meanwhile, below-normal totals appear more likely in the northern and west-central Plains, northern and central sections of the Rockies and Intermountain West, the Great Basin, and western Washington.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-163.7762359</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-67.7534634</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>68.4062844</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:52:16-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 