<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2003-12-09</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Miskus</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — December 09, 2003</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2003-12-09</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2003-12-09</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2003-12-11</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — December 09, 2003

## Introduction


## Hawaii and Alaska
Another round of heavy showers drenched Kauai, Oahu, and the windward sides of Maui and Kona, erasing or easing drought conditions again. On Oahu, the normally drier central and western (leeward) stations recorded several inches of rain during the week, including 24-hour totals (ending 8:45am HST Dec. 8) of 5-10.5 inches at Schofield East, Moanalua, Mililani, Waiawa, and Palisades. On Kona (Big Island of Hawaii), a second week of showers (0.5 to 3 inches) on the leeward side improved conditions from D2 to D1. In Alaska, frigid and mostly dry weather enveloped much of the State, with weekly temperatures averaging 5 to 15F below normal, and lows plunging to -55F at Bettles, -49F at Tanana, and -38F at Northway. With significant precipitation limited to the Gulf of Alaska coastal sites (3.25" at Kodiak, 2.44" at Yakutat, and 2.08" at Seward), abnormal dryness remained in interior southeastern Alaska.

## Southeast
Although all long-term (6 months to 2 years) moisture indicators are normal to wet in the eastern third of the Nation, another dry week in central Florida has generated short-term (30 and 90-days) deficits between 1-2 and 4-7 inches, respectively. Additionally, the Keetch-Byrum Drought Index (KBDI), an index that estimates the dryness of the soil and duff layer for wildfire potential, rose between 500-600 (max=800) in parts of central Florida, thus D0(A) was introduced.

## The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes Region
The Noreaster that dumped over a foot of snow on much of the Northeast (up to 52" at Pinkham Notch, NH) during December 4-7 had previously dropped light to moderate precipitation on parts of the central Great Plains and Midwest a few days earlier. With snow across the western Corn Belt (4 to 8 inches) and rain farther south, liquid-equivalent totals between 0.7 to 1.8 inches in eastern Kansas, northwestern Missouri, and western Iowa, coupled with surplus November precipitation across Iowa, were enough to improve portions of the 3-state area by one category. Lesser amounts (less than 0.5") in eastern Iowa, Minnesota, Wisconsin, and northern Illinois kept conditions status-quo.
In contrast, another week with little or no precipitation across the remainder of the Plains, plus above-normal temperatures, maintained or worsened dryness and drought, especially in the southern Plains. Recent dryness has offset light to moderate precipitation that fell during the first half of November, resulting in an expansion of severe drought northward into the Texas Panhandle, and D0-D1 eastward across the ArkLaTex region. According to the Oklahoma Climatological Survey, deficiencies of 4 or more inches are common across southern Oklahoma since Sep. 1, and year-to-date departures exceeding -12" have accumulated in the southeastern quarter of Oklahoma. In northeastern Texas, 90-day deficits surpassed 7 inches. Significant rains have also bypassed the Austin, TX area to the north and south, creating short and medium-term shortages. Since April 1, Austin has measured only 14.05 inches versus a normal of 25.80 inches. Nearby stations, however, are close to normal for the same period (San Antonio -1.5", Waco -1.4", College Station +4.3"). Additionally, a very dry October-early December (generally 0.1 to 0.4", or about 10-25% of normal) in eastern Colorado shrank the D0-D1 hole over the state by increasing the D2 coverage in eastern portions. The dryness negatively impacted Colorados winter wheat, rated below average in the latest NASS/USDA state summary.

## The Rockies and Far West
An active Pacific jet stream continued to bring storm systems to the Northwest, but the largest totals (&amp;gt;2") were generally confined to coastal and mountain (Cascades, Sierra Nevadas, and northern Rockies) locations. The active jet also brought very mild weather to the western half of the U.S., with weekly departures exceeding +5F throughout much of the Intermountain West and Rockies. With the latest November indices and products available, the map was adjusted to reflect the latest Oregon Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) map. Accordingly, the far eastern (Grand Ronde, Powder, and Burnt; Malheur; and Owyhee) and south-central (Klamath) river basins with low November SWSIs (&amp;lt;-2) were degraded, while the western and central basins were upgraded in Oregon. In addition, the NRCS basin averaged precipitation (Oct. 1-Dec. 9) in southern and eastern Oregon was 64-82% of normal, and basin averaged snow water content ranged from 36-82% of normal through Dec. 9, depicting yet another slow start to Oregons wet season. In northern Utah, Bear Lake dropped to 9% of capacity, or 14% of average on Nov. 30, threatening next years irrigation allotments to Box Elder County agricultural interests if this winters snows are like last years. As of Dec. 1, the NRCS state-averaged reservoir storage as percent of capacity was below average in all Western states (California n/a), but especially in Utah, Nevada, New Mexico, Wyoming, and Oregon. December 1/normal storage (percent of capacity) was 9/65%, 18/52%, 18/52%, 23/56%, and 18/45%, respectively.
In contrast, another week of moderate to heavy precipitation in western Washington, western Oregon, and northern California slightly edged the western-most drought area eastward. In the northern Rockies, 1 to 3 inches of precipitation fell on northern Idaho and northwestern Montana for the sixth consecutive week. Basin averaged Oct. 1-Dec. 9 precipitation was between 108-116%, with Dec. 9 basin averaged snow water content between 108-125%. Although the early 2003-04 water year is encouraging, recent streamflows depict a mixed bag. They have spiked upward toward normal after a precipitation event, but then sharply dropped, failing to sustain average levels. Accordingly, very slight improvement was made in northern Idaho (some D2 removed) as this region will need continued surplus precipitation during the remainder of the wet season, plus favorable snowmelt weather, to alleviate its long-term drought.

## Forecast
Weather events that may have an impact on abnormally dry or drought areas during the next 5 days (Dec. 11-15) include: 1) A departing storm system dumped heavy (1-3") precipitation (after 12Z Dec. 9 into Dec. 10) from northeastern Oklahoma northeastward into southern Wisconsin; 2) A continuing active Pacific jet stream will bring more disturbances to the West. Early on, a southerly storm track should impact the Great Basin, Southwest, and southern Rockies and Plains, while a second system over the weekend should take a more northerly track, affecting the Pacific Northwest, northern Rockies and Plains; 3) After Dec. 10, the central Plains, western Corn Belt, and upper Midwest should remain mostly dry; 4) Florida should see showers early and late in the period.
The 6- to 10-day outlook for December 16-20 calls for below-normal temperatures in the Southeast, with milder-than-normal conditions in the Far West, northern Rockies and Plains, and New England. The greatest likelihood for significant precipitation is expected to occur along the Atlantic Seaboard, with subnormal amounts forecast for much of the current Western, Plains, and Midwest drought areas.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.306273576829</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-80.8875085057768</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965172854</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>64.59937794001</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:36:16-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 