<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2000-03-14</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Staff </gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — March 14, 2000</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2000-03-14</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2000-03-14</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2000-03-16</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — March 14, 2000

## Introduction


## Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico
Mostly dry weather persisted across the Hawaiian Islands. Although light, scattered showers occurred during March 6-8 across Molokai, Lanai, northern Maui, and northern and eastern sections of the Big Island, weekly totals were generally less than 0.10 inches across D1 areas, impacting pastures, non-irrigated agriculture, and wildfire conditions. Continued well-below normal rainfall on the Big Island this year prompted the addition of a D0 area across central sections.

## The Plains, Midwest, and Central Appalachians
Unseasonably heavy precipitation, some in the form of snow, fell on much of the central and northern Plains and upper Midwest. One-half to two inches of precipitation in central Kansas, western Nebraska, most of South Dakota, southern North Dakota, central Minnesota, and northern Wisconsin significantly alleviated D0 dryness and decreased D1 drought areas. The Corn Belt, however, generally received little or no precipitation, and D2 drought remained or slightly expanded as defined by the latest PDI, streamflow, and soil moisture anomaly maps. D0 was expanded into eastern Ohio and central Virginia after their third straight dry week.

## The Rockies and Western States
With the Pacific storm track diving into the Southwest, several storm systems dropped significant precipitation (more than 0.5 inches) on most of California, Arizona, Nevada, Utah, Colorado, and northwestern New Mexico. Northern and central Arizona experienced its third consecutive week of significant precipitation (2 to 4 inches of precipitation this week), diminishing D1 areas to D0 across most of southern Arizona, and eliminating D0 dryness across western Nevada, central Arizona, southern Utah, and extreme northern New Mexico. October 1-March 12 basin average snow water content and precipitation surpassed 2/3rds of normal across northern parts of Arizona and New Mexico. Mostly dry weather, however, continued across the rest of New Mexico as D1 and D2 drought remained.

## The South-Central and Southeastern States
Heavy rains (2 to 5 inches) fell on much of the D2 drought areas of Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama, while light to moderate rains (1 to 2 inches) dampened most of the D0 and D1 regions of northeastern Texas, southeastern Oklahoma, the eastern Tennessee Valley and southern Appalachians, and much of the Southeast, with the exception of Florida, southeastern Georgia, and coastal Louisiana and Mississippi where it was mostly dry. Since the previous week was relatively dry in the Delta, no improvement occurred to the Delta's drought condition. In southeastern Oklahoma and west-central Alabama, however, 4 straight weeks of moderate rains diminished the D0 and D1 areas, respectively. In contrast, the third successive dry week expanded the D1 area into southwestern Florida, and continuing subnormal rains along the eastern Gulf Coast increased the D2 area into southeastern Louisiana, southern Mississippi, and the Florida Panhandle. Abnormal dryness (D0) was added to interior South Carolina after receiving reports from the state's natural resources office.

## Forecast
By mid-week, a developing storm system over the western Gulf Coast will head northeast, producing rain across much of the Southeast, Appalachians, mid-Atlantic, and Northeast. Greatest totals (2 to 4 inches) should fall on the Delta and lower Ohio Valley. By Friday, a new storm system should trek southeastward from the Pacific Northwest into the southern Plains, dropping precipitation on the southern and central Great Plains and western Gulf Coast regions. A cold front should stall over Florida, bringing welcome showers to the state. The March 21-25 outlook indicates that the primary storm track will shift westward, allowing beneficial precipitation to reach the southern High Plains. Above-normal precipitation is indicated for the western half of Texas, while areas from Oklahoma and eastern Texas to the lower Mississippi Valley are expected to receive near-normal amounts during the 5-day period. However, unfavorably dry weather is forecast to return to much of the Southeast, where evaporation rates will be high due to above-normal temperatures. Scattered showers may linger across southern Florida.
During Thursday and Friday, a cold front should sweep through the Midwest, dropping light to moderate precipitation on the central Plains and the Ohio and lower Missouri Valleys. The northern Plains and upper Midwest should remain generally dry through March 20. In contrast, the central Appalachians are forecast to receive moderate rainfall. The ensuing 5 days are forecast to feature near-normal precipitation in most areas. However, with a building ridge of high pressure across the Southeast, drier conditions may work their way into the central Appalachians and parts of the Ohio Valley. Very warm conditions will result in unusually high evaporation rates for this time of year from the northern and central Plains and Midwest to the central Appalachians.
Storm systems should steer north of the Southwest the next few days, keeping southern California, Arizona, and New Mexico mostly dry. This weekend, however, a storm system dropping southeastward from the Pacific Northwest may clip northern sections of Arizona and New Mexico with some precipitation. The 6 to 10-day outlook calls for an increasing chance of precipitation and much cooler conditions across the Southwest. Above-normal precipitation is indicated for March 21-25 in southeastern California and the Four Corners region.
Light trade winds and dry weather are forecast until Friday, with increasing trades and enhanced showers along the windward side of the Big Island during the weekend. However, as the normal rainy season winds down and sea surface temperatures around Hawaii remain slightly below normal, substantial widespread rainfall to end the dryness appears unlikely during the next several weeks.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.3062736</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-77.4943064</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.3856286</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T00:51:54-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 