<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2001-04-17</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Miskus</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — April 17, 2001</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2001-04-17</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2001-04-17</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2001-04-19</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — April 17, 2001

## Introduction


## Hawaii
Light to moderate (and locally heavy windward) showers fell on most locations of Molokai, Maui, and the Big Island, maintaining or easing dryness and drought on leeward areas. On the Big Island, welcome rains (0.75-1 inches) were measured at Upolu and Kahua Ranch in the northwest while 0.7-1.2 inches fell along the western coast, but more is needed before improvement occurs. On Maui, scattered showers dropped light to moderate totals (0.1-1.3 inches) on leeward (western) sections, with greater amounts (more than 2 inches) on windward (northeastern) sites, confining D1, D1(A,F), and D2(A,F) conditions to the western third of the island. No rain was measured at Lanai City, and the 0.1-0.4 inches recorded on Molokai maintained the islands severe to extreme drought.

## The Central Appalachians, lower Ohio Valley, and northern Delta
A stalled cold front was the focal point for numerous thunderstorms, severe weather, and heavy rainfall (1.5-3 inches) across most of the lower Missouri and Ohio Valleys, and in the north-central Appalachians. As a result, abnormal dryness and most short-term deficits were eliminated or significantly reduced across the central and eastern Corn Belt and central Appalachians. However, lesser amounts (0.1-0.6 inches) and unseasonable warmth (weekly departures of +7 to +10F, highs in the mid-80's) were reported in the northern Delta and lower Ohio Valley, maintaining or slightly expanding the areas abnormal dryness, and adding moderate drought to western Kentucky where 30-day (25-50% of normal, 2 to 3 inch deficits), 90-day (50-75% of normal, 3-5 inch deficits), and 6 month (6 to 8 inch deficiencies) precipitation has been subnormal.

## The Plains
A second intense April storm system traversed across the central Plains on Wednesday, less than a week after the initial one, dumping moderate to heavy precipitation (1-3 inches) from northern Colorado northeastward into central Minnesota. Drought was relieved in west-central Nebraska and western Iowa, where year-to-date precipitation has been 150-200% and 125-150% of normal, respectively. In extreme eastern Montana, light precipitation (0.1-0.3 inches) followed last weeks moderate totals (0.5-1 inches), alleviating abnormal dryness. In contrast, another hot (weekly departures +6 to +8F, highs in the 90's) and rainless week in southern Texas slightly expanded D0 and D1 northward, although widely-scattered Monday afternoon thundershowers dropped 0.3-1 inches, locally 2.5 inches, on parts of extreme southeastern New Mexico and adjacent west-central Texas.

## The Southeast
An active weather pattern continued, with the heaviest rainfall (2 to 4 inches) falling on the central Delta and Tennessee Valley, and lesser totals across most of the Southeast. In Tennessee, the rains erased dryness (D0) across southern sections, and shrank moderate drought in western areas. In contrast, Florida (minus the Panhandle), the eastern Carolinas, and southern Louisiana received little or no rain, observed unseasonable warmth (temperatures averaged 6 to 11F above normal, highs in the upper 80's to lower 90's), and increased evapotranspiration. Fortunately, expansion of abnormal dryness or drought was tempered in areas that had recorded several consecutive cool and wet weeks (e.g. Georgia and the Carolinas), but drought (D3 and D4) worsened in central Florida. The second straight dry week in southern and central Florida contributed to further declines in Lake Okeechobee, at 9.92 feet on April 16, down from 10.25 feet on April 3 and approaching its all-time record low of 9.75 feet on July 29, 1981, while 25% of the 44 USGS-measured river sites were at near- to record low streamflows on April 16. NASS/USDA reported that statewide topsoil and subsoil moisture was rated 82% and 86% very short to short, up from 71% and 74% a week ago, respectively. Wildfires were also of concern as Florida, North Carolina, and Virginia reported moderate to large burns as of Friday, including an 8,000 acre fire in Florida. Along the central Gulf Coast, short-term dryness returned in response to 2 consecutive warm and dry weeks, short-term (30-day) rainfall 25-50% of normal, 7-day average streamflows in the lower 25 percentile, high evapotranspiration rates, and lingering long-term shortfalls (20-25 inches for 18 months).

## The West
April remained cold and unsettled across much of the region. Weekly temperatures averaged 3 to 6F below normal, and light precipitation (snow in higher elevations) was reported in the Cascades, Sierra Nevada, and Rockies, with the largest totals (more than 2 inches liquid equivalent) in northern Colorado and southern Wyoming. Compared to a week ago (April 9), average basin snow water content (SWC) generally increased by 5-10% points, and season-to-date precipitation (STDP) grew by 1-2% points. However, the National Water and Climate Center (WRCC) in Portland, OR, cautions that changes in snowpack percent of average become more amplified and may not reflect the historic peak snowpack amount for the season as the average snow water equivalent declines to zero during traditional spring snowmelt. This pattern migrates northward from southern portions of the West as temperatures rise during the spring. In addition, the WRCC noted that the subnormal 2000-01 snowpack is melting at a faster rate than normal since it does not have the usual deep snowpack insulating properties.
Even after 2 straight weeks of favorable weather (cold and unsettled), basin average SWC (on April 16) was still between 45-60% of normal in most of Idaho, 54-64% in Washington, 39-66% in central Oregon, 48-51% in the northern Sierra Nevada, 61-75% in western Montana, and 62-71% in northwestern Wyoming. Basin average precipitation (October 1-April 16) was generally less than 2/3rds of normal in Washington, Oregon, Idaho, western portions of Montana and Wyoming, and northern California. As a result, changes were minimal in the West, except for the alleviation of D0(W) in extreme southern Wyoming, and the expansion of abnormal dryness into northwestern California as significant precipitation has occurred either north or south of this region since March (30 and 90-day precipitation 50-75% of normal).

## Forecast
April 18-22 (Day 1-5) anticipated weather that may affect dry or drought areas is similar to last weeks Looking Ahead summary, namely: 1) the third in a series of strong April storm systems should track across the central Plains northeastward into the upper Midwest by next week, bringing precipitation to central Rockies, north-central Plains, Midwest, and New England; 2) after a brief warm-up, colder and unsettled weather (troughing) returns to the West, with possible snows in higher elevations of Cascades, Sierra Nevada, northern Rockies; 3) high pressure should keep most of the southern Plains and Southeast dry and warm, including Florida and south Texas; 4) drier weather should return to most of Hawaii, with scattered windward showers.
The 6-10 day outlook (April 23-28) predicts another shift in the upper-air pattern, producing: 5) above-normal chances for precipitation in the southern Plains and Great Lakes region, high probabilities for subnormal precipitation in the Southwest, north-central Rockies and Plains, and near-normal precipitation elsewhere; 6) probabilities for above-normal temperatures are greatest in the Southwest and Southeast, with subnormal temperatures expected in the northern Great Lakes region and New England.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.306273576829</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-75.4595048015415</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965172854</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0035990523773</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:36:14-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 