<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2003-05-20</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — May 20, 2003</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2003-05-20</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2003-05-20</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2003-05-22</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — May 20, 2003

## Introduction


## Hawaii and Alaska
Increased precipitation brought an end to D0 conditions in far southwestern Alaska, but continued below-normal totals farther east, along with an increase in fire vulnerability indicators, kept D0 conditions intact across south-central Alaska, with some expansion into central and east-central parts of the state. Most areas in Hawaii experiencing dryness or drought observed little or no rain last week, keeping conditions intact. The eastern sections of Hawaii Island received substantial rains of 1.5 to locally 5.0 inches, but normal precipitation for this region is quite high, and these totals were insufficient to improve the region's D0A conditions.

## The Great Lakes and Northeast
Light precipitation prevailed across northeast lower Michigan and most of Maine, keeping D0H to D1H conditions intact. Farther south, Moderate rains of 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches eased D0AH and D1AH conditions slightly in eastern Ohio, but drier conditions in western sections of both Pennsylvania and New York led to continued D0AH to D1AH conditions. Deterioration to D1AH occurred in far northwest Pennsylvania near Lake Erie while D0AH expanded into southwest Pennsylvania.

## The northern and central Plains
Most areas of dryness and drought from Nebraska and northern Missouri northward to the Canadian border received light precipitation. A few areas recorded scattered totals of 1 to locally 3 inches, specifically parts of south and east Nebraska, adjacent Iowa, central North Dakota, and isolated parts of north-central South Dakota and western Nebraska, but such amounts were not widespread. As a result, the coverage and severity of D0H to D3H conditions were almost uniformly unchanged relative to last week. The eastern and northern extent of D0H in the central Dakotas was curtailed slightly. In contrast, a one category deterioration (to D1H) was noted in part of far southeast Nebraska that missed the heavier rains.

## The Rockies and interior West
Light to moderate precipitation fell on central and northern Montana, central and eastern Utah, and most of Colorado while little or none fell elsewhere. However, despite the uneventful week, some drought status changes were introduced in Colorado and the southern Rockies. Substantial precipitation and unseasonably cold conditions for much of the last 2 to 3 months led to improved water supply outlooks through north-central and northeastern Colorado, where conditions were improved to D0H this week. In addition, a 1-category improvement to D1H or D2H was introduced in parts of interior northwest Colorado for similar reasons. Farther south, however, conditions continued to gradually decline. This is a dry time of year from central New Mexico westward through Arizona, so the lack of substantial precipitation for the last couple of months is not unusual, nor has it resulted in a decline in hydrologic conditions. However, with hot weather frequently accompanying the dryness, surface moisture indicators have deteriorated. 93% of New Mexico has topsoil assessed as "short" or "very short" of moisture, and 66% of rangelands in New Mexico, along with 50% of those in Arizona, were in poor or very poor condition. In addition, fire vulnerability indicators have increased markedly across these areas in the last few weeks. As a result, the regions' D0H to D3H conditions have been reclassified as D0AH to D3AH across central and southern New Mexico and Arizona, and in fact a one-category decline (to D2AH) was recorded in part of east-central and southeastern Arizona.

## The southern Plains and Gulf Coast
The northern and eastern portions of the dry areas from eastern New Mexico and Kansas southeastward through northern Florida generally improved from locally heavy rainfall while drought intensified, in some cases markedly, farther to the south and west. Generally 1.5 to 6.0 inches of rain fell on many locations from central and south Kansas southeastward through much of northern, eastern, and southern Oklahoma, western Arkansas, northern Louisiana, the central Gulf Coast region, and parts of northwestern and northeastern Florida, with isolated totals approaching 10 inches in southeast Kansas, northeast Oklahoma, and northwest Arkansas. As a result, the D0AH to D2AH conditions that covered the south-central Great Plains and northern lower Mississippi Valley generally improved by one category, and the D0A in Florida was restricted to areas in the Panhandle along the Gulf Coast that received little or no rain. In sharp contrast, continued exceptional short-term dryness and hot weather brought one-category drought severity increases to most areas in southern Louisiana, in Texas south of the Red River, across southwestern Oklahoma, and in western Texas and eastern New Mexico. Over the last 30 days, portions of western Oklahoma and north-central and eastern Texas recorded only 1 to 3 inches of precipitation while southern Louisiana, the western, central, and southern portions of Texas, and eastern New Mexico received little or none. These totals are at least an inch below normal in areas east and southeast of New Mexico, west Texas, and the Oklahoma Panhandle, and range from 2 to 5 inches below normal in southwest Oklahoma, much of central and east Texas, and central and southern Louisiana. According to the National Agricultural Statistics Service, topsoil moisture was assessed as "short" or "very short" for 93% of New Mexico, 44% of Oklahoma (despite some areas of substantial rainfall), and 61% of Louisiana. Also, 66% of New Mexico pastures and rangelands were described in "poor" or "very poor" condition, as were 40% of ranges and pastures in Texas, and the proportion of the winter wheat crop in similar condition climbed to 48% in Texas. As a result, D1AH or worse conditions now cover almost all of these areas, with large sections of eastern New Mexico, western Texas, and central to north-central Texas deteriorating to D2AH. In deep south Texas, where antecedent moisture surpluses have mitigated recent dryness to some extent, D0A was introduced, with D0AH identified along the Rio Grande River where reservoir stores are unfavorably low.

## Forecast
Moderate to locally heavy precipitation is expected May 22 - 26 in many areas currently experiencing dryness and drought. At least 0.5 inch is anticipated in northern New England, northwest Florida, northeast lower Michigan, east Nebraska and adjacent Iowa, parts of central and southeast Colorado, northeast New Mexico, southwest Kansas, the Texas Panhandle, much of Oklahoma and the ArkLaTex region, northwest Wyoming, and a swath through central Montana. None of these area are expecting exceptionally large amounts, however, with forecast totals over 2 inches restricted to the Florida Panhandle. In contrast, little or no precipitation is expected in the Great Basin, Arizona, the west-central Rockies, most of New Mexico, the central and north High Plains, much of central, south, and east Texas, and southern Louisiana. In addition, abnormally warm weather is forecast from the Rockies westward. The ensuing 5 days (May 27 - 31) feature enhanced chances for above-normal precipitation in central and east sections of Colorado and New Mexico, south and west Oklahoma, central and north Texas, the central and northeast Gulf Coast region, northern New England, and southwest Alaska. Meanwhile, the odds favor subnormal precipitation in the Great Basin, the Intermountain West, the northern and western Rockies, the northern High Plains, the central and northern Great Plains, and east-central Alaska. Warmer-than-normal weather is expected from the northern Great Plains and southern High Plains westward to the Pacific Coast.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.945187340426</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-66.9540017338536</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965172854</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>65.3817365242718</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:35:27-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 