<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-07-20</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Anthony Artusa</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — July 20, 2010</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-07-20</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-07-20</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-07-22</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — July 20, 2010

## Introduction


## Alaska
Relatively light to moderate precipitation (under 0.75 inch) fell across the dryness regions in central and southwestern Alaska, with scattered locations receiving heavier amounts. In the Panhandle, most locations reported under an inch. This results in only a modest reduction in 90-day shortfalls to this climatologically wet region, thus D0 conditions remained unchanged.

## Hawaii
The western (lee) side of the Big Island has seen some improvements in the drought situation across the middle elevations, which contain prime coffee orchards. Extreme drought (D3) was upgraded to severe drought (D2) in this area. However, the USDA has recently declared all Hawaiian counties farm disaster areas, due to the economic losses incurred from the statewide drought.

## The Great Lakes Region
Temperatures during the past week ranged from 2 to 6 degrees F above normal across the region. Heavy rain (2.0 to 3.5 inches) provided a much needed boost in Wisconsin. The D1 area was upgraded to D0 in Rusk county, with a significant 1-category improvement (from D0 to D-nothing) across northwestern sections of the state. There was also minor improvement across northern portions of Lower Michigan, near Saginaw Bay, where Iosco and eastern Ogemaw counties were upgraded from D0 to D-nothing based on rainfall between 2.5 and 3.0 inches received during the week. Unfortunately, the heavier precipitation continues to miss the core drought area, which is currently located over western Upper Michigan.

## The Northeast
Heavy rain and thunderstorms affected portions of the mid-Atlantic region, with 2 inches or more within a band stretching from the central Appalachians northeastward across much of southern Pennsylvania, north-central Maryland, and New Jersey. As a result, 1-category improvements were widespread across this region. In Maryland, the small area of severe drought (D2) was removed, and stream flows have improved following last week’s rainfall. This area has been impacted by persistent stretches of hot weather, and with dew points frequently over 70F, has resulted in lowered evapo-transpiration rates. In Virginia, there is a sharp contrast between southwestern areas that have recently received some rainfall, from northwestern areas which have largely missed out on beneficial precipitation. Southwestern areas of Virginia are experiencing new grass growth, and pastures are beginning to show signs of recovery. From about Staunton, VA northward however, grasses and pastures are mostly brown, corn and soybean growth has been stunted, and there are varying degrees of heat and drought related stress. In New Jersey, 1-category improvements in the drought, from D1 back to D0, have largely resulted from the recent rains of 2 inches or greater. Rainfall totals for this month range from under 0.50 inch to about 8 inches.
In contrast, where the recent rains did not fall, abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded across most of Connecticut and Massachusetts, and into southern portions of New Hampshire. D0 conditions were also expanded northward from northern Pennsylvania into southern New York. For portions of western and central New York, relief from the dryness has been spotty, and many areas have received little if any rain. This has been offset to some degree however, by a wet June which resulted in fairly normal groundwater levels.

## The Southeast
Hot, dry weather continued across much of the area during the past week. In South Carolina, showers and thundershowers provided slight improvement, despite the hot weather. Soil moisture levels improved somewhat across the state, and were reported as 11 percent very short, and 35 percent short. In Georgia, worsening conditions prompted the expansion of D0 conditions across various portions of the state. Hot weather, with high temperatures ranging from the upper 80s to the middle 90s, undoubtedly contributed to this deterioration. Soil moisture conditions for the state were rated at 4 percent very short, and 39 percent short. In Florida, where the rainy season continues, drought has been minimal. However, on the Space Coast in Brevard and northern Indian River counties, rainfall deficits of 9 inches have occurred since May 1st. Melbourne reported its driest May-mid July period on record (3.83 inches), and Titusville experienced its second driest May-mid July period on record (4.58 inches). Well levels are generally good though, recharged from rains received earlier in the spring.

## The Southern Plains
Very hot weather and little if any rainfall has prompted the introduction of abnormal dryness in northwestern Oklahoma. D0 (Texas and Beaver counties) and D1 designations (nearby Harper county) fit more realistically with 90-day (and beyond) rainfall deficits. There are a substantial number of reports of ponds going dry in this region, and most of the recent storm activity seems to have passed either to the west or to the south of the Oklahoma Panhandle. Over the southeast part of the state, a 1-category degradation (from D1 to D2) was made to Pushmataha, Choctaw, and Bryan counties, whereas nearby counties in Texas were actually upgraded 1-category from severe to moderate drought due to increased rainfall during the past 30 days. This general area of moderate to severe drought near the Red River is also supported by the NLDAS Soil Moisture models.
Nearby, in southwestern Arkansas, hot temperatures, little rainfall, and mounting precipitation deficits warrant a 1-category degradation for Columbia and most of Union counties.

## The Southwest
Temperatures generally ranged from 4 to 8 degrees F above normal across the region during the past week. With monsoon activity lagging behind (as it did last year), dryness across the Southwest is becoming a more serious problem. In Arizona, an exceptionally dry spring and recent dry period, together with weak monsoon activity, has eroded a lot of the gains made this past winter. Prospects for significant monsoon rainfall appear to be good in the next week. The USDA/NASS reports statewide pasture and range conditions degraded this past week, from 30 percent rated good or excellent, to just 9 percent. In Flagstaff, despite unusually heavy snowfall during the past winter, the spring season was dry. Soon after the snow melted away, the forests became tinder dry very quickly and this has made the area much more vulnerable to wildfire activity. Modifications made to the Arizona drought depiction this week include an expansion of D0 dryness across central and southwestern Arizona, while the D1 area of moderate drought in northern Arizona was expanded westward.  In neighboring northwestern New Mexico, the dryness of spring persisted through June into mid-July. D0 and D1 dryness and drought renditions were expanded northward and westward across the counties of Rio Arriba, Sandoval, and San Juan. In northeastern Utah, abnormal dryness was expanded across Duchesne county, based on low stream flows, very little rainfall, and high temperatures.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (July 22-26), a band of heavy rain (2-3 inches) is expected not far south of the drought areas in the Great Lakes region, though the eastern extent of this band may reach into New York state and southern New England, helping to offset any dryness there. Generally light amounts of rain (0.50 inch or less) may fall across the mid-Atlantic states and Southeast, with more significant amounts possible for the Space Coast of Florida. In the Southwest, an expected surge in monsoonal showers and thunderstorms will be welcome, with rainfall totals across much of New Mexico, eastern and central Arizona, predicted to be between 0.50 inch and 2.0 inches. Little if any relief is anticipated for southeastern Oklahoma and adjacent portions of northeastern Texas.
For the ensuing 5 days (July 27-31), the odds favor above-median rainfall over much of the Southeast, the Southwest, Rockies, northern Plains, and Upper Mississippi Valley, as well as along the southern coast of Alaska.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-165.1264349</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-70.5908589</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>67.485814</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:49:52-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 