<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2006-01-31</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — January 31, 2006</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2006-01-31</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2006-01-31</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2006-02-02</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — January 31, 2006

## Introduction


## Alaska
Little or no precipitation fell on most of the dry region last week, although a few locales along the south-central coast reported 0.5 to 1.0 inch. D0 conditions persisted as a result of the continuing dryness, and expanded across Kodiak Island, where 3-month precipitation totals have fallen several inches below normal. It should be noted that the last 45 days have been very dry across a large part of the state, but given the relatively dry time of year, large D0 expansion does not seem warranted at this point.

## Hawaii
A Kona low brought heavy rainfall to parts of the state last week. Some of the higher peaks even reported accumulating snowfall. With precipitation totals of 8 to 12 inches falling on some locales, D0 ended across the southeastern slopes of the Big Island, and the D0 to D1 conditions across Kauai improved by 1 category, leaving D0 restricted to roughly the western half of the island.

## The High Plains and Northern Great Plains
Dry and unseasonably warm conditions again dominated the region, with only a few scattered locations reporting any measurable precipitation. This is typically a dry time of year for the region, so in general areas of dryness and drought were unchanged from last week; however, a few areas of deterioration were noted. D1AH expanded into parts of the west-central and Big Bend regions of Texas, where Lubbock, TX experienced a record 95 th consecutive day without measurable precipitation on January 30, 2006. Farther north, slightly below normal precipitation has been exacerbated by generally windy and warmer than normal weather for the past couple of months. For instance, temperatures at North Platte, NE topped 60F during a record 9 days in January 2006, exceeding their previous record by 50%. These conditions prompted the expansion of D0AH conditions into eastern Colorado and most of central and western Kansas. Elsewhere, D1AH and D2AH conditions expanded slightly in the Texas Panhandle and western Oklahoma, and D1H conditions stretched southward to include areas along the Nebraska/Kansas border, where a number of locations reported near-record low streamflows as January ended.

## The Midwest and Great Lakes Regions
As was the case in the southeastern Plains, widespread moderate to heavy precipitation fell last week on some of the most severely affected drought areas. Anywhere from 1 to locally 4 inches of precipitation fell on southeastern and east-central Iowa, northeastern Missouri, northern Illinois, and many of the areas surrounding Lake Michigan, and amounts below 0.5 inch were primarily confined to central and south-central Iowa and the western half of Wisconsin. During the week, Rockford, IL reported its wettest 24-hour period in more than 5 months, and Moline, IL reported its wettest such period in nearly 20 months. These rains succeeded in pushing 3-month totals into the near- to above-normal range, and induced improvements in both soil moisture and streamflows. Thus, D3AH was eliminated in most of northern Illinois and adjacent areas, except for a small area near and southwest of Chicago, IL where weekly precipitation totals were a bit smaller. In addition, surrounding areas of D0AH to D2AH also shrank slightly, and D0H conditions were eliminated in northeastern Wisconsin and the central Upper Peninsula of Michigan. However, despite the recent wetness, long-term precipitation totals remain well below normal across northern Illinois and adjacent Iowa. Precipitation in both Chicago, IL and Rockford, IL is more than 13 inches below normal since March 2005, and Moline, IL remains nearly 20 inches below normal for the same period.

## The Northern and Central Rockies
Although many areas across the West recorded abundant precipitation again last week, heavy precipitation missed most remaining areas of dryness and drought from Colorado and Utah northward through Idaho and western Montana. Anywhere from 1 to locally over 4 inches fell on southeastern Idaho, western Wyoming, and a few scattered locations in the dry areas of northern Montana, southern Utah, and southwestern Colorado. Most other areas reported light to moderate amounts. As a result, D0H was removed from small parts of western Wyoming, where the already-abundant snowpack continued to increase, while D0AH was expanded into part of southwestern Colorado, where snowpack and cold-season precipitation totals remained well below normal. No other changes were made in the region. Significant precipitation missed most of the dry areas in northwestern Montana, and lingering effects from several years of dryness persisted despite continued abundant snowpack in the D0H areas of eastern Idaho.

## The Southeast
Only light precipitation fell on central North Carolina and adjacent southern Virginia last week, allowing D0H conditions to expand eastward toward the Atlantic Coast and northward into a small part of southern Virginia. Conditions remained locally more severe in the upper Neuse River basin, where water supply issues persisted. Farther south, short-term dryness has increased the wildfire threat across interior southern Florida, and although the introduction of D0A conditions was not yet warranted, the region will be monitored for deterioration if dryness continues.

## The Southern and East-Central Great Plains and the Lower Mississippi Valley
For the first time in many weeks, widespread moderate to heavy precipitation fell on many of the areas experiencing extreme to exceptional drought. Between 1 and 3 inches of rain fell on a broad swath from central Texas northeastward through eastern Oklahoma, western Arkansas, and southernmost Missouri while 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches were measured across adjacent areas. Both Dallas, TX and Waco, TX received more than 1.5 inches of precipitation on January 28, 2006, which was more than their totals for the previous 88 days combined. However, because of the duration and severity of the drought in these areas, conditions improved only modestly. The D4AH region receded from its southern and northeasternmost reaches, and conditions improved to D2AH in relatively small parts of north-central and south-central Arkansas, northwestern Louisiana, adjacent northeastern Texas, and a small part of central Texas. In addition, the northern extents of D0AH to D2AH conditions in south-central Missouri and adjacent Arkansas retreated slightly southward.
Farther east, similarly widespread moderate to heavy precipitation fell on western Tennessee, the eastern fringes of Arkansas, central Alabama, and most of Mississippi and Louisiana away from the Gulf Coast. These amounts fell on areas that have experienced several wet spells during the past few weeks, so improvement was a bit more robust than in areas farther west. In general, last weeks D0AH to D1AH conditions improved by 1 category, ending abnormal dryness in most of western Tennessee, extreme eastern Arkansas, northwestern and upper southern Mississippi, and northeastern Louisiana.
In contrast, only scattered light and isolated moderate precipitation totals were reported in the central Kansas and Oklahoma, southern Texas, and the central Gulf Coast region. As a result, D0AH to D3AH conditions in these areas expanded slightly.

## The Southwest
Dry and warm conditions, featuring meager snowfall totals, continued to plague Arizona, New Mexico, and the southern fringes of Utah and Colorado. A few areas recorded 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches of precipitation for the week in northern parts of the region and in east-central Arizona, but only scattered light showers were noted elsewhere. As a result, dryness and drought persisted or intensified last week. A new area of D3AH was analyzed in part of southern Arizona, where 6-month precipitation totals are now 4.5 to 7.5 inches below normal. In addition, D1AH and D2AH conditions expanded westward in Arizona, and eastward in central and southern New Mexico. The persistently dry conditions set a record in Phoenix, AZ. January 30, 2006 marked their 104 th consecutive day without precipitation, besting their old record by 3 days. Farther north, the combination or warm and dry conditions kept measurable snowfall out of Flagstaff, AZ this winter until January 15, which was 8 days later than their previous record late date of first measurable winter snowfall. In the higher elevations, most sites in central and southern New Mexico and Arizona have recorded only 15% to 45% of normal precipitation since October 1, 2005, and snowpack water content stood at only 5% to 25% of normal at most locations as January ended.

## Forecast
With respect to areas currently experiencing dryness and drought, the next 5 days (Feburary 2  6, 2006) should bring moderate to heavy precipitation to the central Gulf Coast region (1 to locally 2 inches) and to western Wyoming and adjacent Idaho (0.5 to 1.5 inches). Light to moderate precipitation is forecast in eastern Texas, the remainder of Louisiana, the southeastern half of Arkansas, and most of Kentucky. Elsewhere, little precipitation is forecast, if any. Meanwhile, temperature should again average above normal across most of the contiguous 48 states, with near-normal temperatures restricted to the Southeast and southern Ohio Valley. Daily highs should average 9F to 15F above normal in the Southwest, southern and western Texas, the central Plains, and part of northwestern Montana. The ensuing 5 days (February 7  11, 2006) are expected to mark the beginning of a significant shift in the weather pattern. The odds favor below-normal precipitation for most areas currently experiencing dryness and drought, except in the Southwest, southern and western Texas, the northern Plains, and the northern half of the Great Lakes region. During this period, the odds favor colder than normal conditions across the southern High Plains and in all areas east of a line from the central Texas Panhandle northeastward to the north-central Great Lakes region. Above-normal temperatures are only favored in South Dakota, Montana, and northeastern Wyoming.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-77.4710781</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>65.7111933</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:51:50-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 