<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2001-11-20</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brad Rippey</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>U.S. Department of Agriculture</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — November 20, 2001</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2001-11-20</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2001-11-20</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2001-11-21</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — November 20, 2001

## Introduction


## Hawaii and Puerto Rico
In Hawaii, mostly light showers were observed, following recent, drought-easing rainfall. Some of the weeks heaviest rain fell across portions of the Big Island from November 13-15, when the 48-hour total at Laupahoehoe reached 2.81 inches. Meanwhile, following last weeks heavy rainfall in Puerto Rico, more typical showers returned to the island. Abnormal dryness (D0) persisted along Puerto Ricos southern coast.

## The East
A dry weather pattern that developed around September 1 has intensified in recent weeks, resulting in escalating drought effectssuch as diminishing reservoir supplies, wildfire activity, and poor winter wheat establishmentduring a period in which symptoms of drought are often masked by cool weather and diminishing agricultural and municipal water requirements. For example, the Delaware River Basin (DRB) storage area, which provides roughly half of New York Citys water, has experienced sharp declines in water supplies since late summer. While DRB declines are normal through October, the system typically begins to experience recharge during November due to autumn storminess, decreasing water demands, and lower evaporation rates. This year, however, the DRB has continued to lose water at an alarming rate (an average of more than one billion gallons per day since November 1), falling to 77.2 billion gallons on November 19more than 81 billion gallons below normal and nearly 145 billion gallons below the storage one year ago. Streamflows have also plunged this autumn along the Atlantic Seaboard. For example, the U.S. Geological Survery indicated that 69% of the river gauges in the New England drainage areas were recording in lowest tenth of historical flows for November 19, compared with 15% just 11 weeks earlier, on September 3. Similarly low flows and autumn declines were also noted on river gauges in the Mid-Atlantic region (56% on November 19 and 4% on September 3) and the South Atlantic-Gulf region (56 and 15%). Finally, wildfires continued to burn significant acreage in eastern Kentucky (more than 90,000 acres, according to the National Interagency Fire Center on November 19) and adjacent states, while winter wheat in North Carolina (36% very poor to poor on November 18, according to USDAs National Agricultural Statistics Service) and surrounding areas remained in need of moisture for proper establishment. As a result, moderate drought (D1) was expanded to include most areas from Georgia to New England, while severe drought (D2) was increased across the Southeast, particularly in the Carolinas.

## The Plains and Midwest
Warm, dry autumn weather has caused a gradual expansion of abnormally dry (D0) conditions across the northern Low Plains and upper Midwest. According to the Iowa climatologist, statewide temperatures averaged more than 11 F above normal during the first half of November. In addition, no measurable precipitation fell in Sioux City, Iowa, from November 1-19. The warmth and dryness compare to 1999, when Iowa readings averaged nearly 7 F above normal for the entire month, setting a state record. Farther west, Rapid City, South Dakota, noted 15 days with highs at or above 60 F during the first 19 days of November, approaching the stations November record of 16 such days, set in 1904 and 1999. Meanwhile on the High Plains of Montana and portions of Wyoming, warm, dry, breezy weather maintained moderate to extreme drought conditions (D1 to D3). Farther south, conditions contrasted sharply from mild and dry on the central Plains to suddenly wet on the southern Plains. Heavy rain developed across western Texas on November 14 and expanded across adjoining areas during the next two days. A monthly rainfall record was broken in Lubbock, Texas, where 2.87 inches fell from November 14-17, and approached at the Bergstrom A.F.B. near Austin, Texas, where 9.62 inches fell. Much of Bergstroms rain (8.68 inches) fell on November 15, marking its wettest day in nearly 27 years. Another Austin weather station, Camp Mabry, netted 7.55 inches on November 15, its wettest day in 80 years, since 15 inches fell on September 9, 1921. Abnormal dryness (D0) was erased across portions of central Texas, while varying degrees of drought (D1 to D3, or moderate to extreme drought) were reduced across the remainder of central, southern, and western Texas, as well as southeastern New Mexico and southwestern Oklahoma. Winter wheat in Texas exhibited some improvement, from 44% very poor to poor on November 11 to 38% on November 18. Oklahoma also noted slight improvement in wheat condition from last week, from 52 to 48% very poor to poor. In contrast, Montanas wheat declined to 32% very poor to poor, off from 26% on November 11. Farther east, a slight expansion of abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) was placed in an area centered on northeastern Arkansas.

## The West
Drier weather returned to California, but heavy precipitation continued in the Pacific Northwest, primarily west of the Cascades. Especially heavy rain fell in western Washington on November 14, when daily-record totals were observed in locations such as Olympia (3.64 inches) and Seattle (2.61 inches). Wildfire and agricultural concerns have diminished across the Pacific Northwest in recent weeks, resulting in an adjustment of the line designating hydrological drought (W). In addition, areas of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) were reduced slightly west of the Cascades.

## Forecast
Weather features to watch in the next five-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: 1) Dry weather is forecast to prevail in the East until the weekend, when scattered, light showers may provide limited drought relief; 2) Mild, dry weather will persist on the Plains through weeks end; 3) Heavy precipitation will be confined to the West Coast States, primarily in and west of the Cascades and Sierra Nevada, but some rain and snow showers are forecast to reach the Great Basin and northern and central Rockies; 4) The NWS 6-10 day outlook for November 26-30 indicates that a major winter storm will track from the Southwest to the Great Lakes region. Widespread precipitation is likely along and near the storms path, including possible heavy snow from the central and southern Rockies to the north-central U.S. In addition, showers and thunderstorms may develop across the South and Midwest. However, the storm will contribute to the evolution of a drier weather pattern in the Northwest, largely bypass the northern High Plains, and is not likely to produce a long-duration, soaking rainfall in the middle and southern Atlantic Coast States.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.78648281615</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.9510718701392</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.8841923373686</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0035990521218</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:36:49-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 