<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2009-05-12</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Miskus</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Matthew Rosencrans</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Anthony Artusa</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — May 12, 2009</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2009-05-12</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2009-05-12</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2009-05-14</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — May 12, 2009

## Introduction
During May 5-11,  an upper-air ridge (high pressure) over the Southwest brought very warm and dry weather to most of the region during the week, while upper-air troughs (low pressure) off the Pacific Northwest Coast and over the East contributed to stormy conditions. Rainfall totals in excess of two inches were observed in a broad, sweeping arc stretching from the South Central Plains to the lower Ohio and Tennessee Valleys, northeastward into New England.  Additional rains fell over the Carolinas, parts of the Northwest, and northwestern Corn Belt. The stormy conditions brought rainfall maxima of near 12 inches to the ArkLaTex.  In contrast, hot and dry weather was recorded in peninsular Florida, southern Texas, and the southwestern quadrant of the Nation.

## Alaska and Hawaii
Although Hawaii has entered their normal dry season, some areas have been much drier than normal.  This was most prevalent on the leeward side of Oahu, prompting the introduction of D0 conditions.

## Florida
The dry season continued to be abnormally dry and hot.  Little or no rainfall and temperatures 6-10 degrees F above normal for the week exacerbated the drought conditions, prompting an expansion of D3 to just north of the Space Coast.  D2 was expanded to include west-central Florida as conditions deteriorated further, reflected by additional US Geological Survey (USGS) stream flow measurements dropping to the lowest 2 percentile.  Precipitation totals for the southern two-thirds of Florida over the previous six months were less than 50 percent of normal.  South of a West-East line from Levy to Saint-Johns counties, Keetch-Byrum Drought Index (KBDI) values were greater than 550 with maximum values over the central Everglades topping out above 750.  As of May 12, 5 large incidents across Florida are being monitored by the National Interagency Fire Center while 63 new, smaller wildfires broke out over last weekend (Florida Division of Forestry).

## Midwest
Another week of repetitive precipitation events alleviated the abnormal dryness in southwest Ohio.  1-2 inches of rain (0.5-1 inch gain on climatology) across southern Minnesota and southern Wisconsin led to a small trimming of the southern flank of the area in Minnesota/Wisconsin.  The Minnesota NASS reports adequate top soil moisture in the newly trimmed areas.  Stream hydrology in those improved areas was in the historical mid-range.  Soil moisture and precipitation anomalies supported keeping D1/D2 in northern Wisconsin as weekly rainfall amounts were generally under 0.5 inch.

## Northeast, Mid-Atlantic, and Carolinas
Another week of widespread moderate to heavy rains (2-4 inches) in the southern Appalachians, most of Virginia, and the I-95 corridor from Maryland to Massachusetts prompted a 1-category improvement for most of the area.  Exceptions included northern Pennsylvania and southern New York where rainfall totals were less (0.5-1 inch).  The remaining D0 is further supported by 7-, 14-, and 28-day average stream flows remaining in the lower 10th percentile.  For the Carolinas, D0 remained along the Eastern Seaboard due to larger, long-term deficits (90-day departures of -3 to -6 inches, 6-month departures of -4 to -8 inches, and 1-year departures exceeding -12 inches). In the southern Appalachians, 1-, 7-, 14-, and 28-day average stream flows ending May 11 were finally back to near normal.  Lingering long-term rainfall deficits prompted the retention of D0(H) across the southern Appalachians (8-12 inch deficits for previous 12-months).

## The Plains
Recent rains (0.5-1 inch) and fair topsoil moisture supported the removal of D0 from North Dakota.  In the central Plains, the southern portions of the D0 area previously in central Kansas were eliminated due to approximately 2 inches of rainfall.  To the north, however, below normal precipitation (less than 0.4 inches) maintained the abnormal dryness across eastern Nebraska and extreme northern Kansas.  This D0 area reflects 90-day deficits of 3-6 inches.
In the southern Plains, an analysis of newly available data revealed a complicated picture.  In general, improvements were made to southwest Oklahoma and northern and central Texas with further deterioration over southern Texas.  In southwest Oklahoma, 1-category improvement along the border with Texas was supported by recent 1-2 inch rainfall totals with soil moisture levels now at or above normal.  The only Oklahoma reservoirs not in flood control operations are in southwest, but these are used for irrigation and are normally drawn down in the spring.  Arbuckle Lake in Murray County (south-central Oklahoma) was setting record lows three weeks ago but now has 19% of its flood pool filled. The exception is Roger Mills County which missed out on the latest rains.  Little or no rain in the Oklahoma Panhandle did not support any improvement there.
The convective nature of the recent precipitation over Texas led to a complex depiction.  Newly created SPI blend products from Texas A&amp;amp;M supported improvement along the Red River, a thin strip through the center of the state, and the eastern periphery of the previously indicated drought areas.  The 14- and 28-day stream flows indicated the unique pattern of recent wetness in isolated areas, which is reflected in the very tight gradients of drought conditions across central Texas.  The holes in the drought pattern were supported by isolated heavy thunderstorms that recently hit McCulloch, Pecos, and Crockett counties.
A 1-category deterioration (now D3/D4(A)) was rendered over south Texas as most areas received little to no rainfall (less than 0.1 inch) over the past month.  The lack of rainfall, combined with daily high temperatures around the century mark and average weekly temperature 8-14 degrees F above normal served to worsen conditions.

## The West
Recent storminess (0.5-2.0 inches) in Montana provided fodder for improving the drought conditions. The D0 area was removed from eastern Montana and reduced in coverage in north-central Montana. The same system also dropped 1-3 inches of precipitation over western Oregon and western Washington.  Those rains alleviated much of the drought in that region. The exceptions were the Olympic Peninsula and extreme northern Cascades, where the basin average snow water content was 77 and 85 percent of normal, respectively, and water-year-to-date precipitation remained at 85 and 86 percent of normal, respectively.  In central Idaho, 1-2 inches of precipitation and May 1 Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) values near zero supported the removal of D1, and additional reduction of D0 southward.  In contrast, current SWSI for the Bear River and Owyhee basins of -2.4 indicated D1 conditions in southeast and southwest Idaho, respectively. With recent short-term wetness across the northern half of the West and most pasture and range lands rated in good or excellent condition according to National Agricultural Statistic Services (NASS)/USDA, the impacts were deemed to be long-term (H) only.
Farther south, no rainfall, weekly temperatures 8 to 12 degrees F above normal, and highs in the 100s further deteriorated conditions in Arizona and New Mexico.  This was depicted by the expansion of D1(A) into northeast Arizona and D1(A) and D2(A) into central New Mexico. NASS/USDA pasture and range lands were rated 61, 60, and 49 percent poor or very poor in New Mexico, California and Arizona, respectively. The rest of the West remained status quo.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (May 14-18), a storm system in the Midwest will bring showers and thunderstorms to the eastern third of the country.  Mild weather over the East will be replaced by lower temperatures late in the period. On Thursday, another storm system will approach the Pacific Northwest and produce rain and higher-elevation snows. This system will track rapidly eastward across the northern US, accompanied by showers and thunderstorms.  Beneficial rains are expected across the drought areas of peninsular Florida, the mid-Atlantic, Wisconsin, northern and central Texas, and the Olympic Peninsula of Washington.  Dry and warm weather will persist over California, Great Basin, and Southwest.
The Climate Prediction Center 6-10 day forecast (May 19-23) calls for above-normal precipitation over the Atlantic Coastal States (including Florida), and from Colorado northeastward to the upper Midwest. Subnormal precipitation is expected across the West, and from the southern Great Plains northeastward into the eastern Great Lakes region. Warmer than usual weather is forecast for the western half of the Nation, while subnormal readings are predicted for the Southeast and upper Midwest.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-158.2717276</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-73.3338998</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>62.1502622</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:55:26-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 