<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-05-31</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brad Rippey</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>U.S. Department of Agriculture</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — May 31, 2005</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-05-31</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-05-31</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-06-02</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — May 31, 2005

## Introduction


## Alaska
Although no abnormal dryness was introduced, short-term precipitation deficits continued to gradually mount in parts of southern Alaska. April-May precipitation totaled 0.45 inch (37 percent of normal) in Anchorage and 10.14 inches (49 percent) in Yakutat. Juneau netted only 0.89 inch (26 percent of normal) during May, narrowly missing its May 2004 record-low total of 0.84 inch.

## Hawaii
Warm, mostly dry weather persisted in Hawaii, where daily average temperatures were above normal on every day in May at locations such as Lihue, Kauai, and Hilo, on the Big Island. May temperatures averaged 2.2 degrees F above normal in Lihue and Hilo, and 3.8 degrees F above normal in Honolulu, Oahu. Honolulus monthly average temperature of 81.3 degrees F smashed its May 1970 record of 80.2 degrees F. Honolulu also set or tied 15 daily-record highs in a 25-day period from May 4-28. In addition, April- May rainfall totaled just 0.51 inch (21 percent of normal) in Kahului, Maui; 0.91 inch (48 percent) in Honolulu; and 9.92 inches (48 percent) in Hilo. Abnormal dryness (D0) was present across most of Hawaii, with moderate drought (D1) continuing on the Big Island due to concerns about wildfire activity and water supplies for those reliant upon rain-fed catchment systems.

## The Northeast
Short-term dryness (D0) continued to expand across parts of New York and Pennsylvania, despite below-normal temperatures. May rainfall totaled 0.60 inch (18 percent of normal) in the New York cities of Buffalo and Syracuse. It was the driest May on record in Syracuse, edging the 1977 standard of 0.75 inch. On May 29, USDA rated topsoil moisture 39 percent very short to short in Pennsylvania and 34 percent in New York.

## The Plains and Midwest
Showers and thunderstorms dotted the central and southern Plains, helping to stabilize crop conditions. Nevertheless, winter wheat was rated 24 percent very poor to poor in Oklahoma on May 29, along with 21 percent in Nebraska, 20 percent in Colorado, and 19 percent in Kansas and Texas. Some of the recent declines in wheat condition were attributed to disease rather than dryness. Slight improvements in topsoil moisture were noted in Kansas (from 42 percent very short to short on May 22 to 33 percent on May 29) and Oklahoma (65 to 56 percent). Meanwhile, 27 percent of Texas ranges and pastures were rated in very poor to poor condition on May 29, up from 19 percent two weeks earlier. Farther northeast, dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) intensified from the middle Mississippi Valley into the Great Lakes region. D1 was expanded to include a broader area from central Missouri to southwestern Lower Michigan. Illinois corn, rated 71 percent good to excellent on May 22, slipped to 60 percent good to excellent by May 29. Peoria, Illinois, experienced its second-driest May on record (0.69 inch, or 17 percent of normal), behind only 0.47 inch in 1934. St. Louis, Missouri, reported its third-driest spring on record. Selected spring (March-May) precipitation totals included 2.96 inches (26 percent of normal) in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma; 4.16 inches (39 percent) in Peoria; 4.22 inches (45 percent) in Grand Rapids, Michigan; 4.25 inches (42 percent) in South Bend, Indiana; and 4.42 inches (39 percent) in St. Louis. Seasonal (March-May) dryness was also noted in lingering D0A areas of the eastern Dakotas, including the South Dakota cities of Huron (3.85 inches, or 55 percent of normal) and Aberdeen (3.15 inches, or 54 percent).

## The South
In late May, mostly dry weather prevailed in the southern Mid-Atlantic piedmont, leaving intact an area of abnormal dryness (D0). May rainfall totaled less than 2 inches in much of the dry area. Farther west, much more expansive dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) covered many areas west of the Appalachians. Conditions worsened generally north of a line splitting Arkansas and stretching eastward across the northern portions of Mississippi and Alabama. A large area of moderate drought (D1) was introduced in northeastern Arkansas, northern Mississippi, western Tennessee, and the Missouri Bootheel. In fact, it was the driest May on record in locations such as Jonesboro, Arkansas (0.22 inch, or 4 percent of normal), and Jackson, Tennessee (0.42 inch, or 7 percent). In northern Mississippi, Tupelo completed its second-driest May (0.88 inch, or 15 percent of normal) and third-driest spring (8.73 inches, or 51 percent). USDA rated topsoil moisture 78 percent very short to short in Arkansas, along with 66 percent in Alabama, 60 percent in Missouri, and 42 percent in Tennessee. Farther south, showers and thunderstorms chipped away at dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) in the western and central Gulf Coast States, especially along and near the Mississippi River south of the Arkansas/Mississippi/Louisiana triple point. Nevertheless, by May 29, Louisiana topsoil moisture was still rated 84 percent very short to short, while 40 percent of the states pastures were in very poor to poor condition. Farther west, rains largely bypassed the Arklatex region, where moderate drought (D1) bridged across northwestern Louisiana. Meanwhile, heavy showers pounded the formerly dry (D0) area in western Texas, significantly reducing its area of coverage. In the lower Rio Grande Valley, where some moderate to severe drought persisted, January-May rainfall totaled just 2.79 inches (35 percent of normal) in Brownsville and 3.45 inches (36 percent) in Harlingen.

## The West
In late May, hot weather subsided across the Southwest but briefly shifted into the Northwest. Rivers in some Western lowlands, especially those downstream of abundant high-elevation snow packs, continued to run high. For example, the Humboldt River near Imlay, Nevada, climbed 2.25 feet above flood stage (and continued to slowly rise) on the morning of June 1, just 0.75 foot shy of the May 1984 record crest. Parts of Arizona experienced an unusually heavy May rainfall, although the precipitation was not significant enough to warrant a change in the Southwestern depiction of lingering hydrological dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) due to multi-year precipitation deficits. Tucson, Arizona, measured rainfall totaling 0.44 inch on May 27, representing its tenth-wettest May day on record. Farther north, Northwestern ranges and pastures were one of the few remaining agricultural indicators of long-term drought, following a wet spring. On May 29, USDA reported that 21 percent of the rangeland and pastures in Washington and Montana were in very poor to poor condition.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (June 2-6), a blocking high-pressure system over the nations northeastern quadrant will gradually loosen its grip, allowing some showers to spread as far east as the Midwest and as far north as the Mid-Atlantic States. However, the most significant rainfall (1 to 2 inches or more) is expected across the Southeast and the upper Midwest. As a result, widespread relief from dryness or drought is not likely west of the Mississippi Delta or from the middle Mississippi Valley northeastward into the Great Lakes and northern Mid-Atlantic States. Meanwhile, cool, showery weather across the northern High Plains and the Northwest will maintain generally favorable topsoil moisture levels, in spite of underlying hydrological drought. The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for June 7-11 calls for wetter-than-normal conditions in a broad area from the northern half of the Intermountain West eastward through the Plains, Midwest, and interior South. Drier-than-normal weather in areas affected by dryness or drought will be confined to southern Texas. Cooler-than-normal conditions are likely in the West while above-normal temperatures are expected in most of Texas south of the Panhandle, and from the northern and east-central Great Plains eastward through the upper Midwest, Great Lakes region, and northern Mid-Atlantic.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-73.955198</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0018155</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T01:10:05-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 