<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-04-20</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Anthony Artusa</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — April 20, 2010</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-04-20</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-04-20</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-04-22</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — April 20, 2010

## Introduction


## Alaska and Hawaii
Once again, the interior of Alaska has received little to no precipitation, while the Kenai Peninsula to the south has received in excess of 2 inches. Stream flows in Alaska are robust because of the rapid melting of the subnormal snow pack resulting from warmer temperatures. Therefore, no changes were made to the drought depiction in Alaska. In Hawaii, light rains (0.30 inch or less) were reported over the drought areas, with 2.2 inches indicated over eastern Maui, which is not in drought. No adjustments were deemed necessary this week for the Hawaiian Islands.

## Great Lakes Region and Ohio and Tennessee Valleys
Light to moderate rains (0.5 to 1 inch) fell across parts of northwestern Wisconsin, with very light amounts (up to 0.25 inch) reported over northern lower Michigan and northeastern Minnesota. Up to a half-inch of rain fell over upper Michigan. Above-normal average temperatures (8 to 12 degrees F), little rainfall, near-record to record low USGS stream flow levels (daily, 7-, 14-, and 28-day averages), and very low soil moisture percentiles contributed to a two-county eastward extension of D2 conditions in upper Michigan, and the introduction of D1 conditions in northeastern Minnesota, as well as slight westward expansion of the D0 area from northeastern into north-central Minnesota. The impact designation of AH introduced last week reflects the growing short-term dryness in combination with the longer-term hydrological drought.  Light rains (up to 0.5 inch) fell across the band of abnormal dryness (D0) from northeast Ohio northeastward to northern New York, and over northern West Virginia. This continues the springtime trend of subnormal weekly precipitation, while temperatures averaged 2 to 5 degrees F above normal. Most USGS stream flows in the area have dropped below the 10th percentile, especially during the past two weeks. Based on a variety of drought indicators, moderate drought (D1) conditions were introduced to northwestern Pennsylvania, and D0 was re-established in far western New York, in the Buffalo-Niagara area.
In the lower Ohio and Tennessee Valleys, very light rains (up to 0.25 inch) fell, with much of the region receiving no rain at all.  Deficits between 5 and 10 inches have accumulated over the past 60-days in central sections of Kentucky and Tennessee. Temperatures averaged 6 to 9 degrees F warmer than normal, with daytime highs easily exceeding 80 degrees during the week. The D0 area in central Kentucky and Tennessee was expanded to be consistent with recent dryness, as was the D1 area in west-central Kentucky. The impact label 'A' emphasizes short-term dryness as the growing season is underway.

## The Northwest and northern Rockies
Light precipitation (less than 0.50 inch) fell east of the Cascades in Washington and Oregon during the past week. Light to moderate precipitation (0.50 to 1 inch) was reported in northern and central Idaho, with generally light (less than 0.50 inch) precipitation occurring over southern Idaho. Western and southwestern Montana received up to 3 inches of precipitation, with an inch or less reported in western Wyoming. Light precipitation (0.50 inch or less) fell over the High plains of eastern Montana and Wyoming. Minor adjustments were made in the drought depiction across both Montana and Wyoming, with the most noticeable modification being the removal of D0(A) in north-central Montana (due to 1 to 2 inches of precipitation). Temperatures across the Northwest and northern Rockies averaged between 2 and 6 degrees F above normal, contributing to spring snow melt. The average basin water year-to-date (WYTD) precipitation (October 1, 2009 - April 20, 2010), was between 61 to 86 percent of average across much of the northern and central Rockies, and a bit better (74 to 94 percent of average) across the Cascades. No modifications were made west of the northern Rockies.

## The South and southern Plains
Little to no rain fell across southern Arkansas, western Mississippi, southeastern Alabama, and northeastern Louisiana during the past week. Although the winter months were quite wet, this spring has brought minimal rainfall, with 30 and 60-day precipitation 25 to 50 percent of normal across much of this area. This dryness, in addition to stream flows below the 10th percentile (current, 7-, 14-, and 28-days), led to the creation of a moderate drought (D1A) area over northeastern Louisiana, and expansion of D0 conditions across extreme southeastern Texas, northern Mississippi, northern and southern portions of Alabama, and the 3 westernmost counties in the Florida Panhandle (Escambia, Santa Rosa and Okaloosa). With the growing season well underway, planted crops will soon require moisture for germination and establishment. In the south-central Plains, widespread rainfall amounts of 1 to 3 inches in western Oklahoma resulted in the removal of much of the D0 area introduced there last week. Only a small area of abnormally dry conditions (D0(H)) remains in southwestern Oklahoma, to reflect watershed/irrigation issues related to Lake Lugert, especially for Greer, Harmon, Jackson, Kiowa and western Tillman counties. Rainfall amounts up to an inch fell across south-central Kansas, which help to offset the meager 60-day precipitation (25 to 50 percent of normal). Due to recent precipitation, the small D0 areas in far western, and extreme north-central Texas were eliminated.

## The Southwest
Little to no precipitation fell over Arizona, Nevada and southern Utah during the past week. Light to moderate precipitation (0.50 to 1 inch) was reported over northern Utah, Colorado and New Mexico, with a few scattered locations receiving between 1 to 2 inches. Minor adjustments were made to the drought depiction in southwestern Arizona, where abnormally dry (D0) conditions were removed in southwest Maricopa and northwest Pima Counties. Despite the recent lack of rainfall, the lower Gila River is flowing well, and good low desert green-up indicates sufficient soil moisture. Current basin-average snow water content (SWC) in the elevated Mogollon Rim area runs between 83 and 282 percent of normal, after a favorably wet winter season. No changes were made to the drought depiction in California. The D2 area in far northeastern California received little if any precipitation, while the precipitation further south started near or just after 5 am PDT, April 20th and will be accounted for in next week's Drought Monitor.

## Forecast
For the ensuing 5 days (April 22-26), a storm system will bring light to moderate amounts of rain and mountain snow (0.50 to 1.5 inch liquid equivalents) to much of the West early in the period, and trigger showers and thunderstorms thereafter as it slowly moves eastward to the Atlantic coast. Rainfall should be heaviest (2 to 4 inches) across the lower Mississippi, Tennessee and lower Ohio Valleys, providing much needed relief for the drought areas. Beneficial rainfall amounts between 0.50 and 1.50 inches are predicted for the areas of abnormal dryness and moderate drought across the eastern Great Lakes region. Unfortunately, little or no rain is forecast for the drought areas of the upper Midwest and upper Great Lakes region. Although temperatures will start off relatively mild in the East, near to below-normal temperatures will overspread the country from west to east.
For the 6 to 10-day outlooks (April 27 - May 1), above-median precipitation is predicted across much of the West and Northeast. Below-median precipitation is expected over most of the Mississippi Valley and eastern portions of the Great Plains. Below-normal temperatures will occur across much of the East and Southwest, while above-normal temperatures can be expected across the northern Rockies and High Plains.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-161.9028249</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-74.110709</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>67.485814</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:48:51-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 