<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2002-10-22</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Miskus</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — October 22, 2002</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2002-10-22</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2002-10-22</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2002-10-24</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — October 22, 2002

## Introduction


## Hawaii
Widespread, heavy showers drenched the Hawaiian Islands from Maui westward, with the lowest totals on the Big Island. The greatest amounts fell on areas with abnormal dryness or moderate drought (Lanai, Molokai, western Oahu, northern Maui), alleviating all drought except for some lingering long-term dryness - D0(W) - on western Molokai. From October 14-18, selected 96-hour totals included 8.67" at Lanai City, Lanai; 6.48" at Kamalo, Molokai; 6.24" at Lahainaluna, Maui; and 4.23" at Waipio, Oahu. Eastern Kauai also received 3 to 4 inches of rain while 1-2" fell on the western Big Island.

## New England, Mid-Atlantic, and the Southeast
Most of the Eastern Seaboard experienced another week of widespread showers and thunderstorms, continuing a pattern of beneficial precipitation that commenced in mid-August in the Southeast, and mid-September in the Northeast. This week's heaviest rains (2 to 4 inches) fell on the western core drought region (D2-D3), namely the Appalachians and areas just to the east, while 1.5-2.5" of rain further improved conditions across most of New England. In addition, declining temperatures (that also averaged 2 to 6F below normal), greatly-reduced evapotranspiration, and a steady, prolonged rain event further aided moisture recharge. Elsewhere, lesser amounts (0.5-1") were measured along the southern Atlantic coastal areas, maintaining conditions there. During the past 30 days, much of the region has reported over 150% of normal rainfall, translating to surpluses between 2 and 6 inches.
As previously mentioned in past National Drought Summaries, short-term moisture conditions are in surplus, but long-term deficits still remained, especially since September 2001, and in some cases, several years previously (to 1998), adversely impacting large river, reservoir, and well levels. As a result, mandatory water restrictions remain in effect for many New England, mid-Atlantic, and Southeast communities until a prolonged improvement occurs in the aforementioned water sources.
With that said, however, 7-day average mid-October USGS streamflow levels have gradually responded to increased rainfall since early September throughout the entire region, and are now generally in the near to above-normal percentile range. In mid-September, many 7-day average USGS streamflows were at record or near-record low rates (&amp;lt;10th percentile), indicative of severe long-term drought. However, when compared to most recent 7-day average streamflows (ending Oct. 21) in the lower 10th percentile, the differences were dramatic---Alabama (33% vs 0%); Georgia (66% vs 5%); (SC-not available); North Carolina (61% vs 1%); Virginia (71% vs 12%); Maryland (49% vs 3%); Pennsylvania (43% vs 1%); New York (34% vs 1%); and Massachusetts (58% vs 0%). Even in Maine, which had missed most of the recent significant precipitation, the near to record low streamflows dropped from 55% to 8%, confined mostly to far northern locations. Guarded optimism best describes the outlook for further improvement as this area heads into its normal recharge season.

## The Ohio Valley and Great Lakes
Much colder air pushed into the region, producing weekly departures between -7 and -12F, and widespread frosts and freezes. A vigorous storm system dropped southeastward out of Canada into the Midwest on Friday and Saturday, bringing light to moderate precipitation (0.5 to 1.5 inches) to parts of the central and eastern Corn Belt, deleting abnormal dryness in eastern Missouri, central Illinois, and southwestern Indiana. A small portion of southern Illinois remained in D0 as totals were lower (&amp;lt;0.4"). In extreme southeastern Ohio, moderate to heavy rains (1-2") from the Eastern Seaboard system alleviated abnormal dryness.
In contrast, less than 0.2 inches fell on northern Illinois as 30 and 90-day deficits (1 to 3 inches) grew, expanding abnormal dryness, while another week of light precipitation (0.2-0.4") pushed southeastern Michigan into moderate drought.
With the onset of cooler autumn weather, the wildfire(F) impact was removed, although the agriculture(A) impacts remained while winter wheat emerges and pastures continue to grow. Short-term deficits have caused very poor to poor pasture conditions in 50% of Ohio, 44% of Indiana, 36% of Illinois, and 34% of Michigan, according to NASS/USDA.

## The Plains and the West
Little or no precipitation fell on the western half of the Nation, with subnormal readings (weekly departures) in the Rockies (-2 to -6F), Plains (-4 to -10F), and coastal California (-2 to -4F), and unseasonably mild weather (+3 to +6F; highs in the 80's) in the Intermountain West. Although September and October are normally relatively dry months in the West, the Pacific Northwest usually receives 8-15% of its annual precipitation during these two months. Since September 1, very dry weather has covered this area, resulting in short-term deficiencies. Selected sites with observed versus normal 9/1-10/21 precipitation (in) included: Eureka, CA 0.19/2.01; Medford, OR 0.70/1.44; Pendleton, OR 0.33/1.16; Eugene, OR 1.24/3.16; Astoria, OR 1.98/5.72; Olympia, WA 0.91/4.31; Seattle, WA 0.89/3.38; and Wenatchee, WA 0.17/0.63. As a result, atypical short-term dryness - D0(A) - was expanded into western Oregon and southwestern Washington, reflected in very poor to poor pasture conditions (OR 71%, WA 55%, CA 95%) and very short to short topsoil moisture (OR 88%, WA 63%), according to NASS/USDA. Elsewhere, with the onset of cooler autumn weather, the wildfire(F) impact was limited to California and Arizona, while the hydrological(W) and agricultural(A) impacts, namely winter wheat and pastures, covered remaining areas. In central Arizona, the hydrology(W) line edged southward as the Roosevelt Reservoir stood at 11% capacity, just above its Oct. 21 record low, while the Horseshoe Reservoir on the Verde River was at 31 acre-feet (capacity is 110,000 acre-feet).
In the southern Great Plains, a developing storm system triggered numerous showers and thunderstorms on Friday and Saturday, including localized flooding in northern Texas. In Texas, the northeastern Panhandle received 1.5 to 3 inches of rain, erasing abnormal dryness, while the lower Rio Grande Valley recorded 2 to 3 inches, alleviating moderate drought as only hydrological dryness - D0(W) - remained.

## Forecast
Forecasted conditions that may affect current areas of dryness and drought during October 24-28 includes a persistent upper-air pattern of ridging (high pressure) in the West and troughing (low pressure) in the East. 1) This should keep the southern halves of the Rockies and Plains, the Southeast, lower Ohio Valley, and Atlantic Coast States unsettled and cool, with much-below normal temperatures in the Nation's mid-section; 2) the Far West mostly dry with seasonable temperatures; and 3) light precipitation and well-below normal readings across the northern Rockies and Plains, upper Midwest, and Great Lakes region.
The NWS 6 to 10-day outlook (October 29-November 2) features surplus precipitation in the Plains and Atlantic Coast States, while drier-than-usual conditions persist in the northern Rockies and middle Mississippi Valley. Subnormal temperatures are expected from the Rockies eastward, while above-normal readings are forecast in Washington,southern California, and southern Florida.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.306273576829</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-66.9540017338536</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>21.0801502969855</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0018155336346</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:34:01-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 