<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-06-08</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brian Fuchs</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — June 08, 2010</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-06-08</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-06-08</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-06-10</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — June 08, 2010

## Introduction


## Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico
Another dry week and steady reports of drought impacts on range/pasture conditions, livestock health, water supply and fires have led to further deterioration in the form of at least D1 across all of the Big Island now that it covers the windward side. D3 has also spread across the southeast portion of the Big Island as well. Windward Maui and Oahu are now both covered with D0 as well.

## Mid-Atlantic
The recent wet weather pattern (2-4 inches) has led to a breaking up of the D0 found along the coastal reaches of the Carolinas. Pockets of dryness remain, however, as we head into summer.

## Southern Plains and Gulf Coast
The coastal areas received some generous rainfall amounts (2 to 5 inches) from south-central Texas to south Florida.  As a result, most of the changes this week are reflected through improvements to the map.  D0 and D1 have retreated northward in both southeastern Texas and southern Louisiana. Not all shared in the recent rains, though, as D0-D1 both pushed northward into more of Arkansas, northeastern Texas (into the Dallas-Fort Worth region) and even into southeastern Oklahoma. In addition, a new area of D1 has been introduced this week in southwestern Oklahoma where year-to-date totals are running around half or less of where they should be going into the hot summer months. The fringe D0 around this area of D1 in Oklahoma has also expanded.

## The Northeast
Widespread precipitation fell across a large portion of the region last week with totals ranging from 1-4 inches in some parts.  Temperatures were also above-normal for all but a small portion of Vermont and New Hampshire.  This has led to a substantial improvement through the removal of a large amount of D0 across Maine, New Hampshire, Vermont and Massachusetts.  Northeastern and western New York, western Pennsylvania and east-central Ohio are also now depicted as drought/dryness free.  The D1 found last week in north-central New York is now D0 as remnants of longer-term dryness back to the start of the year remain.  In fact, the recent seasonal dryness over the past 30-60 days has also led to a slight expansion of D0 across eastern Pennsylvania and extreme northwestern New Jersey, where the rains of last week missed their mark.

## The West
Cooler than normal temperatures were widespread over much of the West except for Colorado and New Mexico, which saw slightly above normal readings. This was accompanied by generous precipitation totals (3-5 inches or more) across portions of northern California and many locations across the Pacific Northwest. The recent rains, coupled with rapid snow melt in many places across the West, has led to flooding, but the underlying dryness in the basins and their projected low streamflow forecasts issued by USDA-NRCS and the National Weather Service are calling for many basins in Wyoming, southwestern Colorado, Utah, Montana, Idaho and southern Oregon to be less than 70% of average, with a few falling at less than 50% of average. Adequate reservoir storage will be beneficial in staving off some of the impacts that will come later during the summer months. Areas that improved this week include the Sevier basin of Utah (reduction of D0) and northeastern Oregon, all of eastern Washington and southwestern Idaho (removal of D0). There was also a reduction of D1/D2 in the Idaho Panhandle as a result of the heavy rains, snow melt and cooler temperatures. Year-to-date and Water-Year-to-date precipitation and streamflow numbers (October 1 to present) are in better shape after this early summer boost. The same conditions also led to some improvements in northwestern Wyoming in the Yellowstone region where the D2 was reduced a bit, but the D1 and D2 found here is still a situation worth watching. Farther south, the D0 found in the San Juan region of southwestern Colorado shows a slight expansion this week on the heels of the continued dryness in the region.

## Upper Midwest
The past week brought some relief to the dryness/drought with light rains, but most of the heaviest precipitation fell to the south of the D1-D3 core entrenched across northern Wisconsin, Minnesota and Michigan’s Upper Peninsula.  This results in mainly a status quo situation where the rains haven’t been above and beyond what is normally expected this time of year now that temperatures are rising and water demands are beginning to increase.

## Forecast
Over the next 5 days (June 10-14) we can expect to see above-normal temperatures across the southern Plains, Gulf Coast and mid-Atlantic, with the warmest air lodged over the Southeast.  Substantially cooler air (9 to 12 degrees below normal) will fill in across much of the West (except for northern coastal California) and northern Plains. Parts of New England and up into Maine can also expect slightly cooler than normal temperatures during this time. As for precipitation, many of the dry/drought affected regions may be in line for some decent rains over the next five days. This includes the Pacific Northwest, which has already seen a very wet start to the summer months (&amp;gt; 200-300% of normal precipitation across much of the region) with rapid snow melt and rains contributing to flooding in many places. A good portion of Wyoming, eastern Colorado, the central Plains, southern Plains (eastern Oklahoma and eastern Texas) are showing good potential for some significant precipitation. The forecast is also favorable for the Great Lakes region, including much of Minnesota, Wisconsin and northern Michigan including the Upper Peninsula. Finally, the Ohio Valley and Northeast may also share in the wealth.
The CPC 6-10 day forecast (June 15–19) is showing increased odds for above-normal temperatures in the Four Corners region and throughout the central and southern Plains. Everywhere else can expect near-normal temperatures except for central Alaska, where the forecasts are leaning toward below-normal readings. Confidence is a bit low on the precipitation side of things, where chances are better for below-normal rainfall across southern and northern Alaska, the Intermountain West, most of Texas and northern New England into Maine. Better odds of above-normal precipitation are depicted across the northern Plains, Minnesota and northern Wisconsin along with the Southeast.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-161.9028249</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-73.704872</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>67.485814</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:50:50-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 