<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-05-20</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Miskus</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — May 20, 2008</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-05-20</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-05-20</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-05-22</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — May 20, 2008

## Introduction
The week was dominated by upper-air ridging (high pressure) in the West and troughing (low pressure) in the East.  This brought unseasonably hot and mostly dry weather to the Far West, spurring rapid snow melt of the above-normal mountain snow pack, particularly in the Northwest, and causing localized river flooding.  Farther east, a series of cold fronts, with embedded waves of low pressure, produced cool and unsettled conditions, with heavy rains falling on the southern Great Plains, lower Delta, parts of the Southeast, and from the middle Mississippi, Tennessee, and Ohio Valleys eastward into the mid-Atlantic.  Mostly dry weather was beneficial to the soggy western Corn Belt, but unwelcome in central and southern Florida, south-central High Plains, and the northern Great Plains.

## Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico
In Hawaii, little or no rain fell on most of the islands, although a few windward locations on Kauai, Oahu, and the Big Island, plus some leeward stations on Maui and the Big Island, received 0.5 to 1.5 inches of rain.  The limited number of USGS streamflow gauges on Hawaii were quite low (less than 10th percentile, some at record low levels, especially on Kauai, Oahu, and Maui), but no new water restrictions were made this week, and impacts in agriculture and the public water supply had not been felt too strongly.  With the lack of new or worsening impacts, status-quo was maintained in Hawaii, although it will be closely monitored for any further deterioration.
In Alaska, unsettled weather generated light amounts of precipitation and subnormal temperatures in central sections of the state (weekly totals of 0.3 to 1 inch), with some locally heavier totals.  Nenana (in central Alaska) reported 2.95 inches, while McGrath, Bettles, Northway, and Fairbanks (near or inside the D0 area) measured between 0.25 and 0.35 inch.  With the widespread cool and wet weather, the D0 area was slightly edged eastward to reflect improving moisture conditions.
With 1.5 to 2.5 inches of rain falling on west-central Puerto Rico, plus the heavy widespread rains of late April and early May, D0 was further reduced in west-central portions of the island as short-term deficits greatly declined or disappeared.  The rest of the island with D0, however, saw lighter amounts (0.3 inch or less), maintaining abnormal dryness there.

## The Mid-Atlantic, Southeast and lower Delta
Once again, another week of wet (1 to 2 inches of rain) and cool (temperatures averaging 2 to 6 degrees F below normal) weather in the mid-Atlantic alleviated residual D0(H) in the Delmarva Peninsula, and further eroded D0 and D1 in portions of south-central Virginia and north-central North Carolina.  Since April 1, 14.95, 14.13, and 13.40 inches of rain have fallen on Washington/Dulles, VA, Washington/National, DC, and Richmond, VA, accumulating surpluses of 9.05, 8.91, and 7.67 inches, respectively.
Farther south, light and scattered rains (0.1 to 0.5 inch) maintained conditions in the remainder of the Carolinas.  Farther west, however, moderate to heavy showers and thunderstorms, including 4 to 8 inches across northern and south-central Louisiana and central Mississippi (locally 11 inches at Shreveport, LA), eliminated D0 across the lower Delta and improved the D1 to D0 across southern Mississippi where totals were generally lower (2 to 3 inches).  Two to four inches of rain also soaked portions of west-central Alabama and the Florida Panhandle, easing drought by one category in east-central Mississippi and west-central Alabama.  Another 1 to 2 inches of rain in northern Georgia was enough to remove the area's D3 as light to moderate precipitation since early February has been enough to warrant improvements in the state, although long-term deficits (24- to 36-months) exceeding 20 inches still remained, and most 7- and 14-day USGS averaged streamflows remained in the lower 25th percentile.  Similarly, 1 to 2 inches of rain in southeastern Tennessee and southwestern North Carolina produced some slight drought reduction.
In contrast, while western and northern sections of the Southeast received decent rains, the eastern Gulf and southern Atlantic Coasts mostly missed out.  Only 0.1 to 0.4 inch of rain was measured in southeastern Alabama, southern Georgia, and central Florida, and little or no rain fell on southern Florida.  Accordingly, short-term dryness (30- and 60-days) has developed in southeastern Alabama and southern Georgia, and expanded across north-central Florida.  In the latter area, adequate topsoil moisture but low well water levels and 7-day USGS stream flows in the lower 10th percentile required the 'H' impact designation.  In central and southern Florida, the onset of the summer rainy season has been slow to develop as the last decent rainfall (1 to 2 inches) across the southern half of Florida occurred on April 6-7.  Lake Okeechobee continued to drop, reaching an average depth of 9.81 feet, or 3.49 feet below normal, although still far from its all-time record low of 8.82 feet in July 2007.  In addition, numerous large wildfires continued to burn, with the National Interagency Fire Center reporting 4 large, active wildfires affecting 77 043 acres as of May 21.  Accordingly, D1 was expanded eastward and D2 southward.

## The Plains and Upper Midwest
Widespread showers and thunderstorms, some severe, dropped moderate to heavy rains (1 to 5 inches) on much of central and eastern Texas and on parts of the central and lower Rio Grande Valley, with lighter amounts (0.5 to 1.5 inches) falling on the southern High Plains.  In south-central Texas (Burnet, Lampasas, San Saba, and Llano counties), 3 to 5 inches of rain erased abnormal dryness, while over 2 inches of rain in south Texas near Uvalde, Carrizo Springs, Rio Grande City, and Roma shrank the D3(A).  In east-central New Mexico, 1 to 1.5 inches of rain split the D1(A) area in two as lesser amounts fell to the north and south.  Around Laredo (0.4 inches), however, D3(A) remained as the heavy rains missed to the north and south.  Similarly in southeastern Texas (an area from Victoria to Bayport to south of Austin), weekly totals were a meager 0.1 to 0.2 inch.  Significant rains have bypassed this region for the past 2 months, creating short-term deficits of 4 to 6 inches, and D1 was expanded into this triangle.
In the south-central High Plains, a continued lack of significant precipitation and reports from county district conservationists and agronomists indicated conditions worse than have been depicted.  In northeastern New Mexico, the Panhandles of extreme northern Texas and western Oklahoma, southeastern Colorado, and western Kansas, precipitation during the water-year-to-date and past 60-days (main rainy season is the spring) have been dismal, with most location reporting under 25% of normal, and some even less.  In Cimarron County, Oklahoma, few dryland winter wheat acres will be harvested, and little to no acres were available for grazing.  Erosion from wind was being reported for the first time in years.  Accordingly, D1-D3 was expanded to incorporate the areas with the lowest percent of normal precipitation during the past 60-days and back to October 1, 2007, plus declining regional impacts.
Farther north, a windy and mostly dry week (less than 0.1 inch) in the northern Great Plains and upper Midwest caused rapid depletion of the topsoil moisture in north-central South Dakota, eastern North Dakota, and northwestern Minnesota.  In the latter two areas, although long-term precipitation (6- to 12-months) was at or above-normal, short-term deficiencies (90-days or less) have combined with recent strong winds and high evaporative rates to degrade topsoil moisture conditions as well as ripping out some sugarbeet seedlings that will require replanting.  As a result, D1(A) now includes most of eastern North Dakota and extreme northwestern Minnesota.  Finally, changes that were suggested last week for eastern Montana (but accidently omitted) were implemented this week, and included 1-category improvements in climate division 6 (removing some D0) and 7 (D1 to D0, and some D0 removed).

## The West
The Far West, especially the Pacific Northwest, experienced an abrupt transition from unseasonably cool conditions to near-record and record heat as readings soared into the 90s and 100s degrees F.  The summer-like temperatures quickly melted an above-normal mountain snowpack, causing rivers to rapidly rise to near-record levels for mid-May and produce some localized flooding, most notably impacting the water treatment plant for Yakima, Washington.  The extreme heat came after a long spell of subnormal temperatures dating back to mid-March in the Pacific Northwest.  This allowed the mountain snow pack to build as little melted, and even though precipitation was generally below normal, it continued to fall in the form of snow.  Even with the recent melting, basin average snow water content (SWC) on May 20 still remained above-normal at many Washington, southern and northeastern Oregon, northern Idaho, Montana, Wyoming, and Colorado basins.  California's four Sierra Nevada basins were a notable exception, with SWC running at 23%, 1%, 21%, and 50% (north to south), and water-year-to-date (WYTD)  precipitation averaging between 70 and 79% of normal.  In contrast, nearly all of the remaining Western basins average precipitation was close to or above-normal this water year.
Precipitation was negligible across most of the West, except for light amounts (0.1 to 0.5 inch) in western Washington, northern Idaho, parts of the Rockies, and north-central Arizona, and 0.5 to 1.5 inches in central Colorado and western Washington.  In central Oregon and south-central Washington, however, after a good start to the water year (October-December), much drier weather has occurred since the start of 2008, with 25-50% of the normal precipitation falling during the past 90 days.  In response, D0(AH) was extended northward into south-central Washington.  Additionally, winter wheat conditions have deteriorated in Oregon, with 39% rated poor to very poor, while pastures and range conditions rated poor to very poor have declined to 22% and 16% in Oregon and Washington, respectively, according to NASS/USDA on May 18.  In even worse shape was California's pastures and ranges, 91% rated poor to very poor.  Although the Southwest observed hot and dry weather, no changes were made as we wait for the all of the mountain snow packs to melt out, and then reassess conditions.

## Forecast
For May 22-26, upper-air troughing (low pressure) will remain in place over the West while ridging (high pressure) gradually envelops the East.  This will produce cool and wet conditions in the West, even including parts of the Southwest, with a good chance of weekend rains in the northern and central Plains.  Showers and thunderstorms are likely along the central and eastern Gulf early in the period.  In contrast, mostly dry weather and moderating temperatures are in store for the East, although New England may remain unsettled.  Overall, this is a favorable 5-day forecast, with generally dry weather where it is wet and a chance of rain in many drought-stricken regions.
For the ensuing 5 days (May 27-31), the CPC 6-10 day outlook favors wetter-than-usual weather in the Northwest, and from the central Great Plains eastward into the mid-Atlantic and Carolinas.  Subnormal precipitation is expected in Alaska, the upper Great Lakes region, and along the southern tier of States, except for central and southern Florida (normal).  Temperatures are expected to average above-normal across much of the lower 48 States and Alaska, with below-normal readings limited to the upper Great Lakes region, New England, and southern Florida.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.5968457</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.8841923</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>70.9221705</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:41:37-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 