<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2011-10-25</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Miskus</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — October 25, 2011</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2011-10-25</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2011-10-25</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2011-10-27</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — October 25, 2011

## Introduction
Early in the period, an area of low pressure intensified over the Southeast and tracked northward, bringing widespread showers and thunderstorms to most of the northeastern quarter of the Nation. Moderate to heavy rains (more than 2 inches) fell on parts of the Ohio Valley and middle and lower Great Lakes regions, and in southern and eastern Panhandle of Florida, southern Appalachians, and sections of the Carolinas. In the Northwest, a cold front brought unsettled weather to the region on Friday and Saturday, generating light to moderate precipitation (0.5 to 2.5 inches) in the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies. As the large storm system slowly pulled away from the Great Lakes region into eastern Canada, a quick-moving system skirted across the south-central Plains and into the South late in the weekend. This system produced scattered showers and thunderstorms, some severe, and dropped light to moderate rains (1 to 2 inches) on parts of Oklahoma, northeastern Texas, Arkansas, and northern Mississippi. Meanwhile, the rest of the lower 48 States observed tranquil weather. Temperatures averaged above-normal in the West and Northeast, and below-normal from east of the Rockies to the Appalachians and into Florida. In Hawaii, scattered showers fell on Kauai and Oahu, especially on the windward sides, but little or no rain was reported on the eastern islands (Molokai, Lihue, Maui, and the Big Island). Showers fell across most of Puerto Rico, while Alaska observed heavy precipitation in the southeastern Panhandle, light amounts across the southern sections, and little or no precipitation elsewhere.

## Central and Southern Plains
A quick-moving storm system brought rain and severe weather to parts of eastern Oklahoma, northeastern Texas, and central Arkansas, including 1.5 to 2.5 inches from east-central Oklahoma across central Arkansas and into northwestern Mississippi. Northeastern Texas has observed decent rains in 6 of the past 7 weeks, and some 1-category improvements were made there. In Oklahoma, the rains in central sections were disappointing in that very little of the rain made it into the lakes. Similarly, although 1 to 1.5 inches of rain fell on southeastern Oklahoma benefiting topsoil moisture, lake levels resumed dropping after a brief 1-day rise. This included Lakes Hugo, Pine Creek, and Broken Bow in Choctaw and McCurtain counties. Farther east, however, D4 was removed from Okfuskee, Hughes, and Pittsburgh counties as enough rain (1.5 to 3.5 inches) fell. Likewise, D3 was erased from Le Flore County and the Le Flore Watershed as 1.5 to 3 inches fell.   Improvements were also made just to the east in western Arkansas (1.5 to 3 inches) where drought conditions were not as severe as in Oklahoma, and some areas of D1 and D2 were reduced.
In southeastern Texas, the small D3 area west of Galveston was downgraded to D4. Farther north, persistent dry weather and warm weather continued to deteriorate conditions rapidly in eastern Kansas. Little or no rain fell during the week when the normal weekly precipitation would be 0.75 to 1 inch. Extra releases were needed from John Redmond Lake to maintain water supplies to the Wolf Creek Nuclear Facility cooling lake, while many municipalities in the region depend on surface water sources which are steadily falling. This was especially true in southern Kansas where reservoirs were below normal capacity and included Cheney, El Dorado, Elk City, Fall River, and Toronto.  Precipitation shortages are now common out to 90-days as deficits grew, prompting a 1-category decline (D1-D3) across eastern and northeastern Kansas and into northwestern Missouri.
According to NASS/USDA, the southern Plain state crop conditions (Oct. 23) were quite dismal in Texas, Oklahoma, and Kansas. The percent rated poor or very poor in Texas, Oklahoma, and Kansas was: corn, 68, NA, and 48; cotton, 63, 96, and 37; peanuts, 47, 27, and NA; and sorghum, 43, 86, and 53 (New Mexico at 67), respectively.  Agricultural losses in 2011 (only through mid-August) have already reached $5.2 billion (including $2.1 billion for livestock) in Texas and $1.6 billion in Oklahoma.  Texas cotton took a big hit, with losses at $1.8 billion. The previous record for agricultural losses in Texas was in 2006 at $4.1 billion.

## Hawaii
Light showers (less than 1 inch) were not enough to stop a stretch of subnormal rainfall on Kauai. SPI values at Lihue for the 1- to 3-month periods were between -1 to -1.5, consistent with D2 conditions. According to the Kauai USDA/FSA, the lack of adequate rain had some ranchers purchasing feed for their cattle. As a result, D2(S) was added in southeastern Kauai, and the existing D1 was expanded toward the northeast. On Oahu, light to moderate showers were enough to maintain conditions, while last week's deterioration in the eastern islands were still valid this week despite a lack of showers across much of Molokai, Maui, Lanai, and the Big Island.

## Northern Plains and Midwest
After last week's light to moderate rains - the first significant rains in the western Corn Belt since late August - dry weather returned this week. Much of this region, from Minnesota southward into Missouri, has observed well below normal precipitation during the past 60 days. Many of those locations have also experienced less than 50 percent of normal precipitation during the past 90 days, including less than 25 percent of normal precipitation in southern Minnesota. Based upon the short-term blends and 60- and 90-day deficiencies, D0 to D2 was slightly expanded in southern Minnesota, northeastern South Dakota, north-central Iowa, and northern Missouri where precipitation was less than 50 percent. Fortunately, long-term precipitation was near or above normal, maintaining subsoil moisture amounts while keeping most rivers and lakes at adequate levels. Although the dry weather was good for crop harvesting, topsoil moisture rated short or very short by NASS/USDA on Oct. 23 was at 48, 60, 72, 77, and 48 percent in SD, MN, IA, MO, and IL, respectively. Percentage of pastures and range land rated poor or very poor was at 47, 62, and 45 (Oct. 24) in IA, MO, and IL, respectively. In contrast, a slight reduction of drought was made in east-central Illinois where lingering rains from last week's storm dropped 0.5 to 1.5 inches of rain, although D1 was kept in Macon County (central Illinois) where Lake Decatur was still recovering from the drought. Farther west, another dry week in the northern Plains slightly expanded the D0 into southeastern Montana where 60- and 90-day precipitation was less than half of normal.

## Northwest
Another 0.5 to 1 inches of precipitation in northern Idaho (Shoshone County) effectively eliminated the lingering D0. In the Pacific Northwest, subnormal precipitation has been common across the region during the past 30-, 60-, and 90-days, but few impacts have been noticed after a cool and wet spring and early summer. One area, however, that also had 180-day and year-to-date deficits were in southern Oregon (Deschutes &amp;amp; Lake Counties). A D0 was added where the lowest percent of normal precipitation occurred from short (30-days) to medium (180-day) time periods.

## Southeast
Scattered showers and thunderstorms fell on most sections of the Southeast, although the southwestern sections (Alabama and the western Panhandle of Florida) saw minimal amounts (less than 0.3 inches). Where locally heavy totals were reported (more than 1.5 inches), some improvements were made, especially along the edges of the drought boundaries. This included central North Carolina, north-central South Carolina, extreme northern Georgia, in the eastern part of the Florida Panhandle (along the Apalachicola River; Apalachicola received 7 inches and Bristol 4.5 inches), and into extreme southwestern Georgia (2 to 3.5 inches). In southern Florida, last week’s heavy rains lingered into Tuesday and Wednesday as a fetch of tropical Gulf moisture dumped another 2 to 5 inches. Lake Okeechobee continued to rise, and by Sunday was above the Water Shortage Management band and nearing 13 feet by Oct. 26. Accordingly, the D0(L) was removed around Lake Okeechobee. The D0-D1 area was adjusted in north-central Florida per short-term anomalies and USGS stream flow levels (still less than 10 percentile around Cross City).
In contrast, the lack of rain in the short-term has expanded drought in western sections. In central Alabama, growing deficits increased the drought in Chilton, Bibb, and Perry counties, while D0-D2 expanded in the extreme western Panhandle of Florida and adjacent areas of southern Alabama. The D0(S) in northwestern Alabama stretched into adjacent areas of southern Tennessee and northeastern Mississippi as little rain fell and deficiencies grew. The no drought gap left by heavy rains from Tropical Storm Lee between the lower Delta and the Southeast continued to slowly shrink as short-term surpluses steadily declined. In Louisiana, another mostly dry week (0 to 0.5 inches) increased shortages in the state, slightly expanding D1 eastward in climate divisions 3, 5, and 8.  Lastly, the Impact Lines were adjusted and were based upon the SPI values at 3-months (short-term) and 12-months (long-term).

## Southern Rockies and Southwest
The typically drier fall months (between the summer monsoon &amp;amp; wet winter months) continued across this region as little or no precipitation fell, and temperatures generally averaged above-normal. Status-quo was maintained this week, but as the winter months approach and normals slowly climb, a closer eye will be kept on this area for increasing deficits and possible impacts. This is especially true during the current La Nina event when the odds are favorable for subnormal winter precipitation and above-normal temperatures.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (October 27-31), a slow moving cold front, with several areas of low pressure traveling along the front, will traverse across the central and eastern U.S.  This will bring precipitation from the southern Plains northeastward into lower New England. The greatest 5-day totals (1 to 2 inches) are forecasted to occur from northern Texas and eastern Oklahoma into northern Arkansas, along the Ohio River, in the central Appalachians, and to coastal lower New England (NJ, Long Island, CT, RI, MA). Farther south, the track of Hurricane Rina (in the western Caribbean Sea) will be closely monitored to see what, if any, impacts may occur to Florida. The current 5-day outlook has tropical moisture and showers (1 to 1.5 inches) overspreading most of the state except the Panhandle. Later in the period, a weak Pacific system should bring light precipitation to the Pacific Northwest. Temperatures should average above-normal in the West and northern Plains, and subnormal in the southern Plains and the eastern third of the Nation.
The CPC 6-10 day outlook (November 1-5) predicts a general zonal (west to east) upper-air flow over the lower 48 States. This translates to favorable odds of above-normal precipitation in the northern Rockies and Northeast, and subnormal precipitation across the southern third of the Nation from Arizona to Alabama. The temperature probability for below-normal readings is greatest from the Pacific Northwest into the central Rockies, and in the eastern Gulf and southern Atlantic States. Odds are likely for above-normal temperatures in the Southwest and upper Midwest.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.7864828</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-77.7282676</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.3856286</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:58:22-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 