<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2006-03-07</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brian Fuchs</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — March 07, 2006</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2006-03-07</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2006-03-07</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2006-03-09</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — March 07, 2006

## Introduction


## Alaska and Hawaii
Much of Hawaii received precipitation this week, with some locally heavy amounts. Improvements to the D0 categories in both Oahu and Kauai, which received some of the heaviest rains, were made this week. In Alaska, the area of D0 was again dry, with much of the southern coastal region and western portions of the state picking up some precipitation this week; no changes were made for Alaska.

## Lower Ohio Valley and Carolinas
Abnormally dry conditions led to the expansion of D0 conditions through much of the Ohio Valley. Low streamflows and the short-term dryness experienced in the region the last few months led to this expansion. D1 conditions were again introduced into Kentucky as dry conditions prevailed. D0 conditions were also expanded into Tennessee and western North Carolina as the recent dryness has allowed the threat from fires to increase, with several fires being reported.

## The Pacific Northwest and Rocky Mountains
An active weather pattern brought continued wet weather to the Pacific coast, with heavy rains along the coast and snow in the Sierra Nevada range. The water outlook has continued to be positive for this year as snows continue to add to the snowpack in the mountains. Montana saw improvements to their D1 conditions as reservoir levels and snowpacks continue to increase. In the northeast corner of Montana, the D0 conditions also improved as long-term dryness was alleviated. In the southern Rocky Mountains, record low snowpacks for this time of year are cause for concern, but reservoirs are holding steady from the abundant run-off last year, so conditions have not deteriorated too quickly.

## The Plains, Delta, and Corn Belt
Conditions across the Plains, Midwest, and Delta region have continued to be dry overall. Parts of Iowa, Kansas, and Nebraska picked up some rain last week, but amounts were generally less than one inch. These rains helped to reduce the grass fire threat that has plagued the entire region. D1 conditions were expanded in Missouri and Illinois; minimal soil moisture, water supplies, and low streamflows are the main concerns. Portions of western Illinois have had reports of shallow wells going dry in several counties from the extreme dryness. In south central Missouri, well drillers are reporting an increasing number of wells going dry or experiencing reduced pressure. New wells in this region are being drilled to 450 feet, compared to 300-350 feet in the past. Near Branson, a drilling company reported drilling two new wells at depths of 925 feet and 960 feet, respectively. In northern Arkansas, the D1 and D2 regions were expanded as reservoirs and lakes continue to show impacts from drought conditions. In southwest Kansas, the D1 conditions were pushed farther north as streamflows and soil moisture conditions declined. Topsoil moisture was rated at 85 percent very short in southwest Kansas by the United States Department of Agriculture survey. D2 conditions in Oklahoma were expanded to include the entire panhandle. Some stations in this part of Oklahoma have now gone more than 5 months with no rain event totaling more than 0.10 inches of rain.

## The Southwest
No relief this week, as dry conditions prevailed. More than half of New Mexico has a 4-month precipitation (Nov-Feb) total in the 1st to 3rd percentile range. With the dry conditions, fires have become a threat to much of the state. The D2 and D3 conditions were expanded eastward, highlighting the parts of New Mexico showing the most impacts from the drought conditions. The fire threat around Ruidoso, New Mexico, is due in part to dry conditions going back into the 1990s. Ruidoso has not had an above-normal precipitation year since 1997. With an outlook for a maximum of 20 percent of normal flow in the Rio Ruidoso, no flow in the Rio Bonito, and the Sierra Blanca SNOTEL site (above 10,000 feet elevation) having no snowpack, this part of New Mexico is approaching exceptional drought status. In southern California, heavy rains helped to improve the D0 conditions. With all the rain in California in the last week and for the last several weeks, the southern edge of the San Joaquin Valley has missed out on almost all of these events.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (March 9-13): Models are in agreement that the weather pattern during this time will consist of a deep trough over the western portions of the United States and a flat ridge over the east. 1) Significant precipitation is projected for the Ohio River Valley as a series of systems move out of the Plains with plenty of available moisture; 2) A continued wet pattern is expected over the Pacific Northwest and northern California; 3) A series of systems developing in the Southwest and moving onto the Plains should provide for a good chance of precipitation in Arizona, New Mexico, Utah, and Colorado; 4) Temperatures should be cooler over the west and warmer over the eastern half of the United States; 5) Plentiful tropical moisture should bring locally heavy rain to Hawaii; 6) A series of storm systems should bring widely scattered precipitation to the Alaska.
The 6-10 day outlook (March 14-18): There is strong agreement between models in the long-wave pattern during this period. The trough over the western United States will be well inland and the ridge over the east will begin to weaken. 1) Temperatures over the western two-thirds of the United States are projected to be below normal, with the High Plains region well below normal; 2) The extreme southeast United States is expected to be above normal during this time; 3) Warmer than normal temperatures should dominate much of Alaska; 4) Dry conditions should dominate much of the Plains states; 5) Much of the Midwest, Ohio River Valley, and southeast United States should expect wetter than normal conditions; 6) Above-normal precipitation is forecasted for much of California, Nevada, and Utah; 7) Alaska should expect above-normal precipitation in the northern part of the state, with drier than normal conditions along the southern coast.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.5010023</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-75.4595048</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>69.1826336</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T01:13:18-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 