<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-05-17</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Miskus</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — May 17, 2005</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-05-17</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-05-17</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-05-19</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — May 17, 2005

## Introduction


## Hawaii
After a very dry start to the period, showers briefly increased over the weekend in areal coverage on Kauai, Oahu, Maui, and Kona, but they were generally light (less than 0.25 inches), and dry conditions returned again at the end of the period. After subnormal April rainfall across much of the islands (except the windward side of Maui), May has also trended drier than normal, putting the remainder of Kona under D0. Fortunately, a relatively wet January-March has generated near to above-normal year-to-date totals.

## Puerto Rico 
Heavy showers (more than 2 inches) in the western and eastern sections effectively ended abnormal dryness in the northwestern and eastern coastal sections; however, rainfall was much lighter in the southeastern coastal region (0.2 to 0.5 inches), maintaining D0-D1 there.

## Southern and mid-Atlantic
Although storm systems have frequented the East Coast this Spring, significant rainfall has bypassed parts of the mid- and southern Atlantic region. This week, less than 0.5 inches of rain fell, temperatures averaged 2 to 4F above normal, and highs neared 90F. During the past 30 days, 50-75% of normal precipitation has created deficits of 1 to 4 inches in south-central Pennsylvania, and from south-central Virginia into northern South Carolina. 7-day USGS averaged stream flows (ending May 16) have dropped into the lower 25 th percentile, most notably in Pennsylvania. Additionally, 46%, 36%, 20%, and 24% of topsoil moisture was rated very short or short by the NASS/USDA in Pennsylvania, Virginia, North and South Carolina, respectively. As a result, two new D0(A) areas were added in the aforementioned regions.

## Southern Plains and Delta
Scattered showers and thunderstorms finally brought some relief to western Texas, southwestern and central Oklahoma, but farther to the east, little or no rainfall, highs in the 90s, and temperatures averaging 2 to 4F above normal increased abnormal dryness into eastern Texas while expanding moderate drought (D1) along the Red River Valley into portions of the middle and lower Delta. In the south-central Plains, abnormal dryness and moderate drought was whittled away where a cluster of thunderstorms dropped 1-2 inches of rain on the north-central Texas Panhandle and southwestern Oklahoma on May 12-13, then pushed eastward the next day, bringing 1-2 inches of rain to north-central Oklahoma and northern Texas. Over the weekend, additional showers (1-2 inches) moistened the southern Texas Panhandle and along parts of the lower Rio Grande Valley, erasing some of the dryness.
n contrast, warm and dry weather this week, plus subnormal rainfall since mid-April, pushed D0(A) into eastern Texas and northeastern Arkansas where 30-day deficiencies of 2 to 4 inches have accumulated, while pockets of 4 to 6 inch deficits have accrued along the eastern Red River Valley, southwestern Arkansas, and central Louisiana (new D1(A)) added). In Louisiana, 86% of the soil moisture supplies were rated very short or short, while Arkansas reported 46%, according to NASS/USDA. Furthermore, NASS reported that Louisiana crops were beginning to show signs of drought stress, and were in need of rain. In addition, USGS 7-day averaged stream flows dropped into the lower 25 th percentile across both states. In extreme southern Texas, although thundershowers dropped 1 to 2 inches of rain along the lower Rio Grande River, areas to the east missed out, and drought conditions became severe (D2). Since March 1, McAllen, Brownsville, and Harlingen, TX have received 14%, 26%, and 38% of their spring rainfall, respectively, or about 3 inches below normal.

## The Great Lakes Region and Midwest
A strong storm system slowly tracked from the central Rockies northeastward into the Great Lakes region by the weekend, producing severe weather and dumping widespread heavy rains (more than 2 inches) that caused localized flooding in the western Corn Belt. Moderate rains (more than an inch) also fell on the central and eastern Corn Belt. Particularly hard-hit was Wood River and Grand Island in south-central Nebraska, where 8-12 inches of rain fell within 24-hours ending 7am CDT Thursday morning. In general, a one-category improvement occurred in eastern Kansas (2-5 inches), south-central Nebraska (4-12 inches), all of Iowa (2-6 inches), southern Wisconsin (1-2 inches), western, northern, and southern Missouri (2-3 inches), northwestern Illinois (1-3 inches), central and northeastern Indiana (2-3 inches), southwestern and southeastern Michigan (1-1.5 inches), northeastern Minnesota (more than an inch), and western Upper Peninsula of Michigan (1-1.5 inches). All other Midwest and Great Lakes areas remained status quo as light rain dampened this region, albeit light in parts of central Illinois (0.1-0.2 inches) and east-central Missouri (0.3-0.5 inches).

## The Northern and Central Plains
As mentioned above in the Great Lakes Region and Midwest summary, the strong storm system in the Nations midsection also impacted much of the Plains with severe weather, heavy snows, and widespread rain. In western South Dakota, southwestern North Dakota, southern Montana, northern Wyoming, and northwestern Nebraska, enough cold air from Canada wrapped into the system, blanketing western South Dakota and southeastern Montana with a foot, while up to 2 feet covered the northern Wyoming mountains. This was the 4 th out of the past 5 weeks with ample precipitation in the north-central Plains, leading to improvements in much of the region. Weekly precipitation exceeded 2 inches in southern South Dakota, northern, southern, and eastern Nebraska, eastern Kansas, and southeastern Montana, with lighter amounts in northeastern Montana, North Dakota, and western Nebraska and Kansas. Accordingly, a 1-category improvement was made in most areas with over 2 inches of precipitation (western South Dakota, Nebraska), and in eastern Montana and Wyoming after obtaining information from the May 1 Western Water Supply Outlook. Status quo was maintained in the remainder of the Dakotas where precipitation was lighter, while hydrological drought persisted in the Missouri River system ( Lake Oahe still well below normal capacity, requiring the Army Corps of Engineers to construct a new water intake system in north-central South Dakota).

## The Rockies and Western States
After a disparate winter season in the West [disappointing in the northern third (dry and mild), beneficial to the southern half (near-record wetness)], spring precipitation increased in northern areas when it would normally start to decline, and has persisted. As a result, this was the 9 th consecutive week (since mid-March) of unseasonably wet weather that has affected some or all of this area (especially the Northwest), continuing to add onto the (disappointing November-February) water year-to-date precipitation totals, blanketing some higher elevations with late snows, recharging soil moisture levels, aiding stream flows and runoff, and delaying the onset of the normally drier and warm (wildfire and irrigation) late spring and summer season. In addition, after near-record winter mountain snow packs in the Southwest, unseasonably cool and tranquil spring conditions have slowed snowmelt, delaying the onset of potential downstream flooding.
This week, two Pacific storm systems brought widespread, moderate to heavy precipitation throughout the Pacific Northwest, Sierra Nevada, Great Basin, and northern half of the Rockies. More than 2 inches fell on the Cascades, northern Sierra Nevada, across northern Nevada and Utah, and on much of Idaho, Wyoming, southwestern and southern Montana. Plus, with the May 1 Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) and the Western Water Supply outlook information now available, a reassessment of conditions were made. According to the NRCS SNOTEL sites, water year-to-date basin average precipitation has now increased to approximately 70-75% of normal across the Northwest, up from 60-65% back in early March, and more than 80% across most of Montana. Topsoil moisture is generally adequate to surplus, and pasture and range conditions rated poor or very poor by the NASS/USDA have dramatically declined as compared to last year (worst states were Montana, Wyoming, and Washington at 30%, 28%, and 28%, respectively, and most Western states were between 0-20%). May 1 reservoir storage had also improved, some due to the excessive precipitation (e.g. Arizona), and some due to reduced water releases (e.g. Washington and Idaho). Statewide storage on May 1 was now close to or above normal in Arizona, California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, and Washington, and improving but still below 75% of normal [divide %capacity versus normal %capacity] in Nevada (29 vs 62%), New Mexico (35 vs 53%), Oregon (61 vs 82%), Utah (49 vs 81%), and Wyoming (50 vs 67%). The May 1 NRCS spring and summer streamflow forecasts were still expected to be between 25-49% of normal in parts of Oregon, Washington, and Idaho, most likely due to a well below-normal May 1 mountain snowpack (also less than 50% of normal in those areas, including less than 25% in the Cascades). Additionally, the D2(H) areas were removed in northeastern Arizona and northern New Mexico with October 2004-April 2005 precipitation exceeding 150% and reservoirs doing well. Improvements were also made in northwestern New Mexico where the San Juan River basin May 1 SWSI was above +3 (abundant). In summary, the long-term drought in the Northwest has been somewhat dented by an unseasonably wet and cool spring, but hydrological impacts will still take much longer to completely eradicate.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (May 19-23), low pressure in the northern Plains will track southeastward into the mid-Atlantic, bringing rain to most of the Midwest, Southeast, and mid-Atlantic. Meanwhile, another Pacific storm system will dampen the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies; however, it appears as though Pacific storms will take a more northerly track after this system departs, leading to more typical precipitation for late May. It should remain mostly dry in the southwestern quarter of the Nation. The West will gradually warm-up, while near to below-normal temperatures cover the central and eastern U.S.
The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for May 24-28 calls for an upper-air pattern change in the Nation, with ridging (high pressure) in the Southwest and troughing (low pressure) in the Northeast. This translates to drier (more seasonable) and much warmer weather in the West (where abnormally wet and cool conditions have persisted for 9 weeks), and above-normal rainfall in the Northeast. Subnormal rainfall is expected in the central High Plains, northern and southern Plains, Delta, and Gulf Coast States. Cooler than usual conditions should envelop the eastern half of the Nation, with unseasonable warmth from the High Plains westward.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083016389</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.8712894673405</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.9284123273676</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.3856285587646</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:33:52-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 