<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-12-16</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Jay Lawrimore</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — December 16, 2008</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-12-16</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-12-16</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-12-18</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — December 16, 2008

## Introduction
The week was highlighted by a major storm that brought moderate to heavy rainfall across drought-affected areas of the Southeast and parts of the Ohio River Basin from 9-11 December. Rainfall in excess of 4 inches fell across much of Mississippi, Alabama, Georgia, Tennessee and western parts of the Carolinas. This system also brought beneficial precipitation to eastern Kentucky, Virginia, and West Virginia as well as large parts of the Northeast. A severe ice storm struck areas of New York and New England, and late in the period an Arctic front brought cold air to the southern Plains and light freezing rain and sleet from northern Texas to Tennessee, Missouri and Kentucky. Precipitation was generally near average from the coastal Carolinas to Florida, and near to above average from the Midwest to the northern Plains. A major winter storm brought blizzard conditions and record low temperatures from Montana to the northern Plains, but precipitation was not sufficient to bring widespread improvement. In southern California a strong storm system brought heavy rain to drought-affected areas late in the period with snow falling in higher elevations. Precipitation remained below average from the Cascades to the coast and was near to below-average in drought-affected areas of the southern Plains.

## Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico
A Kona low produced heavy rainfall across the islands from December 11-13, producing flooding on Kauai and Oahu. Event totals were from 6.6 to 24.7 inches on Kauai and 4.5 to 18.8 on Oahu but were not sufficient to erase long-term deficits in all locations. One-category improvements were made across the two islands and only the eastern end of Kauai remained abnormally dry (D0), while moderate (D1A) drought and abnormally dry conditions remained on eastern Oahu. Lesser amounts of rain fell on Lanai (4.8), Kahoolawe (4.8), Molokai (3.4 to 6.3), Maui (2.5 to 6.3), and the Big Island of Hawaii (2.0 to 3.6), and the drought classifications on those islands remained unchanged.
Little to no precipitation fell outside of the Panhandle and coastal areas of southern Alaska, where totals generally exceeded 2 inches. The area of abnormally dry conditions in northwest Alaska remained the only designation for the state.
Rain fell across Puerto Rico during the past week with a southwest to northeast gradient of lighter (0.25 inches) to heavier (&amp;gt;1.5 inches) amounts. Drought designations remained absent from the island.

## Mid-Atlantic and Southeast
Widespread rainfall totals exceeding 5 inches resulted in the removal of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1H) in northern Alabama and south-central Tennessee. Abnormally dry conditions ended in southeastern Alabama and broad 1-category improvements occurred across Georgia and the western Carolinas. Rainfall was sufficient to bring an end to extreme drought (D4H) in the region, and heavy rainfall in eastern Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky brought 1- and 2-category improvements there. This left a broad area of moderate drought (D1H) separating severe drought (D2H) in central Kentucky from severe (D2H) drought along the Tennessee-North Carolina border and extreme (D3H) drought over far western North and South Carolina and northeast Georgia. In northeastern North Carolina two to three inches of rain was sufficient to end moderate drought (D1H) and reduce the westward extent of abnormally dry conditions. In contrast, a persistent pattern of below-average precipitation led to growing precipitation deficits along coastal Georgia, leading to the introduction of abnormally dry (D0) conditions. Abnormally dry conditions also expanded westward in the Big Bend area of Florida where USGS 7- to 28-day streamflow was below normal and 90-day precipitation totals less than 75% of average.

## The Northeast
Above-average precipitation fell from West Virginia to Maine with widespread near-average precipitation in western New York and northwestern Pennsylvania. This resulted in the removal of abnormally dry conditions in northern parts of West Virginia and a southward retraction of moderate (D1H) drought in west-central areas of the state and bordering areas of Ohio. An additional 2 to 3 inches of rain in southern Maryland brought an end to the last vestiges of abnormally dry conditions. Although precipitation was average to above average in abnormally dry areas of western Pennsylvania the persistence of 60- and 90-day deficits resulted in no change to the D0 areas in the state.

## The Plains and Upper Midwest
A major winter storm struck the northern Plains with snow totals from 2 to more than 12 inches in Montana and North Dakota. Improving conditions occurred in eastern Montana where abnormally dry conditions replaced moderate (D1AH) drought conditions, and a reduction in the spatial extent of abnormally dry conditions (D0) occurred in northeast areas of the state. In the region of moderate (D1H) and severe (D2H) drought from southeastern Minnesota to the Upper Peninsula of Michigan, precipitation was generally average to above average. Mid- to long-term precipitation deficits remained and were reflected in 7- to 28-day USGS streamflow below the 10th percentile. In southern Texas the continuation of below-average rainfall combined with windy and warmer-than-average conditions led to a small expansion of extreme (D3AH) and exceptional (D4AH) drought.

## The West
Despite recent storms, snowfall and water-year precipitation totals in the western U.S. continued to lag behind average as of the middle of December. A storm system dived southward into southern California during the period bringing rain to major cities and snowfall to areas above 4000 feet east of San Diego. Snow also fell in the Sierras of California during the week but as of December 15 the seasonal total in the northern and southern Sierras was near 70% of average. In much of northern California conditions continued to deteriorate as precipitation during the past month was more than 4 inches below normal. UGSG streamflows remained well below average, and there were new reports of impacts to livestock operations and springs going dry for the first time in 60 years. Reflecting the deteriorating conditions, moderate (D1AH) and severe (D2AH) drought expanded westward in northern areas of the state and an area of extreme (D3) drought was introduced where deficits have been greatest. In western Oregon and southwestern Washington abnormally dry conditions (D0) expanded westward to the coast. In this area USGS 7- to 28-day streamflow values less than the 5th percentile, 30-day precipitation totals less than 50% of average and 90-day precipitation totals less than 70% of average reflected the abnormally dry conditions. In western Montana most locations received only 2 to 4 inches of snow during the past week. Early-season snowpack less than 50% of average for most areas resulted in a 1-category degradation to moderate (D1AH) drought and abnormally dry (D0) conditions. Other changes to drought designations will be made in the coming weeks as the western snowpack continues to develop.

## Forecast
From December 18 - 22, 2008, an active pattern is expected. Precipitation is likely across most of the country with above normal totals from the mid-South and Midwest to the Northeast. A strong storm system will affect the Pacific Northwest early in the period as another exits the Southwest after bringing abundant rain and snow to the region. Normal to cooler-than-normal temperatures are expected from the West to the Midwest and Northeast while the southern Plains to Southeast and Mid-Atlantic will likely be near average to warmer than average. Wintery precipitation will generally be confined to the Pacific Northwest and other high elevation areas of the West as well as the northern tier of the nation from the northern Plains to the Northeast.
From December 23 - 27, 2008, the odds favor continued below-normal temperatures across the northern tier of the contiguous U.S. and the far West, while warmer-than-average temperatures are likely to stretch from New Mexico across the Deep South to Florida. In Alaska, odds favor below-normal temperatures in the southern half of the state and warmer-than-average temperatures north of the Arctic Circle. The odds favor above-normal precipitation across the western third of the nation and from the Midwest and mid-South to the Northeast, while drier-than-average conditions are more likely in Florida and Texas.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-168.1235296</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-75.4595048</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>70.4052714</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:53:39-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 