<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-07-19</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Heim</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Jess Enloe</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — July 19, 2005</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-07-19</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-07-19</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-07-21</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — July 19, 2005

## Introduction


## Hawaii
Scattered showers occurred over the D0 areas this week. Rainfall departures over the last 30 to 60 days were generally near normal, except for stations on Kauai. No change was made to the depiction this week, but the northern islands bear watching in coming weeks.

## The Great Lakes, Upper Mississippi Valley, and Ohio Valley Region
The remnants of Hurricane Dennis slowly rotated across the Ohio Valley during the week, but the hoped for widespread heavy rains failed to materialize. Local reports of 2 to 4 inches came from a few stations in the drought areas of central Indiana, southeast Missouri, and Kentucky, with lesser amounts elsewhere. Showers from a cold front later in the week brought 2 inches or more of rain to a few stations in northeast Indiana and south central Michigan and lesser amounts elsewhere in the region. For the most part, a tenth of an inch of rain or less fell in the northern parts of the region, from Upper Michigan to western Missouri. Much hotter than normal temperatures accompanied the dryness in these regions, with daily records set in Minnesota and Michigan.
Improvement to the drought depiction was made in some areas. D0 was pulled back over much of Kentucky and southwest Tennessee, D1 was washed away in extreme southeast Missouri under rains from Dennis, a donut hole of D-nothing was added in east central Indiana, and D2 was peeled back over south central Michigan and northeast Indiana.
The drought depiction worsened in the northern and western portions of this region. The percent of Wisconsin pasture and range land in poor or very poor condition doubled compared to last week, jumping to 59%. On July 15, Wisconsin Governor Jim Doyle declared a statewide drought emergency to expedite irrigation relief for farmers. D1 was expanded across parts of Upper and Lower Michigan and most of Wisconsin into Minnesota and Iowa, D2 grew to cover the southeast half of Wisconsin and northern Lower Michigan and eastern Upper Michigan, and D0 expanded into eastern Minnesota.
The severe dryness combined with extremely hot temperatures (persistently above the 90s) to stress crops at a critical point in the growing season across much of the Midwest and Great Lakes agricultural belt. Corn and soybean crops from Illinois and Iowa to Missouri suffered, streams feeding the Mississippi River were low, and soils were rapidly drying. In Missouri, ponds were down to about 50% normal depth, two-thirds of the states pasture and rangeland was in poor or very poor condition, and hay and pasture forages, as well as crop yields, were reduced by 50% from a normal yield in some areas. As of July 13, a phase 2 drought alert was in effect for 52 Missouri counties. Nearly three-fourths of Illinois pasture and range land was in poor to very poor condition. D1-D2-D3 was expanded across western Illinois into eastern Iowa, and D3 expanded across northern Illinois into southeast Wisconsin. D1 grew within Missouri and seeped into southeastern Iowa, D2 joined to form a band across east central Missouri, and D0 spread westward across the state into eastern Kansas and northeast Oklahoma.

## The Great Plains
A contrast of precipitation extremes characterized this region during the week. One to 2 inch rains in Nebraska and Kansas were spotty and easily mitigated by the hot windy conditions, with generally dry conditions predominating in the north. In the southern Plains, large areas of heavy rains brought relief to Texas with improvement to some drought areas.
Parts of the Houston metro area received 6 to 8 inches, bringing the year-to-date totals to near normal. Over 6 inches fell during the week in Live Oak County in southern Texas. However, in spite of the rain, the recent severe dryness prompted officials in some Texas counties to continue burning bans, as of July 16. D3 and D2 were pulled back in southern Texas, D1 and D0 retreated from the upper Gulf coast, and D2 was pulled back where heavy rains fell in northeast Texas. However, D2 was expanded and a spot of D3 added in north central Texas where recent rains have been spotty and 30 to 60 day deficits ranged from 3 to 6 inches.
Rapid City , South Dakota had the fifth driest first half of summer (June 1-July 16) with only 1.24 inches of rainfall. Only 0.10 inch of rain fell from June 14-July 16, the driest such period on record. Unusually hot temperatures accompanied the dryness. So far this month (through July 17), Pierre, Aberdeen, Mobridge, and Huron all had one third of an inch or less of rainfall, 0.01 inch for Rapid City, and a trace at Mitchell. Maximum temperatures were 90 degrees or hotter with 3 days over 100 at Pierre and Mobridge, 90 or hotter with 1 day over 100 at Huron and Mitchell, 4 days over 100 at Rapid City and topping at 109 on July 16. D1 was expanded into southwest South Dakota, and D0 expanded across the south central sections into the southeast and north central areas.
In Nebraska and northern Kansas, 100 degree and hotter temperatures combined with strong winds to dry the soil and desiccate crops, rapidly counteracting the beneficial effects of recent rains. While a few areas of the Cornhusker State received recent heavy rain, most of the state has experienced extreme dryness over the last 30 days combined with the extremely hot temperatures. Consequently, dryland crop conditions dropped from 76% good to excellent on July 10 to 53% good to excellent on July 17. D0 was expanded in Nebraska and into northern Kansas, with D1 poking into eastern Nebraska.

## The Northeast
Weak cold fronts and showers from the remnants of Hurricane Dennis brought spotty rain to the area during the week. There were a few reports of 2 inches or more, but many locations missed the substantial rains. D0A was expanded along the Pennsylvania- New York border to encompass areas with 50-70% of normal rain or less during the last 7 to 60 days. D0A was expanded along the Lakes Erie and Ontario shores of New York to reflect moisture deficits of the last 30 to 60 days. Buffalo has had only 0.90 inch of rain for the month to date, about half of normal, and down 1.48 inches since June 1, down 3.97 inches since January 1.

## The West
The upper air circulation pattern conspired to delay the onset of the western monsoon again this week. Hot, dry conditions predominated, with several wildfires scorching the landscape. A few stations in northwest Washington, the extreme northern Rockies, and parts of Colorado, New Mexico, and Arizona received half an inch or less of rain, with local reports of an inch or more. But otherwise little or no precipitation occurred. Instead, the weather was dominated by extremely hot temperatures, with several records set at stations ranging from Nevada and southern California to Wyoming. Much of the Southwest has experienced exceedingly hot temperatures during the last month or so, resulting in very high evaporation rates, especially in Arizona.
As of July 17, 43% of Wyoming had adequate topsoil moisture, down 12 points from last week and down 42 points from the high of 85% on June 12. Supplies were still well above the 5-year average of 25% for the state. Maximum temperatures exceeded 100 degrees on July 13 and broke records at several stations. On July 16, the high temperature of 104 degrees at Casper set a new record maximum for the date and tied the all-time record high which was dated on July 12, 1954. The D2 gap in central Wyoming was bridged, thus forming one area of D2 in the state. This gap had roughly coincided with the area of greatest precipitation departures at 90 days to 6 months.
Some minor adjustments to the impact boundaries and impact indicators were made this week. Impact line segments were added or adjusted over Nebraska, North Dakota, Wyoming, and northwest Colorado to separate H impacts in the Pacific Northwest and Southwest, from A impacts in the southern Plains to Great Lakes and eastward, with AH impacts being added in between from Wyoming to Nebraska.
Although no other adjustments in the West were made at this time, the Drought Monitor will continue to monitor conditions in this region. Changes may be made if the monsoon does not bring notable rainfall soon.

## Forecast
At the end of this week's Drought Monitor valid period, Hurricane Emily was bearing down on the southern Texas-northeast Mexico coast, with several inches of rain anticipated in the Brownsville area. Convective showers will dot other parts of the Texas drought areas. Frontal thunderstorms during the next 5 days are expected to bring an inch or more of rain to drought areas in the Upper Mississippi Valley and Great Lakes, with lesser amounts to the Ohio Valley. A shift in the upper air circulation pattern over the West, combined with tropical moisture from what will be the remnants of Emily, is forecasted to trigger monsoon showers that drop up to a half inch of rain over portions of Arizona and Colorado. Otherwise, little or no rainfall is expected July 21-25 over the drought areas of the West, Great Plains, and mid-Mississippi Valley. Some relief from the heat will come to the extreme northern Plains states during this period, but hot temperatures are expected to continue across most of the drought areas.
For July 26-August 2, near to below normal temperatures are projected for the West with above normal temperatures for the southeastern third of the country. The Southwest monsoon is expected to bring above normal rainfall to portions of the West, while most of the Plains and Mississippi Valley drought areas will be wetter than normal. The Pacific Northwest is forecasted to continue mostly drier than normal.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.306273576829</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-74.0328739972215</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965172854</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0035990523773</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:34:29-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 