<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-11-18</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brad Rippey</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>U.S. Department of Agriculture</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — November 18, 2008</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-11-18</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-11-18</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-11-20</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — November 18, 2008

## Introduction


## Alaska and Hawaii
Recent heavy snowfall brought an end to abnormally dry conditions (D0) along Alaska's Arctic Coast.  For example, Barrow received 23.2 inches of snow last month, breaking its October 1925 record of 21.2 inches.  Barrow received an additional 6.8 inches during the first half of November, ranking as its seventh-snowiest November 1-15 period on record.  Meanwhile, recent showers on Kauai, Hawaii, brought enough improvement in pasture conditions to warrant the removal of severe drought (D2) from the northeastern part of the island.  In addition, Kauai's extent of moderate drought (D1) was reduced.  Elsewhere in Hawaii, however, the drought depiction remained unchanged.

## The East and South
Widespread 1- to 2-inch rainfall totals, with locally higher amounts, fell across the East, resulting in a modest contraction of the drought area.  In addition, rain during the moisture recharge season and diminishing agricultural impacts resulted in the removal of the "A" (agricultural) designation from the northern half of the Eastern drought area.  As of November 16, the U.S. Department of Agriculture rated 73% of Ohio's winter wheat in good to excellent condition, along with 81% of North Carolina's crop.  However, the southern Appalachians' core area of extreme and exceptional drought (D3 and D4) remained virtually unchanged due to significant and persistent hydrological impacts.  Heavy rain (generally 2 to 4 inches) fell across eastern North Carolina, eliminating severe drought (D2) and reducing the coverage of abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1).  The coverage of D0 was also reduced from eastern Maryland into southern New Jersey.  A separate area of D0 across southern Louisiana was reduced sharply in size due to as much as 2 to 5 inches of rain in the southwestern part of the state.

## The Great Lakes Region
Rain and melted snow resulted in 0.5 to 1.0 inch of liquid equivalent totals across the southeastern half of the drought area stretching from the upper Mississippi Valley to Upper Michigan.  The extent of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) decreased very slightly across northeastern Iowa and southern and eastern Wisconsin.  In addition, the designation of the drought region was changed from "AH" to "H", reflecting the increase in topsoil moisture and lack of agricultural impacts at this time of year.

## The Plains
An assessment of rain and snow from earlier storms resulted in the removal of severe drought (D2) from all of western North Dakota and easternmost Montana.  That region became completely free of D2 for the first time since September 25, 2007.  Elsewhere in Montana, there was an expansion of abnormal dryness (D0) and the introduction of moderate drought (D1) on the High Plains just east of the Rocky Divide across the state's northern tier.  Some D1 also crept into southwestern Montana.  Meanwhile, there were no changes to the hydrological dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) on the central High Plains, but very heavy rain, with totals locally in excess of 5 inches, dented the eastern edge of the drought area in Texas.  Nevertheless, a core area of extreme drought (D3) persisted in south-central Texas.

## The West
Flooding subsided west of the Cascades, where November 1-18 rainfall totals included 14.43 inches (166% of normal) in Quillayute, Washington, and 9.94 inches (165%) in Astoria, Oregon.  Although significant precipitation ended after November 12, enough moisture spilled across the Cascades to result in a reduction in the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) in northeastern Oregon and adjoining areas.  Across the interior Northwest, rain resulted in a slight improvement in winter wheat condition.  Between November 9 and 16, the U.S. Department of Agriculture reported that the percentage of Oregon's winter wheat rated in very poor to poor condition changed from 29 to 24%.  During the same period, Washington's wheat rated very poor to poor changed from 32 to 30%.  Farther south, however, short-term dryness intensified in the Four Corners region.  As a result, D0 was introduced in parts of southeastern Utah, southwestern Colorado, northwestern New Mexico, and northeastern Arizona.  California's drought depiction was not changed, although conditions remained ripe for additional wildfire activity across southern areas.  Mid-November wildfires near Los Angeles charred more than 40,000 acres of vegetation and damaged or destroyed nearly 1,000 structures.  On November 14-15, consecutive daily-record highs were reported in California locations such as Burbank (91 and 90 degrees F), Santa Ana (94 degrees F both days), and El Cajon (94 and 96 degrees F).  In addition, winds howled across California, with gusts reaching 75 mph (on November 13) on Whitaker Peak and 78 mph (on November 15) at Camp Nine.  The latter gust occurred near the site of the Sayre fire, which was one of three major incidents (along with the Freeway complex and the Tea fire) to affect the hills near Los Angeles.  The Freeway complex was the largest of the fires, with acreage approaching 30,000 acres by November 18, while the Sayre fire was the most destructive, with more than 600 structures consumed by flames.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (November 20-24), dry weather will prevail nearly nationwide.  Snow squalls will re-develop in areas downwind of the Great Lakes, while rain and snow showers will affect the northern Rockies and the Pacific Northwest.  On November 21-22, a fast-moving storm system could produce light snow across the northern Plains and the Great Lakes region, while scattered rain showers may fall across the Mid-South.  Warm weather in the West will contrast with chilly conditions across the Midwest and East.
The CPC 6- to 10-day forecast (November 25-29) calls for the likelihood of below-normal temperatures in the East, while warmer-than-normal weather will prevail across the Northwest, the Intermountain West, and the northern and central Plains.  Meanwhile, below-normal precipitation across the majority of the U.S. will contrast with wetter-than-normal conditions in southern California and the Desert Southwest.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-161.7681475</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-74.3172158</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>70.4052714</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:43:47-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 