<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2004-01-06</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — January 06, 2004</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2004-01-06</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2004-01-06</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2004-01-08</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — January 06, 2004

## Introduction


## Alaska and Hawaii
Heavy precipitation deluged most of Hawaii for the last 8 or 9 days, resulting in the elimination of D0 conditions across Lanai and Maui, and improvement to D0 for western sections of both Molokai and the Big Island. The former D0 and D1 areas recorded anywhere from 2 to 15 inches of precipitation for the 9-day period ending January 5. Kahului, on Maui, received 5.5 inches, exceeding their total for the previous 10 months combined.
Farther north, scattered light to moderate precipitation fell on southeastern Alaska, keeping D0 conditions intact. Below-normal precipitation totals for periods ranging from a few months to about a year continue to affect the region.

## The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes Region
This was not a good week for areas experiencing dryness and drought in the nations midsection, east of the Rockies. Between 0.5 and 0.9 inch of precipitation fell on south-central Iowa, and 0.3 to 0.5 inch dampened parts of the far northern Plains, the western Great Lakes region, southern Nebraska, southwestern and central Iowa, northwestern Missouri, eastern sections of Kansas and Oklahoma, central and southwestern Arkansas, and northern Louisiana. Meanwhile, broad sections of the upper Mississippi Valley, South Dakota, most of the High Plains, and the south-central and southwestern Great Plains recorded no precipitation this past week.
The weeks meager precipitation kept dryness and drought intact across most of the area, but conditions deteriorated for broad sections of the regions southern tier. Despite light precipitation, 30-day totals were 1 to 3 inches below normal in the ArkLaTex vicinity, with 90-day totals 7 to 10 inches below normal in northeastern Texas and adjacent areas. Thus, D0 conditions expanded northward and eastward into northern Louisiana, southern Arkansas, and east-central Oklahoma while D1 conditions reached eastward through the Red River (South) Valley and the adjacent ArkLaTex region. D0 conditions also expanded to cover most of central Texas. Farther west, more serious drought conditions expanded through the southern High Plains and northwestern Texas. In the last 6 months, only 1 to locally 6 inches of precipitation fell on most of eastern New Mexico, southeastern Colorado, and northwestern Texas (only 17% of normal at Lubbock, TX), resulting in deterioration to D3 and D4 in much of this region. D2 conditions also stretched a bit farther east in the western Red River (South) Valley and the central Texas Panhandle.

## The Rockies and Far West
Cold and stormy conditions again dominated areas from the Rockies westward, resulting in continued slow improvement in the regions protracted drought situation. Between 4 and 6 inches of precipitation fell on portions of central Idaho and southwestern Colorado while 1.5- to 4.0-inch totals were common across part of the Idaho Panhandle, the remainder of central Idaho, areas from far southwestern Montana southward through central Utah and most of north-central, central, and southwestern Colorado. Light to locally moderate precipitation fell on most other areas, although little or none was measured in parts of southern Montana, southern and eastern Wyoming, western and eastern Utah, southeastern Oregon, central and southern Nevada, and lower elevations in the desert Southwest. As a result, the sharp gradient of D0 to D3 conditions again receded to the east across southern Oregon, and conditions improved to D1 through interior southwestern Colorado, where several high-elevation sites have now received over 24 inches of precipitation in the last 6 months. Elsewhere, scattered and relatively small parts of last weeks D1 to D4 areas improved by 1 category in central Colorado, western Wyoming, north-central Utah, and the southern half of Idaho. Snowpack water equivalent remains near- to well-above-normal across most of the Rockies and far West except along the southern tier, the eastern fringes, and parts of the Pacific Northwest. Across most of Oregon, southern Idaho, central and western Utah, all but the eastern tier of Nevada, and the Sierra Nevada now have 125% to 200% of normal snowpack water for this time of year. Because it is still fairly early in the regions snow season, a change in the prevailing weather for a few weeks could still render todays promising numbers moot, but the farther into the season that surplus snowpack water continues, the greater the possibility that significant increases in reservoir storage could be experienced this spring.
Farther south, conditions are not nearly so promising. The higher elevations of southwestern New Mexico are reporting less than 25% of normal snowpack water for this time of year, and the higher elevations of central Arizona and lower northern New Mexico are reporting 40% to 55% of normal.

## The Southeast
Light precipitation in northwest Florida was timely, alleviating impacts from short topsoil moisture for the time being.

## Forecast
January 7 to 12 should bring continued relief to parts of the Northwest, but little or no beneficial precipitation elsewhere. Between 0.5 and 1.5 inches of precipitation are anticipated in the dry areas of northern Oregon, eastern Washington, central and northern Idaho, northwestern Montana, and part of northwestern Wyoming. Between 0.1 and 0.5 inch are expected across northern Nevada, much of Utah, western Colorado, the northern Plains, part of the lower Mississippi Valley, the western Great Lakes region, and the remainders of Oregon, Idaho, western Montana, and western Wyoming. Little or no precipitation is forecast in other current areas of dryness and drought. In addition, temperatures averaging 5F to 12F above normal are expected through most of the Plains, Rockies, and southern Great Basin, likely exacerbating the effects of exiguous precipitation.
For the ensuing 5 days, the odds favor surplus precipitation in southeastern sections of the D0 area in Alaska, the northwestern Plains, and the northwestern Plains. Most other areas of dryness and drought, unfortunately, are expected to receive deficient precipitation, excepting only the southernmost High Plains, the Great Lakes region, the upper Mississippi Valley, the northeasternmost Rockies, most of Nebraska, and southeastern Alaska outside of the Panhandle. Across the southern and west-central Rockies, the Great Basin, eastern Oregon and adjacent Idaho, and Alaska, above-normal temperatures are expected, potentially increasing impacts resulting from deficient precipitation.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.3062736</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-87.7589399</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>64.4921669</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:54:15-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 