<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-06-29</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Laura Edwards</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Western Regional Climate Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — June 29, 2010</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-06-29</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-06-29</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-07-01</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — June 29, 2010

## Introduction
Heavy rains, exceeding 5 inches in some areas, brought substantial improvement to parts of the Great Lakes region entrenched in a protracted drought. Farther south and east, relentless heat from the south-central Plains northeastward through the central and southern Atlantic Seaboard during June allowed dryness and drought to expand and intensify despite locally moderate to heavy rainfall. Little or no precipitation fell from the Rockies to the West Coast, allowing abnormal dryness to expand in a few small areas; however, D0 and D1 conditions were reduced in parts of the northern Rockies and Intermountain West following a re-assessment of conditions. Meanwhile, heavy rains and some flooding led to the withdrawal of D0 in parts of southeastern Alaska, but increasing moisture deficits prompted D0 expansion in the southwest portion of the state.

## Alaska
Heavy rains of  1 to 4 inches wiped out abnormally dry conditions across interior southeastern Alaska, with flood warnings and advisories issued for the Upper Tanana Valley, the Deltana and Tanana Flats, the Eastern Alaskan Range, and the Copper River Basin. In addition, several inches of rain fell on and near Juneau, eliminating D0 in the northeastern Alaskan Panhandle. A few inches of rain fell on most other parts of the Alaskan Panhandle, but D0 was retained because 90-day totals remained 5 to locally 16 inches below normal. In contrast, D0 was expanded into the upper Aleutians where only 70 to 80 percent of normal precipitation (4 to 9 inches less than normal) has fallen over the past 12 months.

## Hawaii
Generally light rainfall kept dryness and drought conditions unchanged from last week, including the exceptional drought (D4) covering part of the northeastern Big Island, currently the only drought identified as exceptional anywhere in the nation.

## The Atlantic Seaboard
Despite scattered moderate rainfall, a hot and generally dry week allowed for rapid drying in many areas, and thus D0A was expanded to cover broader sections of the Carolinas and a large area across the mid-Atlantic and lower Northeast. In addition, moderate drought was introduced in much of central and southern Maryland and some adjacent locales. Temperatures from the Carolinas to southern New York averaged at least 2oF above normal for the last 30 days, with departures reaching +6oF in parts of northeastern North Carolina and the central mid-Atlantic. Precipitation totals in many of these areas were at least an inch below normal during the same period, with departures of -2 to nearly -4 inches observed in a few regions, the largest centered over north-central Maryland. Since late March, rainfall totaled 4 to 7 inches below normal across extreme southern Delaware, the southern tier of Maryland, and portions of central Maryland where moderate drought was introduced this week. Topsoil is short or very short of moisture in 75 to 96 percent of South Carolina, Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware, with 41 percent of pasture lands in poor or very poor condition through the latter two states, according to the National Agricultural Statistics Service.

## The Great Lakes Region
Widespread moderate to heavy rain, with totals exceeding 5 inches in part of north-central Wisconsin, brought broad-scale improvement to many areas that have been entrenched in long-term drought and eliminated surface moisture concerns, at least for the time being. Most of this region has received near- to above-normal totals over the course of the past 3 to 5 months, except in portions of the western Upper Peninsula of Michigan where an area of extreme drought persists. Drought Monitor classifications were improved by more than one category in some sections of north-central and northwestern Wisconsin where 6-month precipitation totals have climbed to near normal levels. It should be noted, however, that dryness dates back multiple years in portions of the northern Great Lakes region, likely making complete relief a slow and arduous process there.

## The South-Central States
Widespread moderate rains eliminated abnormally dry conditions over a large swath of central and western Texas and in portions of northwestern Tennessee and northeastern Arkansas. In stark contrast, heat and evaporation offset localized heavy rains in most other areas, allowing dryness and drought to persist or worsen. Most notably, dryness dating back at least 6 months and temperatures averaging at least a couple of degrees above normal during June prompted the introduction of extreme drought (D3) across a large part of northern Louisiana. Precipitation this year is 12 to locally 16 inches below normal throughout the new D3 area, with some locations reporting less than half of normal precipitation during this period.
In other parts of the south-central states, D0 to D2 conditions improved in a few small areas where heavy rainfall was relatively widespread, but dryness either persisted or intensified in most areas. Some patches of severe drought were introduced across central and northeastern Texas where rainfall totals over the last 2 months were 5 to 7 inches below normal.

## The West
Little precipitation fell from the Rockies westward, generally keeping any dryness and drought intact, to some small-scale expansion of abnormal dryness was noted in southwestern Colorado and central Arizona. Farther north, a re-assessment of conditions led to a significant reduction in the extent of abnormal dryness and moderate drought  in western Montana and northern Idaho, with drought eliminated completely in areas north and west of southeastern Idaho. In these areas, record or near-record June precipitation brought water-year totals to near or above normal levels.

## Forecast
Moisture fueled at least partially by Hurricane Alex will dump heavy rain along most of the Gulf Coast during the first five days of July 2010. At least 2 inches should fall on the southern half of Louisiana and a large part of southern and southeastern Texas, with totals of 4 to 8 inches possible in Texas south and west of Galveston. More modest amounts of 0.5 to 2.0 inches are expected over the rest of Texas and Louisiana, southwestern Oklahoma, most of the dry areas across the Great Lakes region, and the southeastern Carolinas. Meanwhile, little or no rain is anticipated in most areas south and west of Montana, and from most of North Carolina northward through central New York.
The ensuing 5 days (July 6 – 10, 2010) feature enhanced chances for above-normal precipitation in the Alaskan Panhandle and in a broad swath from the Gulf Coast and Texas northeastward through central and eastern sections of the Great Lakes region. Meanwhile, below-median precipitation is favored across northern sections of the Rockies, Intermountain West, and West Coast. Neither abnormally heavy nor abnormally light precipitation is favored in any other current areas or dryness and drought.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-165.126434927972</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-73.6540197039408</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965167357</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>67.485813973247</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:33:51-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 