<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2001-12-04</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — December 04, 2001</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2001-12-04</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2001-12-04</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2001-12-06</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — December 04, 2001

## Introduction


## Hawaii
Moderate to heavy rains doused much of the island chain during November 26 - December 4, bringing substantial, widespread improvement to the protracted drought that has affected parts of the state for more than 3 years. Many locations received 1" to 2 of rain during the week, but scattered orographically-favored areas received much larger amounts, including 5" to 7" on Oahu, over 4" on Molokai, about 6" on Maui, and 14" to 28" on the Big Island. The result was a general one-category improvement to most of the previous weeks dryness and drought classifications, though stubborn D2(A,F) and D1(A,F) held on in western Molokai and northwestern Hawaii Island, respectively. Still, most locations remained below normal for the last 6 months as a whole, and almost all sites from Maui County northwestward through Kauai reported rainfall totals below the 15 percentile threshold for the 1-year period ending November 30, 2001.

## The East
Moderate to locally heavy precipitation (0.5" to 2.0") fell on many areas of the Northeast and New England west of the I-95 corridor, prompting spotty reductions in drought and dryness classifications. In addition, former D0 conditions in central and northeast Pennsylvania, where some of the heavier precipitation fell, were reclassified D0(W) in deference to improved streamflows and the elimination of 30-day precipitation shortages. Farther south, moderate precipitation brushed the southern Appalachians and the western fringes of the dry region, but most areas received only scattered totals of 0.3" or less. Despite recent precipitation in parts of the East, including 2 consecutive relatively wet weeks in central and northern sections, many areas remained 4 or more inches below normal for the last 90 days, with deficits reaching 7 to 10 inches across the southern half of Virginia and parts of adjacent North Carolina and the southern Appalachians. The continuing dryness led to a deterioration from D0 to D1 in the west-central Appalachians, from D1 to D2 in central and southern Virginia, and from D2 to D3 in a swath covering the central Carolinas (where year-to-date precipitation totals are 1' to 1 below normal). Along the Eastern Seaboard and the Deep South (the New England, Mid-Atlantic, and South Atlantic-Gulf hydrologic service regions), 44% of all streamflow sites reported flows below their respective 10th percentile thresholds for December 4, up from 35% one week prior but below the recent peak of 60% reported November 23 and 24, according to the U. S. Geological Survey. Not surprisingly, November streamflow volume into the Chesapeake Bay was the lowest of any November since records began in 1937. Going a bit deeper, groundwater levels are also very low in some areas. In late November, the Washington County, MD site reported groundwater depth at its lowest since November 1986, and among the lowest 1.5% of their 3900 observations since April 1970. Farther north, New London County, CT was at its lowest since July 1991, and was among the lowest 4% of their 2065 observations made since May 1958. Most sites were not as unusually low as these 2 locations, but a majority were significantly below normal. Elsewhere, sub-normal weekly rainfall kept D0 conditions intact along the southern tier of Puerto Rico while abundant rains, ranging from 1" or 2" in north-central Arkansas to between 4" and 8" in northeast Arkansas, eliminated D1 and reduced the extent of residual D0 conditions in that region.

## The Plains
Despite abundant precipitation to the east and west of this region, most of the Plains regions experiencing dryness and drought received only light totals for the week, if any. As a result, D0 and D1 conditions expanded slightly in the northwestern Plains of eastern Montana and western North Dakota, and in the central Plains of northern Oklahoma, central and southern Kansas, and western Missouri. Precipitation totals for the last 90 days were 1 to locally 4 inches below normal in the D0 and D1 areas of the central Plains, and 30-day totals were below 25% of normal in much of western North Dakota and eastern Montana.

## The West
Abundant precipitation again fell on most of the dry regions from the Rockies westward, and unlike the previous few weeks, enough cold air accompanied the storminess to substantially increase what had been sub-par snowpacks in the higher elevations, according to the Natural Resources Conservation Center. The heaviest amounts fell on climatologically-favored areas along and west of the Cascade and Sierra Nevada ridge lines, including coastal California as far south as Monterrey. Almost all of these locales picked up at least 4" of precipitation (liquid equivalent) last week, with totals approaching 14" in parts of northwest Oregon and southwest Washington. This precipitation, in addition to moderate to heavy amounts during the previous few weeks, prompted an across-the-board one-category reduction in drought classification (from previous D0(W) to D3(W) conditions) for the western halves of Washington and Oregon, northern California, and west-central California. Precipitation totals were lower farther inland, but at least moderate precipitation fell on most areas from north-central Colorado, western Wyoming, and western Montana westward, with heavier amounts improving former D3(W) conditions in southern and northern Idaho and northeast Washington. The recent precipitation has substantially improved soil moisture profiles for most areas and eliminated any significant wildfire threat, so the areal extent of the region enveloped by the W qualifier (denoting hydrology as the primary concern) again grew considerably last week. But despite the abundant, beneficial precipitation easing short-term moisture concerns, many areas still have large long-term shortages which will only be eliminated by continued near- to above-normal precipitation for most of the 2001-2002 wet season. Since the start of the last water year (October 2000), most of northern California and areas from the Cascades westward in Washington and Oregon are still 9" to &amp;gt;24" below normal.

## Forecast
Temperatures should average at or above normal throughout the contiguous 48 states for the next 5 days (December 6 - 10), with 5-day averages exceeding 4oF above normal for most locations from the eastern slopes of the Rockies eastward to the Atlantic Coast. In much of the central Great Plains, middle Mississippi Valley, mid-Atlantic, and Northeast, temperatures are forecast to average 12F to 16F above normal. With respect to the areas currently identified as abnormally dry or in drought, little or no precipitation is forecast for much of South Carolina, southern Georgia, northern Florida, the western half of the Plains, and the southern and eastern tiers of the western U.S. dry area. In contrast, at least 1" of precipitation is anticipated in northwest Montana, northwest Wyoming, central and northern Idaho, and the Pacific Coast from northern California northward to Canada. Between 2" and 6" are forecast in areas of Washington and far northern Oregon west of the Cascades. The ensuing 5 days (December 11 - 15) should remain warmer than normal in the eastern half of the country, but more seasonable conditions, and some colder than normal weather, are expected farther west. Below-normal precipitation is likely during this period in southern New England, the I-95 corridor, and the Atlantic Seaboard from Maryland southward through Florida and westward to the Appalachian foothills. However, wet weather could abet improving conditions in northern Arkansas, the central and southern Plains, the southern Rockies, and again in the Pacific Northwest.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-158.2717276</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.9645498</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.8841923</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0033021</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:56:26-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 