<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2006-04-25</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brad Rippey</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>U.S. Department of Agriculture</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — April 25, 2006</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2006-04-25</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2006-04-25</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2006-04-27</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — April 25, 2006

## Introduction


## Alaska
Mostly dry weather prevailed in abnormally dry (D0) areas of the Alaskan mainland, while locally more than 2 inches of precipitation fell across southeastern Alaskas similarly dry Alexander Archipelago. Nevertheless, year-to-date precipitation through April 25 totaled just 9.68 inches (65% of normal) in Juneau.

## The East
Soaking rains fell from the southern Appalachians to southern New England, denting abnormally dry conditions (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2). On April 22, Mid-Atlantic daily record totals included 2.88 inches at Virginias Dulles Airport and 2.13 inches in Wilmington, Delaware. A day later, records for April 23 were shattered in locations such as Bridgeport, Connecticut (5.30 inches), and Islip, New York (4.63 inches). As a result, moderate drought (D1) was eliminated from Delaware and environs, while there was significant erosion of abnormal dryness (D0) from near Washington, D.C., to west of Boston, Massachusetts. Farther south, weekly rainfall totals locally in excess of 3 inches brought some slight reductions in abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) across the southern Appalachians and adjacent foothills. Despite the rain, January 1 - April 25 precipitation totals were as low as 5.95 inches (44% of normal) in Florence, South Carolina, and 4.15 inches (29%) in Lumberton, North Carolina.

## The Gulf Coast States
Little rain fell in the hardest-hit drought areas of southern Texas and the central Gulf Coast region. Thunderstorms in central Texas flattened the northern edge of extreme to exceptional drought (D3 to D4), but little or no rain fell in the lower Rio Grande Valley. Brownsville, Texas, coming off its driest year since 1953, noted just 1.24 inches of rain (24% of normal) from January 1 - April 25. Since January 1, 2005, Brownsvilles rainfall has totaled 15.65 inches, 48% of normal. Farther east, significant rainfall arrived in the central Gulf Coast region after the official cutoff period (6 a.m. CDT on April 25) for this weeks product and will be evaluated for the May 2 Drought Monitor. In Louisiana, January 1 - April 25 rainfall was 40% of normal or less in locations such as Lake Charles (6.14 inches, or 40%), New Iberia (5.52 inches, or 34%), and Baton Rouge (6.67 inches, or 32%). Meanwhile, modest amounts of rain (generally 1 to 2 inches) fell in western Floridas moderate drought (D1) area, but abnormally dry (D0) conditions persisted across most of the remainder of Florida. By April 25, the Keetch-Byram Drought Index, a fire threat indicator that ranges from 0 to 800, exceeded 600 (on average) in four southern Florida counties: Lee, Hendry, Collier, and Broward. Elsewhere, abnormal dryness and drought (D0 through D2) expanded northward across the central Gulf Coast region, including the lower Mississippi Valley, due to hot, mostly dry weather. On April 18, Mississippi highs of 93F in Hattiesburg and 91F in Vicksburg were both 1F shy of monthly record highs (94F on April 29, 1955, and 92F on April 28, 2002, respectively).

## The Plains, Mid-South, and Midwest
At one point last week, blizzard conditions in the Black Hills and environs contrasted with April-record highs in the south-central United States. From April 17-20, Lead, South Dakota, received 64.9 inches of snow and 5.73 inches of liquid equivalent, but nearby Rapid City noted just 1.0 inch of snow and 0.72 inch of liquid. High winds accompanied the storm, with gusts reaching 60 m.p.h. or higher in locations such as North Platte, Nebraska (60 m.p.h. on April 19), and East Rapid City, South Dakota (69 m.p.h. on April 19). Although effects of the storms precipitation were fairly localized, the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) was reduced slightly in the Black Hills and adjacent areas. Meanwhile, dry, windy weather and fluctuating temperatures maintained significant stress on the High Plains pastures and winter wheat from eastern Colorado and western Kansas southward into northern Texas. The percentage of winter wheat rated in very poor to poor condition on April 23 stood at 77% in Texas and 72% in Oklahoma, according to USDA. Those figures for Kansas and Colorado were 31% and 22%, respectively. Moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) continued to gradually expand its domain northward across the central Plains.
The central and southern High Plains temperatures rode a stunning roller coaster, culminating in a widespread freeze on April 26. During a 10-day period in western Oklahoma, Gage noted a high of 99F on April 17, a light freeze (31F) on April 19, a return to hot weather (95F) on April 23, and another freeze (30F) on April 26. Monthly record highs were established in locations such as Dallas-Ft. Worth, Texas (101F; previously, 100F on April 18, 1925), McAlester, Oklahoma (95F; previously, 94F on April 18, 1987), and Fayetteville, AR (93F; previously, 90F on April 6, 1960, and April 12, 1972). For Dallas-Ft. Worth, it was the third-earliest triple-digit reading on record behind highs of 100F on March 9, 1911, and March 21, 1916. Triple-digit temperatures were also observed in several other Texas cities, including Del Rio (101, 101, and 104F from April 16-18), Wichita Falls (101F on April 17), and San Antonio (100F on April 18).
Significant precipitation briefly peppered the southeastern Plains, including a portion of the extreme drought (D3) area centered on southeastern Kansas/southwestern Missouri/northwestern Arkansas/northeastern Oklahoma. For example, Tulsa, Oklahoma, netted 2.36 inches of rain in a 24-hour period on April 24-25. Although there were some modest D3 reductions in the aforementioned four-state area, persistently harsh (hot, dry, windy) conditions farther west resulted in a broad expansion of extreme drought westward across Oklahoma. Extreme drought (D3) also expanded across Texas northern panhandle and environs, but rain farther south brought some improvement (reductions in coverage of moderate to severe drought [D1 to D2]) in west-central, north-central, and northeastern Texas. Farther north, moderate drought (D1) was removed from northern Illinois, based on a re-evaluation of earlier rainfall.

## The West
Warm, mostly dry weather prevailed in the Southwest. Sublimation of a portion of the snow pack reduced spring and summer streamflow expectations in some areas, resulting, for example, in an expansion of moderate drought (D1) across southern Colorado. In central New Mexico, an island of moderate drought (D1) was downgraded to severe drought (D2), since conditions in that region were no longer appreciably better than in surrounding areas. Extreme drought (D3) remained in place across large portions of eastern Arizona and western New Mexico.

## Forecast
Weather features to watch in the next 5-day period (April 27 - May 1) that may affect areas of dryness or drought include: 1) Showers will end across the Southeast on April 27, followed by a brief spell of cool, dry weather; 2) A slow-moving storm will cross the Southwest before interacting with another system over the Plains. Beneficial precipitation will develop in the Southwest on April 27 and linger through the following day in the southern Rockies, where some significant snow is possible; 3) The same storm will cross the southern half of the Plains on April 28-29, producing widespread showers and locally severe thunderstorms; 4) During the weekend (April 29-30), showers and thunderstorms will sweep into the Southeast, while rain will affect much of the Midwest. Rain will spread into the Mid-Atlantic States on April 30 - May 1.
The 6- to 10-day (May 2-6) outlook from the Climate Prediction Center calls for the likelihood of cooler-than-normal weather in the Southeast and above-normal temperatures across the northern Plains and the West. Wetter-than-normal weather in the southern Rockies and New England will contrast with below-normal precipitation across southern Florida and much of the Plains, Midwest, and areas west of the Rockies.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.1559793</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-69.9254</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>24.5183263</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>66.2096767</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T01:13:58-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 