<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-04-01</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — April 01, 2008</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-04-01</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-04-01</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-04-03</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — April 01, 2008

## Introduction


## Alaska
Significant precipitation continues to evade the D0 region, with only 0.1 to 0.5 inch reported at a few scattered locations. As a result, D0 conditions persisted.

## Hawaii
Below normal precipitation fell on the island chain last week, keeping D0 conditions intact.

## Puerto Rico
Moderate to locally heavy rains fell on the northeastern, central, and western parts of the island, with 2 to locally 4 inches falling on part of the interior southwest. However, rainfall appeared insufficient to improve the D0 conditions covering most of the island.

## The Plains
Locally heavy snows lifted parts of eastern South Dakota out of D0 and reduced the southward extent of D1 in northeastern South Dakota. Meanwhile, 1 to 3 inches of rain improved conditions to D0 for a small section of central Texas, and 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches of precipitation dampened the western Upper Peninsula of Michigan and northeastern Wisconsin, but was not enough to improve the abnormally dry conditions in those areas. Elsewhere, light to locally moderate precipitation fell on the rest of South Dakota, western Nebraska, eastern Wyoming, and several other locations scattered across the northern Plains while little or nothing fell from western Kansas and eastern Colorado southward to the Mexican border. As a result, D0 and D1 conditions expanded in southern and western New Mexico, and D3 was introduced in a large part of western North Dakota where recent conditions have been particularly dry. In most these areas where dryness and drought intensified, precipitation totals for the last 6 months have been less than half of normal, and under 25 percent of normal since the beginning of the calendar year.

## The Southeast and Mid-Atlantic
Once again, a storm system brought heavy rain to parts of the Mississippi and Ohio Valleys, but dropped much lower totals on the areas of dryness and drought in the Southeast and middle Atlantic regions. Between 2 and 4 inches fell on portions of central and southeastern Tennessee and isolated sites across Georgia, but totals of 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches were more common in the D0 to D3 areas, with even lower amounts reported in the northern and western mid-Atlantic region, southwestern Virginia, the central and western Carolinas, northern and west-central Georgia, eastern Alabama, and most of Florida.
As a result, the areas of dryness and drought depicted last week changed little. D3 conditions improved to D2 in a small section of southeastern Tennessee which received the heaviest rainfall last week. Meanwhile, D1 to D2 conditions expanded a bit in central and northern Virginia and parts of southern Maryland and Delaware.
In addition, little or no precipitation fell on the southern half of Mississippi, much of eastern Louisiana, and adjacent Arkansas. Since early October 2007, these areas have received 4 to locally 12 inches less precipitation than normal, and as a result, D0 conditions were introduced this week.
Over the last few months, precipitation in the areas of dryness and drought has been closer to normal than was the case for much of 2007, but has still been below normal. For the last 90 days, precipitation totals in a large part of the dry region have been within 4 inches of normal, with larger deficits restricted to southern sections of Maryland and Delaware, the Piedmont sections of Virginia and the Carolinas, northern Georgia, the central Gulf Coast, northeastern Louisiana, and southeastern Arkansas. As a result, large long-term precipitation deficits continue to affect the region, with most areas from the western Carolinas southward through Florida and westward across Tennessee, Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, and adjacent sections of Arkansas and Louisiana reporting amounts 1 to 2 feet below normal since early April 2006.

## The West
Substantial changes were introduced across many of the dry areas across the western states this week, almost none of which were based on conditions observed during the prior week. Early April represents the approximate climatological peak in snowpack for much of the West, and conditions at this time of year provide substantial insight into how streamflows and reservoir stores will unfold as the snow melts and the warmer time of the year progresses. March 2008 was drier than normal for most areas in the West affected by dryness and drought. In fact, Phoenix, AZ recorded its first precipitation-free March since 1984. However, snowpack on April 1, 2008 was near to substantially above normal across a vast majority of the region (basin-averaged amounts below 90 percent of normal were restricted to the central Sierra Nevada, west-central and eastern sections of Nevada, south-central Idaho, and most of the higher elevations across the southernmost Rockies, where peak snowpack tends to occur earlier in the year). This bodes well for the forthcoming warm season, but must be considered along with the dry 2006-2007 winter across most of the region, and even longer-term dryness across Arizona, southern sections of California and Nevada, much of central and western Wyoming, and a few other areas scattered across the West. As of April 1, only Arizona reported above-normal statewide reservoir storage, and 6 states (WA, OR, NV, UT, NM, and WY) reported only 65 to 75 percent of normal, though this of course should be bolstered as the current substantial snowpack melts.
Given all of these factors, a significant reduction was made in the extent of D2 conditions, which are now limited to central Nevada, areas near the Nevada/Oregon/California triple point, part of southeastern Idaho, northern Utah, and southwestern Wyoming. In addition, smaller areas of improvement from former D0 and D1 conditions were introduced in southeastern Oregon, central and southern Idaho, western Wyoming, and southeastern Utah. On the other hand, this re-assessment led to a few areas of deterioration, with D1 conditions returning to the Sierra Nevada, and some expansion of D0 to D1 conditions in parts of southern Utah and northern Arizona.
It should be noted that substantial long-term deficits still exist across much of the Southwest despite near-normal precipitation for the last 12 months. Some of the southeastern California deserts have received less than half of normal rainfall since April 2005, and reports of 50 to 80 percent of normal are common across southern California, central and southern Nevada, and parts of Arizona.

## Forecast
In general, April 2 - 7, 2008 is expected to feature beneficial precipitation in the dry areas across the eastern half of the country, but only spotty, marginal relief at best through the rest of the contiguous 48 states. Between 3 and 4 inches of rain is forecast across Tennessee and adjacent sections of Alabama and Mississippi, and at least 1.5 inches is expected through the mid-Atlantic region, the Carolinas, Florida, much of northern Alabama and Mississippi, southeastern Arkansas, and northeastern Louisiana. Generally 0.5 to 1.5 inches should fall on the remaining areas of dryness and drought in the Southeast, in addition to central and northern sections of Minnesota, parts of southwestern Nebraska and western Montana, and a small section of coastal southern California. In the remaining dry areas, less than 0.5 inch is forecast, with little or none projected for the southern half of the High Plains, New Mexico, Arizona, Utah, and Wyoming. Meanwhile, daily high temperatures should average near to somewhat below normal across the central and northern states, with slightly above average values expected along the southern tier of states.
For the ensuing 5 days, the odds favor wetter than normal conditions in the mid-Atlantic and Southeastern dry areas, the Plains from northern Texas to the Canadian border, and the easternmost sections of the central and northern Rockies. In contrast, below normal precipitation is favored for roughly the southwestern half of Texas, most of New Mexico, Arizona, all but the northernmost reaches of California, Nevada, and Utah, and the D0 area in Alaska. The odds favor neither above nor below normal precipitation in other areas of dryness and drought. Meanwhile, warmer than normal conditions are favored in the dry areas of the eastern states and in southern Texas while unusually cool weather is more likely in most of the West and across Alaska.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-160.236083</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.6151627</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.8869435</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>71.3980481</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:51:01-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 