<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2009-04-21</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Heim</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — April 21, 2009</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2009-04-21</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2009-04-21</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2009-04-23</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — April 21, 2009

## Introduction
As one weather system exited the Northeast at the beginning of this U.S. Drought Monitor (USDM) week, another system entered the country from the west.  The second large, strong, wet low pressure system slowly moved across the country during the week, dumping beneficial precipitation over many drought areas from the central Rockies to the East Coast.  Much of the country, from the central and southern Plains to the Atlantic coast, received an inch or more of precipitation, with locally heavier amounts.

## Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico
Pastures and general vegetation improved this week over parts of Hawaii, so the D3A over the Big Island was improved to D2A.  In Alaska, some streams along the southern coast were below normal, and several stations in the area had below-normal precipitation over the last 7 days out to the last 12 months.  D0 was introduced to the southern Alaska coast at the driest stations.  Puerto Rico was not showing signs of any significant dryness or drought at this time.

## The Eastern States
While an inch or more of rain fell over the northern and western portions of the drought area in Florida during this USDM week, the southern areas received considerably less rain.  About two-thirds of the topsoil and two-thirds of the subsoil, statewide, remained in the very short to short categories, with 40 percent of the pasture rated very poor to poor by the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) as of April 19.  Lake Okeechobee continued to drop, down to a level of 11.56 feet as of April 20 (normal is 13.89 feet).  D0-D1-D2 were pulled back in the northern and west central drought areas of Florida, while D2 and D3 expanded in southern Florida.
An inch or more of rain fell across Ohio and the D1 area of the Mid-Atlantic States.  The wet conditions of this week and last week resulted in the elimination of the D1.  D0 was pulled back in southern Virginia, West Virginia, and Ohio, but spots of D0 were left in southwest Ohio and western West Virginia where long-term precipitation deficits remained.  Streamflow and soil moisture improved, with only 6 percent of topsoil moisture short and 9 percent of pasture rated very poor to poor in Virginia.  While soil moisture improved, the USDA rated 22 percent of pasture land still very poor to poor in West Virginia.  Groundwater levels improved but remained low at some wells, and widespread year-to-date precipitation deficits of 4+ inches, with 6 inches or more in some areas, persisted.  D0 remained over much of the Mid-Atlantic area to reflect long-term precipitation deficits, and the impacts designator was changed to H to reflect lingering hydrological concerns.
Rains fell over the southern Appalachian drought area this week.  But the 1+ inch rains were not enough to eliminate long-term deficits.  Eleven percent of North Carolina’s pasture was rated very poor to poor, and 90-day precipitation deficits ranged from 3 to 6 inches and 12-month deficits exceeded 10 inches, and some wells indicated continued low ground water, in the southern mountains of western North Carolina.  While precipitation deficits have been reduced and streamflows improved in northeast Georgia, lake levels (Lanier and Hartwell) continued low.  Lake Hartwell’s level was 654.13 feet, or 5.87 feet below full pool, as of April 16.  No change was made to the depiction across the Carolinas and Georgia to reflect continuing hydrological drought impacts.

## The Great Lakes and Upper Mississippi Valley Region
The half-inch or more of precipitation that fell across parts of the Minnesota to Michigan drought area had little impact on the long-term deficits.  D2 was pulled back from the Minneapolis-St. Paul area, but no other changes were made this week.  April 19 USDA reports rated 38 percent of soil moisture very short to short and 43 percent of pastures very poor to poor in Wisconsin, and 18 percent of topsoil and 17 percent of subsoil moisture very short to short in Minnesota.  In Iowa, 21 percent of the range and pasture land was rated very poor to poor.

## The Plains
The slow-moving low pressure system dropped an inch or more of precipitation over a widespread area of the central to southern Plains this week, with very heavy rains deluging parts of the drought areas.  Two to four inches of rain and melted equivalent of snow fell over parts of western Kansas, western Nebraska, and northeast Colorado.  Southeast Texas was deluged with over 6 inches of rain over large areas.  Locally heavier amounts were recorded, with the station at Schulenberg, Texas reporting 12.15 inches.  The Harris County Flood Control station measured 6.26 inches of rain in one hour, which is comparable to the hourly rainfall rates that occurred with Tropical Storm Allison.  After the rains, College Station, Texas, was above normal for 2009 and had the third wettest spring, so far, based on data going back to 1951.  As of April 19, the USDA rated Texas crops in very poor to poor condition for 58 percent of the range and pasture land, 73 percent of oats, 74 percent of wheat, and 40 percent of sorghum.  USDA ratings for Oklahoma topsoil moisture improved from 34 percent very short to short last week to 27 percent this week, and from 61 percent very short to short for subsoil last week to 55 percent this week.  Oklahoma crops were rated 32 percent very poor to poor for pasture and range land, 60 percent for winter wheat, 65 percent for oats.  Pasture and range land was rated 46 percent very poor to poor in Colorado and 17 percent very poor to poor in Kansas.
D0 was eliminated from southwest South Dakota, western Nebraska, and southeast Wyoming, and pulled back over Colorado, Kansas, Oklahoma, and the Texas panhandle.  D1 contracted over Colorado, western Oklahoma, and the Texas panhandle.  D2 shrunk in western Oklahoma and adjacent Texas.  D1, D2, and D3 were shaved in Texas from the Pecos River region across parts of the Edwards Plateau.  D0 to D4 were dented in southeast Texas.  The A impacts designator was pulled down to the vicinity of the Colorado-New Mexico and Kansas-Oklahoma state lines.  The remaining D0-D1 in Colorado and D0 triangular wedge in north central Kansas were given an H impacts designator.
In North Dakota, D0 was expanded over the western counties where 30-90 day precipitation deficits were growing and which were farthest removed from the recent flooding in central and eastern North Dakota.  The lack of snowfall, increasing temperatures, low humidity, and windy weather were drying out the western grasslands and increasing fire danger.  D4 was expanded slightly in southern Texas to better reflect long-term severe moisture shortages.

## The West
An inch or more of precipitation fell from this week’s weather system over the coastal and Cascade mountains of the Pacific Northwest, and over pockets of the interior West.  Parts of Nevada received up to 3 feet of snow, with snowpack water content increasing to 110 to 160 percent of average at some eastern and northern basin SNOTEL stations.  The snow will help with soil moisture and ground water recharge in the weeks ahead.  But the system failed to deliver widespread areas of heavy rain and snow across the West this week.  Nevertheless, soil moisture and pastures continued to improve in Wyoming, with April 19 USDA ratings 7 percent short for topsoil and 15 percent poor for pasture and range land.  D2 in Nevada was shaved, D1 was pulled back in northeast Nevada, southern Idaho, southwest Wyoming, and northwest Utah, and D0 was dented in northern Utah where beneficial snow improved snowpack conditions and water year (October-present) precipitation deficits.
The southern areas of the West were largely missed by the system.  The USDA reported April 19 that some dryland grain fields in California were showing poor development due to lack of rainfall.  In Arizona, 37 percent of the range and pasture land was rated very poor to poor, while in New Mexico, 53 percent of the range and pasture land and 61 percent of wheat were rated very poor to poor, and 89 percent of the soil moisture was rated very short to short.  D1 and D2 were expanded in southern California, southeast Arizona, and southern New Mexico, and D0 expanded in Arizona and New Mexico, to reflect the precipitation deficit pattern of the last 30 days to 6 months.  An H impacts designator was added to southern Arizona.

## Forecast
Another slow-moving weather system is expected to track across the country during the next USDM week (April 23-27), bringing half an inch or more of precipitation to a large area from the northern and central Rockies to the Great Plains and western Great Lakes.  Heavier amounts are expected from central Kansas to central Wisconsin.  Above-normal temperatures are forecast for the eastern two-thirds of the Lower 48 States, with below-normal temperatures moving in from the northwest as the weather system progresses across the country.
According to the CPC 6- to 10-day and 8- to 14-day forecasts (covering the period April 28-May 6), precipitation chances will be above normal over Alaska and the central Plains to Mid-Atlantic States, but below normal across the Southwest.  The period should start out dry in the Southeast and Northwest, but precipitation chances might improve later in the period.  Warmer-than-normal temperatures are expected over Alaska and the southern Plains to Mid-Atlantic States, with colder-than-normal temperatures forecasted from parts of the West into the northern and central Great Plains to western Great Lakes.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.3062736</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-72.1474693</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>62.1502622</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:45:41-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 