<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2015-01-06</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brad Rippey</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>U.S. Department of Agriculture</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Heim</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — January 06, 2015</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2015-01-06</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2015-01-06</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2015-01-08</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — January 06, 2015

## Introduction
Very cold weather returned to the western and central U.S. in late December and early January, accompanied by light precipitation.  From January 2-5, snow covered at least 50% of the contiguous U.S.  By the afternoon of January 6, the NWS had issued wind chill advisories for Deep South Texas and along and east of a line from eastern Montana to the central Gulf Coast, excluding southern Florida.  The sudden return to frigid weather, accompanied by occasional snow, increased livestock stress across the Plains and Midwest.  Portions of the southern High Plains experienced a protracted winter weather event, with periods of freezing and frozen precipitation occurring from December 30 – January 2.  Later, on January 5-6, a fast-moving storm left a stripe of snow from the northern Rockies into the Midwestern and mid-Atlantic States.  Meanwhile, Western precipitation was generally light, although snow fell at unusually low elevations in the Southwest.  Some producers in California and the Desert Southwest had to take protective measures to guard against freeze damage to citrus and vegetables.  In California’s key watershed areas, mostly dry weather prevailed for a second consecutive week, following a highly beneficial, 3-week wet spell.  By January 4, heavy precipitation briefly overspread non-drought areas of the Pacific Northwest, leading to melting snow, local flooding, and mudslides.  Farther east, soaking rains returned across much of the South, erasing most of the lingering concerns about dryness and drought.  Some of the heaviest rain, generally 2 to 4 inches or more, fell from eastern Texas to the southern Appalachians.  In contrast, Florida’s peninsula experienced an extended period of warm, mostly dry weather, although colder air arrived late in the drought-monitoring period.  Elsewhere, mostly dry weather in the upper Midwest contrasted with periods of precipitation from the Ohio Valley into the Northeast.

## Central and Southern Plains
Changes across the southern Plains were mostly in the direction of slight improvement, while “status quo” was the rule for the central Plains.  During the drought-monitoring period, significant precipitation fell across southeastern Oklahoma and parts of Texas.  A protracted winter storm brought damaging accumulations of freezing rain to portions of the southern High Plains, including the Midland, Texas, area, especially on January 2.  In addition, parts of the central and southern Plains received some snow on January 3, with daily-record amounts reported in locations such as Dalhart, Texas (4.0 inches); and Wichita, Kansas (3.9 inches).  In the wake of the Plains’ snow, 54.1% of the contiguous U.S. was covered by snow on January 4, according to the NWS.  Farther east, an area of heavy rain covered much of eastern Texas and the southeastern corner of Oklahoma.  Despite the early-January rainfall, long-term precipitation deficits persisted across many areas of the southern Plains, including northeastern Texas.  For example, Dallas-Ft. Worth ended 2014 with a precipitation total of 21.32 inches (59% of normal), followed by 1.29 inches from January 1-6.  At the end of 2014, cumulative reservoir storage in Texas was 62.6% of capacity, compared to 64.3% at the end of 2013.  Historically, reservoirs in Texas are collectively about 80% full in late December.

## Hawaii and Puerto Rico
A strong cold front swept through the Hawaiian Islands on January 2-3, producing widespread showers and high winds.  During the high-wind event, Hawaiian gusts were clocked to 155 mph near the summit of Mauna Kea; 64 mph at Maui’s Kaupo Gap; and 57 mph at Wheeler Army Airfield on Maui.  Kaupo Gap also reported a 24-hour rainfall of 3.53 inches on January 2-3.  In the front’s wake, Lihue, Kauai, notched three consecutive daily-record lows (56, 54, and 57°F, respectively) from January 3-5.  The early-January rainfall staved off the expansion of dryness (D0), except on the Big Island.  For example, D0 returned to windward sections of the Big Island, where Hilo’s rainfall in November-December 2014 totaled 15.13 inches (56% of normal).  In contrast, early-January rainfall on Maui led to the cutting of the existing area of D0 into two pieces.
In late December and early January, showers in Puerto Rico were mostly confined to northern and eastern sections of the island.  As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) remained intact in part of southeastern Puerto Rico, owing to rainfall deficits at both short- and long-term time periods.

## Mid-South
Hit-or-miss rainfall brought a reduction in the coverage of dryness (D0) in some areas, including southeastern Missouri.  However, rain largely bypassed northeastern Arkansas and western Tennessee.  As a result, the eastern edge of moderate drought (D1) expanded slightly in northeastern Arkansas.  From northeastern Arkansas to western Kentucky, dryness appears at a variety of time scales, including all periods from 30 to 180 days.  Jonesboro, Arkansas, recently completed its sixth consecutive month with below-normal precipitation, receiving just 14.03 inches of rain (61% of normal) during the second half of 2014.

## Northeast
Occasional precipitation continued to chip away at dryness (D0) in the Northeast.  In northern New York, Massena received precipitation totaling 1.01 inches on January 3-4, following a rather dry finish to 2014.  During the last 4 months of the year (September-December 2014), Massena’s precipitation totaled 5.68 inches, or 46% of normal.

## Northern Plains and Upper Midwest
No changes were made across the northern Plains and upper Midwest, where “deep freeze” conditions returned in late December and early January.  Effectively, short-term precipitation deficits are “frozen in place” until warmer weather returns.  From October 1, 2014 – January 6, 2015, Fargo, North Dakota, received precipitation totaling just 1.33 inches—just 32% of normal for that 14-week period.

## Southeast
Yet another round of heavy rain swept across the South, further reducing the coverage of dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1).  Near the edge of the remaining small area of D1, New Orleans, Louisiana, received 1.27 inches of rain in early January.  However, from October 1, 2014 – January 6, 2015, rainfall in New Orleans totaled 9.21 inches, or 65% of normal.  Much more impressive rain fell early in the New Year in other areas of the Southeast.  For example, daily-record rainfall totals for January 3 included 4.35 inches in Meridian, Mississippi; 2.47 inches in Tuscaloosa, Alabama; and 2.46 inches in Lake Charles, Louisiana.
The southern tip of Florida has missed out on the recent rainfall.  In West Palm Beach, Florida, rainfall in November-December 2014 totaled just 3.70 inches, or 46% of normal.  Abnormal dryness (D0) has not yet been added, given that hydrological indicators do not pinpoint any drought-related concerns, as well as the fact that southern Florida is in the midst of its dry season.  However, this area remains on a “watch list,” especially if dryness continues and impacts begin to appear.

## The West, Including California
Aside from a few small improvements in Arizona, the Southwestern storm of late-December 2014 and early-January 2015 did not provide enough moisture to dent long-term drought.  Nevertheless, the storm produced some unusual weather in the Desert Southwest, including some rare snow.  In Needles, California, where 0.3 inch fell on December 31, snow had not fallen since February 2, 1985.  Needles had never before received measurable snow in December, and had not seen a greater amount since January 25, 1949, when 2.0 inches fell.  Similarly, an inch of snow fell on New Year’s Eve in Bullhead City, Arizona, marking the first accumulation in that area since January 11, 1949.  Laughlin, Nevada, and Lake Havasu City, Arizona, both reported a trace of snow on December 31 and January 1; snow had not been observed in Laughlin since February 26, 1987, or in Lake Havasu City since January 24-25, 1949.  Meanwhile, Flagstaff, Arizona, reported a 17.3-inch snowfall on December 31 – January 1.  Looking at the drought from a longer-term perspective, statewide reservoir levels remained very low in New Mexico and somewhat low in Arizona.  Based on preliminary information, New Mexico’s storage on December 31 was 53% of average, compared to 51% a year ago.  In Arizona, statewide storage stood at 73% of average at the end of the year, down from 85% on December 31, 2013.
Farther north and west, the drought situation remained largely unchanged, although enough precipitation fell across the western slopes of the northern Rockies to further trim abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1).  In north-central Washington, east of the Cascades, an end-of-year assessment led to a small reduction in the coverage of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2).  End-of-year reservoir reports have begun to trickle in and indicate the statewide storage was higher on December 31, 2014, than a year ago in Wyoming (124% of average vs. 92%), Montana (112 vs. 104%), Idaho (106 vs 84%), Colorado (103 vs 88%), Washington (99 vs. 76%), Utah (98 vs. 91%), and Oregon (79 vs. 68%).  Nevertheless, one concern facing the Northwest—especially in the Cascades and coastal ranges—is the lack of snowpack due to periods of warmth and the large number of “warm” storms.  In early-January 2015, the basin-average water content of the snowpack was mostly less than half of normal for this time of year from the Cascades westward, despite above-normal precipitation since October 1, 2014.
The drought depiction in California and Nevada was not changed.  Nevada’s reservoir storage remained extremely low—only 21% of average at the end of 2014, compared to 30% on December 31, 2013.  (California’s end-of-year reservoir information has not yet been published.)  By January 6, the average water content of the high-elevation Sierra Nevada snowpack averaged just 5 inches—43% of normal for this time of year.  According to the California Department of Water Resources, the water content of the Sierra Nevada snowpack in an average year typically approaches 30 inches by April 1.  In other words, the current Sierra Nevada snowpack contains only 17% of the water typically available when the melt season begins in the spring.  Closer to the northern Pacific Coast, water systems that are not dependent on Sierra Nevada runoff are faring better than inland basins.  For example, storage in Marin County’s seven reservoirs was 99.9% of capacity on January 4, 2015—well above last year’s 56.0% and the average of 74.8%—following runoff from heavy, late-autumn rainfall.  However, average, end-of-year storage in Marin County only represents a tiny fraction (less than three-tenths of 1%) of California’s total average reservoir holdings.  In addition, ongoing impacts of the 3½-year drought along California’s northern coast—and elsewhere in the state—include low groundwater reserves and stress on native vegetation and perennial crops such as orchards and vineyards.

## Forecast
For the upcoming 5-day period (January 8-12), very cold weather will continue to dominate the central and eastern U.S.  During the cold snap, snow showers and squalls will rage downwind of the Great Lakes.  In contrast, mild, dry weather will prevail in much of the West.  During the weekend, rain will develop in the western Gulf Coast region.  As precipitation spreads northeastward early next week, the interaction between moisture and lingering cold air could result in snow, sleet, and freezing rain across parts of the South, East, and lower Midwest.
The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for January 13-17 calls for the likelihood of below-normal temperatures in most areas east of a line from Texas to Wisconsin, while warmer-than-normal weather can be expected across the northern High Plains and the West.  Meanwhile, below-normal precipitation will be the probable outcome across the northern half of the nation, as well as southern California and environs, but wetter-than-normal conditions will likely prevail in the southern Atlantic States and southern portions of the Rockies and High Plains.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.7864828</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-66.0983124</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.9284123</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.3404361</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:57:54-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 