<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-11-11</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Mark Svoboda</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — November 11, 2008</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2008-11-11</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-11-11</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2008-11-13</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — November 11, 2008

## Introduction


## Alaska and Hawaii
No changes are noted in the drought depiction this week within Alaska or Hawaii.

## Great Lakes Region and Upper Midwest
Unseasonally warm temperatures (6 to 10 degrees above normal) covered the region last week. For the most part, this was coupled with very little in the way of precipitation. The exceptions were in parts of northern and southern Minnesota, where 1-2 inches fell. As a result, D1 has been removed from the Arrowhead of northern Minnesota and the D0-D1 has been trimmed and refined in the southern half of the state in order to better reflect the recent improvements along with the longer-term deficits and concerns heading into the recharge season.

## The Plains
A substantial blizzard in the northern Plains brought heavy snows and did lead to some improvement in the Panhandle of Nebraska (slight removal of D0 there) and in southwest North Dakota as well, where the D0-D2 was trimmed on the southern and eastern flanks in response to the recent wetness there. Year-to-date deficits are still in the 3-6 inch range (50-70% of normal) and these are only worse in the 12- to 24-month time frames, so the drought remains.
The southern Plains were greeted with a warm week and heavy late period rains (November 10-11), which have altered the drought depiction there. Specifically, in Oklahoma, D1 has been removed in the north-central counties and the D0 has been reduced slightly in both the north and the east. It should be noted that the D1 in the southern reaches of Oklahoma actually expanded this week as the rains missed them and concerns continue because of the lack of cool-season recharge needed for helping winter wheat and easing grass fires. The fact that the dryness now extends back six months across southern Oklahoma led to a change in the impact label from "A" to "AH", which is consistent with the impact depiction found in Texas.
Speaking of Texas, the benefits were a bit more obvious to the south across the Red River into northern-northeastern Texas and along parts of the middle coast of Texas as well. Heavy rains on the order of 2 to 4 inches fell in both of these regions, leading to the pushing back of D0 to the west in north-central Texas. This was accompanied by a slight trimming of D1 along the Red River around the Oklahoma-Texas border. Along the middle Gulf Coast, the heavy rains helped in the short term, but longer-term deficits are still persisting within the core of D1-D3 located here. These rains did help tighten the D0-D3 gradient found along the coast between Houston and Corpus Christi.

## The Southeast, Tennessee and Ohio Valleys, and mid-Atlantic Coast
Much of the mid-Atlantic and Northeast enjoyed warmer than normal temperatures, but very little in the way of precipitation last week. Dryness over the past 30 to 90 days, coupled with lingering deficits that date back 6 months now, have led to the expansion of D0 across most of western Pennsylvania. The noted long-term dryness has also led to the changing of the impact type in the Ohio Valley region to "AH" instead of just "A" to reflect the duration aspect of the dryness in the region. The other change of note this week is reflected in yet more expansion of D4 across northern Georgia, where year-to-date rainfall deficits are now on the order of 12 to 16 inches or more (50-70% of normal) in Georgia and the western Carolinas. Two-year departures are a staggering two feet across much of the Southeast, leaving the hydrological drought well entrenched. To the east, D1 has again pushed south and west across more of Alabama and D0 continues to inch northward in Louisiana in response to dry conditions over the past 30-90 days. The time of year and cooler temperatures have helped somewhat, but extensive off-season rains will be needed to help reverse the course of the drought before heading into 2009. This is evident in the near-record to record low levels of both rivers/streams and surface storage across much of the region.

## The West
On the heels of heavy rain and snow last week across northern California, generally cooler temperatures prevailed statewide and another round of precipitation fell this past week as well. Totals of 1-4 inches fell across extreme northwest California, from Eureka to points north and east toward Yreka, and along the extreme southwest Oregon coast. After these consecutive soakings, longer-term deficits are being erased and streamflow and soil moisture are responding well. This has led to the removal of D0 and D1 in this corner of California. The same can not be said for points just to the south and east as conditions remain unchanged this week. In fact, a slight expansion of D2 is noted in far northeast California, and farther south, a slight expansion eastward of D2 into the Salton Sea region is depicted this week. Long-term deficits have carried over and are thus far lingering during the young Water Year. In eastern Washington, the recent wetness has led to the removal of D1 and a reduction of the D0 there, but long-term dryness leaves some D0 in its wake for now.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (November 13-17), significant precipitation is expected in and around southern Louisiana, the Carolina coastlines, and the mid-Atlantic. Temperatures for most locales east of the Mississippi are expected to be normal to slightly below normal. Above-normal temperatures are forecasted for areas west of the Mississippi, with the greatest warmth expected across California and into the Great Basin.
The CPC 6-10 day forecast (November 18-22) calls for better chances of above-normal temperatures west of the Rockies (including eastern Alaska), while the Great Plains and all points eastward to the Atlantic can expect to see below-normal readings. Precipitation breaks down into a north-south line, with those in the South, Southeast, Southwest and West having better odds of being below normal. Parts of the western Dakotas and eastern Montana could see above-normal precipitation during this period, as could the eastern Great Lakes states.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-162.6410218</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-74.2801833</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>71.3980481</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:43:42-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 