<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2009-07-28</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Mark Svoboda</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — July 28, 2009</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2009-07-28</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2009-07-28</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2009-07-30</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — July 28, 2009

## Introduction


## Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico
Hawaii and Puerto Rico remain unchanged this week. Over the past week, Alaska benefitted from some heavy coastal rains (3-6 inches), leading to some removal and readjustment of D0 and D1.

## Southeast
Most of the region remains status quo this week, but a few changes are worth noting. Temperatures across much of the Southeast stayed in the normal range. The introduction of a small tongue of D0 is noted in southwestern coastal Florida where wet-season rainfall deficits continue to accrue during the wet season after a below-normal dry season as well. The D0 stretches south from the Tampa Bay area to the western reaches of Everglades National Park in Monroe County. A quiet week with minimal rainfall in Georgia and Alabama leaves them unchanged this week.

## The Gulf Coast
Heavy rains (2-6 inches) fell across most of western Mississippi, southern Arkansas, northern Louisiana, and eastern/northeastern Texas. Most of these areas saw a 1-category improvement, leading to a reduction of D0/D1 in the region. However, many of the remaining areas still in D0/D1 are sitting at just 50-75% of normal precipitation for the year.

## The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic
As has been the case across much of the East this summer, cool weather remained entrenched over much of the region, with some relief coming in the form of rains during the past week across parts of Maryland and eastern North Carolina. As a result, abnormally dry (D0) conditions have retreated in Maryland near Washington, D.C., area. To the south, slight improvement is also depicted this week along the southern coast of North Carolina in the Wilmington region, where 2-4 inches of rain fell. Improvement is also noted south and east of Charlotte where beneficial rains fell as well. The opposite holds true in the western part of the state, where D0 has again pushed west and north toward the Tennessee border.

## The Plains
A mixed bag of conditions this week, resulting in both improvements and degradation. Starting in the north, North Dakota has been quite dry after all the flooding that made the news earlier this year, although the cooler weather has helped mitigate more serious impacts. The D0 has expanded out of Minnesota and spilled into North Dakota from the southeastern corner of the state to the north central counties. In addition, an area of D1 has also been introduced in a core area of east-central North Dakota where 4-7 inch deficits (25-50% of normal) have accumulated over the past 90 days.
Most of Oklahoma experienced a cool week, with temperatures generally running 4-6 degrees below normal. The only good rains in Oklahoma, though, were contained to parts of the extreme Panhandle and southeastern corner, where 2-4 inches were reported. This has led to the peeling back of D0 in the extreme western tip of the Panhandle and across portions of east-central Oklahoma. On the other hand, an introduction of D1 is noted in northeast Oklahoma and an introduction of new D2 is marked in northwest Oklahoma after yet another dry week. The cooler temperatures have helped, but not enough to offset the slowly deepening drought.
Several locations in extreme southeastern Colorado and southwestern Kansas reported rainfall totals of 2-4 inches or more, leading to the removal of Abnormally Dry (D0) conditions there this week.
Texas also sees a combination of degradation and improvements this week. The mixed bag starts with improvements in west-central Texas around the Midland area where pockets of 2 inches or more were reported. This results in D0 pulling eastward in this region and northward through the Texas Panhandle too. The heaviest rains in the state the past week fell across eastern and particularly northeastern Texas, where 3-6 inches fell as of the cutoff this week, with more coming after the deadline and more on the way. Improvements are warranted as both D0 and D1 were pushed south and west. The same can’t be said for most of southern Texas, however, where record heat and no significant rains (most places not getting anything measurable) have coupled to increase the impacts of their exceptional, protracted drought. A slight expansion of D1-D4 is noted here, where many locales are looking at July readings challenging the all-time warmest months on record, with most days exceeding triple digits.

## The West
Decent monsoonal rains continue to benefit eastern and southeastern New Mexico, where 2-4 inches brought about a removal of D2 and a westward retraction of D0-D1 across the eastern third of the state.
In Montana, improvements continue on the heels of more rains this week. D1 has been removed in northeastern Montana, and some small D2 pockets have been removed in parts of central Montana as well. The D0-D1 line has also been pushed north and west a bit, with additional rains falling as July draws to a close. A return to good water levels has led to the changing of the drought depiction in Montana from “AH” to just “A” to reflect these improvements.
Farther west in the coastal reaches of the Pacific Northwest, the record-setting heat is on, with many heat advisories and an increased risk of fire under a dominating dome of high pressure, which has brought triple-digit heat for many days now. D0 now connects virtually all of the West Coast from Washington to southern California, with only a little stretch of coast at the California/Oregon border showing no form of dryness or drought thus far.

## Upper Midwest
Rains managed to miss most of the worst drought-affected portions of Wisconsin and Minnesota, but some parts of north-central Minnesota did see enough to push the D0 and D1 slightly eastward and southward this week around Duluth, and rain also brought some relief to locations along the Minnesota-Wisconsin border. Conditions worsened in the western third of the state, leading to some slight expansion of D1 there and extending D0 into North Dakota as well.

## Forecast
Over the next 5 days (July 30-August 3), temperatures across the United States are expected to be dominated once again by upper-level ridging in the West and troughing in the East. This should result in above-normal temperatures across most of the West and below-normal temperatures from the Rockies eastward to the Atlantic and even down into the Southeast and Gulf Coast states. The greatest anomalies most likely will be across the northern tier states. As for precipitation, the West looks to remain dry except for some monsoonal flow across eastern New Mexico and up into Colorado. The upper Midwest, southern Plains, Southeast, and East all stand a good chance of seeing beneficial rainfall over this period.
The 6-10 day forecast (August 4 – August 8) calls for some relief from high temperatures in the West, with normal to below-normal readings expected. Cooler-than-normal temperatures are also likely across the Upper Midwest and into the Northeast. Warmer temperatures can be expected across most of eastern and southeastern Alaska as well as across the southern United States from the Four Corners region to northern Florida and Georgia. Below-normal precipitation is called for in eastern Alaska, the Upper Peninsula of Michigan, the Great Basin, and parts of the Southwest, continuing across southern Oklahoma and most of Texas into the coastal reaches of the Gulf Coast states. Above-normal rains are more likely across the coastal reaches of the Pacific Northwest, and from the Corn Belt into the Mid-Atlantic and Northeast.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-164.9485811</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-75.0423982</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>62.9233909</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:56:44-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 