<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-11-01</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Heim</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Liz Love-Brotak</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — November 01, 2005</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-11-01</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-11-01</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-11-03</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — November 01, 2005

## Introduction


## Alaska , Hawaii, and Puerto Rico
Streamflow levels in these areas averaged near to above normal during this USDM period. However, precipitation was below normal across parts of Alaska and Hawaii. Dry conditions for the last week to 90 days in southeast Alaska north of the panhandle prompted the introduction of D0. The SNOTEL sites in this area at Upper Tsaina River and Granite Creek were behind average on both precipitation and snow water content. The D0 areas in Hawaii continued dry, so no change was made to the depiction. Interior northwest and north central portions of Puerto Rico had below-normal rainfall this month, but amounts were still 5+ inches in the driest areas.

## The East and Southeast
Noreaster rains of 0.5 to 2.0 inches, with locally heavier amounts, fell over the southwestern Pennsylvania and southeastern Ohio D0 areas the first day of this USDM period. The D0 was pulled back over Ohio and Pennsylvania, with a band of D0H left in Pennsylvania where long-term (90-day and longer) deficits were greatest.
D0 was expanded in the Southeast where another dry week continued a prolonged dry spell. Much of the area has had less than half an inch of rainfall during the last 30 to 45 days. Several stations in the Mississippi-Tennessee-Kentucky-Arkansas vicinity had the driest or second driest October on record, with several Arkansas stations receiving no measurable rainfall for 27 consecutive days or longer. Streams were low, especially in Arkansas where several were at record low levels, including the Buffalo River near St. Joe, the Black River near Corning, and the Saline River near Rye. The Saline River near Rye was flowing at only 8 cubic feet per second, compared to an average of 941 cubic feet per second. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions spread into Alabama, Mississippi, and western Kentucky and Tennessee, joining with the D0 in Arkansas and Louisiana. An A impacts indicator was added to this region. Abnormally dry D0A conditions also expanded in the Florida panhandle and into extreme southwest Georgia. First Level Drought (D1) grew in Arkansas to give a smoother southwest to northeast boundary. The expanded D0 and D1 boundaries generally enveloped the areas with the greatest rainfall departures at the 30 to 60 to 90 day time scales. An island of D1 was added to central Louisiana reflecting significant rainfall deficits. Alexandria has a year to date deficit of over 22 inches and Lafayette is over 20 inches behind. In Georgia, the USDM depiction followed the state Forestry Commission depiction of the greatest Fire Danger Rating and Keetch Byram Drought Index (KBDI) values in the northern and southwestern counties.
D1 First Level Drought pushed into eastern Tennessee to reflect low rainfall during the last 30 to 90 days and the development of local impacts. The NOAA National Weather Service in eastern Tennessee has received reports of very stressed pastures and farm ponds, with farmers having to take water into the fields to animals. The majority of soils are listed as very short on moisture, and there is concern that winter wheat and other crops planted for later harvesting may not get enough rain to germinate. Stream levels are low, resulting in water supply problems for small towns, and several small wildfires have started.
Abnormally dry D0 expanded in the Carolinas to encompass most of the area west of Interstate 95, and the D1 First Level Drought over the piedmont of North Carolina was expanded in central North Carolina and into South Carolina. This area has had below-normal rainfall for the last 60 days, with the Carolina piedmont region recording generally less than 50% of normal. A spot of D2 Severe Drought was added to the northern and central piedmont of North Carolina to reflect severe impacts. Water supply storage in central North Carolina reservoirs was considerably below normal values. Falls Lake had a 34% water supply, while Jordan Lake registered 56% of the water quality pool. Inflows to both of these water supply systems ranked in the bottom ten percentile, based on 76 years of record. According to the state Division of Water Resources, by the end of the October, about a fourth of the population of North Carolina (24%) was affected by voluntary or mandatory water conservation measures. Raleigh has been on voluntary water restrictions since September 21. With the city's water supply critically low, the Raleigh City Council voted November 1 to implement mandatory water restrictions, which would limit how water customers in Raleigh and surrounding communities use their water. In addition to Raleigh, mandatory restrictions would be in effect for Garner, Rolesville, Wake Forest, Knightdale, Wendell and Zebulon.

## The Great Lakes Region
A very dry week resulted in expansion of D0 across the rest of southeastern Lower Michigan with a nose of D1 poking into southeastern Lower Michigan. According to the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, lake level conditions across all of the Great Lakes, except Lake Ontario, were 3 to 7 inches below the levels of a year ago. All were below average for October. Conditions continued to worsen according to streamflow, modeled soil moisture, and the short-term objective blend indicator, so this area will be monitored closely in coming weeks.

## The High Plains, Rockies, and Far West
Parts of the Pacific Northwest, northern and central Rockies, northern California, and the intermountain basin received rain and snow during this USDM period. The heaviest amounts fell along coastal Washington and Oregon, just outside the USDM drought areas. It is too early in the western snow season for high elevation SNOTEL stations to give meaningful departure from normal snow water equivalent statistics. However, several basins in the West had snow water departures well below average. Considering the early phase of the snow season, no changes were made to the USDM depiction in the Pacific Northwest, Rockies, or Desert Southwest this week.
Areas of the High Plains of Montana had above normal weekly and monthly precipitation. The Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) for the Milk River in north central Montana showed considerable improvement over the last 6 months, reaching the slightly wet category by October. D0 was pulled back along this basin to reflect the recent precipitation and improvement in long-term SWSI values.

## The Plains and Mississippi Valley
Very little precipitation fell across much of the northern and central Plains this USDM week. Parts of the Dakotas missed significant precipitation for the last 3 to 6 months. A D0 bridge was added across southwestern North Dakota and D1 was expanded into southwestern South Dakota to reflect 30 to 90 day dryness.
A frontal rain band moved across the southern Plains drought area late in the USDM period, bringing areas of 1 to 2 inch rains. The precipitation had little impact on the drought, as 2 to 3 month rainfall deficits ranged from 4 to 10 inches across the area and local reports in Oklahoma had soil moisture barely responding to the rain. D0 was pulled back in southwestern Missouri where locally 2 to 4 inch rains fell, however poor soil moisture, pastures and very low stock ponds remained a problem across the area.
D0 was expanded from the Texas panhandle into adjoining western Oklahoma counties where conditions have been dry for the last 120 days and soil moisture was low. Abnormally dry D0 was expanded into southeastern New Mexico, where less than half the normal rainfall has been recorded in the last 60 days at Carlsbad (1.35 inches) and Tatum (1.85 inches). D1 First Level Drought was expanded into the eastern portion of the Edwards Plateau, which is the recharge area for the Edwards Aquifer, reflecting low precipitation and groundwater levels. Dropping well levels and below normal rainfall prompted the Barton Springs/Edwards Aquifer Conservation District's board to declare a stage one drought alert for the Barton Springs segment of the Edwards Aquifer. The Buda and San Leanna monitor wells fell below their stage one trigger levels with ground water levels in other area wells also declining. In addition, significant year to date precipitation deficits were noted at Camp Mabry (6.6 inch deficit) and Austin-Bergstrom International Airport (9.3-inch deficit), and Barton Springs discharge was well below its normal seasonal flow. In northeast Texas where D2 and D3 Drought were indicated, several counties have been declared disaster areas by the U.S. Department of Agriculture, including Hunt, Rains, and Bowie counties. The Dallas-Fort Worth airport station recorded only 18.62 inches of precipitation for January-October, ranking this year as the driest January-October since the station opened in 1974.

## Forecast
During the next five days (November 3 - 7), the contiguous U.S. will have a zonal flow as the jet stream sits over the northern tier states. A number of systems will pass through the northern third of the country, keeping the Pacific Northwest, northern Rockies, Great Lakes and Northeast as the areas with increased opportunities for precipitation. The southern two-thirds of the country should continue to experience drier than normal conditions. Above normal temperatures are expected for most of the country.
Over the following five days (November 8 - 12), the pattern stays the same with much of the country continuing to be warmer and drier than normal. Wetter than normal conditions are forecast for the Pacific Northwest and western Great Lakes drought areas. Alaska will be dominated by an Arctic high pressure system. Below normal temperatures and dry conditions are expected to prevail throughout the state; however, the southern coastal areas may see an increased possibility of precipitation.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.7864828</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-77.508827</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>65.5804586</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:51:01-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 