<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2004-07-27</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Heim</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Candace Tankersley</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — July 27, 2004</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2004-07-27</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2004-07-27</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2004-07-29</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — July 27, 2004

## Introduction


## Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico
An arm of D0A was expanded across Alaska to the west coast, basically from near Bethel to Kotzebue, reflecting low 14-day streamflow and below-normal precipitation reports at several stations out to 60 days. No changes were made to Hawaii this monitoring period. Although several stations reported well above normal year-to-date rainfall totals, the 50th state may be an area to watch in upcoming weeks as recent totals have been a little below normal with above normal temperatures. In Puerto Rico, rainfall reports and streamflow levels do not support the introduction of any D0.

## New England and The Southeast
Rainfall totals of up to 2 inches fell over the D0 area of western Connecticut and western Massachusetts, warranting its removal. Although rain fell over the D0 in Maine, amounts were below normal for the Drought Monitor period, so the D0 was left in place to reflect long-term moisture deficits.
Widespread 1-inch-plus rains, with some reports over 3 inches, fell across much of southern Florida, resulting in the elimination of the D0 area there. However, much of southern Florida remains dry at longer timescales, with parts of the Lower East Coast reporting 50% of normal rainfall for the last 2 to 6 months. Even though the heavy rains of this week brought an end to the southern Florida D0, the longer-term rainfall deficits could result in a re-emergence of D0 if the current rainy pattern shuts down.
A frontal system brought rain to a large part of the Southeast, but most of the rain missed the D0 areas of Georgia and the Carolinas during this Drought Monitor period. On July 25, the USDA NASS reported 45% of the topsoil in Georgia short to very short, up from 28% the previous week, and 9% of the pastures in poor to very poor condition. D0 was extended a little further into east central Georgia to reflect hot and dry short-term conditions and long-term rainfall deficits.

## The Far Western States
While scattered showers occurred over central Idaho, rainfall amounts were minor compared to the deficits that have accumulated over the last 5 to 6 years. D4 was extended over the Big Lost and Little Lost basins to reflect very low groundwater observations near Arco and empty reservoirs ... Mackay and Magic reservoirs recently ran out of water. Long-term blended indices, low streamflows, and below-normal precipitation out to 6 months prompted the expansion of D1 across northern Washington to Puget Sound. According to USDA NASS reports, some crops in parts of northwest Washington experienced stress under record breaking heat. A thumb of D2 was extended further into southern California. While this is a dry time of year for this area, the expansion was made to accommodate changes in blended indices and to reflect longer-term deficits.
In southeast Arizona, scattered areas of 1+ inch rainfall occurred based on radar estimates and station reports, mainly in the region between the D3 areas (Graham county), while lesser amounts (subnormal for the period) occurred elsewhere. Rains during this USDM period did little to alleviate 5+ years of precipitation deficits. Record low daily streamflows have been reported by the USGS this month at several rivers in central Arizona, including two perennial streams: the Hassayampa River and the Verde River. Earlier this year, the Salt River Project cut Phoenix water deliveries by 33% for a second year in a row. National Weather Service reports of severe multi-year deficits at several stations across Gila County (which is climate division 4), record low streamflows, and last week's reported ground fissures prompted the slight expansion of the D3 boundaries in Gila, extreme northern Graham and northern Greenlee, and Cochise counties. The changes were made while avoiding the Graham County stations that reported above-normal rain for the period.

## The High Plains and Central States
Heavy thunderstorms visited many Abnormally Dry and Drought areas this week, while just a few areas saw expansion of the boundaries. Much of Missouri was inundated with heavy rain during this monitoring period. Rainfall amounts over the Missouri D0 area ranged from half an inch to 3 inches, which was sufficient to warrant its elimination. Up to an inch of rain moistened southeast and northeast Nebraska this period, prompting the removal of D0A areas which were added last period. One to 4 inch rains chased the D4 out of western Nebraska and southeast Wyoming and also resulted in the contraction of some D3 in the area. In addition, the H/AH impacts boundary was adjusted over Nebraska and Wyoming to reflect the changing dynamic of the moisture deficits.
Further to the south, D0 and D1 were pulled back under a band of 1-3 inch rains in southwest Kansas and part of the Oklahoma panhandle. Heavy rains also occurred west of there, resulting in contraction of the D2 over eastern Colorado into extreme southeast Wyoming, and contraction of D1 along the Colorado Front Range.
Considerable improvement occurred over eastern New Mexico and adjoining western Texas, where 2-inch rains were widespread and weekly totals in excess of 4 inches were observed at many stations. July 25 USDA NASS reports indicated considerable improvement in short-term agricultural conditions. Soil moisture across New Mexico improved to 33% short to very short compared to 70% the previous week, while range and pasture conditions improved to 44% poor and very poor from 59% the previous week. D0, D1, and D2 were pulled back in the area, leaving an island of D0 in the vicinity of Odessa and Midland to reflect longer-term deficits there. The spot of D0 in north central Texas was removed due to rains of up to an inch.
Expansion of Drought Monitor boundaries occurred in the following central states. D0 was expanded in northern Wisconsin to reflect continued below-normal rainfall this period and drying soils. D3 from southeast Montana was expanded into extreme southwest North Dakota to reflect continued dryness of recent weeks and worsening long-term precipitation deficits. In northeast Wyoming, several areas have missed the beneficial rains of recent weeks. D4 in this area was expanded toward the Bighorn Mountains to reflect both the short-term misses and long-term moisture deficits, as well as dessicating impacts on rangeland and cattle. The impacts of the drought can be seen very well in the satellite-based Vegetative Health Index and Greenness Index. These indices show severe vegetative stress all across the region, including northeast Wyoming, southeast Montana, southwest North Dakota, and into western South Dakota almost surrounding the still-green Black Hills. D0 was expanded in eastern Montana up to the Missouri River based on below-normal rainfall reports. A dry week and continued worsening precipitation deficits prompted the expansion of D2 into central South Dakota.

## Forecast
Looking Ahead: Over the next 10 days there will be a shift in the general circulation pattern. Below normal precipitation is forecast for the Far West, the northern Rockies, southern Great Plains and the Northeast. Above normal precipitation is expected over the southern Rockies and southern High Plains as well as the Upper Mississippi Valley and the Southeast. Temperatures are expected to be above normal across most of the contiguous United States with below normal temperatures in most of the Gulf Coast states, northern California and the Pacific Northwest. Little change is expected for the ensuing five days (August 7-11). The temperature pattern will remain essentially the same. The precipitation pattern will be similar, except below normal precipitation will extend across the central Plains to northern Rockies. In Alaska, the abnormally dry and drought areas are expected to receive below normal precipitation throughout the period. Temperatures will average warmer than normal across the southwestern half of the state and below normal across the northeastern half at first, then warmer than normal statewide August 7-11.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-168.123529645809</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-66.9540017338536</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>29.6671420016771</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>68.4617606101219</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:36:47-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 