<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2002-06-25</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Staff </gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — June 25, 2002</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2002-06-25</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2002-06-25</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2002-06-27</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — June 25, 2002

## Introduction


## Alaska and Hawaii
A cold front tracked through northern and central Alaska, generating widely-scattered light showers and cooler weather. Farther south, rainfall increased toward the end of the period in response to a storm system in the Gulf of Alaska, dropping 0.5 to 2.5 inches along the southern and southeastern coast; however, long-term deficits remained. Wildfire potential was somewhat lower than a week ago, but still rated high, with 26 active fires as of June 25. Statewide, the USDA/NASS reported 35% and 20% of the topsoil and subsoil moisture was short, respectively. With more seasonable weather conditions this week, D0 remained.
In Hawaii, high pressure north of the islands produced typical trade winds, with windward and mountain light showers. Molokai received light amounts (Kamalo 0.50; Molokai Airport 0.15), maintaining D0(W) on the western side.

## The East
A stalled front, plus an upper-level low, generated widespread showers and thunderstorms from the eastern Gulf of Mexico northeastward to offshore east of Cape Hatteras, NC. With the exception of Florida, however, most of the significant rains remained right along the coast and over the open waters of the Atlantic. In Florida, another wet week (2 to 8 inches) alleviated dryness and drought in all but the western Panhandle where totals were generally under an inch. Along the immediate Georgia and Carolina coasts, 2 to 6 inches, and locally up to 10 inches, of rain diminished drought by one category. Just to the west, however, totals rapidly decreased, and inland Carolina and Georgia locations recorded little or no rainfall. Although weekly temperatures averaged near normal, highs soared into the 90oFs late in the period, and conditions deteriorated. According to the USGS, 7-day average stream flows hit all-time record lows at 43%, 42%, and 40% of reporting gauges in South Carolina, Virginia, and North Carolina, respectively. These low flows generally encompass the expanded D3 and D4 Piedmont areas that missed the surplus Spring rains and never hydrologically recovered from the record fall and winter drought. Similarly, with the exception of localized moderate rains (0.5 to 2 inches) in northern Virginia, Washington DC, and parts of eastern Pennsylvania and New Jersey, the rest of the mid-Atlantic was dry, and short-term dryness increased, edging the hydrological (W) delineation line northward. In the Northeast, short-term surpluses still persisted even though totals generally decreased this week, with only scattered light showers (0.2-0.5 inches). A heavier band of rain (1 to 2 inches) across northern New York and Vermont, central New Hampshire, and southern Maine erased D0(W) as the large 6-month deficits accumulated during September 2001-February 2002 have nearly disappeared with plentiful precipitation since this March. Elsewhere, however, larger long-term deficits remained, as did the D0(W).

## The Gulf Coast
Widely-scattered, afternoon showers and thunderstorms developed in response to a westward moving upper-level low, dropping localized amounts of 2.0 to 3.5 inches along coastal Louisiana and Mississippi and on south-central Mississippi and Alabama, providing minor relief. Elsewhere, however, many locations received little or no rainfall, and with 2-4and 4-7 deficits for 30 and 90-days, respectively, D1-D2 was added into northwestern and central Louisiana. Abnormal dryness also expanded into central Mississippi, northern Alabama, and south-central Tennessee, where USDA/NASS short to very short topsoil moisture has increased in one week from 31% to 59% in the latter state.

## The Plains and Midwest
A slow-moving storm track across the north-central States triggered widespread, severe thunderstorms that dumped copious rains (4 to12 inches) on the upper Midwest, producing river and localized flooding in Minnesota and Wisconsin and alleviating abnormal dryness in central Minnesota and northeastern South Dakota. Thundershowers also fell on parts of the northern Plains and western Corn Belt, but amounts were less (0.5 to 2.0 inches), and with temperatures averaging 5 to 10F above normal, any benefits from the rain were quickly negated. With little or no rain farther south, abnormal dryness expanded into southeastern Nebraska, southwestern Iowa, northwestern Missouri, and northeastern Kansas, and drought intensified in western Nebraska, eastern Wyoming, western Kansas, and the Rio Grande Valley. Centered near Falcon Lake (on the lower Rio Grande River), long-term drought and brutal June weather (18 of 25 days at or above 100F and no rain) has bumped a small area of D3 into exceptional drought. Cooler conditions in the southern Great Plains limited additional moisture declines, but longer-term impacts have begun to mirror short-term shortages, hence the removal of the A,F delineation.

## The West
Status quo was maintained across most of the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies as seasonable temperatures and scattered light showers kept wildfire danger to a minimum, but conditions continued to degrade in central and southern sections. The dry season is ongoing across most of the West, but many southern locations missed much of their precipitation during the normal wet season (November-March), especially since the start of this year. Selected January 1-June 24 precipitation totals versus normal included: San Diego, CA (1.58 vs 7.62), Los Angeles, CA (1.56 vs 11.35), Las Vegas, NV (0.10 vs 2.28), Phoenix, AZ (0.19 vs 3.10), Flagstaff, AZ (1.22 vs 9.71), and Albuquerque, NM (1.00 vs 3.12). The water year (since October 1, 2001) basin average precipitation was under half of normal in Arizona, most of New Mexico, and across southern parts of California, Nevada, Utah, and Colorado, and even &amp;lt;25% across southeastern California, southwestern New Mexico, and most of Arizona. As of June 24, wildfire danger remained very high to extreme throughout the Four Corners states, with 19 active, large wildfires affecting nearly 645,000 acres. This included the infamous Rodeo and Chediski fires in eastern Arizona, now merged as one 305,000 acre inferno, and the Hayman (137,000 acres) and Missionary Ridge (63,000 acres) fires in Colorado. With many meteorological and hydrological indices, products, blends, and statistics approaching or hitting record lows, plus above-normal weekly temperatures with highs in the 90Fs and 100Fs, no rain, gusty winds, and very low humidities, the Southwestern drought area generally expanded. Farther north, short-term (meteorological) dryness in the west-central Intermountain West, plus lingering impacts from last winters drought in eastern Oregon, slightly expanded D0 and D1 in northern California and eastern Oregon. According to USDA/NASS, 57% and 36% of Oregons winter wheat and pasture was judged very poor to poor, and 68% of its topsoil moisture rated short to very short. Fortunately in California, hydrological drought is not a concern. The states reservoir storage (156 major reservoirs) was at 9.25 trillion gallons ( 96% of normal) as of May 31, just slightly less than one year ago (9.35 trillion gallons).

## Forecast
Forecasted weather that may affect dry and drought areas the next 5 days (June 27-July 1) include: 1) A cold front that will slowly move through the Midwest and East early in the period, but eventually stall in the South this weekend. This should trigger widespread showers and thunderstorms, and bring light to moderate rains to much of the South, from the southern Plains east into the Carolinas. Lesser amounts should fall on New England, the mid-Atlantic, and the Ohio Valley. Cooler weather will cover the South and East, especially this weekend. 2) A strong ridge of high pressure should encompass much of the West, producing dry and hot weather, especially in the northern Rockies and Plains. 3) Scattered wet thundershowers may develop in New Mexico and Colorado, but isolated, mostly dry thundershowers in the Great Basin may increase wildfire chances. 4) In Alaska, a large storm system in the Gulf of Alaska should move northward, bringing widespread precipitation and lower temperatures to much of the state.
The NWS 6-10 day (July 2-6) outlook call for subnormal precipitation in the western Corn Belt and upper Midwest, and along the central and eastern Gulf, mid-Atlantic, and New England Coasts. Above normal rainfall is anticipated for the southern Rockies, south-central Plains, northern Delta, Tennessee Valley, and southern Appalachians. Warmer-than-normal weather is predicted for most of the Nation, with seasonable temperatures in the Pacific Northwest, northern Rockies, southern Plains, and the Gulf Coast States. In Alaska, interior and northern sections are forecasted to be cooler and wetter than normal, with subnormal rainfall along the southern coast.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.878279377974</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-66.959455193362</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>21.0797641710565</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>67.2912562978444</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:37:33-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 