<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2009-02-10</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — February 10, 2009</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2009-02-10</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2009-02-10</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2009-02-12</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — February 10, 2009

## Introduction
For the country as a whole, it was a relatively dry week with a few important exceptions. Moderate to heavy precipitation fell on parts of California and the Southwest for the first time in several weeks, and moderate amounts with isolated heavy totals were also reported in parts of the Great Basin, the Rockies, and the Plains. The continuing dryness in most of the East and South led to dryness and drought expansion, but significant precipitation provided at least limited relief from dryness and drought in parts of the south-central and northern Plains.

## Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico
It was an uneventful week across Hawaii, with scattered moderate to heavy rainfall reported, but an assessment of the precipitation patterns observed during the past several weeks and current streamflow levels prompted some changes on the Big Island. Conditions now look better on the eastern half of the Island, where a significant westward retraction of D0 and a more limited pullback of D1 conditions seemed justified. In contrast, the areas of severe to extreme drought across interior parts of the Island felt no relief, and in fact a moderate expansion of extreme drought conditions was assessed in part of the interior.
Light precipitation fell on most of the abnormally dry areas in Alaska, similar to conditions noted for many of the past several weeks. In addition, snowpack in northwestern Alaska is near or above typical seasonal levels, thus D0 was removed from the northern tier and the northwesternmost sections of the state.
Scattered light to moderate precipitation fell on interior northeastern Puerto Rico, keeping existing D0 conditions intact.

## The East
Little or no precipitation fell on areas east of the Mississippi River last week, fostering some marked expansion of abnormal dryness, and more limited areas of deterioration from abnormal dryness into moderate drought. At least somewhat below-normal precipitation has been observed in areas east of the Appalachians from the lower mid-Atlantic region southward since mid-November 2008, with the last 30 days bringing very little precipitation (generally less than 25 percent of normal) to most areas outside central and northern peninsular Florida. As a result, D0 conditions expanded markedly to cover all areas east of the Appalachians from northern Virginia, southern Maryland, and central Delaware southward to northern Florida. Furthermore, abnormal dryness deteriorated to moderate drought in the southernmost sections of Mississippi, Alabama, and adjacent Florida, parts of southeastern Florida, portions of the central and northwestern Carolinas, and western Virginia. Areas of severe to extreme drought remained unchanged, as did hydrologic dryness in northwestern Pennsylvania.

## The Great Lakes Region
Light precipitation fell on most of the areas affected by dryness and drought, keeping drought classifications unchanged in most of the region, though a little expansion of the D2 area both to the southeast and northwest in Wisconsin seemed warranted based on a re-assessment of precipitation deficits on time scales ranging from 90 days to over a year.

## The Plains
Moderate precipitation (0.5 to locally 2.0 inches) fell on scattered locations across the south-central, western, and northern Plains with little or none reported elsewhere, most notably in southern and coastal Texas, most of Louisiana, southern New Mexico, and eastern Montana. This precipitation was enough to improve former D1 to D2 conditions in parts of southern Oklahoma, and to eliminate former D1 conditions in southwestern North Dakota, although the extent of abnormal dryness was not affected. In contrast, the dry week contributed to building moisture deficits that prompted a slight northwestward expansion of the D4 area in central Texas, a northeastward expansion of D2 into parts of the Houston, TX and Galveston, TX areas, and a broad expansion of D1 into most of the upper Texas and Louisiana Gulf Coastal region. Also, increasing moisture deficits over the last 3 months led to the introduction of D0 across south-central New Mexico, and some expansion of D0 in east-central Montana.

## The West
Moderate to heavy precipitation (over 1 inch) was widespread across the southern Cascades, the Sierra Nevada, the coastal regions of California, and the southwestern California mountains, with amounts of 3 to 6 inches fairly common in southwestern California. However, since this was the first substantial precipitation across the state in several weeks, and because reservoir levels remain low and higher-elevation snowpack is still considerably below normal, drought classification improvements were limited. Specifically, moderate drought was re-classified as abnormal dryness through most of the climatologically arid areas in southeastern California and in southern Nevada while D0 conditions retracted westward out of west-central and southwestern Arizona. For the state of California as a whole, combined reservoir storage has dropped to levels typically observed only once every 10 to 20 years in February, and some areas reliant on relatively small-scale water supply systems are bracing for mandatory water usage cutbacks for the coming spring and summer.
In other parts of the West, light precipitation was the general rule, with scattered areas of moderate precipitation and some isolated heavy amounts (1 to 3 inches) observed. Recent dryness has become an increasing concern in Montana, where D0 conditions were expanded into central, west-central, and southwestern parts of the state. Farther south, the situation changed little across Wyoming, but a re-assessment of conditions, particularly regional snowpack totals for the last 2 years, prompted some reduction in the extent of D1 in the southwestern part of the state and some re-configuration of D0 coverage in central and southern Wyoming as well as adjacent north-central Colorado. The latter region was one of the areas that received moderate to heavy precipitation last week.

## Forecast
At least some precipitation is expected through most dry areas in the South and East during February 12 - 16, 2009, though heavy totals (exceeding 1 inch) should be limited to northwest Pennsylvania and a swath across the Gulf of Mexico and southern Atlantic Coastal states from southern portions of Louisiana and Mississippi eastward through most of Alabama, Georgia, and South Carolina. Totals of 2 to 3 inches are expected in a band from far southeastern Louisiana northeastward through central Georgia. Only southern Florida is expected to evade any precipitation during this period. Elsewhere, precipitation should be more limited from the Great Basin and the Rockies eastward through the Plains and the Great Lakes region. Most of these areas can expect light to locally moderate precipitation, with a few areas receiving up to an inch. However, the dry areas in the northern Plains and from central Texas northward through Oklahoma and westward through most of New Mexico are forecast to receive little or no precipitation. This includes the most severely dry areas in central and southeastern Texas.
Finally, heavy and potentially beneficial precipitation is again expected throughout California, with 2 to 4 inches forecast for the higher elevations and most coastal sections in the state. Even the typically drier central California Valleys should receive at least 2 inches.
During the ensuing 5 days (February 17 - 21, 2009), above-normal precipitation seems most likely again across the Southeast and lower mid-Atlantic region while below-normal totals appear most probable again for southern Florida and for northwestern Pennsylvania. Farther west, below-normal precipitation also appears to be favored through the southern half of the Plains from all of Texas and southern New Mexico northward through eastern Colorado and Kansas. In contrast, the odds tilt toward wetter than normal conditions for the dry area in the northern Plains and westernmost Great Lakes Region. Farther west, above-normal precipitation looks to continue throughout California, extending northward and eastward through Oregon and southeastern Washington, central and western Idaho, all of Nevada, and the western halves of Utah and Arizona. Finally, the abnormally dry areas in Alaska also appear in line for above-normal precipitation.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-168.1235296</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.7395555</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.1738658</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>69.0718767</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T06:44:48-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 