<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-02-08</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — February 08, 2005</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2005-02-08</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-02-08</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2005-02-10</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — February 08, 2005

## Introduction


## The Plains and Midwest
Weekly precipitation totaled 1 to 2 inches at many locations in north-central and northeastern Kansas, and at a few adjacent sites in Nebraska, Missouri, and Iowa. Meanwhile, 0.3 to locally 1.0 inch fell on northwestern Kansas, south-central and east-central Nebraska, and most of the remainder of Iowa. Farther north and west, only scattered light precipitation (0.3 inch or less) was recorded in the upper Mississippi Valley, the northern Great Plains, and the northern two-thirds of the High Plains.
As a result, most areas of dryness and drought across the region were essentially unchanged. The moderate precipitation led to one-category improvements for some of last weeks D0 and D1 areas in northern Kansas. In contrast, growing short-term precipitation deficits and some locally-troubling longer-term dryness prompted slight D0 expansion in northern Missouri and central Iowa, along with some D1 expansion in far northwestern Missouri and southwestern Iowa. Six-month precipitation totals were 4 to 8 inches below normal in most of the new D1 areas, and two-year precipitation totals remained more than a foot below normal at a few locations between Omaha, NE and Kansas City, MO.

## The Rockies and The West
Scattered parts of this large region recorded moderate precipitation totals of 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches last week, including the Washington and northern Oregon Cascades, and scattered locations in north-central Idaho and northwestern Montana, north-central Utah, western Colorado, east-central and southeastern Arizona, and parts of adjacent New Mexico. Less than 0.5 inch fell elsewhere, with little or none reported in central and southwestern Montana, eastern Washington and Oregon, central and southern Idaho, central and southwestern Wyoming, central and eastern Colorado, central and northeastern New Mexico, and areas in and near the Mojave Desert.
Typically, this sort of week would result in few, if any, changes to the Drought Monitor, especially considering the long-term nature of drought conditions in parts of the West. However, a plethora of new data became available within the last week, including February 1 measurements of snowpack water content and reservoir storage, surface water supply indices, and streamflow outlooks, all of which contributed to several changes in the Drought Monitor depiction. In general, these data confirmed that slow but steady relief has been felt in central and southern parts of the region over the last few months while dryness and drought expanded and intensified farther to the north.
Declining long-term precipitation deficits and above-normal to record snowpack water content for early February led to the elimination of dryness in south-central Utah, parts of northwestern and west-central Arizona, and adjacent sections of Nevada and California. For similar reasons, improvement was introduced in northeastern Utah (to D0), southwestern Colorado (to D0), part of central Nevada (to D1), southeastern Utah (to D1), southwestern New Mexico (to D1), southeastern Arizona (to D2), and some areas north of Santa Fe, NM (to D2). In fact, most locations across the eastern and southern reaches of both Nevada and Utah, roughly the western half of Arizona, much of southeastern California, part of central and northern New Mexico, and portions of Colorados southern tier reported above-normal precipitation totals for the two-year period ending in early February. It should be noted, however, that despite steady improvement, reservoir levels remain below normal through much of the region. New Mexico and Utah held only about half of normal reservoir storage on February 1, and Nevada was just over one-quarter of normal, according to the Natural Resources Conservation Service.
In contrast, abnormally mild and dry weather and declining snowpacks led to deteriorating conditions across the northern tier of the West. D4 conditions expanded across southeastern Montana and northeastern Wyoming, D3 pushed into most of the Bear River Basin and portions of western Montana (including significant segments of the Missouri River Basin and the Front Range), D2 expanded a bit in the northeastern quarter of Montana and was introduced across part of northeastern Oregon and northern Idaho, D1 stretched slightly westward in the central Washington Cascades, and D0 was introduced across interior southwestern Oregon.
Many of these changes were inspired by early February snowpack water content reports, which were at or near record low levels for this time of year at several locations across the northern tier of Wyoming, north-central Montana, much of the central and northern Montana Front Range, parts of the Cascades from central Washington southward to central Oregon, portions of interior southwestern and northeastern Oregon, and isolated sites in western Idaho and southeastern Oregon. Statewide, Montanas snowpack was only 63 percent of normal, and only 57 percent of normal in areas west of the Continental Divide, due to a combination of deficient precipitation since October and near-record to record warmth from mid-January through early February. A few parts of Montana noted record low October 1  February 7 precipitation totals, including Butte, where records date back to 1894, and Hamilton, where records date back to 1895. In addition, several other Montana locations and a couple of sites in adjacent Idaho reported the second or third driest such period since local records began.

## The Southeast
A few locations in southern Florida recorded 0.3 to 1.0 inch of precipitation, but most sites observed less than one-quarter inch, if any. As a result, D0 conditions persisted across the southern half of the Florida Peninsula. Rainfall totals were 3 to 6 inches below normal in this region over the last 90 days.
Farther north, precipitation totals since mid-November also range from 3 to 6 inches below normal across broad sections of the Southeast, including most of the northern Florida Peninsula, the Piedmont and Coastal Plains of Georgia and South Carolina, and scattered locations across central and eastern North Carolina, with deficits at a few locations exceeding one-half foot. Most of these areas were persistently wetter than normal for at least several months prior to this, so D0 conditions do not appear warranted at this time. However, the region will be closely monitored as the start of the growing season approaches over the next several weeks.

## Forecast
For the next 5 days, relatively wet weather is expected in central and western New Mexico and across most of Arizona, with 0.5 to 1.5 inches of precipitation forecast. Light to locally moderate amounts are expected across the remainder of the southern Rockies and desert Southwest, much of the central Rockies, western Wyoming, all but southwestern Idaho, portions of northeastern Oregon, parts of southern and western Montana, and southwestern South Dakota. At the same time, little or no precipitation is anticipated across the northern Great Basin, most of the Cascades, eastern Washington, the remainder of Montana and Wyoming, the northern and central Plains, and southern Florida. In addition, above-normal temperatures are forecast throughout the central and northern portions of the Rockies and Plains, with highs expected to average 9F to 15F above normal across the northern half of the Plains states. For the ensuing 5 days ( February 15  19, 2005), the odds favor wetter than normal conditions across central and southern sections of the High Plains and Rockies, and the desert Southwest. In contrast, below-normal precipitation appears more likely in northern sections of California and the Great Basin, the northern Intermountain West, the Pacific Northwest, southern Iowa, southeastern Nebraska, eastern Kansas, and Missouri.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-124.2190831</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-80.0290249</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>24.5183263</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>49.0018155</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T01:09:27-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 