<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2006-06-06</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brian Fuchs</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — June 06, 2006</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2006-06-06</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2006-06-06</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2006-06-08</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — June 06, 2006

## Introduction


## The East
Wet and warm conditions dominated the weather over much of New England this past week. Temperatures were up to 5F above normal for the week through much of the region. Precipitation was commonplace throughout the region, as many locations recorded more than an inch of rain and localized events of more than 4 inches. This wet pattern helped to reduce the abnormally dry conditions over much of New York, Pennsylvania, New Jersey, and extreme northern Maryland.
Dryness continued for much of Georgia over the short term, allowing expansion of D0 conditions into the southwest portion of the state and D1 conditions into the central part of the state. The main impacts in Georgia are currently confined to the agricultural areas, with dry soil moisture conditions prevalent.

## The Gulf Coast
The Gulf Coast of Texas had another week of heavy rains along much of the coast. Corpus Christi received more than 12 inches of rain for the week, which made up most of the precipitation deficits for the region and also allowed improvements with the removal of the D4 conditions. Up to 6 inches of rain fell farther up the coast in Victoria County, Texas, which helped to further improve this region to D1 status. With the precipitation of this last week, a tight gradient of drought conditions has formed along the southern Gulf Coast of Texas. Areas farther inland have not been recipients of this precipitation, and are still battling the impacts from prolonged drought conditions. The cattle industry in south Texas is hurting as ranchers are forced to sell off herds as water and feed have become scarce. San Antonio has held off water restrictions for the time being because the local water table has responded to rains surrounding the area and has risen several feet in the last few weeks.
The eastern portions of the Gulf Coast have remained dry. The southern climate divisions of Louisiana have recorded precipitation deficits of 18 to 25 inches since October 1. Soil moisture conditions are 76 percent short to very short, according to the United States Department of Agriculture NASS report for Louisiana. With this extended dryness, D3 conditions were introduced in southern Louisiana and Mississippi this week, and D2 and D1 conditions were also increased to the north in Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama.

## The Plains and Midwest
Warm temperatures dominated conditions in the Plains and Midwest this week. Scattered heavy rains brought welcomed relief to dry conditions in several areas, but also were not enough to improve on drought conditions in many areas. In parts of Illinois and Missouri, recent rains allowed for an improvement to the D0 and D1 classifications in those states. In Nebraska, up to 2 inches of rain in some locations over the weekend helped to hold off the eastward march of drought conditions in the state. Several stations in Nebraska recorded their driest May on record, with Broken Bow, Nebraska, recording just .19 inches in May, which is 3.32 inches below normal, and Butte, Nebraska, showing only .03 inches in May, 3.91 inches below normal. Drought conditions did expand in Nebraska and South Dakota as areas of D1 and D2 were increased. Many of the impacts showing up are related to water supply and agriculture concerns.
In Oklahoma and Texas, some rains in the Texas panhandle and into Oklahoma helped to hold off deteriorating conditions. Drought conditions were expanded in southwest Oklahoma where major irrigation reservoirs were at just 50 to 60 percent of capacity and are not expected to fill anymore this year. In Oklahoma climate division 7 in the southwest part of the state, it has been the 4th driest water year on record. In Shawnee, Oklahoma water restrictions were put in place for mandatory water conservation as local water supplies were declining rapidly.
Texas conditions were worsening in most locations off the Gulf Coast. In the northeast part of the state, D2 conditions were introduced again as the benefits of a wet spring have started to subside. The D1 area from New Mexico was carried over into west Texas. D2 and D3 conditions were also expanded in climate divisions 5 and 6, as short-term dryness has started to show impacts in this region.

## The West
Continued dry conditions have prompted fire restrictions in all 6 national forests in Arizona. Several fires caused by humans have prompted several expansions of fire restrictions to include banning all open fires. The largest fire in Arizona, the Barranca Fire near Sedona, has burned more than 800 acres so far and is expected to be contained soon. Drought conditions were expanded in northwest Arizona to push both D1 and D2 conditions farther to the northwest.
Conditions in Colorado continue to remain dry. The drought categories were all shifted more to the west this week as water supply issues and agricultural concerns have become worse. Irrigation wells were being shut off in parts of Colorado to ensure flows into the South Platte River basin. The lack of irrigation could result in millions of acres of croplands drying out and left to die if rains dont occur. In the southwest portions of Colorado near Durango, D2 conditions were expanded to the north out of New Mexico due to remaining snowpack tracking 2 to 4 weeks earlier than normal and several fire restrictions in place. Peak flows have already been achieved in many of the rivers and streams in this region because of the earlier-than-normal influx of water into these watersheds.
Short-term dryness has returned to parts of Hawaii. D0 conditions were added to the leeward side of the western half of the Islands. There continues to be adequate water supply and no agricultural impacts yet, but irrigation is increasing to continue crop growth.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (June 8-12): Models are in fair agreement during this outlook period. A general pattern of a ridge over the West and a trough in New England will be the prominent weather features. Temperatures will be warmer in the Southwest but significantly cooler in New England. Precipitation amounts will be greatest in the Cascades and northern Rocky Mountains and upper Midwest into New England. Driest conditions will be in the southern Plains and through much of the Gulf Coast states. An unsettled weather pattern is expected for Alaska for most of the period.  Widespread precipitation is expected, with the greatest amounts along the southerly coast. Dry conditions will dominate Hawaii, as light trades will limit moisture.
The 6-10 day outlook (June 13-17): Outlook confidence is fair in the extended period, as models are not all in good agreement. Above-normal temperatures are favored over the Pacific Northwest. Above-normal precipitation is expected over much of the Ohio River Valley into New England along a boundary of cool air in the Great Lakes region to warmer air over the southeastern parts of the United States. A dry regime is expected over the desert southwest, while a cool and wet pattern over much of Alaska will dominate the weather.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-159.7864828</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-65.6089422</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.9284123</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>65.6765172</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T01:14:17-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 