<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-08-24</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Brian Fuchs</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>National Drought Mitigation Center</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — August 24, 2010</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2010-08-24</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-08-24</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2010-08-26</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — August 24, 2010

## Introduction


## Hawaii and Alaska
The drought depiction was unchanged in Hawaii, where drought persisted across the majority of the island chain.  Mandatory water conservation measures remained in effect for Maui and Honolulu Counties.  In addition, a large wildfire on the Big Island burned at least 1,200 acres of brush in the mountains southeast of Waikoloa.  Farther north, frequent showers continued to dampen parts of Alaska.  In Anchorage, a record-setting streak with at least a trace of rain ended at 31 days (July 18 - August 17).  Abnormal dryness (D0) persisted, however, in a few areas, including the upper Aleutian Islands, the Alexander Archipelago, and the northern interior.

## The Mid-South and the Lower Midwest
Rainfall managed to bypass an area stretching from the southeastern Plains into the lower Ohio Valley, resulting in some expansion or introduction of abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1).  In some cases, heat aggravated the effects of short-term dryness.  From July 19 – August 24, Paducah, Kentucky recorded highs of 90 degrees F or greater on 37 consecutive days, narrowly missing its 1993 standard of 38 days.  In Arkansas, the percentage of pastureland rated in very poor to poor condition reached 56% by August 22, up from 10% on July 25.  Effects of the developing dryness were felt as far north as Indiana, where 28% of the pastureland was rated in very poor to poor condition on August 22.  At the same time, Indiana’s topsoil moisture was rated 60% very short to short, up from 49% the previous week.

## The Northeast
A coastal low-pressure system contributed to a very wet weather pattern in the Northeast.  Rainfall totals of 2 to 6 inches, with locally higher totals, were observed in much of New York, southern New England, and northern portions of Pennsylvania and New Jersey.  As a result, the coverage of moderate drought (D1) was reduced in the northern Mid-Atlantic States and southern New England, while abnormal dryness (D0) was largely eliminated from New York (excluding Long Island) and neighboring areas.  However, rain mostly bypassed northern New England, where abnormal dryness (D0) was significantly expanded in Maine.  In addition’s Maine’s coverage of moderate drought (D1) increased slightly.  By August 22, USDA reported that half of Maine’s pastureland was rated in very poor to poor condition.  Farther south, hit-or-miss showers affected the southern Mid-Atlantic region, leaving a core severe drought (D2) area intact in a broad region centered on northern and eastern Virginia.  On August 22, 62% of Virginia’s corn was rated in very poor to poor condition, along with 53% of the pastureland and 35% of the cotton.

## The Plains
A few pockets of late-season dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) persisted or developed across the nation’s mid-section.  Drought (D1) expansion was most impressive in south-central and southeastern Oklahoma, where very hot, dry conditions have persisted in August.  Hot, dry conditions have been even more impressive in central and south-central Texas, where abnormal dryness (D0) was broadly expanded.  High temperatures in San Angelo, Texas, reached or exceeded 100 degrees F on 26 consecutive days from July 30 – August 24, easily breaking its 1969 record of 18 days.  Elsewhere in Texas, Waco’s string of 25 consecutive 100-degrees day from July 31 – August 24 was its longest such streak since a 29-day spell of triple-digit heat from July 6 – August 3, 1998.  Farther south, August 1-24 rainfall totaled just a trace in San Antonio, Texas, where the last measurable precipitation occurred on July 28.  Meanwhile, a patch of moderate drought (D1) was introduced in northern South Dakota, where little rain has fallen during the last month and some longer-term precipitation deficits also exist.

## The Southeast
The remnants of Tropical Depression Five produced some extreme rainfall totals from the central Gulf Coast region into the interior Southeast.  A small area of south-central Louisiana experienced a two-category improvement (from moderate drought to no drought designation) due to rainfall totals that locally exceeded 10 inches.  Farther north, August 17-19 rainfall totals as high as 10 to 12 inches in Middle Tennessee caused widespread flooding and eradicated abnormal dryness (D0).  In Nashville, Tennessee, the rain helped to end the second-longest stretch of 90-degree weather on record at 31 days (July 18 – August 17).  The only longer such streak in Nashville’s history occurred in 2007 (34 days from July 26 - August 28).  Meanwhile, rainfall amounts (2 to 4 inches, with locally higher totals) were also quite impressive from the southern Appalachians to the southern Atlantic Coast.  As a result, there were widespread reductions in the coverage of abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) in the Southeast.  Although the rain arrived too late to help corn and many other commodities, pastures and immature crops benefited from the boost in soil moisture.  Some areas missed most of the rain, however, leaving pockets of moderate drought (D1).  A core region of severe to extreme drought (D2 to D3) persisted from the Texas-Louisiana border to the Delta.  In fact, year-to-date rainfall deficits of 12 to 20 inches were still noted in several locations, including Bastrop, Louisiana, and Greenville, Mississippi.

## The West
Few changes occurred in the West, where widespread showers were confined to the Four Corners region.  The erratic Southwestern monsoon continued to produce heavy rain in some areas and largely bypass regions affected by dryness or drought.  For example, Flagstaff, Arizona—in a non-drought area—experienced its fourth-wettest June 15 – August 24 period on record, with 9.54 inches of rain.  Flagstaff’s only wetter such periods occurred in 1904 (9.97 inches), 1919 (10.33 inches), and 1986 (14.25 inches).  Flagstaff received at least an inch of rain on July 18, 26, 30, and August 7 and 23, nearing its 1986 standard of six monsoon days with precipitation totaling at least an inch.  Meanwhile, several wildfires flourished in the Northwest, where the Long Butte fire charred more than 300,000 acres of brush and grass in the wilderness of southwestern Idaho.

## Forecast
During the next 5 days (August 26-30), dry weather will prevail nearly nationwide.  Exceptions will include occasional showers in the Gulf Coast region and a surge of monsoon moisture from the Four Corners States into the northern Plains and the upper Midwest.  Markedly cooler air will arrive in the West, while late-season warmth will develop across the Midwest and the Northeast.  The National Weather Service’s 6- to 10-day outlook for August 31 – September 4 calls for near- to above-normal temperatures across the eastern two-thirds of the nation, while cooler-than-normal weather will prevail in the Northwest.  Meanwhile, below-normal rainfall from the southern Rockies into the Southeast will contrast with wetter-than-normal conditions in the western Gulf Coast region and across the nation’s northern tier from the Pacific Northwest to the upper Great Lakes States.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-165.1264349</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-67.4185863</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>67.485814</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:50:22-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 