<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2002-05-07</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Tinker</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — May 07, 2002</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2002-05-07</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2002-05-07</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2002-05-09</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — May 07, 2002

## Introduction


## Hawaii
Despite a dry April, conditions and impacts remained unchanged across the Islands. D0(W) conditions persisted on the western half of Molokai.

## The East
Heavy rains of 3 to locally 8 inches doused the interior Southeast, reducing or eliminating dryness and drought across western South Carolina, southeastern Tennessee, and northern sections of Georgia and Alabama. Farther east, up to 3 inches of rain eliminated short-term precipitation deficits and subsequently the introduction of the (W) qualifier across most of South Carolina, Georgia, and adjacent southeast Alabama. Also, D3 conditions were reduced to D2(W) in a substantial portion of South Carolina and adjacent Georgia.
Farther north, moderate rainfall locally exceeding 2 inches was observed across most of Atlantic Seaboard, except North Carolina. Thus, D0(W) to D3(W) conditions continued their slow, patchy reduction. D2(W) was reduced to D1(W) in southeastern Maine, where many locations are now near or wetter than normal for the year to date. Farther south, D3(W) was replaced by D2(W) from New York City southwestward through central New Jersey, part of southeastern Pennsylvania, and the central Delmarva Peninsula, but various indicators and impact reports led us to maintain D3(W) despite the relatively damp week in parts of northern Maryland, adjacent Pennsylvania and Delaware, and part of southwest Virginia. At this time, Drought Emergencies remain in place from north-central Maryland northeastward through southern and eastern Pennsylvania, all of New Jersey, and the New York City water supply system. Drought Emergencies also continued in central and southern New Hampshire. On a positive note, water stores in the New York City Delaware River Basin finally climbed out of the Drought Emergency guidance level around mid-April, and just pushed above the Drought Warning guidance level in the last few days, primarily in response to heavier rainfall over the last couple of months upstream in the mountains of upstate New York. The system is now holding about 68% of typical storage for this time of year, in the Drought Watch guidance range.

## The Plains and Midwest
Light to moderate precipitation fell on most of the central and northern Great Plains, leading to some slight reductions in the extent D0(A,F) and D1(A,F) conditions in southeast Nebraska, and southern and central Iowa. The (A,F) designations were introduced because unseasonably cool conditions combined with the precipitation to eliminate any immediate wildfire threat from southern Wyoming, northern Nebraska, and southwest Iowa northward to the Canadian Border.
In contrast, only scattered light precipitation was reported across the northern and central High Plains, and above-normal temperatures pushed as far north as the central High Plains as the week progressed, resulting in some increase in D2(A,F) coverage across western sections of Kansas and Nebraska.
Farther south, little or no rain fell on the southern half of the High Plains, and central and southern Texas. In addition, very hot weather continued across Texas, which combined with several weeks of minimal rainfall to allow D0 to expand substantially northward through central Texas, and stretch D1 and D2 conditions somewhat to the north and west from the Rio Grande.
Daily minimum temperatures averaged nearly 11F above normal during the period along the Gulf of Mexico rim, and little or no rain has fallen since early April. As a result, the D0 which expanded northward through central Texas also spread eastward across southern sections of Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama, merging into the D0 areas already in place along the Atlantic Seaboard and most of the Florida Gulf Coast. This region, in addition to much of Texas and the southern High Plains, will require close monitoring for the next few weeks, as precipitation deficits and drought impacts can amplify quickly during periods of little rainfall and persistently hot temperatures at this time of year.

## The West
Areas from the High Plains westward through the Intermountain West experienced little change in drought status during the week. Light to moderate precipitation and below-normal temperatures covered Montana, Wyoming, parts of Idaho, and northeastern Nevada, essentially eliminating the fire risk in the near term across northern sections of the High Plains and Rockies but otherwise leaving last weeks drought status intact. Late in the period, enough cold air filtered into the northern Rockies to allow some precipitation to fall as snow in the northern Rockies.
A re-assessment of long-term conditions and impacts led to the expansion of D4(A,W) conditions in north-central Montana, into areas adjacent to last weeks depiction. As was the case last week, this is the only area of Exceptional Drought in the United States at this time.
Farther south across the four corners states, most of Nevada, and southern California, little or no precipitation was reported, and average temperatures ranged from significantly below normal in southwestern parts of the region to near normal in the southwestern High Plains, leaving conditions essentially as they were last week.
Since mid-January, dryness in the southern High Plains and Southwest has slowly eroded streamflow levels. For the 30-day period ending January 19, on average 10 percent of streamflow reporting sites were below their historic 10th percentile thresholds each day. By May 7, this average for the previous 30 days had increased to almost 29 percent, according to the U. S. Geological Survey. Water supplies remain adequate for the time being across much of Arizona, southern California, and adjacent Nevada. However, farther east, water supply concerns are on the rise in New Mexico and some adjacent areas.
A wet April eliminated D0 conditions across the interior of Alaska, but dry weather has dominated areas farther to the south and east. As a result, D0 has been introduced from the south-central coast eastward through the Panhandle. In fact, spring-to-date has been the driest such period on record at Juneau, Skagway, Haines, Petersburg, and Yakutat, with totals ranging from 5 to 25 percent of normal for the period. Juneaus total for the period (0.99 inch) was only 58 percent of the previous record low (1.70 inches, 1979). The dryness and resultant low streamflows and lake levels have led to reduced hydroelectric power generation, and a general increase in wildfire danger, but for the most part impacts have been minimal so far.

## Forecast
During May 9 - 13, the following forecast developments could impact current areas of dryness and drought: (1) Moderate to heavy rain from southern Maine southward to central Georgia, with 2 to 4 inches anticipated in parts of northern Maryland and adjacent Pennsylvania; (2) Moderate rainfall in much of the Plains, with totals forecast to exceed 1 inch as far west as central Nebraska and the eastern border of the Texas Panhandle; (3) light to moderate precipitation in part of the central and northern Rockies; (4) little or no rainfall from Florida and south Georgia westward across the Gulf of Mexico rim, southern Texas, and from the southern High Plains westward to the Pacific Coast; hot weather could exacerbate the dryness in the south-central and southeastern states. The ensuing 5 days (May 14 - 18) will feature (1) enhanced chances for above-normal precipitation in the Northeast, with cool conditions favored along the northern half of the Atlantic Seaboard; (2) increased probabilities for wet conditions in eastern Montana; (3) likely below-normal precipitation in the northern Intermountain West and northwestern Rockies; (4) continued increased risk of hot weather from the southern Rockies eastward through Georgia and Florida.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-157.306273576829</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-66.9540017338536</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>21.0906463528231</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>62.9447053643662</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T18:37:18-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 