<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2003-02-25</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>David Miskus</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-05-30</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — February 25, 2003</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2003-02-25</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2003-02-25</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2003-02-27</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — February 25, 2003

## Introduction


## Alaska
Although precipitation has increased during February, very mild weather and/or subnormal precipitation since the fall has generated well below normal mountain snow packs in southwestern and southeastern Alaska. The lack of snow has caused significant changes to the planning of the annual running of the Iditarod. With only 50-69% of seasonal (Oct'02-Jan'03) precipitation, less than half the usual January precipitation, less than 50% of the mountain snowpack (Feb. 1), and February 1-24 temperatures averaging 10 to 20F above normal, abnormal dryness was added in the lower Yukon River region (southwestern Alaska).

## Hawaii
Although heavy rains drenched much of Hawaii late last week (February 13-15; 1-7" on Kauai, 0.5-6.5" on Oahu, ~1" on Molokai, 5.5" on Lanai, 0.5-8" on Maui, and 0.25-7" on Kona), three consecutive drier-than-normal months (Nov'02-Jan'03) and a return to drier weather after February 15 maintained drought conditions. An exception to this was Kauai, where more persistent light to moderate showers erased short-term dryness.

## Puerto Rico
After a dry November (51%), December (71%) [island-wide averages], and first half of January, heavy weekly rains in late January and early February (2-6"), then lighter weekly totals (0.5-2") since Feb. 8 has alleviated short-term dryness across most of the island, except in extreme southwestern sections where 28-day totals were subnormal.

## The East
A swath of heavy precipitation (2 to 5 inches), this time mainly in the form of rain, fell from eastern Texas northeastward into eastern Massachusetts. In South Carolina, the 1-2 inches of rain were enough to remove the small D1 region as 7-day average USGS streamflows (ending Feb. 23) rose to near-normal levels. Long-term hydrological concerns (D0), however, remained in Georgia and the Carolinas as reservoir and well levels still reflected several years of drought (since 1998). In northern Maine, 0.3 to 0.7 inches of precipitation was not enough to diminish D0-D1, although the 2 to 3 feet of snow blanketing the area will hopefully melt slowly during the spring, aiding in soil moisture recharge.

## The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes
The heavy precipitation event in the South and mid-Atlantic bypassed much of the Plains and Midwest, maintaining the status-quo. The exceptions included the Ozark Plateau region where 1.5 to 2.5 inches of precipitation eased D0-D1 in southwestern Missouri, southeastern Kansas, northwestern Arkansas, and northeastern Oklahoma. In southwestern Texas, 1 to 1.5 inches of precipitation shrank the D0 and D1 areas, although the Rio Grande River main storage reservoirs (Amistad and Falcon) were still well below the normal conservation capacity (34.5% and 27.4%, respectively). Farther north, another dry week in western and central lower Michigan, northern Minnesota, and northern Illinois produced 90-day precipitation percentages between 25 and 50%, deficits of 1-4 inches, and declining 7-day average USGS streamflows (most in the lower 10th percentile), resulting in expanded D1 and D2 areas.

## The Rockies and Far West
Drier weather returned to the Southwest after last week's deluge, although a vigorous but compact storm system was approaching southern California by the end of the period. Farther north, light precipitation fell on most of the Pacific Northwest and Rockies, but weekly totals were generally below-normal. The exceptions to this included heavier amounts (2 to 4 inches) along the Washington Coast, in the Washington and northern Oregon Cascades, north-central Idaho's Clearwater Mountains and Bitterroot Range, and the Rockies in northern Colorado and western Wyoming. From the Rockies eastward, Arctic air spilled southward from Canada as temperatures averaged 5 to 15F below normal, causing most of the precipitation to fall as snow. In north-central Idaho, persistent light to moderate weekly precipitation since mid-December raised average basin seasonal precipitation and the Feb. 25 snow water equivalent (SWE) close to normal (85-95%), reducing drought by one category.
However, with the West's normal wet season (October-March) nearing its end, and the capacity of reservoirs (courtesy NWCC/NRCS/USDA) averaging well below normal [Feb. 1 vs average] in Arizona [26 vs 46%], Colorado [32 vs 61%], Nevada [20 vs 51%], New Mexico [23 vs 52%], Oregon [35 vs 56%], Utah [38 vs 72%], and Wyoming [35 vs 64%], much more precipitation is needed in the mountains to ensure even normal spring and summer runoff. Unfortunately, the average basin season-to-date precipitation in these 7 states are mostly between 2/3rds to 3/4ths of normal, while the February 25 SWE percentages are generally lower, especially in Arizona, Nevada, Utah, and Oregon.

## Forecast
The 5-day forecast (February 26-March 3) depicts stormy and wet weather early in the period for the Southwest, South, and mid-Atlantic, then a chance for significant precipitation in the Far West, Rockies, central Great Plains, and Northeast by this weekend. Temperatures through March 2 should also be near to below normal across much of the Nation, except warmer than normal in Florida, and a possible brief Monday warm-up in the lower Atlantic Coast States.
The 6-10 day outlook (March 4-8) calls for above-normal precipitation in the northern halves of the Rockies and Plains, the Southwest, Delta and Southeast, and the Atlantic Coast States. Meanwhile, drier-than-normal weather is expected in the Far West, Rio Grande Valley, upper Midwest, and lower Missouri Valley. Below-normal temperatures will persist across much of the Nation, although warmer-than-normal conditions are likely along the Gulf and southern Atlantic Coasts.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-166.192298</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-66.3251397</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>17.8841923</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>63.2933326</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-05-30T01:02:50-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.1-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 