<gmd:MD_Metadata xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" xmlns:gmlcov="http://www.opengis.net/gmlcov/1.0" xmlns:gmlrgrid="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.3/rgrid" xmlns:swe="http://www.opengis.net/swe/2.0" xmlns:gfc="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gfc" xmlns:gco="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gco" xmlns:gmd="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmd" xmlns:gmi="http://standards.iso.org/iso/19115/-2/gmi/1.0" xmlns:gmx="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gmx" xmlns:gts="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/gts" xmlns:srv="http://www.isotc211.org/2005/srv">
  <gmd:fileIdentifier>
    <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2013-07-23</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:fileIdentifier>
  <gmd:language>
    <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
  </gmd:language>
  <gmd:characterSet>
    <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
  </gmd:characterSet>
  <gmd:hierarchyLevel>
    <gmd:MD_ScopeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MX_ScopeCode" codeListValue="dataset" codeSpace="NA">information applies to the dataset</gmd:MD_ScopeCode>
  </gmd:hierarchyLevel>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Richard Heim</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>NOAA, NCEI</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://droughtmonitor.unl.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="author" codeSpace="NA">party who authored the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:contact>
    <gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
      <gmd:individualName>
        <gco:CharacterString>R. Kyle Bocinsky</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:individualName>
      <gmd:organisationName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:organisationName>
      <gmd:positionName>
        <gco:CharacterString>Director of Climate Extension</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:positionName>
      <gmd:contactInfo>
        <gmd:CI_Contact>
          <gmd:address>
            <gmd:CI_Address>
              <gmd:electronicMailAddress>
                <gco:CharacterString>kyle.bocinsky@umontana.edu</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:electronicMailAddress>
            </gmd:CI_Address>
          </gmd:address>
          <gmd:onlineResource>
            <gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
              <gmd:linkage>
                <gmd:URL>https://climate.umt.edu</gmd:URL>
              </gmd:linkage>
              <gmd:name>
                <gco:CharacterString>Montana Climate Office website</gco:CharacterString>
              </gmd:name>
            </gmd:CI_OnlineResource>
          </gmd:onlineResource>
        </gmd:CI_Contact>
      </gmd:contactInfo>
      <gmd:role>
        <gmd:CI_RoleCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_RoleCode" codeListValue="distributor" codeSpace="NA">party who distributes the resource</gmd:CI_RoleCode>
      </gmd:role>
    </gmd:CI_ResponsibleParty>
  </gmd:contact>
  <gmd:dateStamp>
    <gco:Date>2025-09-24</gco:Date>
  </gmd:dateStamp>
  <gmd:metadataStandardName>
    <gco:CharacterString>ISO 19115:2003/19139</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardName>
  <gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
    <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
  </gmd:metadataStandardVersion>
  <gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
    <gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
      <gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
        <gmd:RS_Identifier>
          <gmd:code>
            <gco:CharacterString>4326</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:code>
          <gmd:codeSpace>
            <gco:CharacterString>EPSG</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:codeSpace>
        </gmd:RS_Identifier>
      </gmd:referenceSystemIdentifier>
    </gmd:MD_ReferenceSystem>
  </gmd:referenceSystemInfo>
  <gmd:identificationInfo>
    <gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
      <gmd:citation>
        <gmd:CI_Citation>
          <gmd:title>
            <gco:CharacterString>US Drought Monitor — July 23, 2013</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:title>
          <gmd:alternateTitle>
            <gco:CharacterString>USDM_2013-07-23</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:alternateTitle>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2013-07-23</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="inForce" codeSpace="NA">date identifies when resource became in force</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
          <gmd:date>
            <gmd:CI_Date>
              <gmd:date>
                <gco:Date>2013-07-25</gco:Date>
              </gmd:date>
              <gmd:dateType>
                <gmd:CI_DateTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#CI_DateTypeCode" codeListValue="released" codeSpace="NA">the date that the resource shall be released for public access</gmd:CI_DateTypeCode>
              </gmd:dateType>
            </gmd:CI_Date>
          </gmd:date>
        </gmd:CI_Citation>
      </gmd:citation>
      <gmd:abstract>
        <gco:CharacterString>

# US Drought Monitor — July 23, 2013

## Introduction
A broad upper-level ridge brought above-normal temperatures to the northern half of the United States during this July 23 U.S. Drought Monitor week.  Troughs moving in this upper-level flow pushed cold fronts which brought areas of rain east of the Rockies along with outbreaks of cooler air to the northern states.  An upper-level low retrograding beneath the ridge brought below-normal temperatures and locally heavy rain to the southern Plains and reinforced the Southwest monsoon.

## Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico
Rainfall was below normal at most of the stations in Hawaii this week, continuing a dry trend and prompting expansion of D0 on Oahu and Kauai.  With sufficient rainfall and above-normal streamflow, Puerto Rico remained free of drought and abnormal dryness on the USDM map.  Alaska had a mixed precipitation pattern this week with some stations above normal and others below normal, but the pattern for the last 60 days (and longer) has been very dry.  D0 and D1 were expanded southward to reflect the longer-term precipitation deficits, depleted modeled soil moisture, and persistent wildfire activity.  An oval of D2 was introduced in central Alaska to reflect low streamflow and Standardized Precipitation Index values, as well as a very dry water year for the Upper Tanana basin (SNOTEL measurements rate the basin as having 22% of its normal precipitation for the water year to date).  The impacts were designated SL for short and long-term dryness in the interior and S for the shorter-term dryness surrounding the interior region.

## The East
Long-term conditions remained wet across the East.  While locally heavy rains occurred in a few places, above-normal temperatures and generally below-normal precipitation this week continued a drying trend for the Northeast.  Although soil moisture continued to decrease, little negative impact was felt by agricultural interests so no change was made to the USDM map, although the Northeast region should be watched if the heat and dryness continue. The Southeast averaged cooler than normal with areas of above- and below-normal rainfall.  The eastern half of North Carolina was dry, but there were no signs of drought or negative impacts statewide.

## The Plains, Midwest, and Lower Mississippi Valley
The week was warmer than normal and generally dry for the Midwest, although storm systems brought above-normal rainfall to places, with 3 inches or more reported locally in Upper Michigan, Illinois, and southern Iowa.  Elsewhere, 5 inches or more of rain occurred with a meso-scale complex that moved through southeast Kansas and northeast Oklahoma, 5+ inches fell with storms in west Texas from the retrograding upper low, and 4+ inches were reported from storms moving through the Mid-Mississippi valley in western Tennessee and locally from monsoon rains in southern Arizona and southern New Mexico.
For the Midwest to Lower Mississippi Valley, the heavy rains helped alleviate precipitation deficits in the local areas that they fell in, but they were not widespread and the deficits have been building over the last 30 to 90 days.  Places unfortunate enough to have missed out on the rains had 30-day precipitation deficits of 3 inches or more.  According to July 21 U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) reports, 64% of the topsoil was rated short or very short of moisture in Arkansas with 24% of the pasture and rangeland in poor or very poor condition.  Missouri had 60% of the topsoil short or very short of moisture and Iowa had 57% so rated, which was a jump of 22% since last week.  Consequently, D0 (abnormally dry) conditions spread eastward further into southern Minnesota, Iowa, Missouri, Louisiana, and Mississippi; D1 (moderate drought) expanded in Missouri, Arkansas, Louisiana, and Mississippi; and D2 (severe drought) expanded in southwestern Arkansas.  The rains seem to have missed southeastern Indiana, so a spot of D0 was added where streamflow was below normal, soil moisture was drying out, and 90-day precipitation deficits were greatest.
In the Plains, D1-D2 were pulled back in southeast Kansas-northeast Oklahoma and southeast Oklahoma where 2+ inches of rain fell.  Most of Texas had above-normal precipitation this week, so many parts of the state saw D1-D4 improvement.  But much of the central to northern Plains was drier than normal this week.  In Kansas, D0 expanded in the north and D4 (exceptional drought) in the west.  A spot of D0 was added to eastern North Dakota where soil moisture and 60-day precipitation deficits were driest.  With 70-71% of the topsoil moisture in Nebraska and Kansas rated short or very short, 55% of the pasture and range land in Kansas in poor to very poor condition, 30-day precipitation deficits of 2-4 inches and 12-month precipitation deficits of 10 inches or more widespread across the two states, significant rains will be needed to improve conditions.  Extension office reports indicated that, depending on crop emergence and crop planting times, some corn, soybean, and other crops in eastern Nebraska were burning up while others were still viable.  Much of the variance was associated with rooting structures that are inadequate to meet above ground vegetative water demands.  With many of the fields in the early reproductive stage, rain is especially needed in the next 7-10 days.  Crops were facing a similar predicament in Missouri and Iowa.

## The West
Monsoon rains, enhanced by the retrograding upper low, brought above-normal precipitation to much of the Southwest, while the upper ridge inhibited showers in the Northwest and northern Rockies.  D1 and D2 were pulled back in Utah and D1-D3 were trimmed in Arizona.  Several CoCoRaHS stations near Carlsbad reported 3.00-4.49 inches of rain, so D2-D4 were pulled back in southeastern New Mexico while D3-D4 were shaved in southwestern New Mexico.  Over 6 inches of moisture has fallen in July to date over parts of south central Colorado where D3 (extreme drought) was trimmed, recent rains improved crop conditions resulting in pullback of D3 in northeastern Colorado, and D1 shrank near Denver and other Front Range communities due to improving vegetation and reservoir levels.  But the drought is far from over in the Southwest, with 80% of the topsoil short or very short of moisture in Colorado and New Mexico, 74% so rated in Oregon, and over 60% that dry in Utah.  As of July 21, the USDA reported pasture and range land in poor to very poor condition for 95% of California, 79% of Arizona and New Mexico, 70% of Nevada, and 64% of Colorado.
Drier and warmer than normal weather further dried out soils in the northern states of the West, with the USDA rating topsoil short or very short of moisture for 62% of Wyoming and 47% of Montana, which are jumps of 14% and 10%, respectively, from last week.  The Palmer Crop Moisture Index showed progressively worsening conditions.  This week began with only 4 large wildfires burning in the Northwest, but it ended with firefighters battling over a dozen.  As a result, D0-D1 expanded in northern Idaho and western Montana, and D3 expanded into southwestern Wyoming.

## Forecast
During the next 6 days (July 24-29), an upper-level trough with associated cool front will dominate the weather east of the Rockies, bringing below-normal temperatures and areas of rain.  Half an inch or more of precipitation is forecast from the Plains to the East Coast, except for the Ohio and Tennessee valleys and southern Texas, where very little rain will fall.  An inch or more may fall from the western Great Lakes to Nebraska, and from Arkansas to Mississippi, bringing relief to the newly expanded D0 areas, as well as from Florida to the Mid-Atlantic coastal areas.  The heaviest rains (2 inches or more) are forecast for parts of Kansas and Oklahoma.  Monsoon rains are predicted to continue for the Southwest to central Rockies states, with up to an inch across much of New Mexico and Colorado.  Otherwise, above-normal temperatures are forecast for the West beneath an upper-level ridge with little to no rainfall for the Northwest and coastal California.
The NWS 6-10 day and 8-14 day forecasts (for July 30-August 7) show the highest likelihood of above-normal precipitation for the northern Plains to Great Lakes, then extending down to the Southeast, and the highest likelihood for below-normal precipitation from the Pacific Northwest to the southern Plains.  Above-normal temperatures are expected for the Southwest into western Texas, and for coastal New England, while below-normal temperatures are anticipated for the Southeast, northern Plains to western Great Lakes, and coastal Northwest.  The southern two-thirds of Alaska should be warmer and drier than normal with the north wetter than normal.

## Disclaimer
The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.

</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:abstract>
      <gmd:credit>
        <gco:CharacterString>The US Drought Monitor is produced through a partnership between the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the United States Department of Agriculture and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</gco:CharacterString>
      </gmd:credit>
      <gmd:status>
        <gmd:MD_ProgressCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_ProgressCode" codeListValue="completed"/>
      </gmd:status>
      <gmd:resourceMaintenance>
        <gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
          <gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
            <gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode" codeListValue="weekly" codeSpace="NA">data is updated on a weekly basis</gmd:MD_MaintenanceFrequencyCode>
          </gmd:maintenanceAndUpdateFrequency>
        </gmd:MD_MaintenanceInformation>
      </gmd:resourceMaintenance>
      <gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
        <gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode" codeListValue="vector">vector data is used to represent geographic data</gmd:MD_SpatialRepresentationTypeCode>
      </gmd:spatialRepresentationType>
      <gmd:language>
        <gmd:LanguageCode codeList="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/" codeListValue="eng" codeSpace="ISO 639-2">English</gmd:LanguageCode>
      </gmd:language>
      <gmd:characterSet>
        <gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode codeList="https://standards.iso.org/iso/19139/resources/gmxCodelists.xml#MD_CharacterSetCode" codeListValue="utf8">8-bit variable size UCS Transfer Format, based on ISO/IEC 10646</gmd:MD_CharacterSetCode>
      </gmd:characterSet>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>farming</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:topicCategory>
        <gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>environment</gmd:MD_TopicCategoryCode>
      </gmd:topicCategory>
      <gmd:extent>
        <gmd:EX_Extent>
          <gmd:geographicElement>
            <gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
              <gmd:westBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-168.9506933</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:westBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
                <gco:Decimal>-84.8262964</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:eastBoundLongitude>
              <gmd:southBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>18.9154965</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:southBoundLatitude>
              <gmd:northBoundLatitude>
                <gco:Decimal>68.9672472</gco:Decimal>
              </gmd:northBoundLatitude>
            </gmd:EX_GeographicBoundingBox>
          </gmd:geographicElement>
        </gmd:EX_Extent>
      </gmd:extent>
    </gmd:MD_DataIdentification>
  </gmd:identificationInfo>
  <gmd:distributionInfo>
    <gmd:MD_Distribution>
      <gmd:distributionFormat>
        <gmd:MD_Format>
          <gmd:name>
            <gco:CharacterString>GeoParquet</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:name>
          <gmd:version>
            <gco:CharacterString>1.0</gco:CharacterString>
          </gmd:version>
        </gmd:MD_Format>
      </gmd:distributionFormat>
    </gmd:MD_Distribution>
  </gmd:distributionInfo>
  <!--Metadata Creation date/time: 2025-09-24T13:52:03-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML generated by geometa R package - Version 0.9.2-->
  <!--ISO 19139 XML compliance: YES-->
  <!--geometa R package information:	Contact: Emmanuel Blondel emmanuel.blondel1@gmail.com	URL: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/wiki	BugReports: https://github.com/eblondel/geometa/issues-->
</gmd:MD_Metadata> 