<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020905</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather developments that could have an impact on areas of drought or dryness during the next 2 weeks include: 1) a tropical weather system bringing heavy downpours to coastal Texas, potentially easing drought in South Texas; 2) above-normal rainfall in the lower Mississippi Valley, benefitting dry areas in northern Louisiana and southern Arkansas; 3) below-normal rainfall from the Tennessee Valley to New England as well as the Southwest; 4) beneficial moisture from the Great Basin to Montana. Heavy rains from Tropical Storm Edouard, which is forecast to cross the Florida peninsula on September 5, are not expected to extend far enough north to have a significant impact on the drought areas in Georgia.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>No changes were made in the areas affected by D0 in Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Several inches of rain in many areas resulted in the elimination of D0.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Heavy rains from New England to the Southeast coastal plain significantly relieved drought. Amounts ranging from 3 to 5 inches reduced drought to D0 or better along the coasts from North Carolina to Georgia, while drought generally improved to D1 to D0 farther inland and to D3 to D2 across the Piedmont. Three to five inches of rain also eliminated much of the D4 drought in Virginia, although a large area of D3 persisted across the state. Two to four inches of rain improved drought to D1 from the New York City area southward into northern New Jersey. Drought improved by one to two categories to D2 in southern New Jersey, central Maryland, and southeastern Pennsylvania. Very heavy rains exceeding 5 inches reduced drought from D3 to D0 over southern Delaware and Marylands southeastern shore. Despite the deluge, 52-week rainfall deficits ranged from 8 to 12 inches in this area, resulting in continued below normal water tables. The abundant moisture received during the 7 days ending on September 3 along the Eastern Seaboard resulted in major boosts to soil moisture, virtually eliminating agricultural drought, while the remaining long-term rainfall deficits mean that more rain is needed to bring reservoirs and wells back up to normal levels. Much lighter rains fell in northern New England and from the Appalachians westward, resulting in little or no improvement and even some intensification of drought. Extreme (D3) to exceptional (D4) drought expanded westward across central and northern Georgia, while D2 to D3 drought edged westward in eastern Tennessee. Severe drought expanded westward into Virginias Shenandoah Valley, while D0 (abnormal dryness) expanded across West Virginia and northern and western Pennsylvania. Severe drought (D2) developed across northern Maine.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>Dryness (D0) extended northward from Louisiana into southwestern Arkansas and also expanded westward across southern Alabama into southeastern Mississippi.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, Ohio Valley, Great Lakes">
   <p>Persistent lack of rain resulted in severe (D2) drought developing from eastern Ohio southward into northern Kentucky and westward into southern Indiana. D1 drought also expanded northward into southeastern Michigan. Drought improved by one category in much of Nebraska, where thunderstorms dumped over 1 inch of rain over many areas. Drought also improved from D4 to D3 in western Kansas, but dry weather caused D0 to D1 drought to progress eastward and southward from northern Kansas into Missouri and southeastern Kansas. Abnormal dryness developed in southwestern Oklahoma and stretched southeastward into Texas. Dryness (D0) and drought (D1) expanded northward from the Big Bend area of Texas due to recent hot, dry weather.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Alaska">
   <p>Thunderstorms dumping 1 to 2 inches of rain or more over northeastern Colorado and extreme southeastern parts of the state reduced drought to D2 (severe), but persistent dryness allowed D4 drought to expand eastward to the Pueblo area of southern Colorado. Although the southwest monsoon came back to life, the resulting showers failed to significantly affect the drought depiction elsewhere across the West.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, plentiful rains resulted in elimination of abnormal dryness from Anchorage eastward.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
