<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010524</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Expect widespread precipitation to fall across much of the Ohio Valley, Mid-Atlantic and New England states over the next 3 to 6 days (May 23 - May 28) as an upper level low pressure system moves slowly off to the east. Precipitation will likely be convective with the potential for locally heavy rainfall in some locations. A cold front, extending from the surface low pressure system in the Great Lakes, will likely bring some much needed rainfall to portions of central and southern Florida over the next several days. Below normal temperatures across the eastern half of the US should help reduce evaporation rates over the drought stricken regions and those regions which recently received precipitation. West of the Rocky Mountains, expect warm and dry conditions to persist throughout the period.</p>
   <p>In the 6 to 10 day range (May 28 - Jun 2), anticipate potential for precipitation across the Southern Plains states as well as parts of the Northeast with continued warmth in the West. Potential exists for a frontal system to bring some precipitation to the Pacific Northwest late in the period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Rainfall continued scattered over the Hawaiian Islands, with significant deficits continuing. However, drought areas were expanded last week, so no change this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Eastern States">
   <p>A series of mesoscale convective systems moving along a warm front from the Great Lakes to North Carolina, and along/ahead of a cold front from the central Plains to the upper Ohio Valley, dumped copious rainfall over the last 7 days. As a result, drought conditions dropped one category across much of Illinois to northern Virginia, the area of D2 conditions centered over western Kentucky was reduced in size, and the northern edge of the D2/D3 area centered over western North Carolina contracted. Radar estimates had locally 8 inches or more of rain in southern Ohio and adjoining West Virginia. Some of this rain soaked into the ground, but much was lost to runoff as evidenced by the record daily streamflow at many area stations. The D0 drought category in these areas reflects lingering long-term impacts.</p>
   <p>The week was mostly dry over the Northeast states, with generally less than an inch of rain estimated from radar reports falling in the 24 hours ending Tuesday morning. D1 expanded to cover most of Pennsylvania, much of New York, and most of southern New England, reflecting very low streamflows and low drought indices, soil moisture levels, and long-term precipitation percentiles.</p>
   <p>Most of the southeastern states had subnormal rainfall. D0/D1 expanded, and a small area of D2 was introduced, in Louisiana and southern Mississippi. D2 expanded slightly in southern Florida to reflect very dry soil moisture conditions. A pocket of near-normal rainfall over eastern Alabama and western Georgia was more than offset by above normal evaporation. An area of moderate values of the Keetch-Byram Drought Index (KBDI), used by firefighters, continued to expand this week along the Gulf Coast and up the Atlantic Seaboard. The lack of rainfall contributed to a continuing wildfire problem in Florida, with fires breaking out in coastal Georgia counties.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Heavy rains fell across Oklahoma and the Texas panhandle, much of Kansas, and from eastern Nebraska to Minnesota. Scattered rains, locally up to an inch based on radar estimates, fell over the drought areas of western and southern Texas, so left D0-D2 unchanged. Western and central Nebraska had a dry week, but soil moisture and 30-day precipitation favorable, so left D0(W) over low reservoirs in southwestern Nebraska unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Most of the West had near-normal precipitation for the 7-day period. A drop in soil moisture percentiles in central Montana reflected above normal temperatures and strong winds over the plains, but there were scattered areas of precipitation this week and an area of D3 was introduced here last week. The mountain snowpack in the West continued to melt in all states. No changes were made to the drought categories this week. However, the dry winter in the Northwest and the northern and central Sierra Nevada has led to a level of wildfire threat usually not seen for another two to four weeks. The snowpack has nearly melted in many upper elevations, and streams in those basins are already receding when they are normally rising. Crater Lake, for example, had completely lost its snow cover at Park headquarters by the third week in May, when the average depth is about 80 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Karin Gleason</name>
   <affiliation>National Centers for Environmental Information</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
