<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20111123</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next five days (November 23-27), temperatures are expected to be as much as 15-20 degrees above normal across the Central U.S., spreading westward into the Rockies and Great Basin towards the end of the period.  Near normal temperatures are forecast elsewhere, with below normal temperatures expected to dominate the lower Mississippi Valley and adjacent portions of the southern Plains and Southeast late in the period. A band of heavy precipitation (2 to 3.5 inches) is anticipated from eastern Texas to central Illinois, and then eastward to southern New England.  Very heavy precipitation (5 to 8 inches, liquid equivalent) is predicted for the Cascades and Coastal Ranges of Washington and Oregon, extending into northern California.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (November 28 - December 2) predicts relatively mild Pacific air and zonal flow will prevail across the western and central CONUS, and a trough in the eastern CONUS. Temperatures are predicted to be above normal for most of the northern and western lower 48 states, with the best chances of below normal temperatures across the Southeast. The best chances for above-median precipitation are in the East, while most remaining areas are predicted to have below-median precipitation.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Most of Alaska received little if any precipitation during the last 7 days, and even the typically wet Panhandle received maximum amounts near 2 inches. Stream flows across the state are primarily near to above normal, including the northern Panhandle region. From about Glacier Bay southward however, stream flows are running below the 30-year average. At this time, there is little justification for indicating abnormal dryness (D0) anywhere in the state.  In Hawaii, rainfall amounts were generally light (up to 0.5 inch), except for northeast facing (windward) slopes, where moderate to heavy rains fell (1.0-4.5 inches). The only alterations to the Hawaiian drought depiction were made in Kauai, where rains over the past 2 to 3 weeks warrant a one-category upgrade across the island. Puerto Rico reported mostly light to moderate rains (up to 1.5 inches) during the week. No changes are deemed necessary for the drought depiction in Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Lower Mississippi/Ohio/Tennessee Valleys">
   <p>Widespread heavy rains (2-6 inches, locally heavier) were reported from southeastern Oklahoma through central and northeastern Arkansas through much of Kentucky and Tennessee.  A one to two category improvement was made across this region.  Much of this area has seen at least 110 percent of normal precipitation in the past 60 days, with substantial coverage of 150 to 200 percent of normal precipitation. Lingering dryness (D0) over western Kentucky was eliminated due to this past week’s precipitation.  Current stream flows across Arkansas, the lower Tennessee Valley, and the lower Ohio Valley are near to above normal. The wetness in this region has been remarkably persistent for at least the past 3-months.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Although this past week has been mostly dry across the Midwest, abundant antecedent precipitation significantly replenished surface water supplies across this region, and have also helped to recharge soil moisture after the recent harvesting.  With significant changes made in the regional drought depiction last week, and much less water demand now that the harvest is completed, it was decided to go with status quo this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Precipitation was on the light to moderate side (up to 2 inches) across most of the region during this past week, with heavy rains (2 to 3 inches) observed over the higher terrain of the southern Appalachians and Piedmont area .  The Southeast has experienced mainly long-term (6 months or greater) impacts. In the past 2 months, the largest rainfall deficits (5 to 10 inches below normal) have been in the southern portions of the Central Gulf Coast region.  In Alabama, recent rainfall boosted soil moisture and helped offset further deterioration. Up to an inch of rain has recently fallen across most of South Carolina, in addition to the 2-inch or greater amounts in the upstate area. Groundwater and reservoir levels continue to slowly decline, potentially justifying some degradation in the state’s drought depiction next week. Stream flow percentiles in the lowest quarter of the historical distribution are common throughout the Southeast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Southern Plains">
   <p>As mentioned earlier, southeastern Oklahoma received very heavy precipitation amounts (generally 2 to 6 inches, with isolated amounts of 10 inches in southern LeFlore and Pushmataha Counties) during the past 7-days, and several lakes in the region have recovered up to 7 feet as a result.  Widespread one to two category improvements were made in this area’s drought depiction. In central and western Oklahoma, several inches of rain resulted in 1-category improvements, primarily from exceptional drought (D4) to extreme drought (D3) conditions.  In extreme northeastern Texas, 2-3 inch rains resulted in 1-2 category improvements from Cooke County eastward into Bowie County. Elsewhere in Texas, relatively minor adjustments were made.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Light to moderate rains (up to 2 inches) fell across much of the Northeast and Mid-Atlantic regions, with a few locations in southern Virginia reporting heavy rainfall (2-3 inches).  With adequate precipitation during the past few weeks, and near to above-normal stream flows, no changes were made to the regional drought depiction for this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Although precipitation has been heavy (2 inches or greater, liquid equivalent) in the Cascades and Coastal Ranges of Washington and Oregon, precipitation in the interior Pacific Northwest has generally been under an inch. No changes in the drought depiction were made this week to the area. In the Southwest, Arizona and southeastern California experienced temperatures within a few degrees of normal and fairly light precipitation.  No improvements or degradations were made to the drought depiction this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Anthony Artusa</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
