<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061019</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The next five days (October 19-23) show the potential for a low pressure system to work its way across the country from the Northern Rockies to the Atlantic, with the possibility of scattered precipitation in the northern tier of states and more moderate precipitation in the Midwest and Great Lakes areas.  To the south, scattered, light rainfall is likely.  Below-average temperatures are expected across most of the country for most of the period.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing five days (October 24-28), average to below-average precipitation is expected across most of the country.  Colder-than-average temperatures are expected from the Rockies eastward to the Atlantic, and warmer-than-average temperatures are expected in California and Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Despite localized rainfall totals of more than an inch and some flooding, the depiction across the Islands remains the same as last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Above-average precipitation during the week was reported in Colorado, western Kansas, and parts of Missouri and Illinois, but the amounts were not enough to warrant changes from last weeks drought depiction.  Precipitation over South Dakota during the last few weeks led to the shrinking of the D3 area in the northwest part of the state.  Although beneficial rainfall has recently occurred in this area, lingering impacts from the summers drought remain severe.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, West, and Southwest">
   <p>Precipitation was reported throughout these regions, but conditions remain the same as they were last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Storm systems produced very heavy rain in a narrow band from east Texas to northern Alabama and around the Oklahoma-Texas border into northwest Arkansas.  Significant improvement from last weeks Drought Monitor occurred from Texas through northern Alabama; no drought is depicted this week for parts of Louisiana and Mississippi.  Although precipitation totals in southern Oklahoma were high, the D3 and D4 areas remained unchanged this week because of the long-term effects of the drought.  In Texas, increasing dryness in the northeastern corner of the state and adjacent southwestern Arkansas led to an eastward expansion of the D4-D2 areas.  Recent rainfall led to the splitting of the D3 area; the southern D3 area has been extended slightly southwestward.  The Rolling Plains area of Texas is now in near-average conditions.  South central Florida has been drier than average for the last couple of months, resulting in an extension of the D0 area.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Ned Guttman</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Liz Love-Brotak</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
