<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010315</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) several weather systems are projected to move across the southern United States from Texas to the Carolinas March 14-16 and 17-19 with the potential for severe weather and heavy rains, bringing additional relief to the areas experiencing long-term drought in this region; 2) central and northern Florida may also see some beneficial rains from these systems; 3) a companion storm system March 14-16 is expected to spread snow and rain across the Midwest and mid-Mississippi Valley, providing more relief to the long-term drought areas in Iowa and Tennessee; 4) several relatively weak weather systems are also expected to move across the Pacific Northwest by March 19 and may bring light to moderate precipitation to areas of Washington state; 5) in Hawaii, the probability of more frontal activity than has generally been seen this winter could provide beneficial precipitation in the drought areas March 18-22; 6) the 6-10 day forecast issued March 13 by the CPC for the March 19-23 period shows an expectation for below-normal precipitation across the western third of the United States, including the drought areas in the Pacific Northwest; and 7) the same 6-10 day CPC forecast shows above-normal precipitation for all of the drought areas in the Southeast, including all of Florida.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Puerto Rico, the most recent week was dry across the Island, with no changes occurring in the D0 (abnormally dry) areas along the southern coast. As for Hawaii, dryness has returned to the state following a brief wetter period in early and mid-February. This dryness now exists on a short-term and long-term basis. Honolulu, for example, has received only 25% of normal precipitation for the past 30 days (around 2 inches is the normal) ending March 12, 2001. For the past 90 days, the city is only at 11% of normal ( approximately an 8-inch departure). Over the last year, only 31% of normal precipitation has fallen (a 15-inch departure). Finally, over the past 40 months, since November 1997, only 33% of the normal precipitation has fallen in Honolulu and a deficit of 53 inches has built up over that 40-month period. Given the dryness across the state, and the resulting impacts to agricultural and for wildfires, various drought categories continue to exist from D0 (abnormally dry) to D3 (extreme drought). Drought conditions have intensified to D2 (severe drought) across southern Maui and to D1 (moderate drought) on Lanai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Appalachians">
   <p>The major winter storms affecting the northeastern United States brought less precipitation to areas in western Pennsylvania and southwestern New York that are experiencing D0 (abnormally dry) conditions. Precipitation totals for the week in this area were less than one inch.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>A winter storm March 11-12 dropped more than one inch of precipitation from south-central Kansas through southeastern Nebraska and western Iowa. The remaining D1 (moderate drought) area in west-central Iowa was downgraded to D0 (abnormally dry) because precipitation has been above normal in this area since October 1, 2000. Some long-term concerns remain. No changes occurred in western Nebraska, western Texas and southeastern New Mexico, and the lower Rio Grande Valley. Rio Grande River flows have been reduced to the point that water has no longer been flowing into the Gulf of Mexico during recent weeks. This has potentially serious environmental and economic impacts to the estuary, affecting commercial and recreational fisheries in the area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>A potent storm system moved across the Southeast March 11-12, providing plenty of severe weather and a round of heavy rains, especially from eastern Texas through southern Georgia. One-day rainfall totals exceeded 3 inches in southeastern Alabama, southern Georgia, and the central Florida Panhandle on the 12th. Weekly totals of 2-4 inches were common from northern and eastern Texas through most of Georgia and northwest Florida. Precipitation totals since the beginning of March have ranged between 5 and 8 inches for the D0 areas of southeastern Louisiana, southern Mississippi, and southern Alabama. As a result of these rains, D2 (severe drought) conditions improved to D1 (moderate drought) in parts of northern and far southern Georgia. Drought conditions also improved a category across the Florida Panhandle. The Tallahassee area improved from severe (D2) to moderate drought (D1), although long-term precipitation departures remain.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, most of Tennessee, South Carolina, North Carolina, and Virginia received much less rain during the week and saw little improvement in their drought conditions. Across the Florida Peninsula, little rain fell during the week. Tougher water restrictions continue to be put into place. According to the National Climatic Data Center, statewide precipitation for March 2000 through February 2001 was the lowest recorded. The same is also true for the October 2000 through February 2001 period. Wildfires have now burned 111,000 acres across the state since the beginning of January, which is a greater amount than the annual totals in 10 of the last 20 years.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies experienced another generally dry week March 6-13. As a result of low precipitation totals and snow water content in the snowpack, a large area of D2 (severe drought) was added in eastern Washington, northern Idaho, and northwestern Montana. Precipitation totals and the snow water content in this area generally were 40-55% of average for the middle of March. SNOTEL measurements within the severe drought region in Idaho reveal the lowest snow water content in the last 20 years, with many of these sites approaching the lowest levels reached in 1977, while the Surface Water Supply Index for the river basins in this region generally ranged between -2.5 and -3.3. In Washington, Governor Gary Locke planned to make an official declaration of drought on March 14, releasing $5 million in emergency funds to the Washington Department of Ecology to assist the state in dealing with the drought. The continued dryness also led to an increase of the D0 (abnormally dry) classification in southern Wyoming and small parts of Utah and Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
