<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20021127</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (November 27-December 1), generally quiet weather will prevail over much of the United States. An unseasonably cold airmass will dominate the eastern half of the United States, with a reinforcing shot of Canadian air forecast to overspread the region over the upcoming holiday weekend. While mainly dry weather is expected in the East, downwind areas of the Great Lakes will be a notable exception, where locally heavy lake-effect snows will occur. In the West, temperatures will be near or above normal, with the best chance of rain and snow across the southern and central Rockies over the weekend. For the period December 2-6, below normal temperatures are expected in a broad swath from the northern Rockies eastward to the Atlantic coast, with warmer than normal weather confined to the immediate West Coast. The best chance for above average precipitation will extend from Colorado and New Mexico southeastward along the Gulf Coast and into the Carolinas.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>The situation in Hawaii remained unchanged from last week, with moderate hydrological drought (D1 W) being confined to the western parts of Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Precipitation for the week was generally above normal north of the Mason-Dixon line, with beneficial rain or snow falling across the Northeast. In Maine, up to 2 inches of precipitation fell during the past week, resulting in the elimination of D2 in the Pine Tree State and significant shrinkage of D0/D1 elsewhere. Beneficial rains in New Jersey also allowed for southward push of the existing D0 depiction.</p>
   <p>Farther south, rainfall was generally less than 50 percent of average across the Southeast this week. A wet September and October signaled the end of the short-term drought throughout this region, although long-term moisture deficits remain, in the form of low reservoir, well and aquifer levels. As a result, the D0/D1 areas remain intact this week.</p>
   <p>Across Puerto Rico, rainfall during the past week was spotty and light over most sections of the interior, with above normal precipitation restricted to eastern and western parts of the island. As a result, D0 was expanded northward.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley, Great Lakes, and Plains">
   <p>A series of weather systems brought light to moderate precipitation amounts to the Great Lakes region, with the most significant rain and snow occurring in parts of lower Michigan and northern Ohio. Above normal precipitation allowed for a reduction of D0/D1 across the northernmost counties of Ohio, as both Cleveland and Canton reported totals that were around 1.5 inches above normal for the month to date.</p>
   <p>Otherwise, west of the Appalachians, weather conditions were noticeably drier. Short-term dryness increased in the past week, with soil moisture indicators suggesting a deterioration of topsoil conditions across parts of Iowa, Illinois and Missouri. This acute dryness allowed for a joining of D0 areas in the Midwest.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A storm system brought rainfall and locally heavy mountain snowfall early in the period to Washington, spreading eastward into northern Idaho, much of Montana and north central Wyoming. Despite the rain and snow, basin averaged precipitation throughout the West was generally below average for the hydrologic year to date (October 1- November 25, 2002). Although the past week was predominately dry in the western states, an active weather regime earlier in November maintained near normal river basin precipitation amounts across areas of Wyoming, Colorado and northern New Mexico. Despite these early season gains, the current drought depiction across the West remains unchanged this week, as mountain snowpack remains insufficient for improvement at this time.</p>
   <p>Precipitation in Alaska remained near or above normal across much of the state, and no designation of drought is warranted in the national depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
