<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20090625</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Beneficial precipitation fell this week again in a swath from northeastern California and southern Oregon all the way to the mid-Atlantic and up into New England.  Precipitation also fell throughout the southeastern Plains, and parts of the south.  Little precipitation fell along the Gulf of Mexico, in southern Texas, or in the Southwest.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Above normal precipitation is expected from the northern Midwest, through the northern Great Lakes, and throughout the mid-Atlantic and New England June 25 – 29, 2009.  Additional precipitation is expected in the West, stretching from Idaho down into Arizona.  Summer thunderstorm activity is expected in Florida.  In intense drought areas, such as Texas, little relief is expected.  Temperatures are expected to be above normal extending from the Southeast to the mid-Atlantic and westward to the Plains.  The west coast is largely expected to see below normal temperatures during this period.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (June 30 – July 4, 2009), the odds favor cooler-than-normal conditions in the Northwest and the Northeast.  The interior of the country, from the Rocky Mountains to the mid-Atlantic and Southeast, is expected to see above normal temperatures.  Precipitation is expected to be above normal in the Southeast, in northern New England, and in select locations in the Southwest and the upper Plains.  Below normal precipitation is expected from the southern Plains into the Great Lakes and along the West Coast.  Odds favor dry and warm conditions throughout most of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought conditions remained mostly unchanged across the Hawaiian Islands, in Alaska, and in Puerto Rico.  In Hawaii, drought intensified in Kauai.  Precipitation was near to above normal for much of Alaska, with the exception of around Anchorage. Precipitation again fell in Puerto Rico this week, particularly along the northwestern coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Moderate to much above normal precipitation (2 inches or more) fell in the Northeast with the highest totals falling in southeastern New York and southeastern Maine (4 plus inches).  Western Pennsylvania, extreme western New York, and Massachusetts received above normal precipitation, easing the abnormal dryness (D0) in these areas.</p>
   <p>Rain fell last week throughout much of the mid-Atlantic and down from northern Mississippi and Alabama to North Carolina.  The area of abnormal dryness in North Carolina largely missed the beneficial precipitation and remains unchanged in this week’s depiction.  Above normal precipitation across northern New Jersey, northeast Pennsylvania, and southern New York eliminated the abnormal dryness (D0) there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Most of the drought-affected areas of the region missed the beneficial precipitation that again fell just to their south and east.  Continued long-term deficits resulted in largely unchanged drought classifications in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>This week’s precipitation was highly variable through the Plains.  Every state in the region saw areas of above normal precipitation.  Additionally, parts of the Dakotas through Minnesota saw areas of much below normal precipitation.  Abnormal dryness eased slightly in western North Dakota and parts of Nebraska.  Moderate drought (D1) conditions were introduced into south central Nebraska.  Western Texas received much needed precipitation this week, resulting in improvement in moderate and severe drought categories and abnormal dryness along the New Mexico border.  Extreme drought (D3) was also removed, due to lessening of impacts, from the Haskell county area.   Southern and eastern Texas missed much of this rain.  Moderate drought (D1) was extended over the Houston area as a result.  Much of Oklahoma, with the exception of the panhandle, missed this precipitation as well.  In Oklahoma, moderate drought (D1) expanded slightly in the central part of the state.  Locally heavy precipitation fell in northeast Oklahoma, southeast Kansas, and into central Missouri with totals exceeding four inches for the week in select locations.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Above normal precipitation once again fell from northern California and Oregon, across northern Nevada and southern Idaho, and into Colorado and Wyoming.  A second swath of above normal precipitation fell from western New Mexico up into southern Colorado.  This beneficial precipitation eased severe (D2) and moderate drought (D1) as well as abnormal dryness (D0) in northern Nevada and southern Oregon and through central Nevada.  Moderate drought (D1) and abnormal dryness (D0) expanded slightly in northern Montana, which largely missed the precipitation this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
