<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020703</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through July 12 that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) continued heavy rains are possible in south-central and central Texas July 2-4 and may continue to relieve drought conditions, as well as provide the potential for flash flooding, in some areas; 2) hot and generally dry conditions will continue in the metropolitan areas of the Northeast July 2-4 before a cold front will bring some cooler relief July 5; 3) scattered thunderstorms could bring local relief to dryness along the Front Range of New Mexico and Colorado, the northern Plains, and parts of the Southeast July 2-7; 4) above-normal precipitation is anticipated across the southern Plains and Southeast during the 6-10 day period July 8-12; and 5) a cool and damp pattern has been established July 2 for most of the abnormally dry areas in Alaska and is expected to continue through the July 8-12 period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Abnormally dry (D0) conditions continue across central and southeastern Alaska and long-term hydrological concerns still exist on western Molokai in Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Rainfall totals of 1-2 inches were common across large parts of the East during the past week, with the biggest exception being in the drought areas of Maryland and Delaware, where generally less than 1 inch fell for the week. Columbia, SC, finished with its driest June ever with 0.63 inches for the month (13% of normal). No changes to the drought classification occurred in the East for the week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>The recent week provided considerable moisture across the Gulf Coast. As a result, severe (D2) and moderate (D1) drought conditions improved across parts of Louisiana. Heavy rains around Lake Charles eliminated the abnormally dry (D0) conditions there. Lake Charles has now had 13.75 inches of rain since June 1 (219% of normal). Abnormally dry conditions were also eliminated across east-central Mississippi and central Alabama.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Very hot and dry weather was the main feature across the Plains and Midwest over the past week. Temperatures exceeded 100F from North Dakota south to Kansas, with Bismarck, ND, hitting 111F on June 29, the second-highest temperature ever recorded in the city. The hot and dry combination caused severe drought (D2) conditions to spread across western South Dakota, moderate drought (D1) conditions to spread into north-central and southeast Nebraska, and abnormally dry (D0) conditions to spread across central Iowa and northwest Missouri. Lincoln, NE, shattered its record-low June rainfall total with 0.17 inches, compared to the previous record of 0.56 inches, set in 1911. The 19 days above 90F for June in Lincoln ties for the second highest total, behind 22 days in 1933.</p>
   <p>In Texas, rains across the southern, central, and eastern parts of the state improved D2, D1, and D0 drought conditions in these areas. San Antonio received 9.52 inches of rain for July 1. Austin, meanwhile, recorded 0.92 inches for the same day, but is still 6.82 inches below normal for the year (62%). In addition, the area of exceptional drought (D4) along the lower Rio Grande received some very beneficial rains and provided the second dose of good news for farmers in this region after the United States and Mexico reached an agreement earlier in the week in their Rio Grande water dispute.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A generally dry week took place across the drought and abnormally dry areas in the West, with well above normal temperatures across the northern Rockies and northern Great Basin. As a result, exceptional drought (D4) conditions expanded to include eastern Utah, western Colorado, and southern Wyoming; extreme drought (D3) increased in northeast Wyoming and southeast Montana; severe drought (D2) expanded along the Snake River Valley in eastern Idaho and eastern Montana; and moderate drought (D1) expanded slightly in central and southeastern Oregon. For Southern California, the driest rainfall season (July-June) ever was recorded in Los Angeles (4.42 inches, 29% of normal), Palm Springs (0.41 in, 8%), and San Diego (3.02 in., 31%). Meanwhile, Tucson, AZ, ended June with a record 93 straight days without any rain, and the 104 consecutive days without measurable rain is approaching the record 114 days set in 1950.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
