<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20131107</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>This U.S. Drought Monitor week saw widespread improvements across portions of the South and Midwest. In the South, heavy rains fell late last week across portions of Texas, Louisiana, and Arkansas. The heaviest accumulations were observed in East Texas, South Central Texas, and the Upper Gulf Coast region where rainfall amounts ranged from two-to-six inches with some isolated locations receiving ten-to-twelve inches. The heavy rains swelled rivers and creeks –triggering flash flooding in the state’s capitol, Austin, and surrounding areas. In the Southern Plains, the same system delivered heavy rainfall across eastern Kansas and eastern Oklahoma. In the Midwest, two-to-four inches of rain fell across portions of Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, and Missouri helping to ease drought conditions. Across most of the Eastern tier, precipitation was modest with accumulations generally less than an inch and half. In the West, a cool and dry pattern was observed over most of the region with the exception of rain in the coastal lowlands of Oregon and Washington and mountain snow showers across the Cascades, Central and Northern Rockies, and Intermountain West.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>The NWS HPC 7-Day Quantitative Precipitation Forecast (QPF) calls for moderate to heavy precipitation across the Pacific Northwest. Mountain snow is expected in the northern Sierras (CA), Cascades (OR/WA), Sawtooths (ID), Bitteroots (MT), and Tetons (WY). Modest precipitation totals (less than 1.5”) are expected from eastern Texas extending northeast through the Mississippi Valley, Upper Midwest, and Northeast. The 6-10 day outlooks call for a high probability of above-normal precipitation and below-normal temperatures across the Pacific Northwest, Northern California, and Northern Rockies. In contrast, above-normal temperatures are expected over the southern half of the United States with the exception of southern California. Above-normal precipitation is also expected across the Great Plains Midwest, and South Florida.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The Hawaiian Islands saw some areas of degradation in Oahu and Maui as overall conditions were drier than normal. On the Big Island, above average precipitation for the month of October led to improvements in areas of Severe Drought (D2) and Extreme Drought (D3). Alaska and Puerto remained status quo this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>The Mid-Atlantic was generally dry during the last seven days with some light rains observed over the region. Short-term precipitation deficits and low streamflows led to slight expansion of areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) in the Piedmont of North Carolina and Virginia as well as in the Valley and Ridge region of Virginia. Temperatures were above normal during the past seven days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Wet conditions were observed over northern Missouri, southeastern Iowa, and central/northern Illinois where two-to-four inches of rain fell late last week. One-category improvements were made in areas of Abnormally Dry (D0), Moderate Drought (D1), and Severe Drought (D2) in Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, and Missouri where streamflow and soil conditions continued to improve. The Upper Midwest remained unchanged on the map for this week. Overall, temperatures throughout the region were slightly above normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>The Northeast saw some minor improvements as modest rainfall and lake-effect snow fell across the region leading to the removal of some areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) in New York State. Short-term precipitation deficits led to expansion of areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) in northeastern Pennsylvania. Strong winds, associated with a frontal passage, were observed at Mt. Washington Observatory in New Hampshire where peak wind gusts reached 130 mph on Saturday. The rest of the region remained unchanged on the map for the week. Temperatures throughout the region were generally below normal during the past seven days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>In the northern tier, a generally cool and dry pattern was observed over much of the Dakotas and Nebraska. Near-normal, short-term precipitation totals led to the removal of a small area of Abnormally Dry (D0) in eastern South Dakota. In the southern tier, eastern Kansas and eastern Oklahoma received two-to-four inches of rain late last week, but these rains fell in areas currently not experiencing drought. In southwestern Oklahoma, continued dryness led to the expansion of an area of Exceptional Drought (D4) in Harmon County. During the past week, temperatures in the southern tier were slightly above normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>During the past week, torrential rains soaked the eastern-third of Texas, northwestern Louisiana, and southern Arkansas. The highest accumulations were observed in East Texas, South Central Texas, and the Crossroad region of Louisiana where two-to-twelve  inches of rain fell. Heavy rains inundated soils in South Central Texas leading to flash flooding across the region, but provided much needed water to local reservoir systems. According to the Weekly Weather and Crop Bulletin (USDA/NOAA), the official observation site in Austin, Texas had the wettest October on record with 13.28 inches. In areas affected by the precipitation event, widespread one and two-category improvements were made in areas of Abnormally Dry (D0), Moderate Drought (D1), and Severe Drought (D2) with a large portion of East Texas returning to normal conditions. In the Big Bend region, light rains led to one-category improvements in areas of Abnormally Dry (D0), Moderate Drought (D1), and Severe Drought (D2). In the Panhandle and north-central Texas, persistent dry conditions led to slight expansion of areas of Moderate Drought (D1), Severe Drought (D2), Extreme Drought (D3), and Exceptional Drought (D4). In southern Arkansas and Louisiana, improvements were made in areas of Abnormally Dry (D0), Moderate Drought (D1), and Severe Drought (D2). Temperatures were above normal across the region during the past week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>The Southeast saw some modest precipitation during the past week with greatest accumulations observed over northern Florida. Short-term precipitation deficits led to the introduction of areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) in South Florida and west-central Georgia. Otherwise, the region remained status quo. Temperatures were above normal during the past week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>During the past week, most of the West was dry with the exception of the Pacific Northwest where one-to-two inches of rain fell across the coastal lowlands of Oregon and Washington. Snow showers were observed over the high elevations of the Cascades, Northern and Central Rockies, and Intermountain West. According to the Natural Resource Conservation Service SNOTEL network, mountain snowpack conditions are off to a good start in Oregon, northern Idaho, southwestern Montana, Wyoming, and northern Colorado. Early season snowfall and improving moisture conditions led to one-category improvements in areas of Moderate Drought (D1) and Severe Drought (D2) in Wyoming, northeastern Utah, and northwestern Colorado. The vast majority of the West experienced below normal temperatures during the past week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>David Simeral</name>
   <affiliation>Western Regional Climate Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
