<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050127</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (January 27 - 31), a pair of Pacific storm systems will affect much of the southern half of the United States. Heavy rain will briefly return to southern California, where some flash flooding is possible before precipitation tapers to showers by weeks end. Precipitation will also overspread the Great Basin and the Southwest, providing additional drought relief but bringing the possibility of flash flooding. During the weekend (January 29-30), locally heavy showers are expected to reach the southern Atlantic States. Meanwhile on the Plains, late-week precipitation may total one-half inch or more as far north as southern and eastern Nebraska. However, unfavorably dry conditions will prevail across northern portions of the Rockies and Plains. In the Northwest, only light precipitation is expected east of the Cascades. The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for February 1-5 calls for warmer- and drier-than-normal weather to persist in the Northwest. Mild, mostly dry conditions are also expected across the northern Plains and Upper Midwest. In contrast, wetter-than-normal conditions are likely from the southern Rockies eastward to the southern Atlantic Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The seasons heaviest snowfall blanketed abnormally dry (D0) areas of Minnesota on January 21-22. The Twin Cities netted 6 inches of snow from January 20-22, boosting its season-to-date total to 10.6 inches. East of the D0 area, LaCrosse, WIwith 8.3 inches on January 21-22experienced its snowiest two-day period since January 2-3, 1999, when 8.6 inches fell. However, liquid equivalency of the Upper Midwestern snow only locally exceeded 0.5 inch, resulting in little change to the pocket of dryness. Farther south and west, dry weather and a sudden turn toward record warmth brought some slight expansion of abnormal dryness, especially in northeastern Nebraska. Meanwhile, long-term drought remained deeply entrenched across the northern half of the High Plains, where warm, windy weather eliminated winter wheats protective snow cover and left the crop exposed to potential weather extremes. In Miles City, MT, temperatures climbed from four consecutive daily-record lows (-32, -34, -30, and -27F) from January 13-16 to consecutive daily-record highs (59 and 60F) on January 23-24. On January 20, Cheyenne, WY, posted a high of 66F, tying a monthly record established on January 26, 1982. Billings, MT, coming off its sixth consecutive year of below-normal precipitation, received only 0.21 inch (30 percent of normal) during the first 25 days of 2005. From 1999-2004, Billings measured 63.40 inches (72 percent of normal), more than 25 inches below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>A major winter storm brought blizzard conditions to the Northeast on January 22-23, but produced only light rain showers in the southern Atlantic States. As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) continued in parts of southern Florida. Fort Lauderdale, FL, coming off its driest year since 1989 and ninth-driest year in more than 90 years of records, received 1.92 inches (82 percent of normal) of rain during the first 25 days of January. The fire danger, represented by the Keetch-Byram Drought Index (KBDI), remained high in southern Florida, averaging 529 (on a scale of 0 to 800) in Broward County and 502 in Martin County. KBDI values locally higher than 650 were reported in Broward and Palm Beach Counties, according to the Florida Division of Forestry. High values of the KBDI are an indication that conditions are favorable for the occurrence and spread of wildfires.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, rainfall deficits existed at several time scales along and near the Atlantic Coast as far north as the Carolinas. During 2004, rainfall was more than one foot below normal and less than 80 percent of normal in locations such as Savannah, GA, and Charleston, SC. This year is off to a dry start in the southern Atlantic region, with January 1-25 totals of 0.69 inch (22 percent of normal) in Savannah and 1.16 inches (36 percent) in Charleston. This section of the Atlantic Coast will need to be monitored for possible introduction of abnormal dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A paradoxical situation developed last week in parts of the Northwest, where significant precipitation fell but high temperatures caused snow pack reductions. Monthly record highs were established on January 18 in locations such as Portland, OR (66F; previously, 63F on January 18, 1986), and Vancouver, WA (66F; previously, 65F on January 28, 1931). In parts of the Northwest, however, surface conditions were deceptively wet due to recent precipitation, melting snow, and high streamflows. West of the Washington Cascades, where Quillayute measured daily-record rainfall totals on January 17 (4.54 inches) and 22 (4.36 inches), abnormal dryness (D0) was eliminated due to excessive rainfall and flooding. East and south of western Washington, D0 remained in place due to below-normal seasonal precipitation totals and concerns about low reservoir levels and spring runoff potential. In fact, there was a modest northwestward expansion of moderate to extreme drought (D1 to D3) across central Idaho and western Montana, where season-to-date precipitation (October 1, 2004 - January 25, 2005) generally ranged from 65 to 90 percent of normal and the basin-average water equivalent of the snow pack ranged from 50 to 65 percent of normal.</p>
   <p>Mild, dry weather prevailed elsewhere in the West for the second consecutive week, following a sustained period of heavy rain and snow across California, the Great Basin, and the Southwest from December 27 - January 12. As a result, there were no additional changes to the Western drought depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
