<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20051013</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Heavy to excessive rainfall is forecast for coastal New Jersey, Long Island, and southern Connecticut during the next 5 days (October 13  17), with totals expected to exceed 7 inches in south-central Connecticut and parts of Long Island. In addition, moderate to heavy rains of 1.0 to 2.2 inches are expected in the Big Bend and southern New Mexico during this period, with totals approaching or slightly exceeding and inch also possible in southern Nevada, central New Mexico, far northwestern Washington, deep south Texas and parts of the immediate Rio Grande Valley, and the northern Great Lakes region. Little or no precipitation is anticipated elsewhere. For the ensuing 5 days (October 18  22), the odds favor below-normal precipitation in the Pacific Northwest and in a broad swath from the eastern High Plains eastward to the Atlantic Coast. In addition, areas from the High Plains to the Piedmont east of the Appalachians should also average warmer than normal. In contrast, wet weather is more likely in the Four Corners region, the southern Rockies, and the southern Great Basin, with colder than normal conditions probable in southern Arizona.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Heavy to excessive rainfall is forecast for coastal New Jersey, Long Island, and southern Connecticut during the next 5 days (October 13  17), with totals expected to exceed 7 inches in south-central Connecticut and parts of Long Island. In addition, moderate to heavy rains of 1.0 to 2.2 inches are expected in the Big Bend and southern New Mexico during this period, with totals approaching or slightly exceeding and inch also possible in southern Nevada, central New Mexico, far northwestern Washington, deep south Texas and parts of the immediate Rio Grande Valley, and the northern Great Lakes region. Little or no precipitation is anticipated elsewhere. For the ensuing 5 days (October 18  22), the odds favor below-normal precipitation in the Pacific Northwest and in a broad swath from the eastern High Plains eastward to the Atlantic Coast. In addition, areas from the High Plains to the Piedmont east of the Appalachians should also average warmer than normal. In contrast, wet weather is more likely in the Four Corners region, the southern Rockies, and the southern Great Basin, with colder than normal conditions probable in southern Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Widespread heavy rains, partially fueled by Tropical Storm Tammy, ended drought and dryness in most areas east of the Appalachians. Only a few areas along the immediate coast and in central North Carolina failed to receive at least 2 inches of rain, and totals of 8 to 14 inches were common in a swath from southwestern New Hampshire southwestward into northeastern Maryland, near the Blue Ridge in west-central Virginia, and in parts of western North Carolina. As a result, dryness and drought are now restricted to a small strip of D0 along the coast from southern Connecticut southwestward through the eastern Delmarva Peninsula, and an area of D0H to D1H conditions from south-central Virginia southward through the central Carolinas. The remaining D1H in central North Carolina reflects relatively low rainfall totals compared to other parts of the East last week, long-term precipitation deficits, some low streamflows, and continued low reservoir levels.</p>
   <p>Farther west, moderate rains of 0.5 to 2.0 inches fell along the Appalachians and in the eastern sections of both Ohio and Tennessee, and only light precipitation was reported along the central Ohio Valley and in most of Kentucky and central Tennessee. This kept some degree of abnormal dryness or drought in last weeks dry areas from the central and southern Appalachians westward, allowed D0AH to D1AH conditions to expand westward in the middle Ohio Valley and the central sections of Tennessee and Kentucky, and prompted a decline to D2AH for most of eastern Kentucky and a small part of adjacent Ohio.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, near- to slightly above-normal rainfall totals fell on the D0 area in western Florida, essentially keeping conditions unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The High Plains, Rockies, and Far West">
   <p>Heavy precipitation, including heavy, wet snow in many areas, brought improvement to dryness and drought in the Rockies and High Plains from central Montana and the eastern Dakotas southward through Colorado and western Kansas. Most of these areas received at least 1 inch of precipitation last week, with 2 to locally 6 inches dropping on many locations in Colorado, western Kansas, southwestern Nebraska, southeastern Wyoming, and isolated locations northern Wyoming and southeastern Montana. This engendered the elimination of D2H conditions in Wyoming, improvement to D0H in westernmost South Dakota and part of the Nebraska Panhandle, and the elimination of D0H in southeastern Montana, central North Dakota, and much of eastern Colorado.</p>
   <p>In contrast, only light to isolated moderate precipitation fell on the north-central Great Plains, the southern Rockies and desert Southwest, and from the northern Rockies westward through the northern Intermountain West and Pacific Northwest. Most of the D0H to D3AH conditions in these areas remained unchanged, but declining indicators led to the expansion of D0H into south-central Arizona, and of D0AH into northern Nebraska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Heavy precipitation totals of 2 to locally 8 inches were reported across the northern Great Lakes region, eliminating last weeks D1AH to D2AH conditions in favor of D0H across most of the Upper Peninsula of Michigan, northern Wisconsin, and eastern Minnesota. A small area of D1H was left near Hibbing, MN, where there was a local minimum of precipitation last week that left year-to-date totals nearly 8 inches below normal.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, precipitation totals were much lower elsewhere. Light to isolated moderate precipitation was recorded across most of the rest of Wisconsin, northwestern Illinois, and Iowa while little or no precipitation fell from southeastern Wisconsin and central Illinois eastward. As a result, last weeks D0AH to D3AH conditions generally remained intact, but various indicators prompted deterioration to D2AH in central Illinois and the southern tier or Iowa while D0AH and D1AH conditions expanded northward in central and northeastern Iowa.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains">
   <p>Generally 1 to 4 inches of rain, with isolated totals approaching 6 inches, were observed from southeastern Texas northwestward through west-central Texas, the Big Bend, and southeastern New Mexico. Meanwhile, scattered totals of 1 to 2 inches were reported in upper southern Texas, near the central Red River, and in northeastern Oklahoma and adjacent Arkansas while little or no precipitation was reported from extreme eastern Texas northeastward through central and northern Arkansas. This precipitation pattern brought an end to D0AH conditions in west-central Texas and the Big Bend, and induced improvement to D0AH in part of central Texas. In contrast, some expansion of D0AH to D2AH conditions took place in the areas receiving little or no rain, including the introduction of D0AH conditions into a broad section of central and northern Arkansas and adjacent southern Missouri.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
