<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20140123</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During January 23 – 27, 2014, between 0.25 and 0.75 inch of precipitation (with locally higher totals) is forecast in the dry areas of the Northeast, central Florida, and southern and southeastern Texas. Light precipitation is anticipated in areas adjacent to these and in most of the Rockies. No measurable precipitation is expected elsewhere. The pattern of above-normal temperatures in the western U.S. and below-normal temperatures farther east is expected to continue.</p>
   <p>For January 28 – February 1, 2014, the odds favor above-normal precipitation in the central and northern Rockies and along the northern tier of states from the northern Rockies through the Great Lakes region. Above-normal precipitation is also favored in the dry areas of Alaska. There are enhanced chances of below-normal precipitation in the southern Rockies and in central and southern sections of the rest of the contiguous 48 states from the Appalachians and Piedmont westward to the Pacific coast, except Florida and southern Texas. Neither dryer- nor wetter-than-normal conditions are favored elsewhere. The pattern of above-normal temperatures in the West and below-normal temperatures farther east is expected to continue.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Through most of the dry areas in Alaska, Puerto Rico, and Hawaii, light to locally moderate precipitation fell. A small area in south-central Puerto Rico reported more than one inch of rain. Dryness and drought classifications were unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Moderate precipitation (generally 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches) dampened the areas of dryness and drought in this region. This resulted in the elimination of D1 in east-central New England and from part of the New York City metropolitan area and Long Island. In addition, D0 was trimmed out of part of northeast Pennsylvania, New Jersey, parts of Massachusetts, and small areas in the rest of New England. These areas received above-normal precipitation during the last 60 days, are near- to below-normal for the past 90 days, and significantly below-normal for the last 6-months. D0 was kept in areas classified as D1 last week and/or areas still with significant 180-day deficits of at least a few inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rest of the Contiguous 48 States ">
   <p>Very little if any precipitation fell. As a result, drought and dryness remained unchanged in most areas as moisture deficits crept upward on all relevant time scales (which varied depending on location). In a few areas it seemed appropriate to indicate one-classification deteriorations in the dryness and drought depiction. Specifically…</p>
   <p>D0 was expanded into western Iowa and adjacent areas where 60-day precipitation totals were under half of normal.</p>
   <p>A few areas in southeastern Texas and the Texas Panhandle worsened to D0 or D1 levels which were on the cusp of classifications last week.</p>
   <p>D0 was downgraded to D1 in south-central Louisiana where 6-month precipitation totals were at least 9 inches below normal. In a larger surrounding area of central and southern Louisiana and adjacent Mississippi, D0 expanded into areas at least 4 inches below normal for the last 60 days and recording under 4 inches of precipitation since late December 2013.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
