<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20140102</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>The week began with a sprawling area of high pressure across much of the contiguous 48 states before two low-pressure systems moved across the country.  The first system intensified over the Great Lakes and pushed a cold front to the southeast.  The next storm system moved across the western portions of the contiguous 48 states and tracked from the central Rockies to the Great Lakes.  As a result, most of the wet weather was confined to east of the Rockies, with the heaviest rains across the southeast.  Some light precipitation was recorded across portions of the Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During Jan 1 - 5, moderate precipitation (up to 1.8 inches locally) is forecast across the Gulf coast with lighter amounts through the Tennessee and Ohio Valleys.  Snowfall is also likely across the Great Lakes and Northeast. Elsewhere, light precipitation at most is forecast for the remainder of the contiguous 48 states.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (Jan 6-10), the odds favor above-median precipitation from the northern Rockies to the central and southern Great Plains, as well as the Great Lakes and Northeast.  Dry conditions are favored across the southwest and eastern Alaska.  A storm track into western Alaska should result in above-median precipitation.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation fell across the Alaskan Panhandle, but not enough to alleviate impacts of an earlier dry period, so D0 was returned to the Alaskan Panhandle.  Moderate rains (1.0 – 2.0 inches) fell across portions of the Big Island of Hawaii, so small areas of drought were removed from the depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Lower Mississippi Valley and Southern Plains">
   <p>Light to moderate rains (0.5 to 1.6 inches) fell across southern Texas, prompting a 1-category improvement across most of the region.  A reassessment of conditions led to the removal of the extreme drought (D3) near Corpus Christi, as that was introduced due to an analysis error last week.  A slight adjustment to the placement of the abnormally dry (D0) area was made across southern Louisiana as well, reflecting better alignment with Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI) values out through 12 months and soil moisture model outputs (NASA GRACE-LDAS).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Mid-Atlantic and Southeast">
   <p>An area of abnormal dryness (D0) were removed from central VA as that area is over 150% of normal rainfall over the last 30 days (widespread 4-5 inch totals). Base streamflow has improved significantly at the stream gauges in that region as well since Thanksgiving.  The D0 area across western MD was retained and adjusted to fit the areas where 30-, 60-, and 90-day percent of normal precipitation data indicated the largest deficits.</p>
   <p>Most of the abnormal dryness (D0) was removed from NC, SC, and GA, with the remaining D0 along the immediate coast.  Deficits in the coastal areas of the southeast are shrinking but remain at 1 inch, for 30 days and up to 12 inches for 180 days.  Due to the intermediate wet period out to 60 days, the impacts are being designated as short-term.  Rains totaling 1-3 inches during the past 7 days according to the Advanced Hydrologic Prediction System (AHPS) precipitation estimates across Alabama prompted a 1-category improvement there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Moderate precipitation (0.5 – 1.5 inches) fell across the portions of the northeast, so some D1 (moderate drought) was removed from Rhode Island and Massachusetts.  Some stations in Massachusetts are reporting month-to-date precipitation totals in excess of 4.25 inches.  The rest of the northeast remained the same as last week due to impacts from longer-term dryness (90-day precipitation totals at or below 50 percent).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northern and Central Plains and The Midwest">
   <p>No changes were made to the depiction of drought across this region as most of the ground is frozen so little evaporation or recharge can take place.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies Westward to The Pacific Coast">
   <p>A reassessment of conditions prompted the removal of extreme drought from near Kiowa County in Colorado.  Recent conditions have been dry, but a wet period from Mid-July to Mid-October has mitigated the impacts, do the area is now designated at D2 (severe drought), more consistent with impacts reported by local extension agents.</p>
   <p>Dry conditions have persisted across California and Oregon, so D1 (moderate drought) was expanded across much of western Oregon and D2 (severe drought) was expanded across much of northern California.  According to the California Department of Water Resources, Lake Shasta is currently at just 58 percent of average for this time of year (37 percent of capacity).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Matthew Rosencrans</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
