<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000817</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may influence some of the Nations dry or drought areas are: 1) A cold front should stall along the Gulf Coast this week, triggering scattered thunderstorms in the Southeast, especially from the eastern Gulf Coast northeastward into South Carolina; 2) Residual moisture from Tropical Storm Beryl and Tropical Storm Ileana (Pacific Ocean) may become incorporated into the Southwest Monsoon, enhancing the chances for wet monsoonal showers in New Mexico, Arizona, southern California, and Colorado; 3) A ridge of high pressure should remain over the West, keeping the rest of the Southwest, Great Basin, and Rockies dry and warm; 4) Weather systems should move along the northern tier of States, bringing a chance of rain and lower temperatures to the northern portions of the Rockies and Plains southeastward into the western Corn Belt; 5) High pressure should also keep the southern Great Plains and Delta relatively dry and warm, although cooler weather may arrive by the weekend; 6) Puerto Rico is headed into the normally active (and rainy) portion of the Atlantic hurricane season (August-October).</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Light, scattered showers continued across the windward side of the Hawaiian Islands, while the drought-impacted, leeward locations measured little or no rainfall, keeping drought intact. Only the western coast of the Big Island recorded any significant precipitation, but weekly totals (0.5 to 2.5 inches) were still near to below normal. In Puerto Rico, light showers (0.1 to 0.5 inches) fell across much of the island, but locally heavier totals (2 to 4 inches) in the northwestern and far eastern portions slightly eased dryness there. Elsewhere, with increasing normals during the rainy season and an absence of widespread, heavy rains, deficits generally remained or slightly increased in interior areas, thus keeping abnormal dryness (D0) in the northern slope and central areas, and first-stage drought (D1) along most of the north coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northern and Central Plains">
   <p>Except for locally heavy thundershowers (3 to 5 inches) in western Kansas, mostly dry, windy, and hot weather enveloped the northern and central Plains, further deteriorating conditions, particularly in Nebraska and Montana. According to NASS and the Nebraska state climatologist, 91% and 95% of the topsoil and subsoil moisture in Nebraska was short to very short, 77% of the pasture and range was rated poor or very poor, and the condition of non-irrigated crops continued to decline while some moved too quickly toward maturity. Dryness also developed in states bordering Nebraska (i.e. northern Kansas, northwestern Missouri), but scattered rains in western Iowa kept the drought from intensifying there. Similarly in Montana, NASS reported that 94% of both the topsoil and subsoil moisture was short or very short, and 57% of the range and pasture was rated poor or very poor. Since July 7, Helena, MT hit a record 39 straight days with highs at or above 80F (old record=38 days in 1967). In addition, at least 26 large wildfires raged across the state, enveloping nearly 400,000 acres, according to the NIFC.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>After several weeks of wet and cool conditions, a trend towards drier and warmer weather occurred across much of the Southeast. The exception to this was locally heavy thundershowers (between 2 and 5 inches of rain) in eastern Louisiana, parts of Mississippi, northern Georgia, western Florida, and along the Georgia and Carolina coasts. As a result, some slight reduction of dryness/drought occurred in eastern sections of South Carolina and Georgia, near the Tampa Bay, FL vicinity, and in southeastern Louisiana, southeastern Mississippi, the northern Tennessee Valley, and the southern Appalachians. Elsewhere, however, drought conditions remained constant in the remaining Southeastern areas due to near to below normal weekly rainfall, increasing temperatures and evaporative rates, and still low August 15 streamflows (number of USGS river gauges in the lowest 10% of record were equal to or slightly higher than a week ago). West of the Mississippi River, the lack of any appreciable rains (since July 1, less than half of normal rainfall, and deficits of 1 to 4 inches), increasing heat (weekly temperature departures of +3F to +6F, highs at or above 100F), and gusty winds have combined to rapidly degrade moisture conditions, especially the upper layers. 54% of the range and pasture in Texas was rated very poor or poor, according to NASS. Even Tropical Storm Beryl, which made landfall during the evening of August 14 in northeastern Mexico, brought only light amounts (0.1 to 0.6 inches) to southern Texas. Accordingly, dryness (D0) and drought (D1-D2) increased in most of Texas, Arkansas, southeastern Oklahoma, and northwestern Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Monsoonal thundershowers finally dropped significant rains (1 to 3 inches) on southeastern Arizona and southwestern New Mexico, alleviating D0(A,F) dryness, but this was the exception as the remainder of the West experienced its fourth consecutive week of heat, a lack of rain, and numerous large wildfires. Although highs were not quite as extreme as last week (Ely, NV streak of 90F+ days (21) stopped on August 9; Las Vegas, NV stretch of 105F+ days (21) ended on August 8), readings were still above normal, and the combination of gusty winds and low humidities have produced very high to extreme fire indices. Through August 14, over 50 large wildfires encompassing nearly 600,000 acres charred parts of the Great Basin, Rockies, and Northwest. With the recent ignition of wildfires, the year-to-date National acreage burned (4,926,039) now exceeds twice the 10-year average (2,434,094), according to the NIFC. These conditions, plus additional input from Las Vegas, NV WFO and the NRCS in Idaho, warranted expansion of the D1(A,F) across Utah and western Colorado, new D2(A,F) areas in southern Idaho and northern Arizona, an enlargement of severe drought (D2) in Montana, and a westward increase of D0(A,F) into southeastern California.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
