<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061109</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch over the next 2 weeks that could affect current dry or drought areas include: 1) several more bouts of heavy rains for the Northwest, with some rain and snow extending into Montana, Wyoming, and the northern Plains; 2) mostly dry weather over the Southwest and southern and central Plains from Kansas southward to Texas; 3) near to above-normal rainfall for the Southeast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Heavy rainfall caused flooding in Hawaii during October 31 to November 2, resulting in removal of most of the lingering D0 and D1. Rainfall amounts were especially large along windward sections of Kauai and Oahu, with some locations reporting well over 15 inches. The only dryness remaining affected western portions of Maui. Puerto Rico reported light rainfall amounts across the south, resulting in continued D0 dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northwest">
   <p>Flooding rains struck the region during November 2-7, eliminating abnormal dryness from Washington, Oregon, northern and western Idaho, and northwestern Montana. Widespread flooding extended from northwestern Oregon into western Washington, where 5 to 15 inches of rain fell during the first week of November. The Washington Governor declared a state of emergency in 18 counties. Locally heavy rainfall also caused some flooding in portions of northern Idaho and western Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Light to moderate rains plus a re-assessment based on streamflows and soil moisture resulted in improving conditions for central and eastern Montana. D1 drought became D0 from central to northeastern Montana, while D2 drought retreated slightly in the south and the north. A storm system tracking across the southern Plains delivered beneficial rains from Texas and southern Oklahoma eastward starting on November 5. One to 3 inches of rain reduced the D3 drought area in northern Texas, although reservoirs in this region, including the Dallas-Fort Worth area, showed little response to the moisture. Lake Lavon, for example, a key reservoir east of Dallas, stood at just 36 percent of normal on November 6. Persistent dry weather in South Texas caused the D3 there to expand southward toward the Rio Grande. To the north, D2 to D3 conditions improved to D0 to D2 across southern Oklahoma, but lack of rain farther north allowed D3 drought to expand along the border with Kansas. Dry weather resulted in expansion of D0 across central Kansas and some increase of D1 and D2 in the south. Dry weather caused some expansion of D0 in eastern South Dakota, southern Minnesota, and western Wisconsin. Cumulative precipitation for the past 60 days totaled less than 40 percent of normal from South Dakota into southern Minnesota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Mississippi Valley and the Southeast">
   <p>The frontal system that brought rain to Texas and Oklahoma swept eastward to deliver moderate to heavy rains from Arkansas to Tennessee, Alabama, and western North Carolina.  As a result, Arkansas benefited from a one-category improvement to D0 to D1 across the south, and the D0 retreated in Mississippi and Alabama, with the D0 removed from Tennessee and western North Carolina. Two to 4 inches of rain fell from northern Mississippi into western Alabama. Locally heavy rains reduced the D0 in the Miami area of Florida, but dry weather to the north resulted in slight southward expansion of D0 and D1 over the central peninsula. D1 drought persisted northward into Georgia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southwest, Great Basin, and Rockies">
   <p>This was a fairly dry week outside of the Northwest, with few changes to the drought depiction beyond the improvements in Montana. In Colorado, because of continuing unseasonably high snow depths and normal to above-normal streamflows, the western boundary of D0 was scaled back to near the Divide. There was also a slight pullback of the D1 in Colorado and also in south-central Wyoming. Minor retreat of the D1 took place in far western Wyoming because of continuing good streamflows.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
