<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041007</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a slow-moving system has brought beneficial rain to New Mexico (October 5) and Texas (October 6), and will continue to move across the southern United States, bringing potential relief to the new drought and dryness areas in the Lower Mississippi Valley and the Ohio Valley October 7-11; 2) the Great Lakes region is expected to remain north of this system and stay mainly dry through October 11; 3) a system moving into the Pacific Northwest and Central Rockies could bring light amounts of precipitation October 8-9; 4) a strong storm system could provide wet weather across most of Alaska October 9-10; 5) the trade winds across Hawaii are expected to be near normal October 8-10, with showers expected daily, but models are unclear about a potential tropical disturbance affecting the state October 11-13; 6) a strong ridge over the Canadian Pacific coast and the associated deep trough over the central United States is expected during the October 12-16 period, bringing colder temperatures and potentially beneficial precipitation to much of the eastern two-thirds of the nation.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Continued dryness on the island of Hawaii has led to the establishment of water restrictions at several locations. As a result, the classification for a large part of the island has been changed to a moderate drought (D1). Long-term dryness continues across part of Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Dryness continued to occur across large portions of the lower Mississippi Valley and the Ohio Valley, and into the eastern Plains of Kansas and Oklahoma. The D0 designation (abnormally dry) expanded to cover southern Indiana, southern Illinois, eastern Kentucky, southern Missouri, all of Arkansas, eastern Mississippi, most of Louisiana, eastern Oklahoma, eastern Kansas, extreme southeast Nebraska, and southwest Iowa. In addition, moderate drought conditions (D1) were added across southern Missouri and northern Arkansas. Arkansas and Indiana had their second driest Septembers on record according to the preliminary statewide data, and it was the fourth driest August-September period in Arkansas. Jonesboro, AR, had their driest September since 1897 (0.03 inches, which is 1 percent of normal). In Missouri, Portageville and Steele have had 37 consecutive days with no precipitation through October 4. Pasture conditions have deteriorated rapidly in these areas, with approximately 50% of the pastures in Arkansas now rated as poor or very poor, with additional concerns regarding winter wheat planting, dryland crops, and drying stock ponds.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes">
   <p>Dry conditions continued to spread across Wisconsin and Michigan as September ended and October began. Detroit, MI, set the record for consecutive days without rain at 23 between September 9 and October 1 (the old record was 22, set in September 1908). In Marquette, MI, September was the warmest on record, and the average temperature of the month was 3.6 degrees and 2.4 degrees warmer than the average temperatures for June and August, respectively. In fact, the average temperature for September (61.8F) was just shy of the average temperature for July (61.9F). Precipitation departures of greater than two inches below normal for the month occurred in Marquette, Munising, Sault Ste. Marie, Alpena, Gaylord, Traverse City, Houghton Lake, Grand Rapids (-3.61 inches), Lansing, Muskegon, Detroit, and Flintall in Michiganas well as Green Bay, Wausau, Madison, and Milwaukee in Wisconsin. As a result, moderate drought (D1) conditions spread across eastern Wisconsin and central Michigan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Across the Plains during the week, beneficial precipitation improved conditions for areas experiencing dryness and drought, including eastern New Mexico, northeast Colorado, southeast Wyoming, western Nebraska, and central South Dakota. Laramie, WY, for example, had its wettest September since 1948 (3.03 inches and 306 percent of normal). As a result of this short-term wetness, extreme drought (D3) was removed from the Nebraska Panhandle. In spite of these improvements, long-term hydrological conditions remain severe in many of these locations. Meanwhile, dryness continued across western North Dakota and northeast Montana, which led to a slight increase in the abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) in this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The West was generally quiet during the end of September and into early October. Additional precipitation fell in central Wyoming (Climate Division 9), and conditions there were upgraded from severe (D2) to moderate (D1) drought.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
