<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060330</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (March 29 - April 2), an upper level pattern consisting of a trough in the west and a ridge in the east will dominate the Lower 48 States.  Several frontal systems are expected to make their way across the country, potentially bringing an increase in precipitation opportunities for the Pacific Northwest, the Plains, and Great Lakes.  Temperatures for the western third of the country are expected to be below normal, while the rest of the contiguous US is forecast to have normal to above normal temperatures.  Drier conditions are forecasted to continue for the Southeast and the East Coast.</p>
   <p>Over the ensuing 5 days (April 3 - 7), the Pacific Coast, northern tier states, and western Great Lakes states are forecast to have wetter than normal conditions, while the rest of the US is expected to remain dry.  Conditions are favorable for coastal rain and inland snow in Alaska.  Below normal temperatures are anticipated for the West Coast and northeastern Alaska, while the rest of the country is expected to have normal and above normal temperatures.  The outlook for Hawaii continues to be wet for the forecast period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>In Hawaii, continued heavy rainfall over the islands this drought monitoring period warranted the removal of all abnormally dry conditions. This is the sixth consecutive week of excessive rainfall in Hawaii. The National Weather Service issued flood warnings for Maui and there were several other areas that have been placed under a flood watch. No changes were made to Alaska this week, as the abnormally dry conditions currently depicted are sufficient for this time of year.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East Coast">
   <p>Overall, this area of the nation did not see much precipitation this period. In the Mid-Atlantic States, the D1AH area in Virginia was expanded westward connecting to the D1AH area in Kentucky as well as northeastward as far north as Delaware. This expansion was based on CPCs soil moisture anomaly and percentile maps, 7-day streamflow, all timeframes of HPRCC percent of normal maps from 7 to 90-day and local feedback. In North Carolina, the moderate drought (D1AH) area was expanded westward to cover most of western North Carolina with the exception of the far western corner. Also in the central part of the state, severe drought conditions (D2AH) were introduced into the Tar, Neuse and Cape Fear River Basins. This deterioration was based on local feedback, reports of low streamflow and groundwater levels and HPRCCs 60- and 90-day percent of normal maps. In Tennessee, the abnormally dry area (D0A) was expanded westward to include the eastern half of the Cumberland Plateau. The Chickamauga Basin has a deficit of 11.06 inches, 61 percent of normal, and Melton Hill Basin was reporting 8.2 inches deficit, 66 percent of normal. Elsewhere in the Southeast, the abnormally dry (D0A) conditions along the Gulf Coast expanded across the state of Florida. Minimal amounts of rainfall have occurred across the state the entire month. Naples has received only 0.08 inch and is on track to possibly be the third driest March on record. The last rain event that impacted the state was in early February when some areas received as much as 2 to 4 inches of rain. USGS 7-day streamflow, CPC soil moisture percent of normal, HPRCCs 7-, 14-, 30-, 60-day percent of normal maps and Floridas State Forest Service KBDI all support this introduction. Much of this area remains under a red flag warning with several media reports of brush fires. According to media reports, Palm Bay has 12 acres charred with at least five other brush fires in Titusville, Melbourne Beach and Malabar areas. Much of this area remains under a red flag warning as of the end of the end of this drought monitoring period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Precipitation was scattered over the Plains and Midwest this drought monitoring period. In Minnesota, the D0A that was extended last week was trimmed back to the western edge of South Dakotas climate divisions 3 and 7 and North Dakotas climate divisions 6 and half of 9. This change was based on local feedback, the Midwest Regional Climate Centers (MRCC) 12- and 72- inch depth soil moisture, CPCs soil moisture anomaly and percentile maps, as well as their long-term blends. This was another active week of improving drought conditions in Texas. In the southwestern part of the state, the abnormally dry conditions (D0AH) were retracted eastward removing that area out of dry conditions. This improvement was based on HPRCC 60-, 90-day and six-month percent of normal precipitation maps as well as local feedback. Elsewhere in Texas, the extreme drought conditions (D3AH) in the panhandle were trimmed back based on local feedback and the NWS southern region's 60- and 90-day percent of normal maps. Lastly, the D3AH area in the south-central part of the state was retracted southward due to 1 to 2 inches of rainfall this drought monitoring period and several time frames of the NWS Southern Region's percent of normal precipitation maps. Additional rainfall of 2 to 3 inches fell in this area after the 12Z cutoff for this drought monitoring period, therefore it was not taken into consideration for this weeks depiction. This is certainly an area that will most likely see further improvements next period. In Arkansas, reports of low lake levels in the north-central areas of the state prompted an expansion of D1H conditions into climate divisions 2 and 5. Greers Ferry Lake is currently reporting 75 percent capacity.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Southwest, and California">
   <p>The majority of the West received between 1 and 2 inches of rain this period. Most of the precipitation occurred outside of the drought areas, with the exception of the lingering abnormally dry conditions in the San Joaquin Valley of California. This D0 (abnormally dry) was removed based on the precipitation that fell this period, improvements in CPCs soil moisture anomaly map and several timeframes of the High Plains Regional Climate Centers (HPRCC) percent of normal maps showing the area wet. In Arizona, a fire in Cochise County burned 340 acres as of the end of this drought monitoring period. Low temperatures over the past month have kept evapotranspiration rates low which has helped keep the drought conditions status quo for Arizona; this is an area to watch closely for deterioration over the next coming weeks if conditions continue to be dry. In Colorado, the abnormally dry (D0AH) conditions in the southwestern corner of the state were expanded to cover the San Miguel, Dolores, Animas and San Juan river basin. Moderate drought (D1AH) was expanded westward to include the Upper Rio Grande river basin and the far southeastern corner of Utah based on the HPRCCs 60- and 90-day percent of normal maps and the Climate Prediction Centers (CPC) soil moisture anomaly map. Also, SNOTEL reports in this area have been 50-60 percent of normal and recent snowfall totals have been low. Cortez, Colorado has only received 0.93 inch this month and Durango 1.45 inches. This area is forecasted to receive snowfall over the next drought monitoring period, so it may be an area to watch for improving conditions. Further west in Utah, conditions improved in the D0A area west of Lake Powell which prompted the retreat of D0 southward, leaving the area free of dry conditions. SNOTEL reports Midway Valley is 97 percent of average, Webster Flat 111 percent, Kolob 82 percent and Castle Valley 104 percent average.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Liz Love-Brotak</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
