<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100107</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (January 7-12, 2010), the weather will remain very cold over much of the country with readings falling 10-20 degrees below normal from the Rockies east to the Atlantic. Parts of the West including Arizona, Nevada, California, western Oregon and north-central Montana can expect to escape the chill and see above-normal temperatures. The best bet for precipitation is found along the West Coast from northern California up to Washington. The upper Midwest and parts of the Ohio Valley and Gulf Coast may see moderate totals as well. Much of the West looks to be pretty dry over the next 5 days or so.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day forecast (January 12-16) is beginning to nicely reflect a traditional El Ni&#241;o pattern and calls for better odds of above-normal temperatures in southeast Alaska, the west coast (from California up to Washington) and the northern tier states from Washington east to the Great Lakes region. Cooler temperatures are likely along the Gulf Coast from Texas to Florida and up the east coast from the Carolinas to New England. As for precipitation during this time period, much of Alaska and northern California may see above-normal totals. The Rockies from Colorado up to central Montana are likely to see below-normal precipitation. The other area of dryness forecasted is in the Northeast. Two areas of possible above-normal precipitation are found in the Gulf Coast states along with the Carolinas and the Upper Midwest, including Minnesota and Wisconsin.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Another dry week was reported across many parts of Hawaii, which is seeing streamflows well below normal across many parts of the islands. Changes of note this week include a slight expansion of severe (D2) and extreme (D3) drought on the eastern and southern sides of the Big Island. Pasture conditions there are really beginning to feel the toll.</p>
   <p>After some slight expansion of the D0 last week in Alaska, the status quo holds this week even though it was another generally dry week, even in the coastal regions. The snow water equivalent values continue to fall, which could lead to further degradation if the dry pattern persists.</p>
   <p>Some good rains fell across the northern half of Puerto Rico last week. No changes to the D0 are warranted until the pattern continues and streamflow values rebound.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>The only moderate precipitation recorded in this region fell across the western Upper Peninsula of Michigan, which was outside (for the most part) of the drought region depicted in northern Wisconsin. Consequently, the drought depiction remains as is this week across both Minnesota and Wisconsin.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Cold and dry was the story across most of the Plains from North Dakota to Texas and most points in between. The only change to the map this week is found in a slight improvement in extreme northwest North Dakota, where the favorable recent storm trend has led to the removal of lingering D0 there and in eastern Montana. Little precipitation was found across southern and western Texas, leaving the map unchanged this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>It was a pretty quiet week for the Southeast. The only abnormally dry (D0) area found along the east-central coast of Florida was reduced a bit on the northern edge, where 2-3 inches of rain fell last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The most active weather patterns are being seen across the Pacific Northwest and into western Idaho.  This has been welcomed given the extremely dry month of December (most regions in the Pacific NW were generally less than 50% of normal in the precipitation department). Even in the coastal areas where the precipitation has been the heaviest (2-5 inches), this hasn’t led to surpluses on the Water Year (since October 1). In fact, many of these inland areas are still at D0 or D1 (moderate drought) in southwestern Oregon from Medford over to the Klamath Falls region and along the coastal reaches of northwestern California. The heavier precipitation (3-5 inches) that fell in northern California in and around the Shasta-Trinity Forest region has led to a slight reduction in the northwestern area of severe drought (D2) that still remains there. Generally speaking, low streamflow levels and high snowline elevations are still a concern on the water supply side of things.</p>
   <p>To the east, an expansion of D0 is noted in western Wyoming, extreme northeastern Utah, eastern/southeastern Idaho and western/southwestern Montana. Many of the basins’ snow water equivalent (SWE) totals for this time of year are running at 60-75% of normal, according to USDA-NRCS. An expansion of D1 is also found this week in southwestern Montana, northeastern Idaho and northwestern Wyoming in the Yellowstone region. In addition, a new area of D1 has emerged to the north in the Bitterroot Range along the Montana and Idaho borders. Southern Montana saw D0 connect with the areas to both the east and west. Water year totals have been more generous in extreme eastern Montana along the North Dakota border, leading to a reduction of D0 there.</p>
   <p>The Southwest remains unchanged this week after another dry week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
