<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20011101</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) a mild Pacific cold front will bring only light and spotty showers and snows to the Pacific NW and perhaps parts of Idaho, Montana and Wyoming over the next few days; 2) elsewhere, above-normal temperatures and very little rainfall are expected over current drought areas in the next 5 days ending November 5 as high pressure dominates the weather picture; 3) high pressure continues to hold its grip over much of the country further out as the models continue to show better odds of above-normal temperatures (the exception being that coastal areas along the Atlantic Seaboard may see below-normal temperatures) and below-normal precipitation over just about the entire country during the first two weeks of November; only extreme northwest Washington can expect a better chance of above-normal precipitation.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Although many windward areas of Hawaii saw very good rains last week, very little trickled over into the drought-affected leeward parts. In fact, drought impacts are continuing to be felt, with the latest concerns centered on fire risk over many parts of the islands. D2 (A, F) has now been depicted in western Oahu.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic area">
   <p>Unseasonably warm and dry weather continued over most of the region as high pressure settled in. Streamflow and topsoil moisture readings continue to worsen in the area as well. Many streams along the Atlantic Seaboard are reporting near-record or record low flows on a daily basis. Topsoil moisture shortage (short/very short) percentages are well above 75%. As a result, D1 (moderate drought) continues to push north and east out of North Carolina and into Virginia, parts of Maryland, Delaware, New Jersey and southeastern Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>The widespread nature of this dryness has also led to a heightened concern about fire outbreaks in the coming weeks. Further north, parts of Maine remain very dry as year-to-date precipitation totals are rivaling all-time lows. As a very dry October ends, the D2 (severe) drought has strengthened its hold in Maine and D1 (moderate) drought has pushed south into Massachusetts. On a positive note, continued rainfall in the Ohio River Valley led to a reduction in the D0 W (abnormally dry) and D1 W (moderate) areas in northeastern Ohio and northwestern Pennsylvania.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Little, if any, precipitation fell across the entire region last week. In addition, warm and windy weather was the norm. While cooler weather returned to the northern Plains states, no real beneficial rains accompanied the cooler temperatures. Drier weather over the past 90 days has led to an expansion of D0 (abnormally dry) in Minnesota from Duluth in the northeast down into the southwestern corner of the state and into northwest Iowa.</p>
   <p>The picture in the southern Plains continues to worsen. Rainfall deficits of 6 to 8 inches (50% of normal, or worse) in parts of western and north central Oklahoma have accrued during the June 1-to-date period. Not unexpectedly, then, D1 (moderate drought) has now moved north and east into the Oklahoma Panhandle and over into the Tulsa area as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Once again, all but southern Florida was treated to another warm and dry week. Parts of Georgia and the Carolinas have served as the epicenter for the drought that has now begun to migrate up and down the Atlantic coast. Streamflow readings are low across the entire region, including the Florida Panhandle, as residual dryness left over from long-term drought has turned worse thus far in October with readings of 25-50% of normal rainfall at best. Subsequently, all drought conditions (D0, D1 and D2) continue to expand in these areas, with the most notable change occurring in North Carolina where D1 (moderate) has pushed east to the coast and north into the Mid-Atlantic states.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>In a pattern emulating that of last week, much of the West saw another quiet week weatherwise. Warmer temperatures and drier conditions dominated all but the Pacific NW and the Idaho Panhandle. Although parts of Washington, Oregon and Idaho have been in a more active pattern, the overall picture remains rather static as October comes to a close. The early short-term relief hasnt led to a change in the drought depiction across the West....yet.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
