<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020321</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecast conditions that may affect areas of dryness and drought from March 21-25 include: 1) The storm system moving across the South is forecast to weaken and provide the Southeast with only scattered showers, ending on Thursday; 2) Some significant snowfall is possible across eastern Maine into Friday, while lighter precipitation is likely across interior New England; 3) Light snow, which accompanied the recent return of frigid conditions to the northern Plains and upper Midwest, is ending and will be followed by a few days of cold, dry weather. Rain and snow may return to parts of the Midwest, including Iowa, by March 23 and 24; 4) Farther south, little or no precipitation is expected on the southern High Plains; 5) Cool, unsettled weather is forecast to further boost high-elevation snow packs in northern California, the Northwest, the northern Rockies, and the northern Intermountain West. Meanwhile, warm, unfavorably dry weather will persist in southern California and the Southwest. The NWS 6-10 day outlook for March 26-30 calls for another significant storm system to take shape across the nations mid-section. Above-normal precipitation and temperatures are forecast across the eastern half of the U.S., excluding the southern Atlantic Coastal region, where near-normal precipitation is expected. Meanwhile, mild, dry weather is forecast across the northern High Plains. In the West, near-normal precipitation and temperatures are expected in most areas, although some heavier snow may blanket the southern Rockies.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Locally heavy showers fell across the Hawaiian islands as a cold front swept across the state last weekend. Twenty-four hour rainfall totals reached 5.24 inches (on March 16-17) in Kokee, Kauai, and 10.20 inches (on March 17-18) in Honokaa, on the Big Island. However, an area of moderate hydrological drought, D1(W), persisted across western Molokai. Meanwhile, locally heavy rain (as much as 2 to 6 inches) fell across Puerto Ricos central highlands, but only light showers were observed across the abnormally dry (D0) southern coastal region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Torrential rainfall swept across southern portions of the Ohio Valley and into the southern Appalachians from March 15-17, nosing into the Eastern drought area and causing widespread flooding. The heavy rain fell atop lighter amounts that had dampened the region from March 11-12. Weekly rainfall topped 2 inches from Tennessee and southern Kentucky to southwestern Virginia and western North Carolina, peaking locally at 8 inches or higher in eastern Tennessee and adjacent areas of other states. Most categorical reductions of dryness and drought (D0 to D3) were by one category in the affected area, although some of the areas hardest hit by flooding, such as southeastern Kentucky, were granted a two-category improvement (from moderate drought to no dryness). Rainfall was heavy enough in western portions of the Eastern drought areas to eliminate wildfire and agricultural concerns, leaving these areas with primarily hydrological drought issues.</p>
   <p>Farther south, very warm, dry weather overspread the southern Atlantic region, reducing topsoil moisture in the wake of earlier rainfall. Columbus, Georgia, noted consecutive daily-record high temperatures (85 and 88 degrees F) on March 16 and 17. The Keetch-Byram Drought Index indicated an increased risk of wildfire activity across central Florida, while many citrus growers were required to irrigate heavily during the bloom season. As a result, abnormally dry (D0) conditions were expanded farther south into Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>A narrow band of heavy snow (locally 1 to 2 feet) fell across eastern Wyoming, northern Nebraska, southern Minnesota, and portions of South Dakota from March 13-15, helping to bring a slight reduction of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) across the High Plains and reducing the scope of abnormal dryness (D0) in the upper Midwest. In contrast dry weather persisted in central and western Iowa, allowing abnormally dry (D0) conditions to expand slightly.</p>
   <p>Farther south, hot, windy weather preceded the arrival of a strong storm system. On March 11, dry soils and gusty winds brought blowing dust to the southern High Plains, lowering visibilities to as little as 2 miles in Midland, Texas. By March 13, temperatures soared above 90 degrees F in Texas locations such as Wink (95 degrees F) and Childress (92 degrees F). However, rain developed across the southern Plains on March 18 and 19, dampening topsoils and aiding drought-stressed winter wheat. There was little overall change in the drought picture, which will be re-evaluated after the storm departs the region, although some abnormal dryness (D0) was eliminated across north-central Texas and eastern Oklahoma by rainfall that totaled at least 1 to 3 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Early in the period, a snow storm brought modest reductions in varying degrees of dryness/drought (D0 to D3) across the northern Rockies and northern Intermountain West. Farther west, precipitation continued to chip away at abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) from southeastern Oregon to the northern Great Basin. At the same time, concerns about dryness increased across the foothills of the Blue Mountains of northeastern Oregon and the adjacent Columbia Basin, requiring the introduction of an abnormally dry (D0) designation. Since October 1, 2001, precipitation in Pendleton, Oregon, has totaled 5.29 inches (70 percent of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
