<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20011227</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (December 26 - 31) in the East, 0.25 to locally 1.0 inch of precipitation is expected in western Pennsylvania, western and northern New York, eastern New England, and the Florida peninsula. Meanwhile, little or none is anticipated in southeast Pennsylvania, southwest New Jersey, central Maryland, Delaware, central and eastern Virginia, interior North Carolina, the western half of South Carolina, and central and northern Georgia.</p>
   <p>Farther west, little or no precipitation is forecast for the Plains, though some measurable amounts may fall on northern Texas, southern and western Oklahoma, northern New Mexico, Colorado, northern and southeast Wyoming, and western North Dakota.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, moderate to heavy precipitation (1 to 3 inches) is expected in central and northern California, and in western sections of Washington and Oregon. Light to moderate totals should fall on most other D0 to D3 areas in the West, with only scattered pockets forecast to receive less than 0.25 inch.</p>
   <p>For the first five days of 2002, the odds favor surplus precipitation in Florida, southern Georgia, eastern South Carolina, a broad area from the southwest Plains northward through eastern Wyoming, northern and central California, and southwest Oregon. In contrast, sub-normal precipitation is likely across the interior West, the central and southern Appalachians, the western Carolinas, the mid-Atlantic, the southeast half of Pennsylvania, and the lower Northeast. No tilt of the odds could be discerned in other areas.</p>
   <p>Throughout the 10-day period extending from December 26 through January 5, near- to above-normal temperatures are expected from the Rockies westward while colder than normal conditions become entrenched from the Great Lakes, central Great Plains, and southern High Plains eastward to the Atlantic coast, particularly in areas to the south and east of the Ohio and lower Mississippi Rivers.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Generally seasonable rainfall kept D0 to D2 areas intact across southern Puerto Rico and central and eastern Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation fell on most areas from the Appalachians eastward, keeping dryness and drought relatively unchanged. A few locales with borderline conditions and 0.3 to 1.0 inch of precipitation improved, including Rhode Island and southeast Massachusetts (D2W to D1W), central Maryland and adjacent areas (D2W to D1W), areas to the lee of Lakes Erie and Ontario (D0W ended), and the far southern Appalachians (D2W to D1W). In contrast, much of the southern Atlantic coastal plain received little or no precipitation during the week, causing conditions in some areas to deteriorate. D3 expanded to cover much of central and eastern South Carolina, D2 overspread the coastal Carolinas, and D0 pushed into northeast Florida and southeast Alabama.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Little or no precipitation fell last week, allowing dryness and drought in most areas to persist as depicted on December 18. However, objective indicators and growing precipitation shortfalls allowed D2 to expand into much of northwest Oklahoma east of the Panhandle while D0 and D1 conditions expanded eastward and northward in southern and eastern Kansas, northeast Oklahoma, and interior northern Missouri. The 90-day period ending early December 25 brought less than 25% of normal precipitation to much of the southwest quarter of Kansas and northwestern Oklahoma east of the Panhandle.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Abundant precipitation again fell on the northern half of California and much of western Oregon, but other areas experienced a return to near-normal and locally below-normal precipitation. Between 4 and 8 inches fell on the central and northern Sierra Nevada and from the Cascades westward in California, while 2 to 4 inches were recorded in most other parts of northern California, and the westernmost tiers of Washington and Oregon. Farther east, most sites reported 0.2 to locally 1.0 inch of precipitation, with more in some orographically-favored places. The weeks precipitation led us to continue depicting slow regional recovery from the long-term western drought. Even though near- to well above-normal precipitation fell on most areas during the last 90 days, broad-scale totals in the D1 to D3 areas has not yet been sufficient to ensure substantial reservoir and groundwater recharge when the snowpack melts in spring. Still, the western edges of D1 to D3 conditions were pulled westward in northern California, central and western Oregon, and northeast Nevada. Also, the extent of D3 was reduced in central Idaho and in areas near the Idaho/Wyoming border, where precipitation since the start of the water year (October 1, 2001) had already exceeded half of the total that fell during the entire October 2000 - April 2001 period.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
