<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030220</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>For areas experiencing drought or dryness, the 5-day outlook (Feb.19-24) shows that two areas stand to benefit from precipitation. The first is the Pacific NW, where areas between the coast and the Cascade range can expect 1 to 2 inches. Over on the Eastern Seaboard, 2 to 3 inches or more of precipitation are expected by the end of the weekend from Georgia up into New England. The nation's mid-section should see cooler than normal temperatures while the Southeast and Northeast can expect warmer temperatures.</p>
   <p>The 6- to10-day forecast (Feb. 25-March 1) shows a good chance for below-normal temperatures across all of the West. The rest of the country is expected to see normal temperatures, except for southern Georgia and Florida, which should see above-normal readings. As for precipitation over this period, above-normal amounts are expected from Arizona and New Mexico and along the Gulf Coast and up into Virginia. Below-normal precipitation is expected to continue from the Dakotas over to Michigan and its Upper Peninsula.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>There are no changes to the abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) conditions depicted on this week's map.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>After a month of good rains, a quieter week prevailed last week, leading to no changes to the abnormally dry (D0) conditions depicted there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>The major story in the East this past week was the President's Day Blizzard that affected much of the East Coast. Snowfall totals across the region included near 40 inches in western Pennsylvania, 49 inches in western Maryland, 24 inches at Washington's Dulles Airport, 20 inches in New York City, and a record for both Baltimore (28.2") and Boston (27.5"). However, the drought area in northern Maine largely missed out on the big storm. Meanwhile, across Georgia and the Carolinas, some locations did receive more than 1 inch of precipitation, but long-term groundwater deficits remain. Heavier amounts of rainfall did occur in southeastern North Carolina, and D0 was removed from this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>The blizzard that struck the East Coast on President's Day had its origins in the central part of the country earlier in the weekend. Heavier snowfalls (14 inches in Des Moines, IA) and rains helped improve the drought and dryness conditions across parts of eastern Kansas, eastern Nebraska, eastern South Dakota, Missouri, Iowa and central Illinois. The western Great Lakes were generally dry during the week, and the moderate drought (D1) has now expanded across more of northern Minnesota as a result.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Better late than never. El Nio showed it still has a pulse as southern California and parts of the Southwest went from parched to seeing a plethora of rain early last week when flooding and mud slides garnered much of the attention instead of the ongoing drought. The region benefitted greatly from its first real rainfall of 2003 this past week as a slow-moving storm system dumped upwards of 7-10 inches of rain in the mountains of southern California and 3 or more inches along the coast from San Diego up to Los Angeles and points northward. The moisture also pushed eastward into the Desert Southwest bringing heavy rains to Arizona and extreme southern Nevada. Areas around Phoenix, Flagstaff and Las Vegas reported over 2 inches of rain. Even though long-term deficits were relieved somewhat, one storm won't be nearly enough to erase the drought or bring soil moisture, streamflow and reservoir levels all the way back to normal. Lake Powell on the Arizona/Utah border is still at its lowest level in 30 years. In addition, most of the precipitation this week was in the form of rain, which did little to help out the snowpack situation in the upper elevations. As such, the only improvement has been to pull the lines eastward in southern California, which has tightened the gradient from abnormally dry (D0) in southern California to extreme drought (D3) in Arizona and southern Nevada.</p>
   <p>The Pacific Northwest wasn't quite as fortunate, but some areas along the coastal corridor did see 1-3 inches of precipitation during the week. The Great Basin and Rockies saw a relatively dry week, as only scattered snows fell. The depiction in these parts remains unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
