<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040624</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>For the next 5 days (June 24-28), a series of cold fronts will cross the Plains and Midwest, maintaining below-normal temperatures in those areas. Although only scattered showers and thunderstorms are expected across the Midwest and the northern half of the Plains, the fronts will interact with abundant tropical moisture farther south, resulting in a continuation of locally heavy rainfall across the southern half of the Plains and in the Southeast. A few locations in western Oklahoma and the Texas panhandle may receive more than 4 inches of additional rainfall. Occasional showers are expected across the Rockies, Intermountain West, and Northwest, but dry weather will persist in California and the Great Basin. Gradually cooler weather will accompany an increasing chance of shower activity in the Northwest. The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for June 29 - July 3 calls for the likelihood of additional rainfall across the Southeast and central and southern portions of the Rockies and High Plains. Near- to below-normal temperatures will persist in many areas east of the Rockies, except in the Southeast, while hot weather may return to the Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Unusually warm weather prevailed across southeastern Alaska from June 18-21, maintaining dryness (D0) and setting numerous daily-record highs and at least one all-time record. On June 18, Annette Island achieved 89 degrees F, tying its monthly record established on June 6, 1958, and June 9, 1969, followed the next day by an all-time record high of 93 degrees F. Annette Islands former all-time record was 90 degrees F, set on August 8, 1960. Elsewhere in southeastern Alaska, Juneaus June 1-21 rainfall totaled just 1.15 inches (less than 50 percent of normal), following its driest May on record.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Locally heavy showers pounded portions of the central and southern Plains daily during the monitoring period (June 15-21). Seven-day totals ranged from 2 to 4 inches, with locally higher amounts, across much of Kansas, Oklahoma, southeastern Colorado, and the Texas High Plains, resulting in large-scale drought reductions as much as one category. Although the rain disrupted the Plains winter wheat harvest, moisture was welcomed for pastures and dryland summer crops. Meanwhile, heavy rain (2 inches or more) erased moderate drought (D1) from eastern Oklahoma and western Arkansas.</p>
   <p>Farther north, rainfall of 1 to 2 inches in southern portions of the exceptional drought (D4) area resulted in only very slight trimming of this relatively new feature, which stretched from southeastern Montana to western Nebraska. Despite cool weather (June 15-21 temperatures ranging from 6 to 14 degrees F below normal), rain, and topsoil moisture improvements, severe to exceptional long-term drought (D2 to D4) remained entrenched across the majority of the northern and central High Plains. For the 356-day period from July 1, 2003 - June 20, 2004, precipitation totaled 5.44 inches (43 percent of normal) in Miles City, Montana, 6.87 inches (45 percent) in Denver, Colorado, and 7.24 inches (47 percent) in Scottsbluff, Nebraska. In addition, the June 20 crop condition report from USDA indicated that at least 40 percent of both winter wheat and ranges/pastures were still rated very poor to poor in Nebraska, Wyoming, Kansas, and Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Coverage of seasonal showers remained patchy across southern Florida, leaving a sliver of abnormal dryness (D0) intact. June 1-21 rainfall was 31 percent of normal in Naples and Fort Lauderdale, totaling 1.73 and 2.21 inches, respectively. The average surface elevation of Lake Okeechobee rebounded slightly to 12.72 feet on June 21, up nearly 2 inches from its seasonal minimum elevation in early June.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere in the Southeast, rain continued to dent abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2), despite June 15-21 temperatures averaging as much as 5 degrees F above normal. There were still pockets of concern, represented in part by those stations still reporting below-normal monthly rainfall through June 21. Among them: Charleston, South Carolina (2.26 inches, or 56 percent of normal), Athens, Georgia (2.00 inches, or 73 percent), and Macon, Georgia (2.28 inches, or 95 percent). In contrast, daily-record totals were observed on June 21 in locations such as Augusta, Georgia (1.82 inches), and Columbia, South Carolina (2.98 inches). Those daily totals boosted month-to-date amounts to 7.05 inches (241 percent of normal) in Augusta and 6.98 inches (207 percent) in Columbia.</p>
   <p>On June 20, pastures were rated 23 percent very poor to poor in South Carolina and 18 percent very poor to poor in Georgia, according to USDA. Based on June 22 information from USGS, the percentage of river gauges reporting flows in the lowest 25 percent of values for the date included 34 percent in South Carolina and 39 percent in Georgia, down from 49 percent a week earlier in both states.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>There was some expansion of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) across parts of New Mexico, where significant rain last fell in early April. According to USDA on June 20, New Mexico ranges/pastures were rated 60 percent very poor to poor. New Mexicos topsoil moisture was reported as 78 percent very short to short, worse than the drought-influenced 5-year average of 71 percent. In Albuquerque, New Mexico, June 21 marked the 72nd consecutive day without measurable rain. The streak, Albuquerques fifth-longest on record and longest since March-May 1996, ended with a 0.01-inch rainfall on June 22. Elsewhere, scattered rain and snow showers across the Intermountain West and the central Rockies improved topsoil moisture but resulted in little or no change in the overall Western drought depiction.</p>
   <p>Agricultural and forestry interests continued to monitor the drought, in part due to range conditions and the threat of wildfire activity. In addition to New Mexicos number, the percentage of ranges/pastures rated very poor to poor included 75 percent in California, 61 percent in Wyoming, 49 percent in Colorado, and 45 percent in Arizona. According to the National Interagency Fire Center, several large wildfires were active across the West. On June 22, the Peppin Fire near Capitan, New Mexico, was nearly contained but had charred nearly 65,000 acres of vegetation. Other fires larger than 5,000 acres were reported near Mesquite, Nevada, and Alpine, Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
