<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030508</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) the heavy rains that drenched much of the Midwest May 4-5 moved across Ohio, Pennsylvania, and New York May 6; 2) additional rains fell in the Midwest on May 7; 3) a series of storm systems, and more potential several weather, will move across the central United States May 9-11 and May 13-14 and could bring additional heavy rains to areas that saw heavy rains this past week; 4) much of southern Texas and New Mexico will remain drier and warmer than normal through the 10-day period ending May 17; 5) much of the interior West, however, will remain unsettled and cooler than normal through May 17, potentially providing additional relief in the long-term hydrological drought conditions across the northern Rockies; 6) Hawaii will likely see a return of moderate trades May 9-11 and some windward-terrain focused rainfall; and 7) cooler air will move into Alaska and remain through May 17, ending a long period of warmer than normal conditions, with precipitation possible for the southern half of the state May 10-14.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Temperatures remained above normal across most of Alaska for another week, along with drier-than-normal precipitation. No changes were made to the abnormally dry (D0) area in the southwest part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Following a relatively dry week across the state, no changes have been made to the drought categories.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>In Maine, shorter-term precipitation deficits since January 1 resulted in an expansion of D0 across the southern third of the state. Both Bangor and Portland are at about 75% of normal for their year-to-date precipitation. Meanwhile, improvements in the long-term hydrological resources such as reservoirs and groundwater allowed D0 to be removed from Vermont.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes">
   <p>Heavy rains fell across large portions of the Midwest during the past week, significantly improving conditions in most areas experiencing drought or dryness. The heaviest rains, estimated at more than 4 inches by radar, fell across east-central Nebraska, central Iowa, northern Illinois, southern Wisconsin, southern Michigan, and northern Indiana. An extremely rare two-category improvement in the drought classifications was made in several of these locations. Des Moines, IA, for example, had more rain during the last three days of April (3.55 inches) than for the entire November to March period (3.37 inches). Improvements also occurred in parts of North Dakota, South Dakota, much of Nebraska, Missouri, and Ohio. The only locations not to see any drought-related improvements during the week were most of Minnesota, northern Lower Michigan, eastern Ohio, western New York, and western Pennsylvania.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Above-normal temperatures and generally little rain across New Mexico, Texas, and Oklahoma during the week helped deteriorate drought conditions in some areas. As a result, moderate drought (D1) expanded across eastern New Mexico, western Texas, north-central Texas, and southeast Oklahoma. The abnormal dryness (D0) category was also added across southern Louisiana, southern Mississippi, and extreme southern Alabama. Mobile, AL, has had 14.07 inches of precipitation since January 1, a departure from normal of 10.16 inches (58%).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Above-normal precipitation during April helped improve the long-term drought conditions across parts of Idaho, Montana, and Wyoming. Improvements to the drought levels were made in the Payette and Boise basins north of Boise in west-central Idaho. However, in seven counties in the eastern half of Idaho, Governor Kempthorne declared formal drought emergencies as winter snowpacks will not provide enough water for summer requirements. Areas of Montana and northern Wyoming also saw improvements in the drought categories for the week. Wyoming officials are encouraged by the better-than-expected recovery of several reservoirs along the North Platte River in the southeastern part of the state. All other drought areas in the West remained unchanged for the week, except for an improvement to D0 in the Bluewater Basin south of Grants, NM.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
