<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020620</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecasted weather features that may affect areas of dryness and drought the next 5 days (June 20-24) include: 1) A stalled front off the southern Atlantic Coast should produce widespread showers and thundershowers from Florida northeastward to the mid-Atlantic Coast, with locally heavy rains expected in the eastern Carolinas. 2) Widely-scattered, afternoon thundershowers are possible across most of the Gulf Coast and Southeast with ample moisture available from the Gulf of Mexico, with seasonable or slightly subnormal temperatures. 3) A slow-moving cold front draped across the north-central U.S. may generate scattered thunderstorms in the northern and central Plains, upper Midwest, western Corn Belt, and Great Lakes region, and briefly bring cooler readings to the northern and central Plains. 4) Dry and warm weather is predicted for the Southwest and Far West, with increasing temperatures forecasted for the Rockies and Plains by the weekend.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6-10 day (June 25-29) outlook calls for above-normal precipitation in the southern quarter of the Nation, and drier-than-normal conditions in the Pacific Northwest, and northern sections of the Rockies, Plains, and New England. Temperatures should average above-normal in the Pacific Northwest, Great Basin, northern Rockies and Plains, upper Midwest, and Great Lakes region, with subnormal readings expected in the southern two-thirds of Florida, southern Rockies and Plains, and Rio Grande Valley.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Most Alaskan locations experienced a relatively dry 7-days compared to the past weeks unsettled weather, with totals generally less than 0.25 inches even along the normally wetter south and southeast coasts. Temperatures were above-normal in the west, with departures between +4 and +8F, but seasonable in southern and central sections, keeping wildfires to a minimum. Toward the end of this period, however, dry and warm weather helped to rekindle wildfire activity in central Alaska, with 33,000 acres charred just on June 18. Additionally, long-term (30, 90, and 270-day) deficits still remained in southern and southeastern Alaska, with precipitation 50-75% of normal, thus maintaining abnormal (meteorological) dryness. According to USDA/NASS, most areas could use some rain, with the Tanana and Matanuska Valleys reporting 60% and 40% short topsoil moisture, respectively, while the Kenai Peninsula had adequate soil moisture.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, light showers (~0.25 inches) at Kamalo and Kalaupapa maintained the D0(W) on western Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Sharply contrasting conditions delineated the region. Cool and wet conditions dampened New England and the mid-Atlantic, while little or no rainfall and above-normal temperatures were common from southern Virginia southward into northern Florida. Meanwhile, heavy tropical showers (2 to 8 inches) drenched southern and central Florida, alleviating abnormal dryness. Hydrological (W) drought continued its slow retreat from northern areas as 2 to 4 inches of rain fell across Vermont, New Hampshire, and southern Maine, and 2 to 3 inches were measured at many locations in eastern Pennsylvania, New Jersey, western Maryland, and northern Virginia. Rapid recharge of the New York City Delaware River basin continued, with June 18 storage now at 92% of normal, compared to about 1/3 of normal back in late December and January. Subsoil moisture shortages (wells), however, still lingered in some parts of the mid-Atlantic and northern New England. Farther south, another warm and mostly dry week aggravated short and long-term drought, especially in the Carolina and southern Virginia Piedmont. After near-record August 2001-March 2002 dryness, this area has only received 50-75% of normal rainfall since April 1. In addition, average June 11-17 stream flows were at record low levels at 38%, 36%, and 33% of reporting USGS sites in NC, VA, and SC, respectively. According to USDA/NASS, 83% (SC), 72% (NC), 68% (GA), and 50% (VA) of the topsoil moisture was short to very short, and crop and pasture conditions further declined. Accordingly, exceptional drought (D4) was added to the North Carolina Piedmont.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>Widely-scattered showers dropped 1-2 inches of rain along parts of the immediate Gulf Coast, but most inland locations measured between 0.1-0.5 inches. 30-day deficits between 2 and 4 inches in western Louisiana expanded D1 there. Cool weather (temperatures 2F to 5F below normal), however, somewhat offset the lack of significant precipitation and lowered evaporation rates, maintaining dryness and drought elsewhere.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Widespread, occasionally severe thunderstorms erupted in the central and southern Great Plains, dumping 2 to 4 inches of rain on central and eastern Kansas, most of Oklahoma, and central and extreme northern Texas. Accordingly, a one-category improvement was made in central Kansas, northwestern Oklahoma, and central Texas. Surrounding areas of the central and southern High Plains also received some welcome rain, but amounts were generally between 0.5-1.5 inches, maintaining conditions. An exception was in Texas Big Bend area where 0.5 to 1.0 inches bumped totals since April 1 to between 2 and 4 inches (D3 to D2), while just to the north, 77-day amounts were much lower, 0.1-0.5 inches (D2 to D3).</p>
   <p>In sharp contrast, cool and mostly dry weather prevailed in the northern Plains and upper Midwest, with temperatures averaging 2 to 5F below normal. Unfortunately, southern North Dakota, central Minnesota, and most of South Dakota and Nebraska have missed beneficial, occasionally flooding, June rains that have soaked parts of the northern and central Plains and upper Midwest. Thirty-day deficits of 2 to 4 inches (&lt;50% of normal) were found in most of South Dakota, northwestern Nebraska, and central Minnesota, and 90-day shortages of 4 to 7 inches accumulated in western Nebraska and central South Dakota. With windy and warmer weather returning late in the period, crop and pasture conditions continued to decline. South Dakota has been particularly hard hit, with 65%, 56%, 54%, 54%, and 46% of the winter wheat, pastures, spring wheat, sorghum, and oats in poor or very poor condition (from USDA/NASS). As a result, D0 expanded into central Minnesota and the eastern Dakota, D1 across central South Dakota and northern Nebraska, D2 in southwestern Nebraska and north-central South Dakota, and D3 in extreme southwestern Nebraska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Tranquil conditions returned to the northern Rockies after last weeks deluge, especially in northern Montana, as short-term conditions dramatically improved, but long-term deficits remained. With the recent and abundant precipitation, Montanas winter wheat crop has improved from 62% very poor or poor (May 26) to 46% as of June 16. In contrast, lingering long-term dryness and recent spotty precipitation in eastern Oregon has kept 55% of the winter wheat and 31% of the pastures in very poor or poor condition, expanding the D0 and D1(A,W) area. Farther south, no precipitation, low humidities, high winds, and above-normal temperatures, particularly in the Southwest, provided ideal conditions for wildfires. As of June 18, 16 large, active wildfires affecting over 270,000 acres, were blazing in the West, including Colorados 103,000 acre Hayman fire. With the near-record dry rainy season (November 2001-April 2002) in the Southwest, plus recent warmth and increasing wildfire potential, D1, D2, and D3(A,F) edged westward into southern California.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
