<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040122</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Conditions expected over the next 2 weeks that could influence ongoing dry areas include: 1) rain and snow over Arizona should bring 0.5 to 1.0 inches to many parts of the state from January 21 to 25 as part of a continuing trend toward above-normal precipitation for the Southwest over the next 2 weeks; 2) a snowstorm crossing the central states during January 25-27 will contribute to above-normal precipitation for the Rockies and the Plains during the 6-10 day forecast period of January 27-31; 3) a continuing active storm track will lead to above-normal precipitation for much of the country during week 2 (January 29 - February 4), with abnormally cold air resulting in widespread snow over the Midwest, Rockies, High Plains, and Southwest; 4) a number of storms will lead to above-normal rain over the Southeast for the next 2 weeks.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Variable rainfall amounts over Hawaii resulted in no change to the lingering areas of D0 long-term dryness. Interior southeastern Alaska stayed dry and cold, resulting in continued D0 dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Rainfall has totaled less than 25 percent of normal during the past 30 days from southern North Carolina into southern Georgia, and many streams have been running below normal. Previous ample rains have precluded any significant impacts from the short-term dryness, but this area is being monitored for possible future D0 development.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Tropical moisture overspread the southern Plains during January 14-17, resulting in precipitation amounts ranging from 1.5 to 2.5 inches across Texas, Oklahoma, and southern Kansas, with isolated amounts exceeding 4 inches in Texas. The moisture generally improved drought status by one category across Texas. The abundant rain significantly boosted moisture for winter crops, although much more rain is needed to bring streams, wells, and reservoirs up to normal levels. Overall drought categories remained at D3 levels over west-central Texas and parts of the central High Plains. Persistent below-normal rain and snow led to some expansion northward of the D3 area in western Nebraska. Rainfall amounts of 0.3 to 0.8 inches on January 16-17 allowed D1 drought to improve to D0 in central Iowa, while rain and snow amounts of 0.2 to 0.3 inches resulted in removal of D0 in the northern Illinois-southeastern Wisconsin area. Long-term dryness continued in southeastern Wisconsin, with Milwaukee more than 9 inches below normal since last June, but the lingering area of abnormal dryness was limited to a relatively small area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Some of the rain that hit Texas also fell in New Mexico and southern Arizona, but amounts were mostly under one-third of an inch, and not enough to change drought status. In fact, persistent lack of rain in southwestern Arizona led to expansion westward of the D1 area so that drought covered nearly the entire state. There was no change in drought levels for the rest of the West, as weekly rain and snow amounts over the interior West were light. The water content of the mountain snow pack generally remained above normal over the Intermountain region and near to slightly below normal in the Rockies.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
