<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080710</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Widespread moderate to heavy rains (up to 4 inches) are forecast during July 10 - 14 across most areas of dryness and drought east of the Mississippi River, in addition to much of Arizona, New Mexico, the Texas Panhandle, central and western Oklahoma, and northern Minnesota. Lesser amounts are forecast elsewhere, with little or no rain expected across most of Louisiana and Texas, the northern Plains, California, and the northwestern quarter of the contiguous 48 states. For the ensuing 5 days (July 15 - 19), the odds favor above-normal precipitation across Florida and adjacent areas of the Southeast, and across the northern Plains and the Upper Midwest. In contrast, below-normal rainfall is expected across the interior Northeast, the southern half of the High Plains (including central and western Texas), the Great Basin, the northern Intermountain West, and much of California.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Scattered rainfall totals of 0.5 to 2.0 inches were observed in parts of the Big Island and in northern Kauai, but dry weather prevailed across most of the island chain, keeping D0 to D2 conditions intact.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>On time scales ranging from 30 days to 6 months, a similar pattern of subnormal rainfall has prevailed across the southern and eastern portions of the island. In parts of southeastern Puerto Rico, a new area of moderate drought has been introduced where rainfall totals since the beginning of the year are only around half of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Southern Plains">
   <p>Heavy tropical rains of 5 to 10 inches doused far southern Texas, bringing dramatic drought improvement perhaps a bit too quickly to the region. Rainfall was lighter and more scattered farther north across south-central Texas, generally keeping D2 to D4 conditions intact though localized improvement was noted. Similarly, patches of moderate to locally heavy rains from central New Mexico northeastward into southwestern Nebraska were enough to improve dryness and drought in a few areas, specifically northeastern Colorado, northwestern Kansas, and parts of the Texas Panhandle, but were not enough to significantly alter the drought landscape relative to last week. Meanwhile, it was a dry week across most of southeastern New Mexico, central and northeastern Texas, and much of Oklahoma, where D0 to D2 conditions persisted or expanded slightly.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Light to moderate rains fell on much of the abnormally dry areas in the Northeast, keeping conditions essentially unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northern Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>Moderate rains reduced the extent of abnormal dryness in northern Minnesota, but dry conditions persisted or deteriorated in other parts of the north-central states. Abnormally light rainfall for the past few weeks has led to surface moisture shortages and the introduction of a new D0 area across central Minnesota and eastern South Dakota. Farther west, dryness and drought persisted or worsened in portions of southern and eastern Montana, central and western North Dakota, and northwestern South Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>A seasonably typical pattern of hit-and-miss shower and thunderstorm activity produced highly variable precipitation totals through the regions of dryness and drought in the Southeast. Conditions improved in areas where heavy rainfall (2 to 5 inches) was relatively widespread, specifically across southern Florida and the central and eastern sections of the Carolinas. Meanwhile, drought developed or intensified somewhat in parts of central and eastern Tennessee and southwestern Mississippi. In most of the region, however, conditions remained similar to last week, with exceptional drought continuing in portions of the western Carolinas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Moderate to heavy rains of 1 to locally 3 inches brought improvement to far southern Arizona, but dry weather left other areas of D0 to D2 unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
