<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20021212</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>A series of storms is expected to traverse the western states during the next 5 to 10 days, bringing substantial precipitation to much of the immediate West Coast and the central and northern sections of the Intermountain West and Rockies. December 11 - 15 should bring at least 0.5 inch of precipitation to areas from the western sections of Wyoming and Montana westward through all of Idaho and Washington, most of Oregon, central and northern California, and western Nevada. Potentially inundating amounts of 7 to 15 inches are forecast from west-central California and the northern Sierra Nevada northwestward through west-central Oregon. Farther east, the 5-day period should bring moderate or heavy precipitation (1 to 3 inches) to the D0(W) areas in the mid-Atlantic, but most other dry areas across the country should expect near- to somewhat below-normal precipitation. No measurable amounts are forecast in the western Great Plains, the central and southern High Plains, the southern Rockies, and the desert Southwest during December 11 - 15. For the ensuing 5 days (December 16 - 20), the odds favor above-normal precipitation from the northern Intermountain West, central High Plains, and southern Rockies westward to the Pacific coast. Surplus precipitation also appears likely from the central Great Lakes, central Great Plains, and eastern Texas eastward through the Southeast, Ohio Valley, Appalachians, and Atlantic Seaboard. The only currently-dry areas where the odds favor below-normal precipitation for the 6- to 10-day period are those in the northern reaches of the Rockies, Plains, and upper Mississippi Valley.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>In Hawaii, long-term moderate drought (D1) conditions still exist on western Molokai, causing some hydrological impacts. Meanwhile, D0 conditions were introduced across western portions of the Big Island where precipitation deficits have begun to affect agricultural and pasture conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>D0 conditions persisted following a week with light to locally moderate rainfall, and D1 conditions were introduced across south-central portions of the Island, where only 0.5 to 3.0 inches of rain fell during the last 8 weeks (about 5% to 35% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>A strong winter storm brought a swath of heavy precipitation (generally 1 to 2 inches) through the southern half of the Appalachians, northern Georgia, northwest South Carolina, most of North Carolina, and southern Virginia during December 3 - 6. This precipitation fell as freezing rain in parts of the Carolina Piedmont and Appalachian foothills, where damaging ice accumulations were reported. Farther north, moderate precipitation (0.5 to 1.0 inch) fell on the remainder of Virginia and most of Maryland, southern Pennsylvania, and New Jersey, primarily as snow. Six-month precipitation totals are near to slightly above normal across the D0(W) and D1(W) areas, but substantial longer-term precipitation deficits persist (24-month totals are between 1 and 2 feet below normal) and groundwater levels, though improving, remain below normal in many areas and near record lows at some locations. As a result, only limited improvement was introduced this week, including the elimination of some D0(W) across the mid-Atlantic, and the removal of D1(W) in parts of southern Virginia and northern North Carolina.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, only light precipitation, if any, was reported in central South Carolina, across most of Georgia between the mountains and the coast, and in central and northern Maine, leaving D0(W) and D1(W) conditions intact through these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>In the areas of dryness and drought, measurable precipitation was restricted to regions from central Missouri and southeastern Kansas southward through northwestern Arkansas and adjacent Oklahoma. Totals generally exceeded 1 inch across southernmost Missouri, northeastern Oklahoma, and northwestern Arkansas while 0.2 to 1.0 inch fell on adjacent areas north of this region. This precipitation was beneficial, but still left a large area near the Arkansas/Kansas/Missouri triple point 6 to 9 inches below normal since early September, so D0(A) and D0(A,W) to D2(A,W) conditions in this region remained intact.</p>
   <p>Farther north, the dry week resulted in D0(A,W) conditions expanding into southern Wisconsin, northernmost and east-central Illinois, eastern Iowa, and the central Dakotas. Also, D0(A) was introduced in northeastern Minnesota, where short-term dryness has led to an unseasonably low snowpack. Most other areas remained as they were the previous week, but some changes in the D1(A,W) to D3(A,W) areas in central and western South Dakota were introduced based on a re-assessment of longer-term precipitation patterns (as opposed to the effects of the dry week).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Moderate precipitation (0.5 to 1.0 inch) fell on coastal sections of Washington, Oregon, and California while light amounts (0.2 to 0.5 inch) were measured in other parts of these states from the Cascades westward. Only scattered totals below 0.5 inch were noted in other areas from the Rockies westward to the Pacific Coast, maintaining or slightly deteriorating dryness and drought across these regions. D0(W) was expanded to include the entire Pacific coasts of Oregon and California while Western Utah, northern Nevada, northeastern California, and south-central Oregon all declined from D1(W) to D2(W) this past week. Farther east, the D4(W) area in southwestern Wyoming expanded slightly. The only improvement introduced this week was in southeast New Mexico, where D0(W) conditions were eliminated. This region received moderate precipitation last week, and 6- to 12-month accumulated precipitation totals are now near normal.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
