<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20081211</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Across the country this week, above normal precipitation was limited to the Upper Midwest, the Northern Plains, and areas of lake effect precipitation in Michigan and New York.  Even though a weather system moved through the eastern half of the country this U.S. Drought Monitor (USDM) period, with the exception of small areas of Arkansas and Alabama, precipitation for the week was below normal.  Additional rainfall from a second system just began to impact the Southeast during this period (this storm's impact will be addressed largely on the Dec 16, 2008 USDM).  Temperatures were generally near to above normal west of the Mississippi River and near to below normal to the east, with the exception of northern New England.  The West and southern Plains continue to be dry.  Exceptional drought improved slightly through South Carolina and Georgia but expanded in south-central Texas.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>From December 11 - 15, 2008, normal to cooler than normal temperatures are expected for the north and north-central part of the country roughly from Michigan, down through Kansas, and to the West Coast, including southern California.  The area from New England, down to the Southeast, and across to the Southwest will likely experience normal to above normal temperatures.  Precipitation is expected across most of the country east of the Mississippi River with above normal totals in the mid-Atlantic and New England.  The West Coast, from central California up through Washington, is also expecting above normal precipitation.</p>
   <p>From December 16 - 20, 2008, the odds favor continued normal to below-normal temperatures across most of the western part of the country, including southern Alaska.  The area from the East Coast over to the Great Lakes and down to central Texas is likely to see above normal temperatures as is northern Alaska.   The odds favor near to above normal precipitation across the continental U.S. with the exceptions of the Southeast, Texas, the extreme Northwest, and most of southern Alaska, where below normal precipitation is expected.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Little rain fell across the Hawaiian Islands this U.S. Drought Monitor period.   Drought conditions remained unchanged.</p>
   <p>Across Alaska, precipitation was mixed with above normal in the southern islands and central part of the state, and near to below normal precipitation to the north and south.  Abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded across the Seward Peninsula where Nome is experiencing its eighth driest year on record.</p>
   <p>Notable rain fell in extreme northeast Puerto Rico with additional, lesser rains across the eastern and central parts of the island.  Areas of drought remained unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mid-Atlantic and Southeast">
   <p>A storm passed through the Mid-Atlantic and Southeast December 5 - 6 bringing another week of beneficial rains to Mississippi, southern Alabama, and Georgia.  This eliminated abnormally dry (D0) conditions across much of the extreme southern part of this area.  Further, these rains, combined with cool temperatures, contributed to improvements in Moderate Drought (D1) in southeast Ohio and western West Virginia as well as some slight improvements in exceptional (D4), extreme (D3), severe (D2), and moderate (D1) drought in South Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>A series of fronts passed through the Northeast again this USDM period.  This resulted in the majority of the region receiving just slightly below normal precipitation.  With the exception of the extreme northeast, this region also experienced below normal temperatures.  No changes in drought conditions were made.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>This week, precipitation fell across much of the Upper Midwest.  The Southern Plains received some precipitation but the drought areas of Texas and Oklahoma largely missed the rain.  Abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) expanded in Oklahoma and severe drought (D2) was introduced there this week.  Exceptional (D4) and extreme (D3) drought both expanded in Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Western precipitation was largely constrained to the Northwest and northern tier states this past week.  The most intense precipitation fell in western Washington.  Light, spotty precipitation fell across Colorado as well as down into Arizona and New Mexico.  Drought intensified in California and Nevada with extension of severe (D2) conditions down through Reno and Carson City and westward, joining the tongue of D2 running nearly the entire length of California.  A small area of extreme drought (D3) was also introduced in northern California.  Ground reports in the area have indicated impacts on grazing land and livestock as well as dry springs.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
