<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040318</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Warmer and drier than normal weather is expected across much of the West and Great Plains drought areas during March 18-22, with cooler and wetter than normal weather predominating in the eastern U.S. For the ensuing five days, March 23-27, above-normal precipitation is predicted for the west coast states into the northern Rockies , and from the mid Mississippi Valley to the Great Lakes . Below-normal precipitation is expected across the rest of the drought areas, across the Southeast, and up along the Atlantic Seaboard. Warmer than normal temperatures are predicted for most of the country.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska ">
   <p>There were only spotty reports of precipitation in the drought areas of Alaska , thus no improvements were made. Minor adjustments of the western boundary of the D0 area in Alaska were made to reflect a combination of snow pack anomalies and hydrologic year-to-date precipitation anomalies. In Hawaii a storm system brought as much as 11 inches of rain to the State in a 24-hour period on March 14, resulting in flooding of local streams.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley and Southeast">
   <p>The Ohio Valley has been dry over the last several weeks, but recent rain and snow from a system that moved through the area during this drought monitoring period helped alleviate this short-term dryness. The Southeast continued to dry out, according to soil moisture indices, but a recent storm system brought some relief to the area. However, according to local media reports, a fire ban was put in place for 19 South Carolina counties on March 15, due to a wildfire burning in Oconee County that has drained the State's firefighting resources. In Georgia , conditions have been dry lately but water demand (evapotranspiration) is low this time of year.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley and Great Lakes ">
   <p>Rain and snow fell throughout the region in the latter part of this drought monitoring period. A snowstorm dumped 10-20 inches of snow in D0 areas of the Nebraska , Iowa and South Dakota confluence. However, soil moisture observations after the storm remained below normal across part of this area. Consequently, D0 was pulled back over those areas showing above normal soil moisture departures. In northwestern South Dakota , the D1 was retracted somewhat due to moisture from prior weeks. Some precipitation fell in Wisconsin this period but not enough to warrant improvement, especially since changes were made during the last drought monitoring period.</p>
   <p>As much as 1-2 inches of rain fell in the southwestern drought areas of Texas . The D1 and D2 areas were shaved back slightly to reflect minor improvements. The D0 area in eastern coastal Texas was trimmed to account for 2-3 inches of rain that fell at the end of this drought monitoring period. Up to 24% of Texas range and pasture land was reported in very poor to poor condition by the USDA, as well as 28% of the winter wheat crop. Lesser precipitation amounts were recorded in the Great Plains core drought areas, but not enough to warrant improvement to the current drought situation, thus no changes in the depiction were made.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies , Southwest, and Far West">
   <p>The drought areas in this region received little if any precipitation during this monitoring period, with the exception of .01 - .25 inch in parts of Idaho and Montana . However, melting snow pack in southwestern Idaho has resulted in increasing stream flow, especially in the Owyhee and Weiser basins, so D3 was pulled back from the Owyhee basin. In northeastern Montana , the D2/D1/D0 drought areas were retracted leaving the far northeastern corner free of drought. This is due to melting snow pack and resulting increases in stream flow and soil moisture. The Far West did not receive any precipitation, therefore no improvements were made there.</p>
   <p>Very poor to poor range and pasture land conditions were reported by the USDA in several western and Great Plains states. These include New Mexico with 81% in very poor to poor condition, Arizona with 57%, Colorado with 53%, Kansas with 44% and Oklahoma with 31%. Very poor to poor winter wheat conditions were also reported by the USDA in Colorado with 60%, Kansas with 36%, New Mexico with 26% and Oklahoma with 19%. Although this week's depiction of these drought areas was not changed, these USDA statistics indicate dry conditions are continuing.</p>
   <p>The eastern Snake River Plain Aquifer in south central Idaho , an underground reservoir as large as Lake Erie , is not able to meet the demands being placed upon it. This is considered a hydrological and socio-economic drought impact with long-term implications, being reflected by depleted wells and stressed springs causing conflicts over water rights. The lack of precipitation and resulting stream flow during the last three years, which has not been able to recharge the aquifer, is exacerbating conditions. This situation is currently depicted on the Drought Monitor map as D3 and D4.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
