<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060504</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 5-day period (May 4-May 8) that may affect areas of dryness or drought include: 1) In what could be a replay of this past week, only in smaller proportions, there is the potential for good rains across the Southern Plains and Gulf Coast states, as well as up into the Mid-Atlantic; 2) that same system should drag cooler weather behind it, helping to keep temperatures below normal over the same areas noted above; 3) unfortunately, it doesnt appear likely that the better rains will spill far enough south into southern Texas, where the current D4 is housed. In addition, temperatures in this D4 region will likely be above normal over the next 5 days.</p>
   <p>The 6- to 10-day (May 9-13) outlook from the Climate Prediction Center calls for the likelihood of 1) below-normal precipitation in the Southwest, Florida, and Northeast; 2) above-normal temperatures are expected from Texas across the Gulf Coast region into Florida and up into the Mid-Atlantic and Great Lakes region as well; 3) most of Alaska shows a greater chance of being cooler and drier during this time.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Good rains in the southern reaches of the Alexander Archipelago have led to a retreat northward of the abnormally dry (D0) area found there. To the north, the rains werent as good and the drier long-term deficits have resurfaced. In addition, continued dryness in eastern mainland Alaska has led to a slight expansion of D0.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>After some improvement in the region last week, dryness returned and settled in, resulting in no changes this week for the Northeast. To the south in the Mid-Atlantic region, some beneficial rains (generally on the order of 1 to 3 inches) fell across parts of the Carolinas, resulting in the removal of severe drought (D2) in North Carolina. Moderate drought (D1) remains in those areas that are still seeing impacts because of water supply issues that have streamflow and groundwater recovery lagging behind for this time of year, particularly in western and upper South Carolina, where deficits dating back to October 2005 for many locales are running around 50% (or worse) of normal. This is marked by the H Impact line for North Carolina in particular. The best rains missed their neighbors in western South Carolina and northern Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast States">
   <p>South Florida continues to stay quite dry in advance of the rainy season onset later this month. Naples, FL, just recorded their 4th driest April ever, with a trace of precipitation, and experienced their 2nd driest March-April (0.08 inches). The dryness isnt confined to just Naples or to the short term. Many locations from Orlando southward have seen less than 50% of normal precipitation on the year, with deficits running from 4 to 6 inches (35-45% of normal) below normal since January 1. For Orlando, the 3.86-inch year-to-date total (through April 30) ranks as the driest on record (back to 1952). Some of the cities sharing in the dryness are Key West and Marathon in the Keys, Fort Myers (6th driest Jan-April on record), Vero Beach, and Apalachicola along with Melbourne and Daytona Beach on the east coast. South Florida is in no better shape when looking back to October 1 of last year, with precipitation running at 50-70% of normal over the seven-month period. As a result, a small area of moderate drought (D1) has been introduced across the Everglades region in southern Florida. The threat of fire will remain high until the rains come. In some better news, the rains (2 to 4 inches) that fell across parts of the extreme western Florida Panhandle have led to a reduction of some of the moderate drought (D1) found there.</p>
   <p>Up the Florida coast and to the west along the Gulf Coast, the story was heavy rains last week, with anywhere from 3 to 6 inches or more across extreme southeastern Texas, southern Louisiana, southern Mississippi, southern Alabama, and the extreme western Panhandle of Florida. Removal of the recently introduced extreme drought (D3) in Louisiana, and a general 1-category improvement, was noted in this region. It remains to be seen just how beneficial these rains will be against the longer-term deficits that have been accumulating not only this year, but also back to October of last year. Several locations are still seeing only 25-50% of normal totals, particularly in extreme southern Louisiana and Mississippi, thus the retention of D1 and D2 in these areas.</p>
   <p>Parts of Texas shared in some of the improvements, but other areas saw some worsening of drought conditions over the last week. The good news is that southeastern and south-central Texas saw rains on the order of 2 to 4 inches or more in the Hill Country west of Austin and north of San Antonio. In south-central Texas, this resulted in a retreat of the extreme drought (D3) to the south and an eastward reduction of severe drought (D2) in central and north-central Texas. Unfortunately, the large area of exceptional drought (D4) didnt see that kind of precipitation and remains entrenched. San Antonio just completed its driest May through April 12-month period (surpassing May 1938-April 1939) on record, with only 13.66 inches of rain being reported. As if that werent bad enough, the month of April was very warm and windy as well and many locations (San Antonio, Corpus Christi, and Laredo) saw their hottest April on recordnot the kind of records they need to be setting before the hot season.</p>
   <p>A strip of D2 remains in central Texas, a reminder that although year-to-date totals are normal to above normal, the longer-term deficits reappear quickly, going back to just October of last year, with many locales in central Texas running at 50-70% over that time frame. Many locations around the Dallas-Fort Worth region are running 10 to 20 inch deficits over the past 12 months as well. The news hasnt gotten any better in the Panhandles of Texas and Oklahoma, where the precipitation totals at virtually all time scales back to a year now are pretty dismal. This has led to an expansion and joining of the extreme drought (D3) conditions that continue to affect the region. In the Texas Panhandle, Lake Meredith is a major source for drinking water, and levels there have fallen to a record low recently, down some 37 feet since 1999.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>In particular, the Plains and Midwest shared in the wealth of moisture that also fell across the Gulf Coast region. Eastern Oklahoma, eastern Kansas, western Missouri, and northwest Arkansas saw the best of it, with widespread totals ranging from 3 to 6 inches or more in several places. It was badly needed and has resulted in a general 1-category improvement across this entire area. The large area of extreme drought (D3) has been removed from this region, leaving it contained in western Oklahoma at this time. These states also saw a major reduction in the amount of area under D1 and D2 conditions as well. In addition, the short-term moisture surplus has led to a change from AH to H in these same places because of the long-term lingering deficits that date back to last summer and fall. The recent wet spell has improved the situation but groundwater, local lakes, and streamflow are still lagging along in many of these areas. In fact, dating back to just October of last year, deficits are still running some 10 to 16 inches below normal (around 50% of normal, give or take) through May 1 for these same parts of Oklahoma, Arkansas, Kansas, and southwest Missouri. The change to the Hydrological (H) Impact designation for a large part of the region reflects this underlying concern as we head into the high-demand warm season.</p>
   <p>Farther north, improvement is noted in southeastern Nebraska, southern Iowa, northern Missouri, and northern Illinois, who all shared in nice soaking weekend rains, with totals generally ranging from 2 to 4 inches. The recent wet spell has led to improvements in the area, with reductions in the moderate drought (D1) area and abnormally dry areas (D0) in these states as well. Because of the wet spring, northern Illinois is free of dryness/drought for the first time on the Drought Monitor since April 2005. In fact, as recently as January of this year, D3 was found in these parts. This has certainly been a good change in fortunes that could help to buffer the region should another dry summer develop.</p>
   <p>Not everyone in the High Plains shared in the improvements, though. In western Kansas and southwestern NE, the recent dryness has again turned concerns toward the wheat crop here and the severe drought (D2) has been on a slow but steady northward and eastward course into these parts. They did not see much, if any, rain last week. The H Impact line has been adjusted north as well in northwestern Kansas and southwestern Nebraska to account for this concern.</p>
   <p>In the Great Plains region, the dryness continues across northern Wisconsin and Michigans Upper Peninsula, where the deficits and sunny weather continue to silently mount. This has lead to an expansion of abnormally dry (D0) conditions as well as an introduction of moderate drought (D1) across parts of the Upper Peninsula.</p>
   <p>Finally, an extended dry spell this spring has parts of eastern Ohio off to a slow start in terms of precipitation. This is reflected on the map this week by a slight westward expansion of D0 toward central Ohio.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>In the West, the story continues to focus on the dry wet season felt in the Southwest. Arizona and New Mexico continue to share this plight. Most areas of both states are running at 50% of normal or worse for the Water Year (October 1, 2005, to date). Tucson has just completed their driest September to April on record, with only .79 inches being reported. In fact, that ranks as the driest 8-month period on record. Naturally, this has also led to the driest Water Year to date (Oct. 1Apr. 30) on record as well. Deficits over the past year in central and southern Arizona are running anywhere from 5 to 15 inches below normal (just 25-50% of normal). With this in mind, the region continues to worsen on this weeks map as extreme drought (D3) expands westward slightly and a new area of exceptional drought (D4) is introduced in the southeast corner of the state and over into extreme southwestern New Mexico. Its looking like this region and the surrounding environment will be even more dependent this year on a good monsoon season.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
