<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000309</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Several storm systems will bring rain to the region in the next 2 weeks, but conditions will not improve in Florida and southern Georgia.</p>
   <p>Several bouts of rain and snow starting on March 7 will further reduce dryness in the central and northern Plains, but amounts will not be sufficient to significantly change drought categories in eastern Nebraska and Iowa. The new moisture should nearly eliminate lingering dryness in western Kansas during the next 2 weeks and end drought over most of Minnesota.</p>
   <p>Lighter precipitation is on tap for the Southwest over the next 2 weeks, and long-range forecasts call for abnormally warm, dry conditions through spring. As a result, no additional major improvement is expected in the foreseeable future.</p>
   <p>As the wet season winds down, there is little prospect for substantial relief into summer.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Unusually dry weather continued across the state of Hawaii. Drought (D1) continues in leeward areas, mainly affecting pastures and fire danger. Honolulu has measured 1.35 inches of rain so far this year, versus a normal of 6.20 inches (22% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Precipitation over Kansas and Oklahoma has ended drought over western parts of both states, bringing the dryness rating down to D0. The moisture relieved some of the stress on the wheat crop. Light to moderate precipitation in Nebraska and Iowa was not enough to significantly reduce the severe (D2) drought in these states. July-February precipitation in Iowa was 5.81 inches below normal. Little rain fell over Illinois, Minnesota, and Indiana, allowing D1 to D2 drought to continue.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South-Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>Light to moderate rains over the Southeast stabilized drought conditions from Alabama through Georgia, with severe drought (D2) continuing from Georgia to northern Florida. In Georgia, the drought dates back to May 1998, with a cumulative deficit of 19.3 inches through the end of February 2000. First-stage drought (D1) continued over north-central Florida, and abnormal dryness (D0) continued over the rest of the peninsula. Orlando has measured 1.59 inches of rain this year (26% of normal). Florida range conditions declined to 60% poor to very poor. With little rain and abnormal heat over parts of North Carolina and southwest Virginia, drought (D1) expanded farther eastward into these states. Warm, dry weather also allowed severe drought (D2) to continue over the lower Mississippi Valley and much of Texas, expanding into northern Alabama. In Baton Rouge, Louisiana, year- to-date rainfall totals only 3.43 inches (30% of normal). In Texas, precipitation from July to February was 7.65 inches below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Storms brought more rain and snow to California, eroding remaining areas of dryness in the extreme south. Rain and snow over the Southwest on March 5-6 brought some relief to Arizona, New Mexico, and southern Utah. In Arizona, these were the heaviest amounts since dryness began last October, with Phoenix reporting 2.50 inches of rain. This moisture was helpful, but grazing areas in the Southwest need more for marked improvement. Water supplies in major reservoirs remain adequate.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
