<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20051229</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Moderate to heavy precipitation (1 to locally 4 inches) is expected during December 28  January 2 from the Cascades and northern Nevada eastward through northern Utah and western sections of Wyoming and Montana. Similar totals are also forecast for central California. Meanwhile, 0.5 to 1.0 inch is anticipated across the remainder of Utah, central Nevada, northern Arizona, central Wyoming, central and northeastern Montana, the northern and eastern Great Lakes region, northern Mississippi, Tennessee, Kentucky, and adjacent Ohio. In contrast, little or no precipitation is forecast across the Southwest and through the central and northern Plains. Meanwhile, above-normal temperatures are expected across all regions of dryness and drought, except central California, with daily high temperatures expected to average 12F to 16F above normal through most of the Great Plains and northern High Plains.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (January 3  7), the odds favor above-normal precipitation across the central Rockies, Intermountain West, and Pacific Coast States as well as most of the Great Lakes and the central and eastern sections of Kentucky. In contrast, below-normal precipitation appears most likely in the southeastern Rockies and most of the Plains. Warmer-than-normal weather is again expected to cover most of the nation, specifically from the Great Lakes, eastern Kentucky, central Tennessee, and central Louisiana westward to the Pacific shores.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Very little precipitation fell on interior southeastern Alaska, keeping D0 conditions unchanged. Farther south, Hawaii also experienced a drier-than-normal week, with substantial precipitation reported only in a few areas where normal amounts are quite large. As a result, D0 and D1AH conditions persisted across the island chain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, Great Lakes Region, and Upper South">
   <p>Below-normal precipitation was observed across a vast majority of the region, keeping areas of dryness and drought intact. South-central Tennessee and northeastern Mississippi were the only exceptions, where 1 to 3 inches of precipitation eliminated last weeks D0AH conditions and prompted a slight reduction in the southward extent of the D1AH conditions in Tennessee.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, between 0.5 and 1.0 inch of precipitation fell on the rest of southern and eastern Tennessee, across easternmost Kentucky, in west-central North Carolina, and on a few small areas in west-central Illinois and northern Missouri. Meanwhile, areas from eastern Kansas, northeastern Arkansas, and northeastern Texas eastward recorded 0.3 to 0.5 inch while points to the west of this area reported only isolated amounts of up to 0.2 inch.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Intermountain West, and West Coast States">
   <p>Moderate to heavy precipitation fell on a broad swath extending from the Cascades eastward through western sections of Montana and Wyoming. Most locales recorded 0.5 to 2.0 inches, but larger amounts ranging up to 6 inches were reported along the Cascades, across much of the Idaho Panhandle, and through southwestern Idaho and adjacent Oregon.</p>
   <p>As a result, there was some erosion of the western edges of the D0H and D1H conditions near the Cascades, a slight reduction in the northeastward extent of D2H conditions in Washington, and the elimination of D0H conditions, at least for the time being, across parts of southeastern Oregon and southwestern Idaho, where mountain snowpack and precipitation totals since the start of October are slightly to substantially above normal. Farther north, D1H conditions persisted across the Idaho Panhandle despite the wet week because mountain snowpack and 3-month precipitation totals were still below normal.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, scattered precipitation totals of 0.5 to 2.0 inches were reported across interior central California and north-central Wyoming. However, across most of the Rockies, New Mexico, and Arizona, little or no precipitation fell, keeping areas of dryness and drought intact.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
