<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20131212</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>For the second straight week, a powerful storm moved across the country and into the eastern U.S. this US Drought Monitor week.  This storm followed a similar track along the East Coast to the Thanksgiving Storm of last week.  Snow accumulated from the Upper Midwest where Duluth gained over 10 inches from the storm, through the Mid-Atlantic, shutting down government offices in Washington DC, and into New York where Central Park received a trace.  The Southern Plains experienced snow, sleet, and freezing rain from the event.  The highest liquid precipitation totals fell through the Southeast and in the Tennessee Valley with rainfall in areas of central Alabama received over five inches in a day and well over six inches during the week. This weather caused thousands of commercial airline flights around the country to be cancelled and thousands more to be delayed.  The major hubs of Dallas/Fort Worth and Chicago appear to have been most impacted.   Highways ground to a halt in the Southern Plains and multi-car pileups were not uncommon.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the December 12-16, 2013 time period, the probability of precipitation is above-normal for nearly the entire eastern U.S. and in the Northwest early in the period. A below-normal chance of precipitation is expected in the rest of the West and spreads to the entire country by the end of this time period.  Below-normal temperatures are expected across most of the eastern U.S. with the exception of Florida.  Above-normal temperatures are expected for   from the Southern Plains extending into New England.  An above normal chance of precipitation is also present across areas of the West, particularly in the Southwest.   Temperatures are expected to be below-normal across the country, with the exception of the East Coast during this time.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (December 17-21, 2013), the odds favor normal to above-normal temperatures across the CONUS with the exception of a swath from North Dakota, through the Great Lakes, and into New England.  Additionally, southern Alaska is likely to experience above-normal temperatures. Below-normal temperatures are forecast for the previously mentioned part of the North and Northeast as well as across most of Alaska. Above normal-precipitation is likely across the Northern tier of the country and along the East Coast.  Most of southern Alaska is likely to experience above-normal precipitation.  Below-normal precipitation is expected from throughout the Southwest and into the Southern Plains. Western Alaska is also likely to experience below-normal precipitation.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Beneficial rains continue to fall across Puerto Rico.  However, it was not enough to improve the Abnormal Dryness (D0) there.  Likewise, drought conditions remained steady across Alaska and the Hawaiian Islands this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Northern Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Snow that feel this week in northwest Nebraska alleviated some Severe Drought (D2) there.  Nearby in southern South Dakota, the snow alleviated some Abnormal Dryness (D0).  Large amounts of snow fell in select areas around the Midwest.  This led to removal of Moderate Drought (D1) in northern Minnesota and improvements in Abnormal Dryness (D0) in the same areas and carrying over into North Dakota.  Lingering drought impacts in northern Minnesota have been changed to “L” to represent their longer timescale impact given the short-term precipitation abundance.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>The second intense storm in two weeks moved through the East over the weekend and into the early part of this week dropping rain throughout the Southeast and snow on many areas of the Mid-Atlantic.  Philadelphia received over eight inches of snow.  Other locations received beneficial precipitation that improved their drought status.  Areas of West Virginia, Pennsylvania, Alabama, Mississippi, and Georgia all saw a reduction in Abnormal Dryness (D0).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southern Plains">
   <p>Recent precipitation improved drought conditions in some parts of Texas.  Northwest Texas saw an improvement in Extreme Drought (D3).  Southwest Texas saw improvements in Severe (D2) and Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormal Dryness (D0).  Southeast Texas saw improvement in Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormal Dryness (D0).  Northeast Texas saw improvement in Severe Drought (D2).  Likewise, Louisiana, Arkansas, and Oklahoma saw improvement in Abnormal Dryness (D0).  Conversely, Abnormal Dryness (D0) expanded in southeast Kansas and into west-central Missouri where the last 30 days have been very dry.  Abnormal Dryness (D0) expanded in southern Texas and Severe (D2) and Moderate Drought (D1) expanded in central Texas.  Lake Brownwood in central Texas is below 58% full and has instituted stage 2 drought restrictions. Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormal Dryness (D0) also expanded in northwest Oklahoma.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Abnormal Dryness (D0) expanded again this week in the northern Cascade Mountains in Oregon and Washington as well as on the Oregon Coast.  These areas continue to miss most of the recent precipitation that has fallen around the Northwest and have significant deficits for the year.  Beneficial precipitation has continued to accumulate in Utah.  Severe (D2) and Moderate Drought (D1) improved in the central, southern, and eastern part of the state.  Further improvements may be necessary in coming weeks through this area and in northern Arizona should precipitation continue.  Southeast Montana also saw a decrease in Severe Drought (D2) resulting from the recent precipitation events.  The rest of the West remains unchanged this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
