<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020912</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather developments that could have an impact on areas of drought or dryness during the next 2 weeks include: 1) tropical moisture streaming northward from the Gulf of Mexico merging with a cold front to bring widespread rains during September 14-18 from southern Georgia to New England; 2) showers during September 11-13 depositing .5 to 2.0 inches over Colorado, Kansas, Oklahoma, and northern Texas; 3) above-normal rain over the Northwest during the next 2 weeks.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Due to low rainfall since August, D0 (A,F) developed in western Maui.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Warm, dry weather caused drought to expand into areas that missed the previous weeks heavy rains. D2 drought expanded southward into central and western Maine and into New Hampshire. D1 drought expanded westward across southern Vermont into New Yorks Adirondacks and along Lake Ontario. D1 drought also expanded to include most of Pennsylvania, where topsoil moisture was rated 90% short to very short by USDA. Severe drought (D2) also expanded northward toward central areas of the state. D4 drought persisted from southwestern Virginia into Georgia, with D2 to D3 drought expanding westward into Virginias Shenandoah Valley.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>Hot, dry weather caused D0 dryness to expand deeper into Mississippi from the east, and to cover most of Alabama. D1 drought extended across central and southern Alabama. D1 to D4 drought persisted over Georgia. The heaviest rains from Tropical Storm Faye fell outside of the drought zones in Texas, but several inches of rain did scale back the drought in south Texas. Dryness (D0) in Louisiana expanded northward into eastern Oklahoma.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, Ohio Valley, Great Lakes">
   <p>Most of the region from Missouri to Ohio reported little rain during the past week, an outbreak of thunderstorms on September 3 in southeast Ohio being the main exception. D0 dryness expanded westward and northward into southern Michigan and northern sections of Indiana and Illinois. D2 drought poked southward to cover much of northern Kentucky. All drought categories edged westward across Tennessee. Thunderstorms on September 9-10 reduced drought somewhat from South Dakota to Kansas, but dry weather to the east allowed drought to extend eastward and southward into western Missouri and eastern Kansas. Dryness (D0) also expanded into central and northeastern Arkansas. D2 (severe drought) developed in southwest Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Alaska">
   <p>Widespread thunderstorms continued to eat away at drought across the West, with several inches of rain falling locally in Arizona, Colorado, and New Mexico. A slight reduction of drought levels took place in northwest Wyoming, eastern Idaho, and parts of Utah, Colorado, Arizona, and New Mexico. A somewhat-reduced area of D4 persisted from the four corners area eastward across southern Colorado as well as across southern Wyoming. Continued rains eliminated abnormal dryness over Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
