<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050428</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During April 27  May 1, moderate to heavy precipitation (1 to 2 inches) is forecast for the western slopes of the Oregon Cascades, west-central and the southeastern quarter of Wyoming, northern Colorado, much of southern and western Nebraska and adjacent Kansas, and the southern Great Lakes region. In contrast, little or no precipitation is forecast for the northern Great Lakes region, the Dakotas, northern portions of the Rockies and Intermountain West, southern Arizona, central New Mexico, central and eastern Oklahoma, and northeastern Texas. Widespread below-normal temperatures are anticipated during this period for all current areas of dryness and drought, except southern Texas. Daily highs are expected to average at least 15 oF below normal across the northwestern Plains and the northern Rockies. The ensuing 5 days (May 2  6) should be wetter than normal from western sections of Colorado, Wyoming, and southern Montana westward through most of Utah, Nevada, Idaho, Oregon, and southeastern Washington. The odds also favor surplus precipitation in the south-central Plains and lower Mississippi Valley while deficient totals are expected in northeastern Montana, most of the Dakotas, and the northern and western portions of the Great Lakes region. Meanwhile, continued below-normal temperatures should be observed from north-central Montana and the High Plains eastward to the Atlantic while warmer-than-normal conditions are expected to envelop the Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Generally 2 to 7 inches of rain eradicated last weeks D0 conditions in both northwestern and south-central Puerto Rico. Meanwhile, 1 to 3 inches improved D1 conditions to D0 in northwestern Puerto Rico while 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches of rain left D0 to D1 conditions essentially unchanged in southeastern Puerto Rico. Less than 30 percent of normal rainfall has been measured across the D1 area since the beginning of the year while the current D0 areas received 30 to 60 percent of normal during this period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northern and Central Plains">
   <p>Some of the heaviest precipitation in months fell on western and southern South Dakota and parts of northern and central Nebraska, with 3 to locally 5 inches measured in south-central South Dakota. This eliminated any widespread agricultural dryness in areas south and west of central South Dakota, and induced a general 1-category improvement in assessed Drought Monitor conditions across much of southern and western South Dakota and northern Nebraska. As a result, D3H conditions are now restricted to the Black Hills and extreme western South Dakota, and surface moisture shortages limited to the central and northern Dakotas.</p>
   <p>In sharp contrast, Less than 0.5 inch of precipitation was measured across all but southwesternmost North Dakota, the northeastern quarter of South Dakota, and the southern tier of Nebraska. Dryness and drought conditions remained essentially unchanged in these areas, with some D0A and D1AH expansion in central and eastern sections of the Dakotas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Western States">
   <p>Heavy rain and snow fell on many areas from central Montana and southern Idaho southward through large portions of the Rockies, Great Basin, and Four Corners states, including many of the D3H and D4H areas that needed it the most. The heaviest amounts (2 to locally 6 inches) were recorded in south-central Montana, south-central Idaho, northeastern Nevada, part of north-central Utah, and near the western Washington/Oregon border while totals below 0.5 inch were restricted to the northern and southern tiers of the West, southern Oregon, much of central and northwestern Wyoming and adjacent Idaho, southeastern Utah, and central New Mexico. A few locales in the northern Rockies received record or near-record daily snowfall early in the period.</p>
   <p>Despite the beneficial heavy precipitation, significant 2- to 6-year precipitation deficits still covered large parts of the central and northern portions of the West, and one storm system cannot eradicate such protracted dryness. Therefore, improvement might not be as expansive nor as large in magnitude as some might expect. Still, a broken pattern of one-category improvements to last weeks D0H to D4H conditions covered areas from central Montana and southern Idaho southward into central and eastern portions of Arizona, including the elimination of dryness (former D0H conditions) in parts of northeastern Nevada, lower northern Utah, central Arizona, and portions of south-central and north-central Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains">
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation fell on parts of Oklahoma, Arkansas, Louisiana, and Texas last week, but totals exceeding an inch were restricted to southwestern Arkansas and several other isolated areas. Widespread below-normal precipitation on 30- to 90-day time scales prompted the expansion of D0A into much of Louisiana, southeastern Arkansas, parts of northern and eastern Texas, and most of Oklahoma east of the Panhandle. Meanwhile, D1A conditions expanded to cover most of central, south-central, and southwestern Oklahoma. Most of this D1A area recorded less than half of normal precipitation during the last 90 days, and below 25 percent of normal since late March. Farther south and east, most of the new D0A areas received less than half of normal precipitation during the last 60 days.</p>
   <p>Little or no precipitation fell on deep southern Texas, prompting some northward D1A and D0A expansion. D0A conditions now reach as far north as Corpus Christi along the Gulf Coast of Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
