<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010809</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) cold fronts crossing the Midwest and East this weekend and early next week, bringing needed rains and lower temperatures to many dry areas; 2) cooler weather and showers over the next 5 days in the Oklahoma/Texas Panhandle area; 3) below-normal rains over eastern interior Texas for the next 2 weeks; 4) the return of above-normal temperatures to the Great Plains and upper Midwest next week.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico and Hawaii">
   <p>Drought persisted in Hawaii. Abnormal dry areas were removed from Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Central Plains">
   <p>Heavy thunderstorm rains (2-8 inches) ended D0 dryness in southeastern Iowa, northeast Missouri, northwestern Illinois and near Chicago, and southern and northern Wisconsin. D0 dryness remained near central areas of Iowa, Minnesota, and Wisconsin, and central and northeastern Illinois, while D1 drought edged westward from eastern portions of Michigans Lower Peninsula. Kansas was hot and dry, but D0 expanded only slightly northward, as heavy rains had fallen during the previous week. High heat offset much of the benefits of heavy rains in Nebraska, as D0 or D1 remained over portions of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Hot weather caused dryness to increase in areas that missed the heavier rains, most of which (1-4 inches) fell in southern New York, Massachusetts, and eastern Pennsylvania. D1 drought developed across northern Vermont and New Hampshire and expanded westward in Maine. D0 dryness expanded to include New Jersey, the New York City area, and Connecticut. USDA rated topsoil moisture 88% short or very short in New Jersey and Connecticut, up sharply in the past 2 weeks. Abnormal dryness persisted across much of upstate New York, as the heat offset the benefits from scattered thunderstorms.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Heavy rains associated with Tropical Storm Barry eased long-term dryness on the Florida peninsula, with widespread weekly totals ranging from 4 to 8 inches, and locally higher amounts along the east coast. Groundwater levels improved significantly, but remained below normal in north-central areas. Aquifer levels were generally normal or above across south Florida. As a result, D0(W) was located over north-central Florida and D1(W) was limited to the Ocala area. To the south, Lake Okeechobee levels have risen nearly 2 feet in the past month. Very heavy rains removed dryness along the Georgia coast near Floridas border, with D1 improved to D0 elsewhere along the coast. In North Carolina, heavy rains eliminated dryness in the extreme west, but dry weather caused D2 drought to expand eastward to the Charlotte area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Mid-South">
   <p>High temperatures and negligible rainfall allowed D1 and D2 drought to expand northward and eastward in Oklahoma and Texas, as the mercury continued to soar into the triple digits. Extreme (D3) drought grew larger in southwest Texas. Severe drought (D2) covered southwestern Oklahoma and much of central Texas. Drought (D1/D2) persisted over northeast Arkansas and extreme western Tennessee.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Alaska">
   <p>Continued above-normal rains allowed some retreat of the D0/D1 dryness/drought in eastern Montana, but extreme heat prevented additional improvement. There was little change elsewhere in the D1/D2/D3 drought situation across the West, although some D2 drought improved to D1 in northwest Washington due to improved reservoir levels in the Skagit basin.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
