<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100603</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (June 3-7) temperatures are expected to be well above normal for most of the United States.  A ridge will build in from the southwest with the greatest anomalies over west Texas and New Mexico, where temperatures are projected to be 9-12 degrees above normal.  Precipitation should be widespread over much of the eastern half of the United States with the greatest amount expected over Illinois and Ohio and along the Gulf Coast.  The Pacific Northwest looks to be wet and cooler than most locations as several weather systems will impact the region. The CPC 6-10 day forecast (June 8–13) temperatures over the southern United States are likely to be well above normal with the best chances centered over Texas.  Chances for below normal temperatures are best over upper New England and the Pacific Northwest.  The best chances for precipitation will be in the northern plains through the Midwest while below normal precipitation is expected over Texas and Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Gulf Coast">
   <p>Dry conditions continue along the Gulf Coast areas of Texas and Louisiana.  D1 was expanded in both Texas and Louisiana while D2 was introduced into much of central Louisiana.  D0 was expanded westward in Texas and northward out of Louisiana and into Arkansas.  Tyler, Texas, finished May with 0.38 inches of precipitation being recorded, which was the 3rd driest on record.  Tyler only recorded 1.21 inches of precipitation for April and May combined, which is well below the normal of 8.16 inches for both months (15 percent of normal) during the wettest two months of the year.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>D3 was introduced on Oahu this week and D0 was extended over all of the Big Island.  Irrigators are looking at a 30 percent reduction of water on Oahu as agricultural issues continue to plague the Big Island.  No changes were made to Alaska or Puerto Rico this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Low streamflows as well as drying soils were common through much of New England.  In the short term, conditions continue to be dry, and this is reflected with an expansion of D0 through much of New England and a new area of D1 in New York just to the east of Lake Ontario.  In the area just to the east of Lake Ontario, year-to-date standardized precipitation index (SPI) values are approaching -2.5 and precipitation deficits during this time are 9-12 inches below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Improving conditions over the last few months have allowed for a reduction in the D0/D1 intensities over western Montana.  Over the last 60-90 days, this area has received 100-150 percent of normal precipitation.  Along with decent snows this winter, the region has improved. The small pocket of D1 was also eliminated in central Washington this week as conditions have improved.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Upper Midwest">
   <p>The dryness continues to hamper Minnesota, Wisconsin and Michigan.  Multi-year deficits continue to grow as impacts from the drought worsen.  D2/D3 conditions were expanded to include much of the upper peninsula of Michigan and portions of north central Wisconsin. D0 was introduced into southeast Minnesota as 3- to 4-inch deficits are common through this area for the spring. Since October 1 through the end of May, Houghton, Michigan, is 11.63 inches of precipitation below normal, with only 0.74 inches in the first three months of this year.  Impacts associated with water supply and power generation are starting to become common.  Some power generators are coming close to having to shut down due to lack of flows.  Several lakes are 1 to 2 feet lower already than last year, with docks exposed to the lake bottom, with no water under them.  Since 2002, areas of Wisconsin are 30 to 35 inches below normal, which is more than a season’s worth of precipitation.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Eric Luebehusen</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
