<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20130711</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>During the past week, a strong and persistent area of high pressure dominated the circulation over the western half of the lower 48 states, with some monsoon moisture bringing isolated rains (0.5 0 - 2.8 inches) to the southwest. Southerly flow around the Bermuda High supplied ample moisture and an upper-level trough provided the energy for widespread heavy rains (1.0 – 10.4 inches) across the southeast, triggering flooding from the Gulf Coast to the Great Lakes.  As the moisture thinned out, rains across the northeast were sparser with isolated heavy rains across New York and Vermont.  Dry conditions continued across the Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (July 16-20), the odds favor above-median precipitation over western Alaska, the southern Rockies, the Northern Great Plains, Western and Central Gulf Coasts, and from the Great Lakes to the Mid-Atlantic.  Dry conditions are likely across the Pacific Northwest, eastern Alaska, and the Central Great Plains. Temperatures are likely to be above normal west of the continental divide, and from the Midwest to the Northeast, with below-normal temperatures favored over New Mexico and the Southeast.</p>
   <p>The next 6 days (July 10-15) favor wet weather across most of the eastern half of the Nation, east of the Ohio and Mississippi Rivers, with heavy rains forecast from the Gulf Coast to the Mid-Atlantic.  Some rains associated with the North American Monsoon are also likely during the next 5 days across Arizona and Colorado, largely bypassing New Mexico.  Generally, less than 1.0 inches of rain is forecast across the area from Texas to Illinois, California, and the Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Some rains (0.5 – 1.7 inches) fell across southwest Alaska, prompting the removal of D0.  Those rains contrasted with the continued dry conditions across interior Alaska were fires have been threatening towns.  The Stuart Creek 2 Fire, east of Fairbanks, resulted in an evacuation order being issued Sunday for hundreds of residents in the area just north of the fire.  Accordingly, D1 was expanded were the continued dryness corresponded with low streamflows.</p>
   <p>Over Hawaii, minimal rains were reported.  D0 (abnormal dryness) was introduced to the slopes of Kauai and Oahu, where the lower elevations of the leeward slopes were drier than normal for both islands.  On the Big Island daily rainfall frequency was near normal on the east-facing slopes but the average rainfall per day was well below average, so D0 was expanded.  Additional intensification was pursued as June rainfall totals were well below normal over the higher terrain and the leeward portions of the Big Island. USDA Farm Service Agency reported that farmers destocked pastures in the existing D3 area in the northwest corner of the Big Island, consistent with the current depiction.</p>
   <p>Widespread rains fell over most of Puerto Rico with some stations reporting over 3.0 inches of rain for the week.  No drought or dryness is currently indicated for Puerto Rico, although south-central Puerto Rico has been drier than normal during the past 30 days.  This area will be watched for future drought development.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England and mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Deep, southerly flow brought significant moisture northward from the Gulf of Mexico to the Great Lakes and Northeast.  Significant rains (0.5 – 4.4 inches fell) across New England, with lower amounts over most of the Mid-Atlantic, except western Virginia where rainfall totals exceeded 2.0 inches.  The rains that fell across southwestern Pennsylvania prompted the removal of some abnormal dryness (D0) from that region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Moderate to very heavy rains (1.0 – 10.4 inches) fell on most of the remaining D0 over northern Florida and southern Alabama.  Therefore, the remaining area of abnormal dryness (D0) was trimmed considerably across Alabama and Florida.  Streamflows across southern Alabama have responded to where no areas of dryness were evident when considering streamflow values.  The remaining D0 areas are based in medium term deficits at 30 and 60 days (3.5 and 5.0 inches, respectively).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southwest and West">
   <p>Some monsoon moisture streamed northward over the Southwest, making it as far north as the Great Salt Lake, bringing isolated rains to Utah, Colorado, Arizona, and New Mexico.  The heaviest rains (1.0 – 2.6 inches) were confined to southeastern Arizona and the highest of terrain in central New Mexico, therefore the rains had little impact on the drought in New Mexico.  Some small reductions in drought intensity were noted in Arizona where SPI values rebounded slightly in response to the rains.  Likewise, the same plume of moisture brought rains to the Salt Lake City area, prompting the removal of some moderate drought (D1) from that region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Southern Plains, and Lower Mississippi River Valley">
   <p>Dry conditions persisted across most of the southern Great Plains and Lower Mississippi River Valley.  The temperatures were generally below normal (1 – 4 deg F) for the week, which still means warm across that portion of the lower 48 states.  Accordingly, the coverage of drought conditions was increased across the Southern Great Plains.</p>
   <p>D0 was expanded to cover much of Arkansas and northwestern Louisiana, supported by SPI-3 (Standardized Precipitation Index over 3 months) values.  In a reassessment of conditions over Arkansas, a 2-category degradation (introduction of D1, moderate drought, where no drought was indicated in the previous map) was included as SPI-3, SPI6, and USGS (United States Geological Survey) real-time, 7-, and 14-day stream flows all indicated a rapid drying of the area.</p>
   <p>Much of the same conditions were present across Oklahoma and Texas, so drought conditions intensified over those two states.  Accordingly, D2 (severe drought), D1 (moderate drought) and D0 (abnormal dryness) were expanded across much of eastern Texas.  The impacts from the ongoing drought are becoming more intense as the drought lingers.  For instance, the Brazosport Water Authority implemented Stage 3 of its Drought Contingency Plan.   Inflows into the Lower Colorado River have trickled down to 10 cfs (from the Llano River) with Lake Travis and Lake Buchanan at 35 and 37 percent of capacity, respectively.   Medina Lake, near San Antonio is down to 5 percent capacity.   Farther north and west, across Oklahoma and southeastern Colorado, reports indicate sage brush and large trees dying and even some cacti turning brown. These reports come from the areas that have been in D4 (exceptional drought) for quite some time.  The percent of topsoil reports as short or very short from the USDA National Agricultural Statistical Service (NASS) across Texas increased by 13 percentage point, while it increased by 25 percentage points across Oklahoma.</p>
   <p>Some drought expansion was also introduced across Kansas, where topsoil moisture reports indicated an increase of 38 percentage points for the portion of reports indicating short or very short moisture amounts.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Northern Plains">
   <p>Some rains (0.5 – 1.7 inches) fell on the drought area in Minnesota, so some minor adjustments were made to the drought depiction there, with D1 being trimmed slightly where the heaviest rains fell.  The rains that swept across South Dakota were not enough in amount or in coverage to drive a change in conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Matthew Rosencrans</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
