<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041021</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>In addition to the storm currently pushing through California on October 20, w eather that may affect areas of dryness or drought during the next 10 days include: 1) Areas of moderate to heavy precipitation across the central Rockies and parts of the Southwest as the West Coast storm lifts northeastward. More than 2 inches are anticipated in a large part of northwestern Arizona, with totals exceeding 1 inch expected from western Arizona northeastward through eastern Utah and northwestern Colorado. 2) Moderate to heavy precipitation (0.5 to 1.5 inches) from the Great Lakes southwestward through the east-central Plains states during October 20  25. 3) Little or no precipitation through October 25 in a swath from eastern New Mexico northeastward through southern and eastern Nebraska. 4) A good chance for above-normal October 26  30 precipitation in most areas of dryness or drought from the northern Great Plains and southern High Plains westward to the California coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>A dry week led to unchanged conditions in these states. Moderate drought (D1) continued in eastern parts of the Big Island in Hawaii, and abnormal dryness (D0) persisted on Maui and across parts of Alaska</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States and Great Lakes">
   <p>Moderate to heavy precipitation continued to relieve drought and dryness in much of the central United States, though some dry areas missed the bulk of the precipitation. Farther north and west, precipitation was much more sparse in the Great Lakes and central Plains regions. The extent of improvement was more limited in these areas, and dryness actually expanded slightly in a few locations.</p>
   <p>The southern halves of Illinois and Indiana recorded more than 2 inches of precipitation, with 4 or more inches falling on several areas. Farther south, between 1 and 3 inches dampened southeastern Missouri and adjacent areas of Kentucky, Tennessee, and Arkansas. Unfortunately, heavy precipitation generally evaded areas farther to the south and west, where most of southern and northwestern Missouri, northwestern Arkansas, northeastern Oklahoma, eastern Kansas, and western Iowa. Meanwhile, spotty 1- to 3-inch precipitation totals were noted in both the northern and southern parts of the Great Lakes region, with light to locally moderate amounts recorded in the middle.</p>
   <p>As a result, D0 retreated from Indiana, all but northern and southwesternmost Illinois, western sections of Tennessee and Kentucky and adjacent parts of Arkansas and Missouri, and portions of both southern and north-central Michigan. In addition, conditions improved from D1 to D0 in much of southeastern Missouri and adjacent areas, and in both northeastern and southeastern lower Michigan.</p>
   <p>In contrast, another fairly dry week allowed D1 to expand westward in Wisconsin, and spread D0 conditions further into western Iowa, southeastern Nebraska, northwestern Missouri, and the northwestern Great Lakes region. Over the last 90 days, less than half of normal precipitation has fallen on most of the D1 areas in Michigan and Wisconsin while 50 to 70 percent of normal was measured across most other parts of the Great Lakes region, western Iowa, and eastern sections of Nebraska and Kansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The High Plains, Rockies, and Far West">
   <p>Although a potent storm plowed into the West on Tuesday and Wednesday, the bulk of this precipitation fell after Tuesday morning. For the previous 7 days, there were some areas of moderate to heavy precipitation, but the bulk of the region recorded only light to locally moderate amounts. At San Diego, 0.09 inch fell on October 17 after 182 consecutive days without precipitation, the longest since their records began in 1850. Elsewhere, between 1 and 4 inches fell on large parts of central and northwestern Montana, and in the coastal, east-central, and northern sections of California. As a result, D0 was eliminated in parts of these areas, and the D1 and D2 areas receded in some places. Farther north, similar 1- to 4-inch amounts were recorded in central and northwestern Montana, but with multi-year precipitation deficits still affecting much of the state, drought improvement was much more limited. D2 was eliminated in most of northwestern Montana, and the D2 through D4 areas all contracted slightly in scattered sections of central and southern Montana.</p>
   <p>Most other areas of dryness and drought from the Rockies westward received less than 0.5 inch, with slightly higher totals in parts of the Intermountain West and Great Basin still not enough to induce any tangible relief.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, 1 to 2 inches of precipitation eroded the extent of D0 and D1 conditions in northeastern Colorado, and scattered totals of 1 to 2 inches improved conditions to D1 in part of south-central South Dakota and north-central Nebraska.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
