<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20021031</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through November 9 that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: Over the next 5 days (October 31 - November 4), isolated rain and snow showers will have little effect on long-term precipitation deficits across the Rockies, Plains, Midwest, and East, while locally heavy rainfall will be largely confined to former drought areas in Deep South Texas. The return to an overall drier weather pattern will follow abundant October precipitation in many areas along and east of a line from the southern High Plains to the upper Midwest. Most of the West will remain cool and dry, while the remainder of the U.S. will also experience below-normal temperatures. The NWS 6 to 10-day outlook (November 5-9) calls for a continuation of below-normal temperatures across the eastern half of the U.S., but a return to near- to above-normal readings from the High Plains westward. Near- to below-normal precipitation is forecast across most of the U.S., excluding the Southeast, New England, the northern High Plains, and the Pacific Northwest. The onset of seasonal precipitation in the Northwest, though delayed, would provide a much-needed boost in soil moisture for winter grains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Mostly dry weather returned to areas from Oahu to Maui, following heavy showers the previous week that led to reductions in dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1). As a result, hydrological dryness (D0) remained confined to western Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England, Mid-Atlantic, Southeast, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Despite beneficial autumn precipitation, hydrological drought concerns persisted in many areas from Georgia to Maine. Through October 28, year-to-date precipitation deficits included 8.57 inches in Washington, D.C., 5.69 inches in Baltimore, Maryland, and 5.78 inches in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Since September 1, 2001, deficits in those three cities remained greater than one foot (16.80, 13.60, and 12.46 inches, respectively). Farther south, Atlanta, Georgia, received 12.07 inches of rain (176 percent of normal) from September 1 to October 28, but will still need 7.62 inches during the final 64 days of the year to avert its driest 4-year period on record (157.39 inches from 1893-96). A core region of moderate to severe hydrological drought (D1 to D2) stretches from northern and eastern Georgia to southeastern Pennsylvania and southern New Jersey, while a small wedge of extreme drought (D3) lingers across the western Carolinas. A secondary area of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) persists in northern Maine. Meanwhile, abnormal dryness (D0) was introduced across southern Puerto Rico, where rainfall since September 1 has totaled generally 50 to 60 percent of normal and below-normal precipitation has been observed since July.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley and Great Lakes">
   <p>Widespread showers erased abnormal dryness (D0) in parts of the Ohio Valley, but a broad area of moderate drought (D1) continued across northern Indiana, northern Ohio, and much of Lower Michigan. Coming off its driest September on record (0.29 inch), Flint, Michigan, netted only 1.27 inches of rain during the first 28 days of October. For the 58-day period ending October 28, precipitation included 2.59 inches (38 percent of normal) in South Bend, Indiana, and 1.56 inches (27 percent) in Flint.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and the West">
   <p>Widespread precipitation (rain, freezing rain, and snow) from southern Nebraska southward contrasted with mostly dry weather farther north. Erosion of dryness and drought was fairly significant on the central and southern Plains, with all categories (D0 to D4) receding northward and westward. Abnormal dryness (D0) was also removed from Deep South Texas, although recognition is given that the holdings of the international reservoirs on the lower Rio Grande remain very low. The U.S. share in the Amistad-Falcon system stood at 29 percent of conservation capacity on October 19, up from the August 1998 record low of 19 percent. Farther north, a sharp, early-season cold outbreak held late-October temperatures as much as 20 degrees F below normal on the northern Plains. Meanwhile west of the Rockies, a cool, mostly dry weather pattern led to little change in the overall drought picture, which includes a variety of agricultural, hydrological, and--in the Far West--wildfire concerns. Soil moisture shortages became more apparent in the Northwest, where winter wheat needed precipitation for germination and development. As of October 27 in Washington, topsoil moisture was reported by USDA as 66 percent very short to short, while subsoil moisture was 64 percent very short to short. September 1 - October 28 precipitation totals were as low as 0.05 inch (4 percent of normal) in Klamath Falls, Oregon, and 0.06 inch (4 percent) in Montague, California. Autumn precipitation was also well below normal in typically wetter coastal locations, such as Astoria, Oregon (2.05 inches, or 28 percent of normal, since September 1).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
