<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010920</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During September 19 - 24, a series of frontal systems will affect the eastern half of the United States, along with associated areas of rain. Showers will benefit areas from the Great Lakes eastward into the Northeast, providing some relief to areas experiencing D0 to D2 levels of dryness. Farther south into the Piedmont areas of the Carolinas, more scattered showers and thunderstorms will provide light to moderate precipitation amounts, easing dryness in these locations. A rich tropical airmass will reside across Florida, providing a recipe for almost daily scattered showers and thunderstorms as weakening frontal boundaries dissipate across the northern part of the state. Clusters of showers and thunderstorms may develop over the southern plains along the tail end of a frontal boundary, providing some needed rainfall in north Texas and Oklahoma. From the Rockies westward, little precipitation is expected during this period, with the exception of mainly light amounts along the coastal areas of Washington and Oregon. Looking ahead to September 25 -28, above normal precipitation is favored along the immediate Eastern Seaboard and along the Gulf Coast. Below normal precipitation is expected over a large area of the country west of the Mississippi, with only the Pacific Northwest having better odds for surplus rains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>The overall drought depiction remains unchanged this week, with precipitation amounts rather spotty and light from Kaui to Maui. Very little rainfall on the Big Island resulted in the slight eastward expansion of D0, as measurable precipitation was restricted mainly to the windward facing eastern third of the island. The islands will continue to be monitored for signs of deterioration or improvement as the wetter time of the year approaches for many areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast, Great Lakes Region, upper Mississippi Valley, and northern Plains">
   <p>Wet weather highlighted conditions during the past week across much of South Dakota, the eastern half of Nebraska and western Iowa, where many stations received 1 to3 inches of rain. These beneficial totals erased D0 over a good portion of South Dakota, with subsequent shrinkage of D0 in Nebraska and removal of D1 in the southeast tip of the Cornhusker state. A strong Canadian high pressure system pushed a rather vigorous cold front through the Ohio Valley, with showers and thunderstorms affecting a narrow swath from eastern Ohio, northern Pennsylvania eastward to the New York City metro area and the southern New England coast. This allowed for a slight reduction in D0 from northern New Jersey eastward across Long Island. Farther to the south, precipitation with the cold front was quite limited, allowing for D0 expansion into the District of Columbia, and D1 growth into north central Maryland. Little if any precipitation fell across upstate New York and the Adirondacks, prompting the introduction of D0 into this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Tropical Storm Gabrielle dumped heavy rains on the Florida peninsula, with widespread 4 to 6 inch amounts. The heaviest rain fell in the Tampa Bay area, and along the east coast from St. Augustine to Daytona Beach where locally 10 to12 inches were recorded. The recent deluge effectively eliminated the remaining vestiges of drought in south Florida. Farther to the north, a small area of D0 remained as lighter rains from Gabrielle, reflected in lower streamflows, continued to support a long term footprint of leftover hydrological drought. Across the Carolinas, spotty precipitation amounts affirmed the ongoing drought depiction, plus the expansion of D0 in the South Carolina low country, as river gauge data indicated a sharp decline in observed streamflow along the north and south forks of the Edisto River. In Georgia, D0 was also shifted farther south as precipitation since the beginning of August has been less than 50 percent of normal in these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Tennessee Valley area">
   <p>Clusters of showers and thunderstorms affected central and eastern Oklahoma during the past week, allowing for a westward trimming of D0 and D1 depictions. Continued dry conditions in parts of the Oklahoma panhandle and extreme north Texas resulted in expanded D1 into this area, as crops showed increased stress. Recent rains in deep south Texas increased topsoil moisture, although subsoil conditions remained quite dry so D1 continued in the Brownsville area. Across west Texas, spotty precipitation during the past week did little to alleviate ongoing severe drought conditions. Showers and thunderstorms that erupted in Middle Tennessee dumped locally 1 to 3 inch rainfall totals, allowing for the removal of some D0 near the Tennessee River. Farther east in Tennessee, recent dry weather across the Cumberland Plateau required the addition of D0 in this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>There was little overall change in conditions in the West over the past 7 days as little if any precipitation fell across Washington eastward into western Montana. A storm system provided only limited relief to the ongoing drought from southern Oregon and Idaho eastward into northwestern parts of Wyoming, with spotty precipitation amounts of one half to one inch. High fire danger remained a concern across interior sections of Washington, Oregon, the chimney of Idaho, western Montana and into California, although the total number of acres burned year to date was below the 10 year average.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
