<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040909</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather conditions that could have an impact on areas of drought or dryness across the United States over the next 2 weeks include: 1) mostly dry weather over California and the Southwest, with the West switching back to unseasonably cool weather by September 14; 2) generally above-normal rainfall across the Northwest, but most of the rain falling outside the current drought region; 3) above-normal precipitation across Montana and North Dakota during week 2, September 16-22.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Damp, cool weather reduced the fire danger across the state, shrinking the D1 area in the eastern interior basin. Weekly temperatures averaged 7 degrees F below normal in the eastern interior basin, and rainfall totaled as much as 3 inches in the Panhandle.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Recent below-normal rainfall has resulted in declining river flows and the introduction of D0 over the eastern part of the Big Island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>A cold front triggered heavy rains across the upper Midwest, including up to 4 inches on Minnesota during September 4-6, ending D0 dryness. Moderate rains over the northern lower peninsula of Michigan eliminated the dryness there. In Wisconsin, no more than light rains allowed some expansion of the D0 dryness area toward the southwest.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>The area of heavy rains that affected Minnesota extended southwestward into western Nebraska and southeastern Wyoming, with widespread amounts over 1 inch, and up to 3 inches in extreme northwestern Nebraska and adjacent South Dakota. On September 5, the 2.92 inches that fell in Chadron, Nebraska made this the wettest day since September 18, 1986. Drought generally improved by one category, from D3 to D2, in southwestern South Dakota, extreme western Nebraska, and southeastern Wyoming. Large precipitation deficits continued in the Nebraska Panhandle despite the recent rains, with Scottsbluff reporting a year-to-date total of 6.50 inches, which is 51 percent of normal. The moisture also eliminated D0 dryness in northeastern South Dakota and southeastern North Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>The remains of Hurricane Frances dumped heavy rains on Georgia and South Carolina on September 6-7, finally eliminating abnormal dryness that has lingered since spring. The storm dropped 5 to 8 inches of rain across much of Georgia. By Tuesday, rivers had exceeded flood stage in Georgia, the Carolinas, and large areas of Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>While all eyes were trained on Florida and Hurricane Frances, the circulation associated with an eastern Pacific Hurricane transported rainfall from eastern Arizona into western Colorado. One to 2-inch totals were common, with over 2 inches in parts of western Colorado. Unseasonably cold air allowed snowfall to accumulate over high elevations in the Rockies, including Colorado. The area of D2 and D3 drought receded slightly westward in western Colorado, while the D3 area retreated a short distance in southeastern Arizona. Elsewhere, outside of some 1-inch totals in northern Utah, weekly precipitation totals were generally light in the interior West, resulting in little change to the drought depiction. Dry weather resulted in high fire danger indices in California and the Great Basin. Warm, windy conditions helped to spread a large fire north of San Francisco, with the Geysers fire scorching over 12 thousand acres by September 7. Nevertheless, overall fire activity across the West was light.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
