<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080103</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>A series of upper-level troughs moved across the nation during this U.S. Drought Monitor week, generating weather systems that brought rain and snow to many areas.  Three major systems brought beneficial rain to the Southeast.  Drought expanded in a few parts of the northern and southern Plains as dryness persisted.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>For the period January 3-7, a strong upper-level trough will bring a series of Pacific weather systems into the western U.S.  Precipitation amounts of an inch or more are expected over much of the Rockies and Arizona highlands, with several inches of moisture over California and the western half of Oregon and Washington (amounting to several feet of new snow in the higher elevations).  Half an inch to an inch of precipitation is forecast for the intermountain basin.  It will be mostly quiet across the rest of the country with only the Great Lakes and southeast Florida expecting a few tenths of an inch of precipitation.  A cold front and low pressure system may bring precipitation to the Mississippi Valley by the end of this period.  Temperatures should average near to above normal for most of the country, but slightly cooler than average along the east and west coasts.</p>
   <p>For January 8-15, above-normal precipitation is expected from the Southwest to the Great Lakes, while the Gulf to mid-Atlantic coasts are forecast to average drier than normal.  The period should start out wet in the Pacific Northwest but dry out later.  Generally dry conditions are expected to continue across much of Alaska.  Warmer-than-normal temperatures are forecast east of the Rockies, while conditions should average colder than normal in the Far West and across Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The week was drier than normal across most locations in the southern half of Alaska.  D0 expanded into the interior southeast where mountain snowpacks and 90-day precipitation continued below normal.  An inch or less of rain fell across most of Puerto Rico this week, but December monthly totals were wetter than normal.  The rainfall pattern over the Hawaiian Islands was mixed this week, but, like Puerto Rico, for the month of December it was wetter than normal.  No changes were made in these areas this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Precipitation occurred across the Northeast D0 area, but amounts were generally an inch or less and not sufficient to erase longer-term deficits.  D0 remained across parts of Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island, reflecting lingering hydrological impacts.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and South">
   <p>Half an inch or more of precipitation fell over a few areas of the central Plains.  The snowfall over eastern Colorado was welcomed, but it was not enough to erase longer-term deficits.  D1 was expanded slightly in north central South Dakota to reflect growing deficits.  Two areas of D1 were added to southern Texas where precipitation for the last 4 months hovered around the 25 percent-of-normal mark or less, and D0 expanded westward in southern Texas.  The south Texas dryness, aided by windy conditions and above-normal temperatures, threatens the emergence of recently planted wheat and has increased the risk of wildfires.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, and Midwest States">
   <p>Two to 4 inches of rain fell in a huge band from southern Mississippi to eastern Virginia, bringing short-term relief to the Southeast drought areas.  Locally more than 4 inches were reported in parts of southern Alabama and Georgia, but the needed rains largely missed central and northern Alabama.  While beneficial, the rain was not sufficient to ease long-term deficits.  Tuscaloosa, AL, had a deficit of 31.02 inches for 2007 through December 30, or 46 percent of normal.  Anniston, AL, was down 29.39 inches for the year, or 43 percent of normal, and Huntsville was down 28.68 (50 percent of normal) resulting in the driest year on record.  Year-to-date deficits for 2007 were still 20 inches or more across most of Alabama, southern Tennessee, northwest Georgia, and parts of the Carolinas, and 12 inches or more across most of the Carolinas, Tennessee, and Mississippi, in spite of the recent rains.  Greenville-Spartanburg, SC, had the driest year on record with 31.08 inches of precipitation.  The week's rains benefited local water supplies in the region, with several reservoirs rising a foot or more in North Carolina, but it was not enough to ease water restrictions.  The increase at Falls Lake, north of Raleigh, added 2 weeks to the city's dwindling water supply, but the lake was still 8 feet below normal.  The two main water supplies for Durham now provide a water supply to 60 days, but Lake Michie was still almost 18 feet below capacity and Little River more than 24 feet below.</p>
   <p>D4 and D3 were contracted in the Carolinas, Georgia, and Alabama, and D2 and D1 were pulled back in South Carolina, Georgia, Alabama, and Kentucky.  D0 was sliced in Alabama and Kentucky, and D2 was dented in eastern Virginia.  The rain increased soil moisture and was very beneficial to agriculture, so generally the AH impacts designation was removed from areas receiving 2 inches or more.  This resulted in a contraction of the AH impacts area to basically central and northern Alabama.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Like last week, winter storms this week brought welcome rain and snow to many basins.  A few areas in the northern Rockies received an inch or more of moisture, but amounts were generally less than an inch with most areas less than half an inch.  The heaviest amounts of 5 inches or more, again, occurred over the drought-free parts of Oregon and Washington.  Continued low reservoirs, below-average mountain snowpack, and long-term precipitation deficits resulted in no change to the depiction in the West.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
