<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20090528</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>During May 19-25, a slow-moving, low pressure center continued to bring very heavy rains (weekly amounts up to 12 inches, and storm totals to 25 inches) that produced localized flooding, effectively putting a huge dent into the drought. By the weekend, the low finally tracked northwestward, moving into the central Gulf coast and later into the northern Delta. Even after the low moved away, scattered showers and thunderstorms continued across Florida. In the Four Corners region, unseasonably heavy rains during the pre-monsoonal dry season fell across Arizona, New Mexico, Utah and Colorado. Rains started early in the period and continued in earnest, with a slow northeastward movement.  Scattered showers and thunderstorms fell on the Great Plains, but drier and warmer weather prevailed across the Great Lakes region and New England. In the Far West, hot and dry weather was observed.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (May 28 – June 1) heavy rain (1 to 2 inches) is expected for southern Texas and most of Florida, with moderate rains predicted in the southern and central Rockies.  Light to moderate rains may fall across the Upper Midwest drought areas, with more significant rains (1-3 inches) forecast in the eastern Great Lakes region and Northeast. Unseasonably heavy rains (up to 0.5 inches) are anticipated in the D2 area of northeast California and northwest Nevada. Elsewhere, little or no rain is expected in the remainder of the West and northern and central Plains. Well above normal temperatures are predicted for the Northwest, with cooler than normal conditions across the Upper Midwest, Great Lakes region, and New England.</p>
   <p>The Climate Prediction Center 6-10 day forecast (June 2-6) indicates warmer than normal conditions in the Four Corner states, southern Plains, Washington state, and Alaska. Subnormal temperatures are predicted for the eastern third of the Nation.  Above normal precipitation is forecast for the Northwest and Southeast, with drier than normal weather expected in the Southwest, southern Plains, and eastern half of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>In Alaska, although stream flow levels are at near-record high levels due to rapid snowmelt and ice jams, precipitation has been lacking since April 1. During the past 60 days, precipitation deficits of 8 to 14 inches have accumulated along the southern Alaska coast from Cordova to Yakutat, and D1 was introduced.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, another week with little or no rain on both the windward and leeward sides of the Islands promoted all former non-dry areas (leeward sides of Oahu, Molokai, Maui and the Big Island) to D0.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Florida">
   <p>A rare, slow-moving May storm dumped widespread copious amounts of rainfall, especially on northeastern sections, dramatically easing the drought across the state.  Most of Florida received heavy rains (more than 4 inches) with locally up to 2 feet (25.49 inches at Ormond Beach, 23.75 inches at the Flagler County State Fairgrounds, and more than 21 inches at Daytona Beach) and a prolonged period of strong onshore winds.  Prior to this storm, south Florida had experienced one of its driest dry seasons (November 1-April 30) on record. The South Florida Water Management District reported the driest 6-month period since records began in 1932. West-central Florida was also gripped in drought and had enacted some of the tightest water restrictions in recent memory. The fire danger, which had been extremely high across central and southern Florida (KBDI 600-750, corresponding to extreme dryness) has greatly diminished (most locations now less than 100). Soils are completely saturated across northern and central Florida, and the widespread rainfall has sufficiently moistened soils and greened up vegetation (courtesy of Florida State climatologist David Zierden). Average stream flows, at record low levels two weeks ago, have undergone a major reversal with many now at record high levels. As of May 26, Lake Okeechobee was at 10.87 feet, up from 10.55 feet eight days ago, and still rising as swollen rivers over the Kissimmee River basin drain southward into it. As a result, widespread 1 to 2 category improvement was made throughout Florida. Exceptions included lingering D1(H) northwest of Lake Okeechobee where rainfall was at a minimum (2 to 3 inches) compared to surrounding areas, and extreme southern Florida where southern Miami-Dade County wells were still in the lowest tenth percentile and had yet to show significant recovery. After the data cutoff period, however, some wells had begun to quickly rebound.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast and Mid-Atlantic, and Carolinas">
   <p>In the eastern Great Lakes region, D0(A) was expanded northward and westward to Lakes Erie and Ontario due to a lack of rainfall (nine consecutive sunny and warm days) and minimal precipitation earlier in the month. Most of western New York has recorded under an inch of rain for May, and USGS average stream flows (1-, 7-, 14-, and 28-days) are in the lower twentieth percentile. Farther east, light scattered showers (0.5 to 1 inch, locally up to 2 inches) fell on  northeastern Pennsylvania and northwestern New Jersey, but long-term deficits (4 to 8 inches at 6 months) still remained, therefore so did D0(H). In North Carolina, little or no rain fell on the northeast portion of the state, maintaining D0(H). In contrast, 2 to 3 inches of rain fell on the southern Appalachians (from northeastern Georgia to northwestern North Carolina) providing additional relief from abnormal dryness in that region. Some D0(H) remained due to below normal lake levels in northeast Georgia and the western Carolinas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>In the north-central Great Plains, scattered showers and thunderstorms dropped 1 to 3 inches of rain on parts of southern and central Nebraska and eastern South Dakota, effectively removing the abnormal dryness in east-central and northeastern Nebraska.  This also prevented further northward and eastward expansion of D0 into eastern South Dakota and southwestern Minnesota.  In contrast, drier conditions (rain totals 0.1 to 0.4 inches) allowed for an increase in D0 into extreme eastern Nebraska and south-central South Dakota (Lyman and Jones counties).  No impacts were designated in this region as rapid progress of crop plantings occurred, but rainfall will be needed soon for emergence and crop establishment before topsoil moisture becomes critically deficient.</p>
   <p>Farther south, continued hit-and-miss showers and thunderstorms occurred across the southern Plains, with the heaviest rainfall amounts (1.5 to 3.5 inches) falling on parts of north-central, south-central, and extreme southern and southwestern Texas, and in southern Oklahoma. Accordingly, 1- to 2-category improvements (via Texas A&amp;M SPI blend synthesis) were made in southwestern Texas (Reeves, Loving, Jeff Davis, Ward, and Winker counties) and around the El Paso area; in central Texas, a 1-category improvement to D1 was made in Nolan, Taylor, Callahan, Coke, and Runnells counties; and in extreme southern Texas, an upgrade from D3 to D2 was made in Zapata, Starr, and Hidalgo counties.</p>
   <p>In northern Texas and the Oklahoma Panhandle, however, less than 0.5 inches fell, and combined with above-normal temperatures, conditions deteriorated.  In the southern Texas Panhandle, degradation to D1 occurred in Hockley, Lubbock, Crosby, Lynn, and Garza counties, while D1 was added to Oklahoma’s Texas County where another dry week occurred on top of a very dry season (less than 20 percent of normal past 30 days, and 60 percent of normal the last 90 days).  A slight expansion of D0 was also made across the Oklahoma Panhandle which has missed the heavy rains experienced by the rest of the State.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Low-level moisture and a slow-moving cold front brought unseasonably heavy, widespread showers and thunderstorms to much of the Four Corner States throughout the week, well before the typical onset of the Southwest monsoon (“non-monsoonal rains”). Weekly amounts generally ranged from 0.5 to 2 inches, with 2-4 inches reported in central Arizona, southeast Utah, western and central Colorado, and a few locations in southeastern New Mexico and west Texas. As a result, widespread 1- to occasionally 2-category improvements were made, especially where only short-term drought was previously indicated. This included removing D1(A) in northeastern Arizona and southwestern New Mexico, and splitting the D2(A) in southeast New Mexico in half where 1.5 to 2.5 inches of rain fell. In southwest New Mexico, a 2-category improvement was made as recent rains eliminated short-term deficits and instead created surpluses out to 90-days. In northern Arizona, May 22 rains at Holbrook totaled 3.50 inches breaking Holbrook’s previous wettest day (2.87 inches) on July 8, 1914. At Page, 1.84 inches of rain was the third highest daily total in the last half-century. What made these amounts unusual is that May is normally in the middle of Arizona’s dry season. Normal ANNUAL rainfall is 6.74 inches at Page and 9.20 inches at Holbrook. Additionally, improvements were made in Utah and Colorado, with only D0(H) remaining in southeast Colorado where D1 had been previously.  In contrast, drier weather in northeastern New Mexico (0.1 to 0.4 inches) expanded the D1(A) there.  Although the Far West was generally dry and unseasonably warm this week, no degradation was made as the long, normally dry summer season was underway, with plenty of time for additional deterioration.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Upper Midwest">
   <p>Dry and warm weather prevailed across southern and central Minnesota, and temperatures averaged 3-6 degrees F above normal as highs reached into the upper 90’s. Evaporative rates were also quite high as St. Paul Campus Observatory in Ramsey County recorded its third highest single day pan evaporation (0.63 inches on May 20) since records began in 1972. Accordingly, the dryness (D0 to D2) was expanded westward into south-central Minnesota, with D2 covering Anoka, Ramsey, Dakota and Washington Counties.  There is a benchmark lake (White Bear) in Washington County that is within 11 inches of its all-time record low from the drought of 1988. According to NASS/USDA, Minnesota top-soil moisture was 38 percent short or very short, good for farmers to make significant progress on corn and soybean plantings, but eventually becoming detrimental as the crops emerge and grow. In contrast, light to moderate (0.5 to 1.5 inches) rains fell further west and south, keeping abnormal dryness at bay in northern Iowa, southwestern Minnesota, and eastern South Dakota.  In northern Wisconsin and the western Upper Peninsula of Michigan, little or no precipitation fell again, slightly increasing D1-D2 across the region. In addition to USGS stream flows in the lower twenty-fifth percentile, a May 23 article in the Milwaukee Sentinel Journal stated that some lake levels in northern Wisconsin have fallen by as much as 8 feet from their highs, while others dropped to their lowest point in 70 years.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Anthony Artusa</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Matthew Rosencrans</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
