<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20081002</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>During this U.S. Drought Monitor (USDM) week, an upper-level disturbance brought beneficial rains to parts of the Southeast, then moved up the East Coast as a nor'easter.  A series of weak cold fronts moved across the Pacific Northwest states then into the northern Plains, Upper Midwest and East Coast.  Hurricane Kyle brought rain to parts of New England by the end of the week, and showers moistened southern Florida and extreme southern Texas.  Otherwise, dry high pressure dominated the country.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 6 days (October 1-6), a strong low pressure system and Pacific front will move into the western U.S., bringing cooler temperatures and rain, with possibly snow to the higher elevations.  An inch or more of moisture could be measured in some places.  The system will bring rain to the Plains near the end of the period.  In the meantime, an upper-level low over eastern Canada will bring continued showery weather to the Great Lakes and Northeast.  This low will move off the continent later in the period, leaving dry high pressure to dominate much of the eastern U.S.  Southern Florida could receive up to an inch of rain during the period from scattered showers and thunderstorms.</p>
   <p>The outlook for October 7-15 calls for wet weather in southern Florida, along the storm track in the northern tier states from the Pacific Northwest to the western Great Lakes, and in the Great Plains, with dry weather from the southern Appalachians to the Northeast.  Alaska is expected to be wet in the southeast and drier in the west.  Warmer-than-normal temperatures are forecast for the eastern half of the country, with below-normal temperatures expected in the West and across much of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The week was cooler and drier than normal across most of Alaska and drier than normal across eastern and north central Puerto Rico and most of the Hawaiian Islands.  No change was made to the D0 in Alaska.  Only a few stations in the northern Hawaiian Islands were wetter than normal, and streams averaged slightly to much below normal across most of the islands.  No change was made to the USDM depiction in Hawaii this week.  With heavy rains last week, the month ended wetter than normal along the southern coastal areas of Puerto Rico with near normal rainfall in the northern interior regions.   Streams were above normal across the island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes and Upper Midwest">
   <p>Frontal rains of 1-2 inches with locally heavier amounts fell from northeastern Kansas to western Lake Superior.  As a result, the spot of D2 in northern Minnesota was removed.  But rainfall was considerably less in central to southern Wisconsin.  D2 was added to east central Wisconsin to reflect significant 60-90 day rainfall deficits, dry soil moisture, and continued low streamflow.  The heavier rains missed Fairbault and Martin counties in south central Minnesota, where D2 was added over the areas with the greatest 60-90 day precipitation deficits.  D1 was expanded slightly in the adjacent north central Iowa counties.</p>
   <p>Scattered frontal showers dropped a few tenths of an inch of moisture over southern Indiana, but this was not enough to compensate for deficits which have built up over the last 60-90 days, so D0 expanded across southwest Ohio and much of southern Indiana.  The fronts fell apart as they moved across the lower Ohio and Tennessee valleys.  D2, D1, and D0 expanded across western Kentucky and central and western Tennessee where pasture and range land in poor to very poor condition increased over 10% this week, to 77% in Kentucky and 47% in Tennessee.  D1 expanded to cover the Guyandotte River counties in West Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Plains">
   <p>While only a few tenths of an inch of rain fell across northwest North Dakota this week, D1 and D2 were pulled back to reflect improving hydrologic conditions.  However, D1 expanded in Mercer County and D2 expanded in Bowman County in southwest North Dakota.  D0 was trimmed in southwest South Dakota to reflect improving hydrologic conditions.  In southeast South Dakota, D0 expanded to reflect deteriorating soil moisture conditions, but nearby D0-D1 was shaved under beneficial rains in Bon Homme County.</p>
   <p>Very little rainfall was reported in southwestern, central, and south central Oklahoma over the past 30 days.  Based on localized soil moisture deficits, D0 was introduced into several parts of the state, specifically central Oklahoma and along the Red River where soil moisture conditions were driest.  Meanwhile, the Oklahoma panhandle returned to the dry conditions it had experienced earlier this year, continuing drought designations there.</p>
   <p>In west Texas, the spot of D2 along the confluence of the High Plains, Edwards Plateau, and Trans Pecos regions was removed, and D1 and D0 trimmed back to reflect improving hydrologic conditions.  The last 2 weeks here have had no rain, but prior to that it has been wet.  Soil moisture conditions and precipitation for the last 30 to 90 days were wetter than normal, so improvement was shown.  To the southeast, the D3 oval in south central Texas expanded, as did D2 and D0 on its southern boundary.  September 2008 tied with 1931 as the third driest September since 1856 at the Austin City climate location, and September 2008 was the eighth driest since 1906 at Del Rio and ninth driest since 1871 at San Antonio.  The Austin City climate station recorded only 0.02 inch of rain this month.  The year-to-date ranked as the seventh driest January-September at Austin and fourteenth driest at San Antonio.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and East Coast">
   <p>Widespread 2+-inch rains fell across the East Coast from the Carolinas to Maine, with locally heavier amounts greater than 5 inches in places.  Improvement was made to the USDM depiction where streams responded to the heavy rains, including retreat of the D0 and D1 in the central Carolinas and south central Virginia.  Lesser rainfall amounts were measured in northeast North Carolina, but the amounts were enough to shrink the D0-D1-D2 there and in extreme southeast Virginia.  No change was made to the D2 areas of western North Carolina, where 3+ inches of rain fell, because hydrologic conditions failed to improve significantly (streamflows continued very low).  The heaviest rains largely missed the D0 from the Chesapeake to southern New Jersey and the D0-D1 in central to northwest Pennsylvania.  These areas were trimmed along the edges where 2+ inches of rain fell, but otherwise subsoil moisture remained deficient.</p>
   <p>Areas south and west of the Carolinas were left high and dry this week.  All of the Dx categories expanded in Georgia and Alabama, with D0 creeping into the Florida panhandle.  Streamflow, soil moisture, and pasture and range land conditions continued to deteriorate in these areas.  Augusta, Georgia recorded only 0.95 inch of rain (2.64 inches below normal) during September, Savannah, Georgia had only 1.42 inches (3.66 inches below normal), and Asheville, North Carolina only 1.70 inches (2.02 inches below normal).  In Alabama, September 2008 was the third driest September for Tuscaloosa (which had 0.60 inch of rain), sixth driest for Birmingham (0.40 inch), and eighth driest for Anniston (0.81 inch).  D0 was added to the Tampa Bay area of Florida where streams were low and deficits were accumulating in rainfall and soil moisture.  The Tampa weather station has received only 7.13 inches of rain during August and September, a departure of -7.01 inches (or 50% of normal), and the Tampa Bay area has an 8-12 inch deficit over the past three months.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>There were a few areas that received rainfall amounts of a few tenths, with an inch or more falling in northwest Washington.  But generally the week was dry.  No change was made to the depiction in the West.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
