<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001207</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features through mid-December that may affect the countrys drought areas include: 1) Tranquil weather should prevail across much of the Nation until this weekend; 2) A storm system dropping southeastward from Canada is forecast to drop light snow on the northern portions of the Rockies and Plains into the upper Midwest this weekend; 3) A second storm is forecast to develop in the central Rockies on Sunday and bring precipitation to the northern half of the Plains and western Corn Belt, and eventually the Great Lakes region, Ohio and Tennessee Valleys, and parts of the Delta and Southeast early next week. As the system progresses eastward, precipitation should also fall on the central Appalachians; 4) Significant precipitation should bypass drought areas of Texas and Florida through mid-week, and the sluggish start to the wet season in the Cascades and Sierra Nevada should continue well into next week; 5) no immediate relief is expected for both Puerto Rico and the leeward sides of the Hawaiian Islands.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>A relatively dry week across Hawaii, except for a few windward showers (0.5-1") on the Big Island early in the week and locally heavy showers (almost 4") across Kauai late in the week Since the islands received generous rains from late October into mid-November, this weeks dryness maintained the non-hydrological dryness (D0 and D1) on Molokai, Lanai, and western sections of Maui and the Big Island. In Puerto Rico, ever since Hurricane Debby dropped heavy rains on much of the island in late August, the northern and southwestern sections of Puerto Rico have measured subnormal precipitation, with 3-month totals under half of normal and accumulated deficits between 15 and 25 inches. Accordingly, abnormal dryness (D0) is introduced for the aforementioned portions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley and Mid-Atlantic Region">
   <p>Although light precipitation (0.1-0.5") fell on much of this region, it has not eased short-term deficits produced from a near-record dry October. Two-month percentages ranged between 25-75% of normal, with departures of -3 to -6 inches. Many streamflows in eastern Kentucky, southwestern Ohio, West Virginia, and Pennsylvania reflected this dryness as they continued to gradually drop below the 25th percentile. Short-term indicators suggested that abnormal dryness (D0) expanded across southern and eastern Kentucky and into central Pennsylvania.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Over the drought areas, only light snow (2 to 4 inches) fell on the Upper Peninsula of Michigan and most of Iowa (liquid equivalent: 0.1-0.3"), insufficient for drought amelioration. Much of Nebraska and the eastern thirds of Wyoming and Montana, however, received little or no precipitation as drought conditions persisted across these areas. Based upon the November indices, the D1 and D2 areas (in southern and western Iowa, respectively) were slightly adjusted (expanded) to reflect drier long-term indicators, while the hydrological designation in northwest Missouri was removed.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>After a very wet November, mostly dry and unseasonably cold weather enveloped the Southeast. The pause in precipitation halted additional reduction of dryness, although long-term hydrological drought persisted. In Florida, however, most of the state received less than 75% of normal November rainfall, with some southern locations recording under 25% as drought worsened across much of the state. Nearly 60% of the states 42 reporting streamflow levels were below the 10th percentile on Tuesday, including 26% at record low flows, according to the USGS. Additionally, the NRCS SCAN site at Sellers Lake, FL, although a sandy soil pedon, still measured only 1-3% of water by volume at the 2, 4, 8, and 20" soil depths, and 14% at 40"(45% is usually considered saturation). Accordingly, a new area of exceptional drought (D4) was centered near Orlando (Y-T-D precipitation of 28.79", 62% of normal, 17.55" deficit). Farther west, light precipitation (0.1 to 0.5") returned to southern Texas after a weeks respite, continuing a trend of wet weather since mid-September. Taking into account this and the latest November indices, D0(W) was removed from around the Del Rio vicinity as the areas long-term indicators were near-normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Weak storm systems brought light to moderate snowfall (liquid equivalents of 0.3-1.2") to most of the northern and central Rockies. Since October 1, SNOTEL basin average precipitation was close to or above 100% of normal in southwestern Montana, eastern Idaho, extreme northwestern Wyoming, and northeastern Utah, allowing for some removal of D0 in those regions. In contrast, little or no snow fell on north-central Montana, keeping drought intact. Subnormal precipitation continued in the Cascades and Sierra Nevada as SNOTEL basin averages remained between 40-60% of normal; however, impacts remained negligible with at least 4 more months remaining in the wet season (November-March).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
