<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050728</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>No relief is found in the 28 July - 1 August forecast for the drought areas in the Mississippi Valley and Central Plains as little to no rain is expected over Illinois, Missouri, and Kansas over the next 5 days.  Expect dry conditions to persist in the Pacific Northwest as well with above normal daytime temperatures and lack of rain in the forecast.  Very little to no rain is projected for the southern tip of Texas as well.  Plenty of rain, however, is anticipated across the Southeast, in particular the Atlantic Coast States from Georgia to Virginia, where below normal daytime temperatures will also occur.</p>
   <p>For 2 August to 8 August there may be some relief in the Pacific Northwest with above normal precipitation forecasted for Washington, northern Idaho, and Montana.  But, expect above normal temperatures throughout Montana.  Hot and dry conditions are still expected to persist over the Central Plains and Middle Mississippi Valley.  The Southwestern Monsoon is expected to continue to bring scattered showers to portions of the Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes were made to any of these areas this drought monitoring period. Alaska is just beginning to indicate short-term dryness and may be an area to watch in the next coming weeks. Month-to-date precipitation was a mixed signal over Hawaii. Precipitation amounts were not substantial enough to warrant improvements in the abnormally dry areas. Puerto Rico is beginning to show some dryness in the long-term indicators, but recent rainfall amounts have been high enough to leave status quo this period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Small amounts of spotty precipitation occurred in this region during this weeks drought monitoring period. Coupled with high temperatures, rainfall amounts were not substantial enough to remove the D0As in the Northeast or at the North Carolina - Virginia border.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes, Ohio Valley and Mississippi Valley">
   <p>During this drought monitoring period, impacts were changed throughout this entire region from A to AH to reflect dryness that has persisted over the long-term (6 months) as well as hot temperatures the area has seen during this week. Changes to this weeks depiction include the severe drought areas in Upper Michigan and the northeastern corner of Lower Michigan being expanded. These areas did not receive the heavy amounts of rainfall that impacted most of the Great Lakes region. Both areas are still indicating dryness out to the 30-day percent of normal map as well as showing up dry in the Climate Prediction Centers (CPC) soil moisture map.  All categories in southern portions of Lower Michigan had improvements during the period, ridding the southern part of the state of D2 and leaving a strip of D1 along the shoreline. These changes are supported by radar estimate totals of 2 to 4 inch rains over the period and also by the Midwest Regional Climate Centers (MRCC) and CPCs soil moisture maps.</p>
   <p>In the Ohio Valley, several changes were made this period to account for the heavy rainfall that affected the area during this drought monitoring period. In Ohio, abnormally dry conditions were retracted slightly westward removing dry conditions from West Virginia; ACIS 30- and 60-day percent of normal maps and the CPC soil moisture map show improvements in this area. In Indiana, the abnormally dry area in the southern half of the state was retracted to indicate improvements in soil moisture and streamflow reports due to this periods rainfall event depositing up to 2 inches.</p>
   <p>In Wisconsin, the southwestern area of D2 was retracted due to local reports of recent rainfall totals of 4 to 8 inches and also to reflect improvements shown on the CPC and the MRCC soil moisture maps. Heavy rainfall affected southeastern areas of Minnesota, leading to a retraction of moderately dry and abnormally dry conditions eastward. In Iowa, D0, D1 and D2 were expanded westward in southeastern parts of the state that were missed by the heavy rainfall event that took place early in the period. CPC soil moisture map along with the MRCC's 12 and 72 inch soil moisture maps, blends and 7-, 30-day percent of normal maps also support this expansion.</p>
   <p>Illinois had a mixed precipitation pattern this drought monitoring period. While some areas received heavy rainfall, other areas were largely missed. In the eastern part of the state a small area of D3 and D2 was retracted in climate division 5 due to station reports of over 4 inches of rainfall. In the western and central parts of the state, D3 was expanded to the southwest connecting with the expansion of D3 in Missouri. According to media reports, Illinois Governor Rod Blagojevich sent a request to the USDA on Monday the 25 th, requesting all 102 counties in Illinois receive federal disaster aid. More than 117,000 farmers statewide have reported crop production losses with 16 of those reporting a total loss. A near-record dry period from March to June stunted crop growth during months when crops were pollinating and moisture was absent. Also in Missouri, officials are considering sending in a request for all counties in their state to receive aid as well, they hoped possibly by the end of this week a decision will made whether or not they will need to make the request. Changes in Missouris drought depiction this period include the moderate and severe drought areas being expanded westward to account for the local reports of agricultural impacts and the long-term deficits reported in several time frames of the High Plains Regional Climate Centers (HPRCC) ACIS percent of normal maps. The heat wave that moved through both areas has proved to be too much for the crops to withstand. Columbia, Missouri reported a high temperature of 105 degrees on Sunday the 24 th coupled with minimal amounts of moisture, 0.08 inch of rainfall since June 14, 2005. This area is one to watch in the coming weeks for worsening conditions if current situation continues.</p>
   <p>In Arkansas, moderate and severe drought areas in the northwestern corner were expanded based on local reports of minimal rainfall amounts this drought monitoring period.  Also, several cities have imposed water bans in efforts to conserve for the remainder of the dry period. Harrison is currently experiencing their 5 th driest year to date and 2 nd driest Spring on record. The D1 and D2 areas in the southeastern corner of the state were expanded westward. Other changes in the region include an extension of abnormally dry conditions further south in western Mississippi. All changes were based on below normal rainfall and hot temperatures, the CPC blends, ACIS 7-day and 30-day percent of normal maps and CPCs soil moisture map.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Rocky Mountains and West">
   <p>In Nebraska, the abnormally dry area in climate division 2 was expanded northward, leaving just a small strip of no drought along the Nebraska and South Dakota border where locally heavy rains fell this period. Elsewhere in Nebraska, the tongue of D1 in the southeastern part of the state was retracted slightly westward due to heavy rainfall. The D1 was also expanded northward into climate division 5, based on minimal rainfall amounts, hot temperatures and high winds. In South Dakota, the no drought donut hole was expanded towards the northwest based on radar reports of 2 to 4 inches of rainfall. Also in South Dakota, the D2 was retracted slightly in the southwest corner based on local reports and several time frames of the ACIS percent of normal maps indicating moderate improvements in that area. In Kansas, the D0 area was expanded southward into the northern part of climate division 8 based on low streamflow reports and low to zero precipitation falling this period.</p>
   <p>In Texas, the extreme drought area remaining in the southern tip was upgraded to D2 along with all other drought areas in the southern part of the state which were affected by Hurricane Emily rainfall amounts from 2 to 4 inches. While this is a substantial amount of precipitation, rains were not enough to warrant further improvements at this time. Brownsville is still reporting only half of the normal precipitation for year-to-date. This area of southern Texas is an area to watch in coming weeks in hopes of the longer-term deficits improving. Elsewhere in Texas, a small area of D0 was extended from New Mexico into southern portions of climate division 5. This area received no rainfall this period and dryness is evident on ACIS 7-day to 60-day percent of normal maps.</p>
   <p>In Arizona, abnormally dry conditions were expanded to cover most of the western half of the state with the exception of the southwestern corner to account for recent fire activity reports by the National Interagency Fire Center (NIFC) and also based on 7- to 60-day percent of normal maps. The spotty, slow starting monsoon produced a few areas of above normal rainfall but the majority of the state remained dry.  Also in Arizona, the D1 in the southeastern corner of the state was expanded eastward to include remaining areas of climate division 7 based on below normal rainfall and local reports of agricultural impacts and low streamflow. A new impacts line was added into Arizona this week, delineating the H and AH impacts being felt at this time in the state. In Colorado, abnormally dry conditions were expanded to cover most of the eastern half of the state. This introduction was based on CPCs blends, local reports of hot temperatures and minimal amounts of rainfall. An agricultural impacted notation was also made to account for short-term dryness.</p>
   <p>Montana received very low amounts of precipitation and has also been experiencing above normal temperatures during this drought monitoring period.  Reports from the NIFC indicate fire activity has increased during this period.  Changes made in Montana were moderate. The D1 area in the north central region of the state was expanded northward into climate division 3 and the southern area of severe drought was expanded into climate division 5 based on ACIS 14-day to 60-day percent of normal maps and local reports of worsening conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Jess Enloe</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
