<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070802</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Temperatures were at or below normal for much of the United States this last week, with the northern High Plains and the West recording temperatures that were 4 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit above normal.  Precipitation was varied, with local reporting stations observing over 2 inches in some places.  The monsoonal rains were going strong over much of the Southwest, with welcomed rain</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (August 2-6), temperatures over the northern Rocky Mountains, High Plains, Ohio River Valley, Mid-Atlantic and New England are expected to be well above normal.  Temperatures are expected to be 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal, with the area around the Great Lakes experiencing the warmest temperatures.  Temperatures are expected to be cooler than normal over much of the Southwest and Gulf Coast, where rains are forecasted to continue.  Precipitation should continue in the Southwest with the monsoonal flow, and active conditions over the Southeast will hopefully provide relief from the drought conditions.  Precipitation maxima over the next several days are centered over southern Arizona, west Texas, Colorado, Nebraska, Wisconsin, Maine, the Florida panhandle and southern Georgia.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlook (August 7-11) has a trough over the western United States with ridging over the Midwest.  Temperatures are expected to be above normal for most of the country, except over the West Coast.  Precipitation will likely continue in the Southwest and be above normal over the High Plains and northern Rocky Mountains.  Below-normal precipitation is projected over much of California and Nevada and through much of the Southeast, Mid-Atlantic and northern New England.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="The High Plains">
   <p>The northern High Plains recorded temperatures 6-8 degrees Fahrenheit above normal this week, and little or no rain.  Very localized heavy rains fell across Wyoming, Nebraska, and Kansas.  In Nebraska and Kansas, the D0 conditions were improved as recent rains helped to make up precipitation deficits rapidly.  Wyoming and Nebraska had some improvement of D1 with the help of the recent rains.  In the Dakotas, intensification of the dryness was widespread.  After a very wet spring, conditions have dried out rapidly in eastern South Dakota, northwest Iowa, and southwest Minnesota, with some stations not recording any precipitation since late June.  Several recording stations in eastern South Dakota have had record low rainfall for July, several coming in at less than 0.25 inches for the month.  Hawarden, Iowa, had no rain in July while Centerville, South Dakota, had only a trace.  The flash drought has prompted the expansion of D2 over much of eastern South Dakota, with damage to crops and cattle deaths prominent over the area.  In western South Dakota, an intensification of the current drought has allowed D2 to expand to the east.  North Dakota saw an expansion of D0 conditions in the southwest part of the state as dryness in the region has spread, with impacts to crops starting to develop.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>The dryness observed in eastern South Dakota is also impacting Minnesota.  Precipitation during the growing season has been below 50 percent for much of the state, impacting the agricultural industry.  D1 and D2 conditions were expanded over much of southern Minnesota this week. Recent dryness has also allowed D0 to expand through Missouri to Illinois and in the northern portions of lower Michigan.  D2 conditions have migrated north in Indiana and into southwest Michigan.  Scattered rains this last week have allowed for improvements in Ohio and Kentucky.  In Ohio, the D1 was reduced in central Ohio to the northern portions of the state.  In Kentucky, D2 conditions were improved to D1 in the northern portions of the state, but D1 and D2 conditions expanded in western Kentucky.  D1 conditions also spread into Wisconsin and Michigan along the shores of Lake Michigan, as dryness over the last few months has impacted these regions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Temperatures were near normal over much of the region, with portions of upper New England above normal.  Precipitation was varied and widely scattered.  Drought areas that did receive rain did not observe enough to warrant any changes.  D2 was expanded in Maryland, Virginia, and Delaware as dryness over the last 90 days is below 25 percent for much of the Delmarva region. Most agricultural producers in the region have commented that even with rain now, yields are going to be substantially lower than average.  D2 conditions were improved in western Virginia, where recent rains have helped conditions.  D0 conditions were expanded into southern New Jersey this week while D1 conditions in portions of West Virginia were improved to D0.  D1 in western New York was expanded because of the recent dryness along the lake plains region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>With scattered rain last week in the Southeast, drought conditions did not improve, but instead expanded in some areas.  Even with recent rains, many recording stations were below normal for July.  Mississippi is a good example of conditions in the Southeast: the last 30-day period is one of the wettest on record, but the last 180-day period is the driest on record.  D3 and D4 conditions in Alabama also expanded to cover much of the northern and central portions of the state while D3 conditions expanded in southwest Georgia.  D2 and D3 conditions expanded to include western Tennessee and into eastern Arkansas.  North Carolina saw an expansion of D1 to cover the southern part of the state and D2 expanded in the west.  Near record low streamflow and reservoir levels are a big concern in North Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Dry and mainly hot conditions dominated the week in the western United States.  The seasonal monsoon rains started in Arizona, with relief from the heat along with widely scattered precipitation.  Drought status was maintained this week, as the effects of the recent wet pattern were not known at this time.  If the pattern continues, changes in the Arizona drought status should be warranted.  In Idaho, the areas of D2 in the south were expanded north with regard to the very low streamflow conditions in several basins that are close to record low levels.  The record-breaking heat continued in Idaho, as Pocatello recorded the warmest July on record, with records going back to 1939.  For Montana, the recent heat has really taken a toll on crops around the state as well as water supplies.  D2 was expanded in northern Montana from the Idaho border and to the east as well.  Two pockets of D1 in Utah were removed in favor of D2 conditions that cover almost the entire state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
