<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20031009</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may have an impact on dryness or drought areas during the next 2 weeks: 1) Over the next 5 days, October 9-13, tropical moisture streaming northward from Mexico should deliver from 0.25 to over 1.0 inch of rain to eastern Arizona and much of New Mexico, west Texas, Oklahoma, and Kansas; 2) From 0.5 to 2.0 inches of rain will fall over western Washington in the next 5 days, but most of the interior West outside of Arizona and New Mexico will see below-normal rainfall and above-normal temperatures over the next 2 weeks; 3) Below-normal rainfall is expected in the Minnesota-Iowa-Wisconsin area over the next 2 weeks.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>There was no change in the D1 to D2 drought over Hawaii and the D0 dryness in southeastern Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region and Middle Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Rain or snow across Michigan and eastern Wisconsin resulted in D1 and D0 retreating so that most of lower Michigan improved one category to D0 and normal conditions extended into northeast Wisconsin. The area of D2 drought in west-central Minnesota has been reconfigured to conform with soil moisture reports. D2 drought persisted from southeastern Minnesota into much of Iowa and northwest Missouri, as this region saw little rain this past week. D3 drought persisted in extreme southeastern Minnesota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Another 1 to 2 inches of rain over large parts of Maine eliminated the lingering area of dryness. Most wells and streams are now at normal or above-normal levels, and soil moisture is ample. Plentiful rains also eliminated the D0 area in northern parts of New York and Vermont.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>One-half to 1-inch rains led to some retreat of D0 and D1 areas in south-central Kansas and northeastern Oklahoma. Soil moisture remains very low in northern and western Kansas, with topsoil moisture rated 89 percent short to very short in the northwest crop district. To the north, warm, dry weather led to expansion of D1 across far western North Dakota and slight northward expansion of D2 in north-central South Dakota. Lake Oahe in northern South Dakota tied its record low elevation at 23 feet below normal levels.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Although short-term dryness has reduced soil moisture in parts of the Southeast, especially in Georgia, where state topsoil moisture was rated 56 percent short to very short, adverse impacts have not been widespread, and no areas of D0 or worse are being depicted at this time.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Warm, dry weather caused a slight westward extension of D2 and D1 in Washington and Oregon, but there was overall little change in the western drought situation. Showers in New Mexico, Arizona, and Utah delivered spotty short-term relief, but much more precipitation is needed to relieve water shortages in the region. Near-normal summer rains in addition to over 0.5 inches in the past week resulted in a D3 to D2 improvement in northwest New Mexico. In southern Utah, the elevation of Lake Powell was nearly 90 feet below levels typical for October.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
