<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061116</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Next week, precipitation is expected to occur mainly in the Northwest and Northeast; the remainder of the country should stay mostly dry.  Maximum temperatures are expected to be below average from the Southeast northward along the Appalachians into the eastern Great Lakes region.  The rest of the country should experience warmer-than-average maximum temperatures.  Minimum temperatures are expected to be above average throughout most of the country except for the Southeast, where they are expected to be below average.</p>
   <p>During the ensuing week, precipitation is expected to continue to be above average in the Northwest.  Except for the Great Lakes region, below-average precipitation is expected from the Rockies eastward to the Atlantic; the driest areas are expected to be in the central Plains.  Average precipitation is expected for the Great Lakes.  Temperatures are expected to be above average in the western two-thirds of the country, with the highest temperatures in the central Rockies.  Below-average temperatures are expected east of the Appalachians from the mid-Atlantic region to the eastern Gulf Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Summary">
   <p>This weeks Drought Monitor has only a few changes from last week.  In South Carolina, persistent dryness in the Savannah River Basin led to intensifying the drought category to D1; the impact in this area is mainly hydrological.  In Minnesota, the D0 area of abnormal dryness has been extended southward and westward in response to minimal precipitation over the last 30 days.  In Oklahoma, continued dryness resulted in a southward and slightly westward expansion of the northern D3 area.  Since the crop seasons are ending in many parts of the country, the impacts of drought are now mostly hydrological.</p>
   <p>Although the drought intensities were not changed or introduced on this weeks map, areas that are being closely monitored for changes include California, where dryness is increasing; Florida, where dryness has been persistent; and Montana, where precipitation events have been increasing in number and intensity.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Ned Guttman</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Liz Love-Brotak</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
