<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20031204</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may have an impact on abnormally dry or drought areas during the next 5 days (Dec. 3-7) include: 1) Another Pacific storm system that should drop precipitation on the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies, and possibly on parts of the Great Basin and central Rockies, somewhat similar to this weeks precipitation pattern. 2) The rest of the West, Plains, and upper Midwest should experience light or no precipitation.</p>
   <p>The 6- to10-day outlook for December 9-13 calls for below-normal temperatures across the southern Rockies and Plains, with warmer-than-normal conditions across the northern tier of States, Ohio Valley, and the mid-Atlantic. Unfortunately, the greatest likelihood for significant precipitation is expected to occur in non-drought areas (Delta and Southeast), while drier-than-normal weather is forecast in the northern and central Rockies, northern Plains, and upper Midwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>A strong cold front, enhanced with tropical moisture, dumped copious showers on most of Hawaii during late November into early December. Selected 72-hour (8 am HST Nov. 29 to 8am HST Dec. 2) totals on each island included: Kauai---Kokee 5.22", Lihue Airport and Kapahi 3.83", and Wailua 3.74"; Oahu---Luluku 15.30", Ahuimanu Loop 14.96", Wilson Tunnel 14.70"; Molokai---Makapulapai 4.98", Kamalo 3.71"; Lanai---Lanai City 1.69"; and Maui---Kaupo Gap 4.04", Mahinahina 2.37", Ulupalakua 2.33". Isolated, heavy showers also fell on Maui Nov. 28-29, including 9.06" at West Wailuaiki, 4.63" at Oheo Gulch, and 1.54" at Hana. The rains were widespread and heavy enough to provide a one category improvement on Oahu, Maui, and Lanai (from D1 to D0), and on western Molokai (from D2 to D1). However, D2 persisted over western Kona (Big Island), which missed the heaviest rains (3-day totals were generally between 0.25 to 1.25 inches).</p>
   <p>Light weekly precipitation (0.1-0.3 inches interior, 0.5-2 inches along the coast) that was near to below normal, failed to eliminate the area of abnormal dryness (D0) in southeastern Alaska. In addition, temperatures averaged 5 to 15F below normal, with lows dropping to -31F at Northway and -35F at Minchumina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Three straight weeks of moderate to heavy rain (this week, 2-5 inches on November 27-28) eliminated D0 dryness in southern Louisiana. In Wisconsin, although mostly dry this week, surplus precipitation during 4 of the 5 previous weeks (late October-late November) produced delayed moisture improvements, including above-normal 7-day averaged streamflows ending Dec. 1, 30- and 90-day surpluses of 2-4 inches, and normal to moist short and long-term drought indices. As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) was removed in south-central Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, little or no precipitation fell across the Plains and upper Midwest, maintaining drought and dryness from northern Texas northward into the Dakotas and Minnesota. According to a Nov. 12 press release by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Lake Sakakawea (western North Dakota) and Lake Oahe (central Dakotas), both part of the upper Missouri River, continued to drop in response to long-term drought throughout its runoff basin and upstream. Lake Sakakawea fell one foot in both October and November, and started December 19 feet below normal, and 7 feet lower than last year at this time. Lake Oahe dropped 3 feet in October, falling 2.5 feet below its record low set in November 1989, or about 23 feet below normal. Ft. Yates, ND abruptly lost its water source in late October due to dropping levels on the Missouri River. It has since been restored, but the town is under a boil order as their intake was silted.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>An active Pacific jet stream brought frequent storm systems to the Pacific Northwest, dropping between 2 and 8 inches of precipitation from coastal Washington and Oregon eastward into the Cascades and on northwestern California, but the heaviest rain and snow mostly fell outside the drought areas. An exception was in northern Idaho and the immediate surrounding areas, where 2-4 inches fell. Moderate precipitation has fallen each week since mid-October, generating basin-averaged precipitation (since Oct. 1) between 115-130% and snow water content between 120-130%. And, all the individual short and long-term blend components depicted normal or moist conditions, hence the reduction from D2 to D1(H) in the Idaho Panhandle. Elsewhere in the interior West, precipitation was generally light or non-existent, maintaining drought conditions. Another example of water concerns in the West is Lake Mead on the Colorado River mainstem, southern Nevadas main water source. According to NASAs Earth Observatory article, Lake Mead has dropped 60 feet since 2000, and is forecasted to drop another 15-20 feet by next year at its current usage and recharge rates. Currently at 1,139.45 feet elevation (max=1,229 feet), the forecasted drop would bring Lake Mead near the 1,125 foot level where mandatory drought emergency restrictions begin. The all-time record low elevation occurred in 1965 at 1,100 feet.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
