<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20101007</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>The combination of Tropical Storm Nicole and a slow moving cold front brought significant drought relief along the Eastern Seaboard, from South Carolina to Maine.  Locally intense precipitation totals for the week amounted to 15 to 20 or more inches in North Carolina and Virginia.  The heaviest rainfall was measured from the Chesapeake Bay south through eastern North Carolina, and a tight gradient developed between the coast and inland areas that received more rainfall.  Major flooding caused several deaths in North Carolina, as well as damage to agricultural fields.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>In the near term, lingering remnants of the western US trough will continue to bring scattered showers across the Great Basin.  The Pacific Northwest is projected to have a rainmaker system come onshore around October 8.  As the cold front in the east moves offshore, dry conditions will take over, and may help in any flood recovery efforts.  In the extended outlook for the next six to ten days, cooler temperatures are projected to prevail in the Atlantic states from Massachusetts to Florida.  Warmer temperatures than normal will settle in California and the northern states from Washington to Wisconsin.  Across the contiguous US, below average precipitation is expected for the bulk of the states, with some exceptions for northern Montana and the Northeast.</p>
   <p>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: http://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Great Lakes">
   <p>Areas of northern and central Ohio received some beneficial rains that sufficiently improved their region to drought-free conditions.  Local reports indicate that along the Ohio shoreline of Lake Erie, weekly rainfall totals of three to five inches were common.  Additionally, a lack of reported impacts and positive observations of field conditions contributed to an increased area of no drought in the Buckeye State.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, a refinement of the depiction in Kauai led to much of the higher elevations being upgraded to D0 or D1.  The lower elevations in the southeastern part of the island remain in extreme drought.  On the Big Island, there were some modest improvements in the west due to September rainfall.  And on Oahu, the last two weeks have brought beneficial wetness to remove any abnormally dry conditions on the northeastern slopes.  Kappapala Ranch in the southeast is still in the midst of exceptional drought, being on track for their driest year on record.</p>
   <p>Alaska and Puerto Rico had no change in drought conditions this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Widespread and significant improvements across the region due to Tropical Storm Nicole resulted in one to two category changes in the drought depiction this week.  A large north to south swath of no drought now exists from the Vermont and New Hampshire to the Chesapeake Bay.  The storm track brought the heaviest rains inland, so some areas of abnormally dry and moderate drought remain in New Jersey, Connecticut and Maine.  Hydrological and agricultural impacts are still being felt, despite the recent precipitation, and impact lines are depicted accordingly.  Storm totals of two to four inches were common in Pennsylvania, with locally higher rainfall in the four to seven inch range.</p>
   <p>Two category improvements, from severe drought to no drought, were made on the map this week from Maryland southward to North Carolina.  The relatively narrow band of heavy rainfall left coastal areas in lingering drought, as well as the Appalachian mountains to the west.  Many observations of four to eight inches of rain in the Washington, DC area were reported.  Portneys Overlook in St. Mary’s county on the Eastern Shore had as much as 14 inches of rain over the two-day period of September 30 to October 1.  Further south, Trent Woods, NC reported 20.26 inches of rain over the two days, and most other observers in Craven and Pitt counties measured more than 15 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Precipitation deficits and increasing wildland fire risk were contributing factors in expanding areas of severe drought in Florida and Alabama.  In addition, agricultural impacts are being noted in the region due to the extended dry period this growing season.  Along the Atlantic coast of Florida, moderate drought, D1, was expanded from the Georgia border to Orange county.  A new area of severe drought (D2) was introduced on the map in northeastern Florida, where impacts on water resources and agriculture have been particularly acute.</p>
   <p>In the Florida panhandle, concern is mounting with each week of dry conditions.  Areas of D1 and D2 were expanded to reflect long-term deficits in precipitation, which has also been reflected in other drought indices.  Nearby counties in Alabama are also included in severe drought.  Agriculture reports of a potentially poor peanut harvest have supported this depiction.  Lines designating these and areas hydrological impacts in the region are depicted on the map.</p>
   <p>Southwestern Louisiana has been lagging behind normal precipitation for several weeks.  In the last 30 to 60 days, rainfall deficits have been steadily increasing.  This week, extreme drought is shown in this region to reflect the impacts and low stream flow measurements of five to ten percentile for the last week and month.  Lake Charles is about 19 inches below normal precipitation for the year so far, and Alexandria airport had its driest September on record.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Most of this region remained unchanged from last week.  A small area of moderate drought, D1, was expanded in northeastern Colorado to reflect rainfall deficits over the last two months. Reports of poor rangeland conditions around the area were a factor as well.  This area has been slowly degrading recently, with scattered convective storms that have helped keep local areas in an abnormally dry state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
