<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061130</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>A large, moist weather system moving over the central part of the country November 28 and 29 will move across then exit the eastern U.S. during the next 5 days (November 30-December 4) and be followed by generally dry weather. Temperatures will average above normal in the eastern U.S. ahead of the weather system and below normal across the western and central U.S. beneath the upper-level trough. Pacific storm systems will brush southern Alaska but the rest of the state is expected to remain drier than normal.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for December 4-8 calls for above-normal precipitation across Alaska and the southern Plains States, and below-normal precipitation across the western and north central U.S. and southern Florida. Temperatures are expected to be above normal across Alaska and below normal across most of the contiguous States.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The rainfall pattern across Hawaii this Drought Monitor week was mixed, with some stations wetter than normal and others drier than normal. Stations across Kauai were persistently dry for the last 90 days, but no changes were made to Hawaii. Dry conditions continued this week across much of Alaska, contributing to an unusually dry November-to-date. However, no change was made to the depiction due to the generally wet conditions of October. Rainfall in Puerto Rico was generally an inch or two, but many stations received considerably less, especially over the D0 areas, so no change was made to the depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>A cold front and associated precipitation was approaching the area at the end of the Drought Monitor week. However, persistent dryness over the past several weeks, worsening modeled soil moisture conditions, and, in central Oklahoma and northern Texas, persistent low reservoirs resulted in expansion of some drought areas this period. According to local reports, in central and southern Texas, the combination of strong winds and above-normal temperatures has caused great deterioration in drought conditions. Numerous stock ponds have gone dry, most reservoir levels were very low, and streamflows were near zero. D3 and D4 expanded eastward and slightly northward along the Kansas-Oklahoma border, the D0-D3 in southern Texas and the D3 in northern Texas were expanded eastward, D1-D3 in west central Texas were expanded westward, the D3 areas in northern and southern Texas were merged across central Texas, and D4 in northern Oklahoma was tweaked eastward.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>D0 was contracted over southern Mississippi where November rains improved long-term conditions. Half an inch to an inch of rain fell across parts of Georgia and South Carolina early this Drought Monitor week, resulting in the contraction of D0 and D1 in those 2 states. The rain missed Florida, where month-to-date and year-to-date deficits continued to grow, and streamflow and modeled soil moisture percentiles were low. The Suwannee River Water Management District in northern Florida issued a Phase I Water Shortage Advisory on November 16, asking all residential, commercial, agricultural and industrial water users to voluntarily reduce water consumption through conservation measures. D2 was added in northeastern Florida generally east of Interstate 75, and D0 expanded in southeastern Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West, Great Basin, and Rockies">
   <p>Dry conditions in northwestern Colorado have caused a poor hay and wheat crop this year. There are few weather stations in the area, but recent satellite-based drought indices (VegDRI) show serious drought across much of Moffat County. Based on SNOTEL snow water equivalent reports, mountain snowpack in northwestern Colorado and nearby Utah was below normal for the start of this snow season. Precipitation circulating around a low pressure system at the end of the Drought Monitor period was falling along the southwestern slopes of the Colorado mountains, but away from Moffat County. So D0 and D1 in southern Wyoming were extended into northwestern Colorado and adjacent northeastern Utah.</p>
   <p>D2 was extended into southeastern Wyoming based on recent (60-90 day) dryness. Abundant Pacific moisture fell across parts of northern California. Southern California remained dry; however, this area normally has an arid climate and it is early in the winter wet season, so no change was made to the depiction in California this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Ned Guttman</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
