<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080821</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (through August 25), the fate of the southeastern drought will depend largely on the track of Tropical Storm Fay.  As of 2 pm (EDT), August 20, the official forecast from the National Hurricane Center took Fay on a mostly westward path across northern Florida into southern portions of Alabama and Mississippi.  On this track, most of the hardest-hit drought areas from northern Georgia into southwestern Virginia would miss out on much-needed rainfall.  Nevertheless, abundant to locally excessive rain will likely bring significant improvement to southernmost drought areas in the eastern Gulf Coast region, with Fay's remnants taking a possible northward turn into the Tennessee Valley early next week.  Farther north, high pressure will maintain mostly dry weather over the Mid-Atlantic, although a few showers may provide some moisture late in the period.  In the Midwest, a cold front will trigger showers and thunderstorms, although the heaviest rain may end up falling in eastern areas with the remnants of Fay.   Locally heavy showers will continue over the Delta, with moisture gradually working westward back into the central and southern Plains over the weekend.  Out west, mostly dry, warm conditions will prevail.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (August 26-30) calls for additional, much-needed rainfall over the southeastern quarter of the nation as well as portions of the northern Plains.  In contrast, drier-than-normal conditions are expected to persist over southwestern drought areas as well as central portions of the Corn Belt.  Favorably cooler weather is anticipated from the southern Plains into the Southeast, while above-normal temperatures prevail in the Southwest and from the northern Plains into New England.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, declining pasture conditions over south-central Maui and northwestern portions of the Big Island led to an increase of drought from D2 to D3. Drought worsened (to D1) on Lanai due to degraded pasture conditions as well.  In contrast, trade-wind showers resumed over northeast Kauai, reducing D1 to D0.  Meanwhile, near-normal rainfall over the past 30-plus days across the eastern quarter of the Big Island allowed for some improvement here as well (D0).  In Puerto Rico, D1 was expanded slightly eastward due to spotty, generally light rainfall and a decline in the vegetative health index.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Isolated, locally heavy showers did little to offset the expanding dryness in the region.  Rainfall over the past 30 days was less than 60 percent of normal across central Maryland and northern Virginia, and less than 30 percent of normal across much of central and southern Virginia.  Consequently, the northward expansion of moderate to severe drought continued, with D0 dryness reaching as far north as Maryland.  Dryness also expanded on the Delmarva Peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Locally heavy rain in southern and eastern areas halted the southward expansion of drought, with improvements noted from the South Carolina coast southward into Florida.  In the latter region, slow-moving Tropical Storm Fay erased lingering long-term drought over Lake Okeechobee, with additional rain from this system expected to grace portions of the Southeast during the upcoming week.  In contrast, rapidly declining streamflows and soil moisture levels were clear indicators of the expanding drought in Tennessee and Kentucky.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Delta">
   <p>Widespread showers (locally more than 3 inches) led to additional reductions of D0 and D1.  In central Louisiana, however, persistent longer-term rainfall deficits coupled with generally light rainfall (less than one inch) over the past week led to only minor modifications of the D2 drought area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Cool, unsettled weather prevailed over most areas, with additional showers in southern New Jersey further easing D0 dryness.  Rain continued to bypass central and northern Pennsylvania, however, which has led to an introduction of D0 across northern portions of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Favorably wet weather continued across much of the region, resulting in additional drought reductions from the Dakotas southward into Texas.  In particular, lingering D4 drought in south-central Texas was erased following another week of 1 to 3 inches (locally more) of rain.  Heavy rain (3-6 inches) in eastern Texas erased lingering drought in this region.  Heavy to excessive rainfall (locally more than 8 inches) wiped away drought over the southern half of Oklahoma, while more drought relief (1-4 inches of rain) was noted in the Texas and Oklahoma panhandles.  Improvements noted in southern Texas were in response to additional rain and favorable drought indices.  Widespread showers and thunderstorms also eased dryness from southeastern Colorado into Nebraska and western Minnesota.  Improvements in D2 and D3 coverage across northern North Dakota were the result of recent rainfall and improving drought indicators, such as streamflow levels and the vegetation health index.  In contrast, significant short-term precipitation deficits (30-day rainfall less than 50 percent of normal) are impacting portions of the Corn Belt; the dry conditions are most prominent in central and northern Minnesota (D1), while D0 was introduced to the western Corn Belt and from northern Wisconsin and the Upper Peninsula of Michigan southeastward into northern Ohio.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Rangelands in northern California deteriorated under persistent dryness and daytime temperatures in excess of 100 F, with a coinciding expansion of D1 and D2 drought.  The last of southern California's D0 was changed to D1 under a persistent dry weather pattern.  Elsewhere in the region, no changes were made to drought designations.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Eric Luebehusen</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
