<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070301</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch over the next 2 weeks that could affect current dry or drought areas include: 1) another storm system crossing the central states on Thursday-Friday, March 1-2, this one expected to bring 1 to 2 inches of precipitation and moderate to heavy snow to the drought areas in Minnesota and Wisconsin; 2) the same storm system bringing moderate to heavy rains to the Deep South and the Tennessee Valley; 3) generally normal to above-normal precipitation across the northern states, including the Great Lakes region, for the next 2 weeks, but mainly dry weather and above-normal temperatures across the Southwest and central and southern Plains. The updated monthly forecast for March indicates warmth and dryness for the Southwest and above-normal precipitation for Minnesota and Wisconsin.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>There was no change in the D0 area in Alaska, as precipitation was light. Heavy showers hit windward sides of Hawaii, but the rainfall was not widespread enough to bring significant reductions in the D0 area at this time. A second week of good rains in Puerto Rico reduced D1 and D0 dryness in north-central and northeastern parts of the island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Central States">
   <p>The frontal system that later evolved into an impressive low pressure center dropped 1 to 2 feet of snow over the California Sierra on February 21-22. By Saturday, February 24, a mammoth low pressure system over Kansas was spreading rain, snow, and ice across the Plains and Upper Midwest and severe weather to the South. Snow totals of 1 to 2 feet during February 23-26 in southern Minnesota eliminated D0 there. Record snows fell to the east in Wisconsin, but these fell south of where they were most needed. Likewise, precipitation amounts were lower in northern Minnesota, with most locations in the D3 area recording 0.5 inches or less. As a result, there was little change in the drought situation from northern Minnesota to northern Wisconsin. To the west and south, amounts were sufficient (over 1 inch) to reduce the D0 in the eastern Dakotas and eliminate the D0 in southeast Iowa and adjacent parts of Illinois and Missouri. A variety of precipitation forms benefited the drought area remaining in Nebraska, with weekly totals exceeding 1 inch in central parts of the state. Given the weeks rain and snow, and cumulative totals since October exceeding 150 percent of normal in central Nebraska, the D0/D1/D2/D3 areas all retreated westward. In northeastern Colorado, although storm amounts were modest, D1 retreated northward based on estimated soil moisture and cumulative precipitation totals. Weekly amounts exceeding 0.5 inches resulted in a slight reduction in the D0 and D1 area in Kansas and a very minor reduction of the D1/D2 area in Oklahoma. The area of severe to extreme drought persisted in central Texas, where little rain fell.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="East">
   <p>Rainfall totals less than an inch were not enough to relieve the D1 drought in eastern Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky, although the moisture was sufficient to reduce the D0 in northern Kentucky and West Virginia. Farther south, unseasonably low streamflows and below-normal rainfall since January caused the D0 area to expand from Alabama into parts of Mississippi. D1 drought expanded westward into Lee County in southern Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>In California, a second bout of heavy rain and snow from Saturday through Tuesday reduced D1 and D0 over the northern half of the state, with the D1 retreating south of Lake Tahoe. Impressive snowfall totals piled up in the Sierra Nevada, with 2 to 4 feet common, and up to 5 or 6 feet in the higher elevations. Nevertheless, snowpack remained below normal, and snow water content totaled less than two-thirds of normal from the Tahoe area southward. D1 remained, although diminished, across most of southern California, while D2 persisted south of the San Joaquin Valley. An increase in mountain snows resulted in a slight retreat of the D1 in southeastern Arizona. Moderate to heavy rain or snow reduced the drought area slightly in western Wyoming, eastern Idaho, and southwestern Montana, while improved mountain snow water content led to some drought reduction in south-central Montana and northern Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
