<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001130</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features during the next 10 days that may affect some of the nations dry or drought areas include: 1) During the remainder of the week, orographically heavy precipitation will ease early-season precipitation and snowfall deficits in the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies. Precipitation is forecast to spread as far south as the southern Cascades and Sierra Nevada. 2) At midweek and again at weeks end, generally light precipitation (rain and snow) is expected from the Midwest to the Mid-Atlantic region. 3) Rainfall is possible during the next few days along the western Gulf Coast and across extreme southern Florida. 4) The NWS 6-10 day outlook for December 4-8 calls for a possible return of significant rainfall to the South, including lingering drought areas in the southern Rockies and southern Plains. Widespread rain may reach areas as far east as the southern Appalachians, but below-normal amounts are forecast across Peninsular Florida.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Locally heavy rainfall abated in windward locations, while mostly dry weather prevailed in leeward areas. Abnormally dry (D0) and first-stage drought (D1) conditions remained intact from Molokai, Lanai, and western Maui to western portions of the Big Island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley and Mid-Atlantic Region">
   <p>Despite recent rainfall, agricultural effects of dryness (D0) were still being felt as far north as the Mid-Atlantic region, where Virginias topsoil moisture remained 38 percent very short to short as of November 26 and producers were concerned that late-emerging winter wheat could be damaged by cold weather, according to USDAs National Agricultural Statistics Service. An area of abnormal dryness (D0) was also expanded northward to encompass portions of the middle Ohio Valley and the central Appalachians, where significant rain last fell in late September or early October. Streamflows are beginning to reflect the dryness in West Virginia, eastern Ohio, and southwestern Pennsylvania, areas that in some cases never completely recovered from moisture deficits that developed during the regions major drought of 1998-99.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Another cool, mostly dry week brought little change to the overall drought picture. The exception to the dry pattern was near the Great Lakes, where the lake-effect snow machine generated widespread squalls in abnormally dry and first-stage drought (D0 and D1) areas across northern Michigan. The Plains/Midwestern situation remained most serious in eastern Nebraska, western Iowa, and northeastern Kansas, where first-stage to severe drought (D1 to D2) continued, and in the middle one-third of Montana, where severe to extreme drought (D2 to D3) persisted. Due to a variety of indicators, including low streamflows, sub-soil moisture and surface water shortages, and long-term precipitation deficits dating back as much as 15 months, abnormally dry (D0) conditions were expanded eastward across southern Iowa and increased slightly in eastern Kansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Heavy rain further eased long-term drought across the South. More than 2 inches of rain soaked areas from southeastern Oklahoma and eastern Texas to western Alabama, while at least 4 inches fell from northeastern Texas to northwestern Mississippi. The rain eliminated an area of extreme drought (D3) from southeastern Mississippi to west-central Georgia, leaving the region with severe drought (D2). A pocket of extreme drought (D3) persisted, however, in the southern Appalachians. Significant rainfall also returned to the southern Atlantic region, although much of Floridas peninsula remained very dry, with a large area of extreme drought (D3) continuing across central areas. November 1-28 rainfall in southern Florida was as low as a trace in Ft. Myers and 0.64 inch in Ft. Lauderdale. In contrast, month-to-date rainfall reached 14.24 inches in Galveston, Texas, and 11.16 inches in Little Rock, Arkansas. In Louisiana, New Orleans total of 11.72 inches represented its fifth-highest November total and wettest November since 15.27 inches fell in 1992.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>After a slow start to the wet season along and near the Pacific Coast, including the Cascades and Sierra Nevada, precipitation began to increase in late November. Even though October-November precipitation averaged only approximately one-half of normal in the Cascades and Sierra Nevada, impacts remained insignificant at this early stage in the season. In the northern Rockies, however, where season-to-date precipitation totals have been similarly low, dryness (D0) was a concern due to lingering longer-term moisture deficits. According to USDAs Natural Resources Conservation Service, October 1 - November 28 precipitation totals were as low as one-third of normal in some northwestern Montana river basins, and ranged from 50 to 80 percent of normal in most of Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
