<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20051215</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a system moving across the northern Plains and Great Lakes December 13-15 is providing some moderate snowfall amounts in these regions, as well as heavy snow for the Black Hills in South Dakota; 2) another system moving across the Gulf Coast December 14-15 is dropping heavy rains near Houston and has the potential for some severe weather; 3) this storm system will move into the Mid-Atlantic region December 15-16, with the potential for freezing precipitation in many areas; 4) another system will move across southern Texas and the Gulf Coast December 18-19; 5) several Alberta Clippers will move through the Great Lakes over the weekend and next week, causing some light snow accumulations along with heavier snowfalls in the lake-effect snow areas of Michigan; 6) the moderate trades across Hawaii will diminish December 15-17, while strong westerlies will create a relatively unsettled pattern next week and increase the chance for showers statewide; 7) the eastern United States will remain generally cold and dry for the December 20-24 period; and 8) the western United States will remain generally quiet through the period, with above-normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation December 20-24.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Precipitation during the week brought relief to the eastern side of the Island of Hawaii, but the dryness continues across parts of the other Hawaiian Islands. The week was generally dry in the D0 area of eastern Alaska, and no changes were made there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="North Carolina">
   <p>A second straight week with precipitation amounts approaching 1 inch allowed for some additional removal of D0 to take place in western North Carolina. The D0 and D1 regions were not changed for the week in central North Carolina, where longer-term precipitation departures remain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Plains">
   <p>The drought and dryness conditions across the central Plains remained mostly unchanged during the week. A small area of improvement occurred in the northern Black Hills region of South Dakota as a result of heavy snows during November and early December.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Most of the Midwest remained cold for the week, with temperature departures exceeding 10F degrees from eastern Ohio through the central Rockies. A series of systems added to the snow cover across the region as well. Minor improvements in the drought depictions occurred around Lake Michigan in eastern Wisconsin and western Michigan, where some of the precipitation was heaviest. Otherwise, the extreme drought area in eastern Iowa and northern Illinois remained unchanged. According to NCDC, the March through November period was the driest on record since 1895 for Climate Divisions 1 and 2 in Illinois, which includes both Chicago and Rockford. Because of dry conditions, exacerbated by ice caused by the cold temperatures, water levels continue to fall along the Mississippi River. Barges are now facing some travel restrictions in the region between St. Louis, MO, and the confluence with the Ohio River. Already low from the regional dryness, the Army Corps of Engineers estimates that ice formation during cold outbreaks can reduce the remaining flow by about half, increasing the potential for transportation-related problems.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Another relatively dry week took place across the regions of the South experiencing drought and dryness. Some rains did fall on the eastern edge of the drought area in Mississippi, but not enough for any improvements to take place. Conditions continue to deteriorate in southwest Arkansas, northwest Louisiana, eastern Texas, and eastern Oklahoma. The March through November precipitation totals were the driest in the 111-year record, according to NCDC, for the Southwest Climate Division in Arkansas, Oklahomas Southeast Climate Division, and the Northeast Climate Division in Texas. As a result, there was some expansion of both the severe (D2) and extreme (D3) drought conditions in these areas. All of the Dallas-Fort Worth metropolitan area is now within the extreme drought region. Both D1 and D0 expanded across additional areas of Louisiana and eastern Texas for the week as well. In Arkansas, negative 12-month precipitation departures reached 21.1 inches in Mena, 19.7 inches in Glenwood, 17.3 inches in Clinton, and 17.1 inches in Amity and Oden. Meanwhile, near Amarillo, TX, Lake Meredith on the Canadian River was within 3 feet of an all-time record low level. The map now reflects that the impacts in this region are both hydrological and agricultural.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The week was relatively quiet across the western United States. As a result, the only change made in this region for the week was an introduction of D0 into parts of central Arizona and an expansion of D1 across the southeast part of the state. Maps produced by the NRCS National Water and Climate Center show both low elevation and high elevation stations at 0-40% of normal precipitation since the beginning of the Water Year for most of the state, following on a below-average summer monsoon season in southern Arizona. USGS streamflow gauges along the upper Gila River also show relatively low flows for this time of year.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
