<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020207</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) The Pacific NW should continue to see relief in the next 5 days (2/6-2/11) with some relief (.5 to 1 inch liquid equivalents possible) forging its way into parts of Idaho, western Montana and the Yellowstone and Teton areas of Wyoming as well; 2) much-needed rains and/or snow are expected in the Southeast and Mid-Atlantic states, with 1 to 2 inches possible in the Florida Panhandle, Georgia and up the coast into the eastern Carolinas and Virginia. The Northeast and New England area can also expect to see .5 to 1 inch or so; 3) All but the deep South and Southeast should see unseasonably warm temperatures over the same time frame; 4) Looking out a little further, the 6-10 day forecast (2/12-2/16) continues the warm pattern for everyone east of the Rockies except Florida, which comes in at normal. The precipitation outlook during this time indicates a likelihood of below-normal precipitation across California, Nevada, Arizona and southwestern Utah. Above-normal precipitation is projected for the South and Southeast and up into the Mid-Atlantic and Northeast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>On the heels of good rains last week, heavy rains continued this week across the Hawaiian Islands. The generous rains of the past few weeks have eliminated dryness from all but western Molokai. Puerto Rico saw another quiet week resulting in no changes.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>The massive winter storm that swept across the country from Malibu to Massachusetts brought plenty of rain, ice and snow into parts of the Northeast and New England. Generous snow and/or rains of 1 to 3 inches were enough to bring relief to western Pennsylvania, northern New York and parts of Vermont, New Hampshire, Massachusetts and Maine. Although not enough to remove drought from the region, it was welcomed. In general, the front lines of the drought are retreating eastward.</p>
   <p>Most of the rain and snow fell well north of the moderate (D1) and severe (D2) drought region in the Mid-Atlantic. In fact, the warm, dry week allowed for a modest expansion of drought conditions from southern Georgia up into the eastern Carolinas as well as in eastern Virginia and Maryland. Much of the Mid-Atlantic and New England states saw record warmth during November-January. For Vermont and Massachusetts, it was the warmest November-January period on record, and many other states came in with their second warmest November-January on record. This was coupled with record or near-record dryness in much of the area. For Maine and Connecticut, it was the driest November-January to date.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The regions most powerful storm brought up to a foot of snow in many places and a lot of rain and ice in others. Benefitting from heavy rains were areas of west central Texas, the Texas Panhandle, Oklahoma and Kansas. As a result, drought decreased one category throughout the drought-affected areas in the region. Unfortunately, western Kansas did not share in the wealth, leaving valid concerns about the winter wheat crops condition.</p>
   <p>Conditions over the last 2 to 3 months have led to an expansion of moderate (D1) drought, and abnormally dry (D0) conditions have spilled out onto the Plains from the Rockies into parts of western Nebraska, the Dakotas and into Minnesota. In fact, Minnesota, Iowa and Wisconsin just came off of their warmest November-January on record.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Most of the West saw a very quiet (dry) week. After gaining early-season momentum, the accumulation tap has been reduced to a trickle or has been shut off altogether across a great deal of the region. Decreases in snowpack percent of average were running as high as 13% in some places, according to SNOTEL data reports out of USDA/NRCS. Even in the Sierra Nevada basins, things have fallen back toward normal for the water year as far as snowpack and water equivalents are concerned.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, they continue to play the waiting game for some major snows in the Rockies. Conditions in Wyoming, Colorado, Arizona and northern New Mexico continue to bear the brunt of the dryness in the region. This is of concern, especially in the northern Rockies where Montana and Wyoming have seen dryness for the better part of 3 years in some parts. Moderate (D1) drought has now pushed south out of Wyoming into northern Colorado and also westward across southern Colorado and into southern Utah while abnormally dry (D0) conditions have pushed farther south and west in Arizona, which is coming off its 10th driest November-January period in 107 years of record keeping. Snowpack and snow water equivalent and basin precipitation values for the water year to date are at or below the 50% mark in the D1 areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
