<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20160512</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>An active weather pattern over much of the eastern United States brought with it cooler than normal temperatures for most areas east of the Mississippi River.  Areas of the Mid-Atlantic and Florida recorded above-normal precipitation with departures of up to 2 inches above normal for the week.  Temperatures were also cooler than normal over the Southwest as above-normal precipitation from southern Oregon to western Arizona helped to keep temperatures down.  Areas of the central Rocky Mountains recorded up to 4 inches above normal precipitation as a series of low pressure systems developed there and tracked onto the Plains.  Drier than normal conditions dominated much of the South and much of the northern United States had above-normal temperatures.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5-7 days, the Plains, Midwest, and Northeast remain in a very active weather pattern; the greatest precipitation amounts are projected from northeast Texas into southern Missouri, where up to 5 inches of rain is forecast.  With this active pattern, a shot of cold air out of Canada will impact temperatures all the way into the south, with below-normal temperatures.  Temperatures are expected to be coolest over the central Plains with departures of up to 15 degrees below normal.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlooks show that the best chances for above-normal temperatures are in Alaska and the southern United States from Texas to the Carolinas.  Projections show that the below-normal temperatures could be experienced over the Pacific Northwest, Midwest, and New England.  A wetter than normal pattern looks to be likely as there are above-normal chances for precipitation above normal over areas from the Pacific Northwest, Central Plains, and most of the eastern United States.  The greatest chances of above-normal precipitation are expected over the lower Mississippi River Valley and the Great Basin.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes were made this week for Alaska, Hawaii, or Puerto Rico.  It can be noted that there has been substantial precipitation over southeast Alaska recently.  With below-normal snowfall through the winter, determining the balance between the low winter snow accumulation and current precipitation has been difficult, which led to unchanged conditions this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="High Plains and South">
   <p>Areas of Nebraska and South Dakota were above normal for precipitation this week as a series of storms tracked through the region.  After a reanalysis of the region, portions of the D0 in western North Dakota were improved this week.  Additional rain over the D0 areas in Kansas allowed for the removal of most of the remaining abnormally dry areas in the state with only a small area of southeast Kansas remaining.  In Oklahoma, D0 was improved in the central and western portions of the state while in Texas, D1 was removed from the western panhandle and D0 was expanded to the south in the eastern panhandle.  New areas of D0 were added in south Texas in response to developing dry conditions while some improvement to D0 was made in west Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Most of the Mid-Atlantic had close to normal precipitation this week, with some areas of Virginia, Maryland, and West Virginia recording up to 3 inches above normal precipitation for the week.  Coupled with the cooler than normal temperatures, most indicators responded to the recent rains and allowed for improvements.  Full category improvements were made to the D0 and D1 regions, leaving behind some lingering D0.  An area of D1 remains in southern Pennsylvania and western Maryland where less precipitation has occurred and the indicators are still on the dry side.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Most of the Midwest was drier than normal this week, with only areas of western Iowa, northern Illinois, and northern and southern Missouri above normal for the week.  Even with the dryness, drought is minimal in the region and no changes were made this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Most of the region was drier than normal for the week with Tennessee, Alabama, and Mississippi up to 2 inches below normal.  Areas of the Florida peninsula and eastern North Carolina recorded above-normal precipitation with departures of up to 2 inches above normal.  Improvements were made to the D0 in eastern North Carolina as most indicators are now depicting wet conditions.  With the continuing dryness in Georgia, Tennessee, and Alabama, degradations to the drought status were made.  In Georgia, D1 was expanded in the northwest while D0 shifted to the south; in Tennessee, D1 shifted to the northwest in the eastern part of the state and to the west in the central part of the state. In Alabama, D0 shifted to the west and south.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Most of the Northeast was drier than normal this week.  As this short-term dryness has continued in the region, abnormally dry conditions have expanded.  For this week, D0 was pushed toward the west in western New York and a new area of D0 was added in northern New York.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West">
   <p>As an analysis of conditions in New Mexico and Colorado was done, D0 conditions were improved in southeast Colorado and eastern New Mexico and the D1 in eastern New Mexico was removed.  Abundant precipitation in Wyoming this week allowed for a full category improvement to the D0 and D1 conditions in the southwest part of the state.  Northeast Utah also was improved as D0 was removed over this portion of the state.  Based upon recent conditions and discussions that started last week, areas of D2 and D3 were improved over southern Nevada and southern California.  For all of the West, the indicator type was changed to “L” (long-term drought) as the areas of short-term impacts have improved enough to remove that designation.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Deborah Bathke</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
