<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041104</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 5-day period (November 4-8) that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include... 1) a much more stable and drier pattern is expected over the next five days for all but the southeastern and eastern United States, which should bring a dry break to southern California; 2) temperatures over the same period are expected to be well above-normal (3 to 9 degrees Fahrenheit) for much of the High Plains, northern Rockies, Intermountain West, and the Pacific NW.</p>
   <p>During the 6 to 10-day period (November 9-13), 1) precipitation is expected to be above-normal for the Southern Plains, High Plains, and Pacific NW. In addition, the Central Plains, Central Rockies, Great Basin, California, and southern Oregon are looking at below-normal precipitation totals; 2) Alaska and all points east of the Missouri River are expected to see cooler than normal readings while most of the western United States should enjoy warmer than normal temperatures.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Despite heavy rains over portions of the Hawaiian Islands, central Maui continued to experience dryness during October, prompting a downgrade to moderate drought (D1 A) conditions due to agricultural concerns.</p>
   <p>After a pretty quiet week in Alaska, there are no changes to this weeks depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Although it was a relatively quiet week in the High Plains, a system did drag across the Dakotas last week bringing some decent rains (1 to 2 inches) to parts of northern South Dakota and southwestern and southeastern North Dakota. Improvement is noted on this weeks map mainly in central and southern South Dakota where abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) have been pushed back to the Missouri River. In addition, extreme north-central South Dakota saw some reduction in the severe drought (D2) area there.</p>
   <p>Heavy rains (2 to 4 inches) fell across parts of northeastern Oklahoma, southeastern Kansas, northwestern Arkansas and southwestern Missouri. The recent rains, coupled with those of the past 30 days, has led to more improvement in these areas resulting in the removal of moderate drought (D1) in southwest Missouri, removal of abnormally dry (D0) conditions in the other states and a pushing eastward of the D0 in Missouri where significant 60- and 90-day departures still exist.</p>
   <p>Looking at the Great Lakes region, between 1 and 3 inches of precipitation (and more in some locales) were reported in north central Wisconsin and in the thumb of Michigan. Consequently, most of the moderate drought (D1) has been reduced and the abnormally dry (D0) area has followed suite and been pushed eastward toward Lake Winnebago in eastern Wisconsin. While some areas are now depicted as free of dryness, it should be noted that a significant corridor of below-normal totals (see the D0 here) exists going back into the 60 to 90-day period. This corridor stretches out of Iowa and into southern Wisconsin and into southern Michigan as well. Given the time of year and recent wetness, no major impacts are being reported. If a dry pattern persists this fall and into winter, it will be a region to watch when the spring thaw comes.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>On the heels of an incredible wet weather pattern during the past few weeks, things were relatively (compared to the recent deluges) drier this past week. Even so, extreme southern coastal California still saw heavy rains on the order of 2-4 inches (from San Diego up to the Los Angeles metro area) last week, which is well above normal for this time of year. After a record setting October (many locales saw an unbelievable 1000% of normal for the month), moderate drought (D1) has now completely receded from the coastal reaches of southern California and has been pushed out of the San Joaquin Valley to the east as well. Year-to-date precipitation totals are still running well below normal (50-75%) across many of the central valley and coastal areas of the state leaving abnormally dry (D0) conditions in place even after this recent bout of wetness. While the record rains have served as a great start (while also bringing unfortunate flooding) to the new water year, they are not enough to eliminate all concerns and water supply issues this early into the wet season. In addition, it is too early to tell if the winter pattern will set up this way and persist in conjunction with the development of El Nio, or whether it will simply be an aberration.</p>
   <p>As for the other states in the West, this past week brought generally good patches of precipitation to parts of central Arizona, southwestern Colorado and northeastern Utah. They too have been in the grips of a 5-year drought, leaving most cautiously hopeful about the fast start as it isnt the first time theyve had a good start to the water year only to see it fizzle out down the stretch. As such, things remain in a holding pattern on the map. There has been some definite short-term improvement, but we still have a long ways to go to bring ground water, streams and reservoirs up to their pre-drought levels.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
