<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20161103</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>The U.S. Drought Monitor saw continued deterioration of drought conditions in the south and southeast as dry conditions and above average temperatures prevailed during the past week further impacting soil moisture and agriculture across the region. Parts of the interior U.S. also saw a deterioration in conditions due to a continued lack of rainfall combined with well above average temperatures. Conversely, rains along the coast in New England and in the Pacific Northwest provided relief to those drought stricken areas.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>The National Weather Service Quantitative Precipitation Forecast calls for continued dryness during the next week across the drought impacted areas of Alabama and Georgia as well as a broad area spanning from the southern half of California northeastward to North Dakota. More precipitation is forecast for the Pacific Northwest and along a band from New Mexico to the Northeast as fronts move through these areas. In general, warm conditions will dominate the temperature forecast for most of the country in the week ahead.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>There were no changes to the drought depiction in these areas this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest and Lower Ohio Valley">
   <p>Much of the Midwest remained drought-free. In the Lower Ohio Valley, continued rainfall shortages combined with temperature departures of up to 12 degrees above normal resulted in a full category intensification of drought conditions in central and western Kentucky. The majority of the state is now in moderate (D1) drought. In eastern Tennessee, exceptional (D4) and extreme (D3) drought expanded to the northeast with moderate (d1) drought now covering the remainder of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Rainfall accumulations in excess of 150 percent of normal eased drought conditions along the coast and eliminated short-term drought across much of the region. Southern Maine, southern New Hampshire, and eastern Massachusetts saw a reduction in severe (D2) and extreme drought (D3). Longer-term hydrologic impacts remain in this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Short-term precipitation deficits and well above average temperatures led to an increase in the depiction of abnormally dry conditions across parts of western and central Nebraska as well as in western Kansas. The panhandle of Oklahoma saw an increase in moderate drought (D1) and abnormally dry (D0) areas while the southeast part of the state also saw an expansion of these categories as well as in increase in severe (D2) drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Warm, dry conditions continued to dominate the weather in the southern states over the last week. Average temperatures of more than 10 degrees above normal were reported and rainfall continued to be virtually absent in all but a few isolated locations. This resulted in an expansion of extreme (D3) drought in the east-central part of Mississippi. In Texas, areas of abnormal dryness expanded a small pocket of moderate drought (D1) was introduced in the panhandle. East Texas also saw an increase in abnormally dry conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>The southeast saw little to no precipitation over the last week resulting in with 30 day accumulations of generally at an inch or less across the majority of the region. Meanwhile temperatures averaged up to 12 degrees above normal causing further drying of vegetation and soils and resulting in additional agricultural impacts. These conditions are reflected with an expansion of extreme (D3) drought in the north-central and northeast parts of Georgia and an expansion of abnormal dryness along the southeastern edge of the state’s drought affected areas. Alabama also so a deterioration in drought conditions. The two regions of exceptional drought (d4) present on last week’s map were connected and extreme (D3) drought expanded westward in the state. Additionally, North Carolina saw a slight northeastward expansion of extreme (D3) drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation eased drought conditions in Northern California bringing a reduction in moderate (D1) drought. Short-term drought impacts have essentially been eliminated in eastern Oregon, but longer-term hydrologic impacts (denoted by the area enclosed within the solid black line) remain. A dry October resulted in the expansion of abnormally dry conditions in the northern half of New Mexico as well as across much of Colorado. Colorado also saw a widespread expansion of moderate (D1) drought along the higher elevations east of the Continental Divide, along the Front Range corridor, and across the eastern plains.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Deborah Bathke</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
