<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20011011</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) a storm system bringing 1 to 2 inches of rain from Texas eastward to Georgia and northward to the Great Lakes region on October 10-14; 2) 1 to 2 inches of precipitation over western Washington and northwestern Oregon during October 10-15; 3) generally light and below-normal rainfall from eastern Georgia to Virginia over the next 2 weeks.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Significant rains allowed D2 drought to be upgraded to D1 on the northern tip of the Big Island and D0 to be removed from the windward side of Maui.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast, Great Lakes Region, upper Mississippi Valley, and northern Plains">
   <p>A return to drier weather caused streamflows to drop and abnormal dryness (D0) to expand southward from New Hampshire and Vermont into northern Massachusetts. Dryness also expanded westward into New Yorks Mohawk Valley and into the southern Adirondacks. D1 drought expanded slightly southward in south-central Pennsylvania, and continued over the northwestern part of the state and extreme northeastern Ohio. D0 dryness also expanded southward into southeastern Ohio. Abnormal dryness (D0) developed over northeastern Minnesota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Lack of significant rains allowed D1 drought in eastern Georgia to expand into South Carolina and northward through the North Carolina Piedmont into southern Virginia. As the dryness is affecting agriculture as well as water supplies, the hydro designation was removed from the depiction. In Virginia, USDA reported that pasture conditions were at extremely critical levels.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Tennessee Valley area">
   <p>Rains brought some scattered relief to west and south Texas, but the overall drought picture changed little, as severe drought persisted in southwest Texas and southeastern New Mexico. Drought also remained over northeastern Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation in the Northwest was generally light except for 1 to 2 inch amounts in western Washington. The overall drought picture changed little, with moderate to extreme drought persisting across the northwestern quadrant of the country. In Montana, the area of D3 (extreme drought) expanded westward to the Continental Divide. Extreme drought remained over much of the state, with serious water shortages affecting towns in the central part of the state along the Musselshell River, which has run dry. Very serious water shortages also exist from near Havre southward through Lewistown to the Wyoming border and west to the Divide.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
