<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000608</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>A few features to watch over the next 10-day period include: 1) high pressure building over the central U.S. will bring above-normal temperatures to the Midwest, especially over the next few days; 2) the heat would tend to worsen drought over Nebraska, Iowa, and Missouri, but instability during the week could contribute to rain from thunderstorms that may compensate to some extent for the heat; 3) tropical moisture associated with Tropical Depression One in the Gulf of Mexico may bring rain to Texas and the Mississippi Valley during the next 5 days, possibly bringing some drought relief to Louisiana; 4) it is too early to say if the moisture will continue advancing northward to eventually benefit dry areas in the Midwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Conditions continued to deteriorate in Hawaii, where all non-drought areas were downgraded to D0 dryness and D1 drought persisted over leeward areas of Oahu, and D2 drought continued leeward areas of Maui and the northwest coast of the Big Island. D0 dryness continued along the north coast of Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>More heavy rains (over 3 inches) hit southern Minnesota, southern Wisconsin, eastern Iowa, and northern Illinois on May 30 to June 2, causing flooding and a further retreat of the drought southward in eastern Iowa and western Illinois. Rains to the south and west were not as heavy, resulting in severe drought (D2) continuing over eastern Nebraska, the southwestern half of Iowa, and northern Missouri. Extreme drought (D3) expanded slightly in southeast Nebraska and migrated farther eastward in northwest Missouri and northward into southwest Iowa. Precipitation deficits since last July in the severe drought area generally exceeded 10 inches. The rains slightly reduced the area of severe drought in west-central and central Illinois (D2W), but the heaviest rains fell north of the drought area. Drought in Illinois has affected water supplies but crops have fared well, as soil moisture remained abundant over most of the state. Stage one drought (D1W) lingered in west-central Indiana. In Missouri, the heaviest rains missed most of the severe drought areas in the northwest and southeast. Dry weather caused drought (D1) to extend southward into northern Kansas, while abnormal dryness covered extreme western Kansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South-Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>Heavy rains (2 to 5 inches or more) swept across much of Texas on June 1-5, causing flooding and eliminating short-term deficits over eastern and northern halves of the state, and causing the extreme drought in southwest Texas to retreat slightly southward. The heaviest rains tended to stay north of the Odessa-San Angelo areas, allowing extreme drought to persist to the south and west. Despite the recent rains, long-term rainfall deficits (D0W) continued over northern Texas. Reservoir storage was increasing rapidly in the North Central, Low Rolling Plains, and Edwards Plateau regions, but dropping in the High Plains, Trans-Pecos, South, and South Central regions. Thunderstorms swept across the remainder of the South and Southeast during June 5-6, bringing only a minor improvement to drought conditions. Extreme drought (D3) continued to stretch from southeast Louisiana to South Carolina and southward to central Florida. Category-four drought persisted in southeast Louisiana despite some rain. Showers reduced drought on Florida's southern Peninsula, causing the Everglades area to improve to D0 (abnormally dry) status.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>High temperatures intensified dryness across much of the Southwest. Showers brought some drought relief to New Mexico, mainly in the east. The moisture caused a slight retreat of D0 dryness in the east, but western areas remained dry. Severe to extreme drought continued over most of the southern two-thirds of the state. Hot, dry weather caused drought (D1F,A) to advance northward in Arizona, with abnormal dryness (D0) penetrating southern parts of Utah and Colorado. The dryness increased fire danger and hurt rangeland conditions. Rain and snow caused D1 drought to retreat southward in Montana, but dryness (D0) increased in Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
