<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100715</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (July 15-19), 2 inches of rain is forecast across the long-term drought area encompassing northeastern Minnesota, north-central Wisconsin, and western Upper Michigan. Somewhat less precipitation (1 to 1.5 inches) is expected in eastern Upper Michigan and northern Lower Michigan, as well as over southeastern New York including Long Island, Connecticut and New Jersey. The mid-Atlantic region should receive up to 0.5 inch of rain, while farther south, 2 to 3 inches of rain is forecast for portions of the Southeast. Little relief is predicted across Texas and southeastern Oklahoma during the next 5 days, with rainfall amounts generally ranging between 0.10 and 0.25 inch. Up to an inch of rain is anticipated across the drought area in the lower Mississippi Valley. In the Southwest, 0.25 to 0.50 inch of rain associated with monsoonal showers and thunderstorms is expected over Arizona and New Mexico, with locally heavier amounts possible.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (July 20-24), the odds favor above-median rainfall across the Upper Great Lakes region, and below-median rainfall over southeastern New York, southern New England, New Jersey, the southern Plains, and southwestern and south-central portions of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>South-central and southeastern parts of mainland Alaska received over 2 inches of rain during the past week. Unfortunately, these heavier rains mostly missed the areas of D0 dryness over the southwestern and central Interior sections of the state. A few locations in the Panhandle received 1 to 2 inches of precipitation, while others received much less. Even the higher amounts of rain result in only a modest reduction in 90-day shortfalls to this climatologically wet region, thus D0 conditions remained unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Once again, only light rainfall (up to three-quarters of an inch) was recorded across most of the state last week, with an isolated report of 2 inches observed over Oahu. Dryness and drought remained unchanged through most of the state.  The only areas of exceptional drought (D4) affecting any part of the United States exist in part of northwestern and southwestern Hawaii Island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Atlantic Seaboard">
   <p>Very warm, humid weather continued across the East Coast states this week, though not quite as hot or dry as during the previous week. Temperatures ranged from 8 to 12 degrees F above normal throughout the Northeast, and 4 to 8 degrees F above normal throughout the mid-Atlantic region. Weak weather disturbances moved across the region, bringing greater coverage of showers and thunderstorms, though many areas still received little or no rainfall. Heavy rain (2 or more inches) fell across western counties in New Jersey, but much of the state continued to miss out on the heavier precipitation, prompting a 1-category degradation, from D0 to D1 drought conditions. In addition, D0 dryness was expanded from southeastern New York and Long Island into western Connecticut, where negative rainfall departures of 4 to 6 inches have occurred over the past 60 days.  Farther south, moderate to heavy rains (1.5 to 4 inches) fell over northern portions of the Chesapeake Bay shoreline, prompting a 1-category improvement, while the lower Delmarva Peninsula missed out on the heavier rains, contributing to a southward expansion of D1 conditions.  The rain that fell within the past 1-2 days is not taken into account by CPC’s 3-month or 6-month SPI tools, nor the NLDAS Top 1-meter and total column soil moisture tools, which support a significantly drier depiction.  In the eastern Panhandle of West Virginia and adjacent north-central Maryland, little rain and pervasive dryness warranted a 1-category degradation of drought, from D0 to D1 conditions. At Shenandoah Junction, WV, which is located near Harper’s Ferry, only 1.07 inches of rain has been observed since June 14th. This one month period includes a string of 22 consecutive days without measurable rain.</p>
   <p>Little rainfall and very warm temperatures resulted in an expansion of D0 dryness across southeastern portions of North Carolina, and southern and western portions of South Carolina. In terms of soil moisture for the North Carolina coastal region, the percentage of soil moisture rated short increased from 37 percent last week to 51 percent this week. Crop reports still indicate concerns of stress, particularly the corn crop. In South Carolina, soil moisture levels also regressed, with 41 percent rated short. The dry weather and increased evaporation rates have had a substantial impact on both agriculture and wildfire activity.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Recent heavy rains over central Upper Michigan contributed to one and two category improvements in the area. The town of Munising, in Alger County, has received 3.93 inches of rain so far in July, and 8.32 inches of rain in June. Just west of Marquette, MI, 8.93 inches of rain has fallen since June 1st, which is the second highest rainfall on record for that time period, with records dating back to 1961. This area continues to receive well above normal rain this month, and is only a third of an inch shy of normal rainfall for July. The Keweenaw Peninsula has been missing out on much of the rain this month, justifying the maintenance of D2 drought conditions. This is also consistent with lingering low water levels at reservoirs in western Upper Michigan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South-Central States">
   <p>During the past week, heavy rain (2 inches or more) fell across much of eastern and southern Oklahoma, northern-, central-, and southeastern Texas, northern Arkansas, and portions of Louisiana. Even with this beneficial rainfall, it is unclear as to what significant improvements can be made in the drought depiction at this time, and a reassessment of conditions will be made next week for possible modifications.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Little to no rain fell over the Pacific Northwest during the past week, with light shower activity (0.1 to 0.5 inch) being reported over portions of the northern and central Rockies. No changes have been made to the regional drought depiction this week. At this time, the only remaining areas of drought north of the southern Rockies and east of the Great Basin are D1 areas in western Wyoming, where longer-term deficits remain substantial and recent relief has been less robust.</p>
   <p>Light to moderate showers (up to an inch) fell over central and southeastern Arizona, with a few spotty locations receiving between 1.5 and 2.5 inches of precipitation. Monsoonal showers and thunderstorms are gradually increasing in coverage across both Arizona and New Mexico. About a dozen sites in New Mexico, mostly in the southern part of the state, reported rainfall amounts in excess of 2 inches. Little if any rain was observed over the dryness and drought areas of Nevada.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
