<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100930</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>During the first half of this U.S. Drought Monitor (USDM) week, the Bermuda High dominated the weather across the southern tier states while tropical moisture moved across the Southwest and became entrained in the westerly flow across the Midwest to Great Lakes.  A shift in the weather pattern occurred later in the week with the passage of a vigorous cold front into the South and East, followed by a large, slow-moving upper-level low pressure system.  The front and upper low tapped Gulf of Mexico moisture to bring widespread beneficial rains to the drought areas of the South and East.  While beneficial, the rains were not enough to erase long-term precipitation deficits in most areas.   The Far West and intermountain basin saw little if any precipitation.  Agricultural impacts have been mixed.  Crop harvesting is ahead of schedule in many areas because of the drought, but the dry ground is inhibiting planting of fall and winter crops and stressing crops still in the ground.  September 26 U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) reports revealed a huge area of parched soils, with 70% or more of the topsoil rated “short or very short” of moisture (dry to very dry) from Mississippi to Indiana and from Georgia to Pennsylvania.  Nearly 90% of the topsoil was short or very short in Alabama, Kentucky, West Virginia, Maryland, Virginia, and Connecticut.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Early in the September 29-October 4 period, moisture from the remnants of Tropical Storm Nicole will become entrained in the circulation and move up the east coast, with an inch or more of rain expected from the coastal Carolinas to New England by October 4.  Some areas could receive several inches of rain in total.  An upper-level ridge will dominate the West, with warmer and drier than normal weather, while a cold upper trough holds sway over the eastern United States.  This pattern continues for October 5-13, with dry weather progged for most of the country, including Alaska.  Temperatures are expected to be warmer than normal for much of the West to the Great Lakes and Alaska, and cooler than normal for the Southeast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="East and South">
   <p>Widespread 2 to 4-inch rains fell across much of the South and East from Alabama to Maryland, with 1 to 2-inch rains over most of the Northeast, but this was not sufficient to erase deficits which have built up over several months.  For example, in spite of the week’s rain, September month-to-date precipitation totals were still below normal across most of the Northeast, resulting in no change to the USDM depiction.  River levels spiked upward temporarily with the rain, but long-term hydrological conditions remained depressed.</p>
   <p>Bands of 4 to 8 inches of rain, or more, fell across parts of Georgia, Florida, the Carolinas, and extreme southeast Virginia.  Wilmington, North Carolina, reported a record 10.33 inches of rain on September 27 (but the drought has been so severe there that the station still had a precipitation deficit for the year-to-date and March-to-date).  These heavy rains resulted in significant improvement in some areas.  Long-term moisture conditions were brought to near normal under the heaviest rains, so drought conditions were eliminated (changed to “D-nothing”) in west-central Alabama, central Georgia, the northern coastal plain of South Carolina, the southern coastal plain of North Carolina, and the adjacent piedmont area of North Carolina and Virginia.  One-category improvements were made to parts of the D1 and D2 areas from Alabama to Virginia.</p>
   <p>Other parts of the South received considerably less rain.  Scattered 1-inch showers dotted the Lower Mississippi Valley, but rainfall amounts were generally half an inch or less.  Severe agricultural impacts continued in many areas.  According to USDA reports, from September 19 to 26, the percent of pasture and rangeland in poor or very poor condition increased from 29% to 42% in Louisiana, from 37% to 45% in Tennessee, and from 33% to 67% in Mississippi.  D0 expanded across Tennessee and D1 ballooned across most of Mississippi.  D0-D1-D2 were expanded in southwest Arkansas to reflect severe impacts, including the complete lack of pasture lands available for grazing, dried up ponds and lakes, and 100+ year old oak trees shedding leaves and dying.  D0-D1-D2 also expanded in northeast Arkansas into adjacent western Tennessee, and in southern Louisiana.     Southeast Georgia missed out on the rain as well, so D1 expanded to the coast and an oval of D2 was added.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Great Plains and West">
   <p>Beneficial half-inch-plus rainfall in the northern and central Plains shrank the D0 and eliminated the D1 in north central South Dakota and trimmed the D0 in western Nebraska.  In the southern Plains, the edges of D0 in southwestern Texas, the Texas panhandle, and east Texas were adjusted, with minor expansion in some parts and trimming in others.  The oval of D1 in northeast Texas was eliminated and D1 dented in east Texas.  An oval of D0 was added to southeast New Mexico and adjacent Texas.  The D0 in eastern Oklahoma and along the Missouri-Arkansas border was contracted.</p>
   <p>The rains mostly missed southwest Kansas, so D0 was extended across this area where long-term moisture deficits were greatest.  This resulted in a joining of the western Oklahoma D0A with an expanded Colorado High Plains D0.  D1 was added to northern Colorado, along the Rockies and adjacent foothills, with a little spillage of D1 into southeast Wyoming, where precipitation deficits were consistent at several time scales.  In Wyoming, conditions were dry with 54% of the topsoil rated short or very short, but impacts were minimal and this is early in the historically-dry fall season for much of the state.  Seventy-one percent of the topsoil in Colorado was rated short or very short, and the dryness in eastern Colorado was affecting fall and winter crop planting decisions, so an A impact designation enclosed the D0/D1 from western Oklahoma, across southwest Kansas, up to (but not into) the Colorado Rockies.</p>
   <p>With the shift in weather patterns, temperatures in the West were above normal for the week, increasing evapotranspiration.  The downtown Los Angeles, California weather station set an all-time high temperature record on September 27 with a maximum of 113 degrees F (records go back to 1877).  D0 was expanded in Wyoming where minimal precipitation occurred this week, to make the USDM depiction consistent with longer-term deficits.  A small strip of Wyoming D0 spillage was pulled out of Montana to bring the USDM depiction in line with the Montana state drought assessment.  USDA reports indicated that 31% of Idaho’s topsoil was rated short or very short and 22% of the state’s pastures and rangeland poor or very poor.  The satellite hybrid VegDRI indicator revealed areas of vegetative stress which coincided with precipitation deficits on the Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI) maps, so a spot of D0 was added to southwest Idaho and D0 expanded from Wyoming across southeast Idaho and into more of northern Utah.  USDA reports for Utah rated 50% of the topsoil short or very short, and 14% of the pastures and rangeland and 23% of the stock water supplies in poor or very poor condition.  An oval of D1 was added to cover the worst impacts from Cache to Morgan counties as reflected in the USDA reports, VegDRI, and SPI.  D0 expanded in eastern Nevada into adjacent Utah.  The AH impact boundary over Oregon, California, and Nevada was contracted to encompass just the D1 and D2 areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>It was another drier-than-normal week across most of the Hawaiian Islands.  Local reports indicated that lower elevation pastures in east Kauai were in the worst condition in many years, so D3 was expanded to the northeast on the island.  In Alaska, most stations were below-normal for the week, with long-term deficits accumulating across the Anchorage to Kodiak Island area, which prompted the addition of D0 there.  The southern half of Puerto Rico was drier than normal, but longer-term precipitation was near- to wetter than normal, so the island remained drought-free.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Ohio Valley and Great Lakes">
   <p>Heavy rains (4-8 inches or more) deluged the Upper Mississippi Valley and northern Great Lakes, while 1 to 2-inch rains fell across the southern Great Lakes, northern portions of the Ohio Valley, and parts of the central Appalachians.  Southern portions of the Ohio Valley received half an inch or less of rain, which did little to alleviate long-term deficits and agricultural impacts.  Short-term and long-term deficits were eliminated over Michigan’s Upper Peninsula and the northern edge of the Lower Peninsula, so the D0 there was deleted, but beneficial rains mostly missed the drought area on the Minnesota Arrowhead.  The western edge of the Arrowhead D0 was trimmed back, but the D1-D2 was left untouched.</p>
   <p>September 26 USDA reports rated 60% or more of the pasture and rangeland in poor or very poor condition in Indiana (60%), Kentucky (65%), and West Virginia (67%).  D0 expanded into northern Indiana and southern Michigan and D1 grew in Indiana, but rains were sufficient in central Ohio to dent the D0 and D1 there.  D0 expanded to cover most of West Virginia and D1 advanced south along the Appalachians to better represent the long-term moisture deficits in the state and agricultural impacts.  In West Virginia, 57% of the corn crop, 75% of the soybeans, and 85% of the apple crop were rated poor to very poor.  D0 extended into the dry areas of Kentucky and adjacent southwest Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
