<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100624</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next two days, a cold frontal system will push across the Great Lake states and the Northeast, which could possibly bring some much-needed relief to the drought-stricken areas in that region.  Excessive heat will continue to be a factor in the Gulf Coast states over the next U.S. Drought Monitor period.  In general a trough will begin to settle in the West and the East, and a ridge will form in the central states over the next week and beyond.  Warmer than average temperatures will then dominate the Heartland going into the extended six to ten day period.</p>
   <p>Over the next six to ten day period, outlooks are projecting above normal temperatures throughout the central United States, including many areas that have been in developing drought conditions, from the Dakotas to Texas.  Warmer temperatures in combination with the forecast below normal precipitation centered on Kansas will be a welcome change for those in Nebraska and South Dakota who have experienced large scale flooding this spring.  But this same forecast could worsen drought in western Oklahoma and northern Texas.  Above average precipitation is forecast in the Southeast for this period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, a reassessment of conditions on the Big Island prompted a one category improvement on the eastern slopes, removing moderate drought from that area.  Degradation of conditions on Maui motivated an expansion of moderate and severe drought categories on that island.  Water quality is being impacted in this area due to the continuing drought.</p>
   <p>Alaska and Puerto Rico had no change in drought conditions this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Abnormally dry conditions have been developing in the Baltimore-Washington, DC area, and eastward over Delaware.  This week D0 is depicted on the map to reflect rainfall deficits of up to four or five inches in areas over the last 30 days.  Some impacts are also being reported, such as deteriorating vegetation health.</p>
   <p>In North Carolina, dry conditions are also developing along the Tennessee border and D0 was introduced this week.  Lower than normal streamflow and lack of precipitation have been notable in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mississippi River Valley">
   <p>An introduction of abnormally dry conditions was needed in the Mississippi River Valley in southeastern Missouri and the surrounding areas of Tennessee and Arkansas.  A combination of heat and lack of rainfall prompted this new area of D0.  Some cities such as Bloomfield, Glennonville and Alton, MO have had no measurable precipitation for June to date.  Missouri has been drought-free since Christmas 2008, with the exception of one week in October 2009.</p>
   <p>A tongue of abnormally dry conditions was extended up river along the Arkansas/Mississippi border as well.  This is a reflection of continuing precipitation deficits over the last 30-60 days, and lower than average streamflow for this time of year.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast">
   <p>A small reduction in the extent of abnormally dry conditions in Pennsylvania and New Jersey this week after an evaluation of the last 30 to 60 days.  Well-timed rainfall has brought this area into drought-free conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>Numerous adjustments and a large expansion of drought in Texas were made on the map.  These changes are in response to continued shortages in precipitation and the Standardized Precipitation Index for the last 30-90 day periods, in addition to increasing reports of agricultural impacts.  With the exception of the region that received extremely heavy rainfall two weeks ago, most of east Texas is in developing or worsening drought conditions. A large expansion of abnormally dry conditions was made along the Red River where moisture deficits are evident in rainfall and soil moisture data.  In central Texas additional area of D0 was introduced from Dallas-Fort Worth curving south and west to the Pecos River.  The Dallas-Fort Worth area experienced its third driest May 1 to June 20 period on record since 1899.  Moisture deficits anywhere from three to nine inches are being reported fot the last 90 day period.  D0 is also shown in the coastal counties from Corpus Christi to Galveston.  Moderate drought has been making agricultural impacts in central Texas, and an area of D1 is depicted this week from the Red River to Temple.  In east Texas, moderate drought is expanded from Louisiana to cover all of the border counties and inland to Houston.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>In the northern states, a one-category improvement was made across much of the Idaho panhandle and western Montana.  Spring precipitation was near or above normal in this region, and water resources have been replenished.  A small area of moderate hydrological drought remains along the border.  Cooler than average temperatures have also alleviated drought conditions, and severe drought is no longer evident.  A one-category improvement was made in and around Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming.  Precipitation and streamflow for the last 30 days were cause for this depiction.</p>
   <p>Southwestern Colorado’s drought situation continues to degrade, as D0 was expanded this week to include Rio Grande, Archuleta, La Plata and Conejos counties.  Lack of precipitation over the last few months has contributed to these dry conditions, and low streamflows are also supportive of this depiction.</p>
   <p>A slight expansion of abnormally dry conditions was made to include northern Yavapai county, Arizona.  Continued lack of rainfall and increased concern over wildland fire prompted this adjustment to the map.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Upper Midwest">
   <p>Improvements due to recent wet conditions in Minnesota and Wisconsin brought many southeastern Minnesota counties into drought-free status.  This region reaches eastward across central Wisconsin.  A tight gradient from severe to no-drought areas is evident from north to south in central Wisconsin.  Lake levels continue to be low, and are being compared to those of the 1930s.  Some locally heavy rain measurements of more than two inches were cause for improvement in Waseca county.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Laura Edwards</name>
   <affiliation>Western Regional Climate Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
