<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070329</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>From March 28 to April 2, a classic spring storm will affect much of the nation.  Locally severe thunderstorms will erupt on the Plains March 28-30, followed by generally weaker, early-April showers and thunderstorms across the eastern one-third of the U.S.  Meanwhile, heavy, late-March snow will gradually shift from Utah and western Colorado northward into eastern Montana and parts of the western Dakotas.  Rain showers will return to the Midwest toward the end of March and spread into the Northeast in early April.  According to the National Weather Service, storm-total precipitation may reach 1 to 3 inches across the majority of the Plains and the upper Midwest, with some higher amounts possible in north-central Texas and near the Montana-Wyoming border.  Elsewhere, mostly dry weather, accompanied by a return to warm weather, will prevail into early April from California to the southern Rockies.  Mostly dry weather will also persist in the southern Atlantic region, including Florida.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for April 3-7 calls for near- to above-normal precipitation across the majority of the U.S.  Mostly dry weather will be confined to eastern Alaska and the southern two-thirds of the West, while wet conditions will be most likely across Texas and the Great Lakes and Northeastern states.  Unusually warm weather will prevail across much of the West and Southeast, while cooler-than-normal conditions will be confined to areas from the northern and central Plains into the Northeast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Once again, there were no changes in the depiction of dryness and drought for Alaska and Puerto Rico.  Mainland Alaskas abnormally dry (D0) areas experienced another cold, dry week, while heavy rain (locally 2 to 6 inches) in Puerto Rico uncannily fell just north of the areas affected by dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1).  Isolated weekly totals approaching 2 inches across the southwestern quadrant of Puerto Rico were insufficient to change the drought depiction.  Puerto Rico also noted a continuation of unusually warm conditions; for example, San Juan posted 33 consecutive days with above-normal daily average temperatures from February 22 to March 26.  San Juan also collected a daily-record high of 92F on March 23.  Meanwhile, relatively tranquil conditions returned to Hawaii, following mid-month downpours across portions of the western and central islands.  Farther east, on the Big Island, short-term rainfall deficits began to mount, even in non-dry areas.  For example, Hilos March 1-27 rainfall totaled just 4.25 inches (34 percent of normal), but the year-to-date sum stood at 30.71 inches (99 percent).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Record-setting warmth enveloped the Southeast, aggravating the effects of persistently dry weather.  On March 25, temperatures exceeded the 90 mark as far north as Augusta, Georgia (91F).  For the week (March 20-26), temperatures averaged as much as 15-20F above normal across the interior Southeast.  A precipitation study of northern Alabama (Climate Division 1) showed that rainfall for the most recent 26-month stretch (January 2005  February 2007) totaled 98.02 inches, the lowest in that region for any corresponding period since January 1954  February 1956, when 96.87 inches fell.  In addition, short-term dryness intensified across the Southeast.  Through March 27, month-to-date rainfall totaled less than one-third of an inch and was less than 10 percent of normal at several locations, including Fayetteville, Arkansas (0.29 inch), and Greenwood, Mississippi (0.17 inch).</p>
   <p>Agriculturally, Southeastern dryness was a double-edged sword: planting advanced rapidly, but pastures, winter grains, and emerging summer crops were growing under increasingly stressful conditions.  Irrigation continued in Floridas citrus groves to maintain favorable conditions during the bloom period, and some Southeastern producers were already watering corn and other emerging summer crops.  By March 25, Mississippis corn was 76 percent sown (36 percent emerged), versus the 5-year planting average of 20 percent.  However, USDA rated Mississippis topsoil moisture 84 percent very short to short, and pastures were rated 36 percent very poor to poor, up from 19 percent a week ago.  In Florida, topsoil moisture was 90 percent very short to short, while pastures were rated 80 percent very poor to poor.</p>
   <p>Coverage of dryness and drought was expanded to cover the Southeast in its entirety, with the exception of the western and central Gulf Coast regions.  An area of extreme drought (D3) was introduced along the Alabama-Tennessee border, while moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) covered areas from the southern Appalachians and adjacent western slopes southwestward to the coastal areas of Alabama and Mississippi.  In addition, severe drought continued to expand in the vicinity of Floridas Lake Okeechobee, which fell to 10.55 feet on March 27 and stood just 1.58 feet above the record-low average surface elevation established on May 24, 2001.  Since 1932, the level of Lake Okeechobee has fallen to 10.50 feet or below during just seven droughts: 1956, 1962, 1971, 1981, 1990, and 2001.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>March has been a little wetter than previous months across the upper Great Lakes region, but conditions ranging from abnormally dry (D0) to extreme drought (D3) persisted.  For example, March 1-27 precipitation totaled 4.04 inches (150 percent of normal) in Marquette, Michigan, following an extremely dry period from June 2006 to February 2007.  From June to February, Marquettes precipitation of 19.32 inches (71 percent of normal) was the third-driest such 9-month period there since 1961.  One significant drought impact that continued to plague the upper Great Lakes region was the unusually low surface elevation of Lake Superior.  At the end of February 2007, the average water level of Lake Superior stood at 599.7 feet above mean sea level, 1.3 feet below the February 2006 daily mean and 1.6 feet below the long-term February daily mean.  The Lake Superior record minimum February daily mean surface elevation of 599.6 feet was established in 1926.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, conditions remained unchanged across the northern half of the Plains but mostly improved farther south.  Abundant rains (2 inches or more) fell across the northwestern half of Oklahoma and south-central and southeastern Kansas, helping to eradicate the lingering pocket of severe drought (D2) and reducing the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1).  Heavy rainfall also struck central and south-central Texas, eliminating exceptional drought (D4) and significantly shrinking the areal extent of other drought categories.  Month-to-date rainfall climbed to 5.64 inches in San Antonio, Texas, representing its third-wettest March behind 6.12 inches in 1992 and 5.91 inches in 1921.  In contrast, short-term dryness (D0A) expanded to cover parts of eastern Oklahoma and northeastern Texas.  In eastern Oklahoma, March 1-27 rainfall totaled just 0.49 inch (16 percent of normal) in Muskogee and 0.80 inch (23 percent) in McAlester.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Temperatures fell from the previous weeks lofty levels but remained above normal for the 7-day (March 20-26) period.  Late in the period, favorably cooler, wetter weather arrived in the West in conjunction with a developing storm.  Nevertheless, the overall Western depiction exhibited a worsening trend due to a disappointing winter wet season, prematurely melting snow, and worsening prospects for spring and summer runoff potential.  In particular, drought areas of the Southwest and Intermountain West were connected, resulting in a net expansion of moderate drought (D1) across Nevada, Utah, and adjacent areas.  Farther south, however, some much-needed precipitation fell across central and southeastern Arizona, helping to slightly reduce the coverage of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
