<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100617</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 day (June 17-21) temperatures are expected to be warmer than normal over much of the eastern United States and into the High Plains.  Temperatures will range from 6 to 9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal over Kansas and Oklahoma to 12 degrees Fahrenheit below normal in Montana.  The western United States will have temperatures below normal during this time.  An active precipitation pattern will be observed along the northern portions of the United States and along the southeastern coast.  Precipitation maxima are expected over Montana, Iowa, southern Wisconsin and Florida.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (June 22-26) has temperatures expected to be well above normal over the eastern half of the United States, with the greatest anomalies over Arkansas.  Cooler than normal temperatures over California and Oregon should be expected as well.  The wet pattern should persist over the northern United States and drier than normal conditions over the southern plains and into the central Rocky Mountains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Southeastern Alaska had a very dry May, with Ketchikan recording only 2.12 inches, or 24 percent of average precipitation.  Juneau measured 1.25 inches for the month, also 24 percent of normal, and the fourth driest May on record.  For the last three months, Ketchikan is over eight inches below normal and Juneau is almost two inches below normal in precipitation, or 70 and 79 percent of normal respectively.  Monthly average temperatures were above normal, and some daily record high temperatures were also recorded in this region, which can exacerbate drought.  As a result of these factors, D0, abnormally dry conditions, was introduced this week to southeast Alaska.  The depiction of drought on this week’s map did not change in the Interior, where wildland fire behavior has been more like summer.  Hawaii and Puerto Rico had no change in drought conditions this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Dry conditions expanded this week to include more of the Coastal Plain in North Carolina.  Lack of rainfall over the last 30 days, low streamflow and elevated drought indices more typical of late summer contributed to this designation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>Record rainfall in Texas was worthy of a one- to two-category improvement in a swath from San Antonio to Texarkana, resulting in no drought depiction.  Two inches or more of rain fell along this line, with local seven-day totals of more than 10 inches.  Elsewhere in Texas, the abnormally dry conditions expanded along the Gulf Coast from the Brazos River to Lake Charles, Louisiana.  This new area includes Beaumont, Houston and Galveston, all of which are reporting precipitation deficits of over an inch for the month.  For the year to date, Beaumont is 11.98 inches below normal, Houston Hobby 8.97 inches below normal, and Galveston 5.34 inches below normal.</p>
   <p>In Oklahoma, significant precipitation brought reductions in the extent of dryness in the southwestern part of the state.  Oklahoma Mesonet stations in the counties of Comanche, Grady and near Oklahoma City reported from two to over 11 inches of rain on June 14th.  The area of D1 was reduced to Washita county and northern Caddo county.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Heavy rainfall over the past week and a half in the upstate New York area, including Buffalo, were reason for an improvement in drought conditions.  Abnormally dry conditions were removed from this region.  Buffalo airport has already measured the tenth wettest June on record, as of the 15th of the month.  Soil moisture and streamflow are improved as well.  Elsewhere in the Northeast, no changes were made.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>An assessment of conditions in northeastern California, southern Oregon and northwestern Nevada led to an improvement in the depiction of drought.  The area of D2 Severe Drought was reduced to Klamath county and the surrounding area.  Drought impacts continue to be reported in the Klamath River basin.  The extent of moderate drought is now smaller in northern Nevada.  The spring season was wet and cool, with some late-season snow in May.  This all contributed to a delay in the peak runoff in the mountain streams, and reservoir storage is overall currently in good condition leading into the summer dry season.  In California, rangeland conditions are reported as being in good to excellent condition statewide.</p>
   <p>Conditions in Colorado improved somewhat in the northwestern part of the state, and in northeastern Utah.  The Yampa River region has improved to non-drought conditions this spring.  Additionally, observers in this region have measured near normal rainfall for the water year so far (since October).  In the past several days, over an inch of rain has fallen at John Jarvie Ranch, UT and at a remote weather station nearby, warranting a one-category change to D0 in far northeastern Utah and northwestern Colorado.</p>
   <p>New Mexico’s drought is worsening with continued lack of precipitation over the last six weeks, and extremely high temperatures are increasing demand for water.  The first two weeks of June have been the third warmest on record at Albuquerque, since 1892.  Average temperatures are more than five degrees above normal across most of the state.  The bulk of last week’s abnormally dry region was downgraded to moderate drought, or D1.  D0 was extended to cover most of northern and central New Mexico.  The state is drying out quickly this spring, and pasture and rangeland conditions are deteriorating.  For the month of May, some areas in this expanded drought region received less than 10 percent of normal precipitation.  Just a few scattered locales received 60-80 percent of normal for the month.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Upper Midwest">
   <p>Rainfall in Minnesota helped to alleviate dry conditions in that state.  Improvements were made in the Canadian border counties of Lake of the Woods and Koochiching, as well as in the western part of the Twin Cities metropolitan area.  These locations are now drought free on the map.  Lake levels in the eastern Twin Cities area are still low.  A one-category improvement was made along the North Shore, over Duluth and Two Harbors, as a reflection of above normal precipitation for the last 90 days.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
