<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100114</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (January 14-19, 2010), a nice warm up is in store for almost the entire country, with some readings expected to be 10 to 20 degrees above normal in the northern Plains. More modest warming is expected elsewhere, but it is a nice change of pace from the bitter cold of the past few weeks. The best bet for significant precipitation (one inch or more of liquid equivalent) seems to be concentrated across the Pacific Northwest and northern California, which could really use it. The other area worth noting, for those drought-affected regions, is across southern Texas, where the odds favor some beneficial rains.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day forecast (January 19-23) is also quite favorable precipitation-wise and perhaps reflective of a pattern change as a result of El Ni&#241;o (favoring above-normal precipitation across the southern tier states). The odds are good for above-normal precipitation across most of the West (all but the northern border regions of Washington, Idaho and northwestern Montana). The best chances are found over most of California, southern Nevada and Arizona. West Texas (the Big Bend area in particular) looks to remain dry during this time frame. The entire eastern half (all but southern Florida) of the country has increased chances of above-normal temperatures, with the best chances found in the Upper Midwest and Great Lakes regions. The Southwest and most of California are looking at better odds of seeing below-normal temperatures to go along with the increased chances of precipitation noted earlier.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawa, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The dry pattern persisted again last week across the state of Hawaii, which is seeing below-normal streamflows across many parts of the islands. In addition, pasture conditions continue to worsen in the lower elevations. Changes of note this week include a slight expansion of D3 drought in western Molokai and western leeward Maui. D0 now covers all of Kauai, Oahu and the Big Island.</p>
   <p>Dry conditions and lagging snow totals led to some expansion of the D0 this week across parts of Alaska. Snow water equivalent values continue to fall, resulting in a push of D0 into parts of the Kenai Peninsula (Anchorage area).</p>
   <p>A continual pattern of good rains fell across Puerto Rico last week, leading to the removal of D0 on the island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>The significant precipitation that fell in this region managed to miss the drought-affected regions of Minnesota and Wisconsin. The D1 and D2 drought in this area seems to be locked in for the winter.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>The Great Plains also felt the brunt of the cold arctic outbreak, with temperatures falling 10 to 20 degrees below normal for this time of year. In Texas, which is the only state showing any form of drought in this region, the D0-D2 remain unchanged after a dry week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>The big freeze and significantly below-normal temperatures (10- to 20-degree departures) that spread southward out of the Great Plains and spilled into the Deep South and Southeast were the major story this past week. There are no changes to the map’s depiction in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A relatively dry week shows no areas improving their status. The only areas really benefitting from recent storms seem to be contained to the coastal regions of the Pacific Northwest, which is not currently in drought.</p>
   <p>As for the rest of the story, D0 continues to spread across more of eastern Nevada, southern Idaho, northern Utah, western Wyoming and northwestern Colorado. Temperatures were generally cooler than normal in these states, but many of the basins are only running at 50-75% of normal snowpack, with snow water equivalents (SWE) following suit at 50-75% of normal as well.</p>
   <p>Reservoir conditions are a mixed bag across the West according to USDA-NRCS, with below-normal values in Nevada, New Mexico and Oregon but closer-to-normal values for Arizona, Colorado and Wyoming. Streamflows across the West are generally below normal for all but the Pacific Northwest and Rocky Mountain Front Range.</p>
   <p>After yet another dry week in the Southwest, and compounded long-term by a very modest monsoon season, changes for the worse are noted this week. An expansion of D0 is noted in central New Mexico as well as a slight incursion of D1 and D2 in those extreme western counties bordering Arizona. In Arizona, D2 now covers most of the state, and a slight expansion is also noted in the D3 across the northeastern Arizona tribal land region. Impacts are starting to flow in with regard to severely impacted range conditions in Arizona, and also in many states in the Southwest and four corners region. The D2 has also spread out of Arizona and connected with previous areas of D2 in southern Nevada and southeastern California in the Mojave Desert region. Rainfall totals in this area are only coming in at 25-50% of normal or worse in some spots, a little better in others, but generally, not good with each passing dry month. There may be some hope on the horizon, though, with a shift in the weather pattern as detailed in the Outlook section summary below.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
