<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20021205</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) the storm system that brought beneficial moisture to New Mexico December 3 will affect much of the Southeast and Mid-Atlantic region with snow, sleet, freezing rain, and rain December 4-5; 2) dry weather will continue to be the major event in most of the West during the next week (December 5-9); 3) the western ridge is projected to flatten some during the 6-10 day period (December 10-14), allowing more precipitation to return to the West Coast; 4) as a result of a flatter western ridge, temperatures will moderate during the same 6-10 day period across the northern U.S., although the dry pattern is expected to continue; and 5) additional precipitation is expected in the southeastern U.S. December 10-14.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>In Hawaii, long-term moderate drought (D1) conditions still exist on western Molokai, causing some hydrological impacts. November was dry across the state, with Hilo recording only 2.86 inches of precipitation (18.4% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>The past week was generally dry and cold across the East, including the abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) areas in Maine and from New Jersey to Georgia. Generous lake-effect snows did fall east of Lakes Erie and Ontario. In the Mid-Atlantic region, groundwater levels continue to improve in most places. Because of the groundwater recovery, the abnormally dry (D0) category was removed from central and southern Delaware, as well as southeastern Maryland. No additional changes were made to the abnormally dry and drought areas in the East. It was another dry week across Puerto Rico as well, prompting a slight expansion of the D0 area here. Percent of normal precipitation for the past eight weeks is generally less than 50% in this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>Like the East, the Midwest and most of the Plains experienced a dry and cold week. Lake-effect snows were common in many areas and even some areas that normally don't see lake-effect snow (eastern Michigan, eastern Wisconsin, Chicago) got in on some of the action. Overall, the month of November was very dry across the entire region. As a result of this continuing dry period, moderate drought (D1) expanded across northeast Missouri, northern Illinois, and northwest Indiana. In western Missouri, the severe drought (D2) category expanded to include Kansas City (43% of normal over the last six months), Springfield (37% of normal over the last three months), and Joplin (33% of normal over the last four months).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>For a majority of the West, the past week was warm and dry. A storm system did bring beneficial precipitation across southern California and parts of Arizona before moving east as the week continued. As a result, an area of extreme drought (D3) east of San Diego was improved to severe drought (D2). Large year-to-date negative precipitation deficits still remain for the major cities in the Southwest (Phoenix -4.79 in., Tucson -3.93 in., Flagstaff -9.10, San Diego -7.33 in., Los Angeles -9.41 in., and Las Vegas -2.75 in.). In the Northwest, Boise, ID, is on pace to establish their driest calendar year on record in 2002. As of December 3, year-to-date precipitation had totaled 4.93 inches, which is a departure of 6.03 inches below normal. The lowest calendar year precipitation total for Boise was set in 1966 with 6.64 inches. Normal December precipitation for Boise is 1.38 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
