<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040610</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Ongoing or forecast weather over the next 2 weeks potentially having an impact on dryness or drought areas include: 1) heavy rains over central and eastern Texas and central and eastern Oklahoma on June 8-9, as well as locally heavy rains in south-central South Dakota on June 8; 2) low pressure over the northern Plains bringing rain to the Dakotas and Montana on June 10-12; 3) frequent showers over the Southeast; 4) much cooler over the West at the start of the forecast period, but turning hotter around June 15, with the heat likely to persist in the West and northern Plains well into week 2, and little or no rain over the Southwest the entire period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Seven-day rainfall exceeding 1.0 inch in the interior southeast reduced the D0 area. Amounts were in the normal to below-normal range over the remainder of the D0 area, including the Panhandle.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>A drier week over most of the Midwest benefited farmers following the drenching rains of the previous week. In the High Plains, additional showers resulted in some pullback of the D0/D1/D2 areas in the eastern Dakotas, but mostly dry weather caused expansion of D2 in western South Dakota and southwestern North Dakota. Heavy rains in northern Texas removed D0 dryness in the north-central and northeastern areas, and removed D1 drought from the southern Texas Panhandle, but D1 drought expanded eastward from southern New Mexico into the southern High Plains of west Texas, where little rain has fallen during the past 2 months. Heavy showers in eastern Oklahoma caused a slight reduction of the D1 area in the southeast portion of the state, but dry weather in the west-central part of the state caused expansion of the D1 there. Dryness in parts of east-central Kansas allowed D0 to expand eastward, while D2 drought grew in southwestern Kansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Heavy showers eased dryness across Florida, southwestern Georgia, and southeastern Alabama. In Florida, rainfall totals for the 7 days ending on June 8 exceeded 4 inches in parts of the southern interior, the central east coast, and the northwest. The moisture resulted in removal of D1 in northern and southern Florida, and D0 in much of the peninsula south of Gainesville except for the extreme south. Totals ranging up to 1 inch or more had little impact on the continuing drought in most of Georgia and South Carolina, although the D0/D1 area retreated in southwestern Georgia. In southeastern Georgia, the rains were not enough to prevent D2 from expanding southward toward the coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>Hot weather over the West allowed drought to persist, with temperatures 5 to 10 degrees F above normal in the Great Basin. The heat moved into the Rockies and High Plains late in the period, with highs in the mid to upper 90s in parts of Colorado, South Dakota, Nebraska, and Kansas on June 6, and triple digit readings in eastern Colorado and adjacent Kansas and Nebraska on June 7. The Southwest stayed generally dry this period, but rain and some high-elevation snows spread across the Pacific Northwest into northern Montana. Although precipitation amounts were generally less than 1 inch in northern Montana, the Drought Monitor showed some improvement based on the weekly precipitation and updated streamflow and reservoir information. D3 or worse conditions remained over much of southern Montana and portions of west-central Montana. Cumulative precipitation in Great Falls from October 1 through June 5 totaled only 61 percent of normal, but Helena, to the southwest, recorded 93 percent of normal. Miles City, in the D3 area in the east, recorded a meager 49 percent of normal for this time period. Stream flows reached record lows for this time of the year in parts of southeastern Montana. To the south, dry weather allowed D3 to expand in southern Wyoming. Rain and mountain snows further eroded dryness in western Washington and northwestern Oregon.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
