<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20131010</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Weather Summary: Heavy precipitation hammered the northern and (to a lesser extent) eastern tiers of the large dry area in the central and western United States. A broad region from southern Montana and the northern half of Wyoming eastward across western and central South Dakota, southern North Dakota, and parts of the western Great Lakes region received at least 2 inches of precipitation, as did portions of the central Great Plains and lower Mississippi Valley. Amounts of 3.5 to locally 7.0 inches were widespread across west-central parts of the Dakotas, most of which fell as snow. The resulting blizzard set several snowfall records in the region, including areas of western South Dakota that had been affected by dryness and drought. Rapid City, SD measured 23.1 inches October 4-5, 2013, breaking their old 2-day record of 20.4 inches set in April 2001. By October 6, Rapid City had already set a new October monthly snowfall record (23.1 inches), which was 150 percent of the old record observed in 1919. Snowfall amounts reached 58 inches near Beulah, SD, and a wind gust of 71 mph was recorded at Ellsworth AFB. In addition, blizzard or near-blizzard conditions also covered areas westward through much of Wyoming, eastward through the central Dakotas, and southward into northwestern Nebraska, at least briefly.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, heavy precipitation (2 to slightly over 4 inches) fell on much of an area from eastern Nebraska northeastward through the western Great Lakes, and scattered parts of the lower Mississippi Valley.</p>
   <p>Moderate rain fell in association with a frontal system on most of the dry areas in the East and on scattered locations across the northeastern tier of Hawaii, but most of the state reported light amounts of 0.5 inch or less. Similar amounts were reported in the Southeast, the west-central and southern Plains, the southern half of the Rockies, the Intermountain West, and the dry areas along the West Coast.</p>
   <p>This pattern resulted in broad areas of improvement, with only isolated areas in Texas and northwestern Kansas deteriorating.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During October 9-13, a slowly-moving coastal storm is expected to drop heavy rain on much of the mid-Atlantic and lower Northeast. More than 1.5 inches is expected from extreme southeastern New York and northeastern Pennsylvania southward through northern and eastern Virginia and northeastern North Carolina, with amounts approaching 4 inches along the immediate East Coast. Farther west, another round of heavy precipitation could be in store for the western Dakotas and adjacent areas, where 1 to 2 inches are anticipated. Similar amounts are expected in central and northeast Texas. Generally moderate precipitation of at least 0.5 inch is forecast for the central Rockies and in northwestern and southeastern portions of the Plains, including the western lower Mississippi Valley. Across other areas from the Rockies westward, only a few tenths of an inch of precipitation is expected, with little or none forecast along the extreme southern tier and in the central Pacific Coast.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (October 14-18), the odds favor above-normal precipitation across a large swath from Wyoming and South Dakota southward through the High Plains and eastward to the Atlantic Seaboard, except in Florida and the adjacent Southeast. The likelihood of above-normal precipitation is highest across the central and southern Plains. In contrast, below-normal amounts are favored in the northern Intermountain West and along the northern half of the Far West. In Alaska, enhanced chances for above-normal precipitation exist statewide.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Despite nondescript weekly rainfall reports across Hawaii, impact assessments led to a westward retraction of D0 and D1 on Kauai and Oahu Islands. Meanwhile, D1 expanded to cover all of Lanai. Conditions were unchanged elsewhere.</p>
   <p>The areas of dryness and drought in Alaska received only a few tenths of an inch of precipitation, if any. D0 and D1 areas remained unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East Coast">
   <p>The moderate precipitation in the mid-Atlantic and Northeast kept further deterioration at bay, but was not enough to bring significant improvement. Thus, the D0 areas remained unchanged. Farther south, light precipitation along the coast of the Carolinas allowed moisture shortages to increase slightly, but not enough to prompt a deterioration in the Drought Monitor depiction. During the last 90 days, the dry areas along the East Coast received 3 to locally 7 inches less precipitation than normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The heavy to record precipitation along the northern tier of this region brought widespread improvement. Large areas of 1-category improvement and a couple small areas of 2-category improvement (most notably near the Black Hills) were brought into Wyoming, northern Nebraska, South Dakota, eastern North Dakota, southern Minnesota, Iowa, and portions of Illinois and Wisconsin. In the northwestern Plains and adjacent Rockies, surplus precipitation dates back at least to the beginning of the calendar year. However, even though some areas received heavy precipitation this week, 60-day totals remained 3 to locally 8 inches below normal in most areas from south-central Oklahoma northeastward across southeastern Kansas, central and northern Missouri, central and western Illinois, central and southeastern Iowa, and portions of central Minnesota and western Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>Farther west, 30-day precipitation amounts were below normal across western Texas, but in the central High Plains, above-normal precipitation exists on time scales dating back at least 90 days. As a result, small areas in western Texas deteriorated, but most of the region remained unchanged despite the dry week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Lower Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Once again, a scattered to broken pattern of moderate to locally heavy rain affected the region. Enough rain has fallen near the Mississippi/Arkansas/Louisiana triple point and across southern Louisiana in the last 2 weeks to engender 1-category improvements in substantial parts of these regions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Half of the Rockies, the Intermountain West, and the West Coast">
   <p>Little or no precipitation fell on these areas, but surpluses have accumulated along the northern tier of this region during the last 30 to 60 days, leading to improvement in parts of Oregon, Idaho, and southwest Montana. Elsewhere, dryness and drought remained essentially unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
