<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010927</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During September 26 through October 1, much of the nation will experience tranquil weather which is not uncommon for this time of year. The most notable exceptions will be across the Florida peninsula, where a wave of low pressure will traverse a stalled frontal boundary providing the potential for heavy rainfall across parts of the Sunshine State. Early in the period, an upper level low pressure system across the Great Lakes and Northeast will provide generally cloudy, cool conditions along with scattered showers which will help ease existing dryness. Looking ahead to October 2 to 5, more dry weather will persist across a large portion of the country, with the best chances for precipitation continuing across Florida and the immediate southeastern seaboard. Odds favor below normal temperatures continuing in the East, with unusually warm weather for the northern plains westward through the Rockies.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>The drought depiction remains unchanged this week, with continued spotty precipitation amounts across the Hawaiian chain during the last 7 days. The islands will continue to be monitored for signs of deterioration or improvement as the wetter time of the year approaches for many areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast, Great Lakes Region, upper Mississippi Valley, and northern Plains">
   <p>A major storm system ushered in fall with significant rainfall across a large area that extended from the Plains eastward to the Atlantic Seaboard. Showers and thunderstorms effectively eliminated remnant D0 in eastern Nebraska and adjacent areas of southwestern Iowa. A second D0 area was removed across central Illinois and eastern Iowa, as precipitation here exceeded 200 percent of normal during the past week. Generous steady rains in Michigan boosted streamflows and increased soil moisture, chasing D0 from the Upper Peninsula and replacing D1 with D0 across the Lower Peninsula. A hydrological line was placed around the Great Lakes indicative of wet topsoil conditions in the wake of recent rains. Farther east, heavy rains on the order of 2 to 4 inches doused portions of the Northeast, with the heaviest concentration of rain falling across upstate New York into central Pennsylvania. This broke drought depiction regions in two, with areas of eastern New York losing nearly all traces of dryness, and shrinkage of D1 in Maryland and western Pennsylvania.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>A cold front brought a corridor of moderate to heavy rains to much of the Southeast, prompting the addition of a hydrological drought line this area. Rainfall in the Piedmont was in the 1 to 2 inch range, with over 2 inches in the Charlotte area which justified the removal of D2. Otherwise, the areal extent of drought depiction remained fairly steady this week as long term water deficiencies remain. Across Florida, most rains this week were confined to the panhandle and the northern Peninsula, with predominately dry weather for the southern part of the state. Although water levels remain near or above normal in most Florida aquifers, levels in the Floridan Aquifer were around 2 feet below normal, requiring the expansion of D0(W) southward into the Orlando area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Tennessee Valley area">
   <p>In Texas, 1 to 2 inches of rain across the central part of the state allowed for a westward shift of D0. Scattered thunderstorms in the Oklahoma panhandle allowed for a contraction of D1, while heavy rains in neighboring Kansas pushed the D0 boundary to the Sooner state line. Frontal rains across the Tennessee Valley promoted the removal of D0 across middle Tennessee and the Cumberland plateau, while farther to the west, lighter rains in northeastern Arkansas held D1 and D2 portrayals steady this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Dry weather prevailed over much of the West, with little net change in overall conditions. An upper level storm system provided rainfall to southern Oregon, northern California and northern Nevada late during the period, with some locations across the higher terrain receiving over an inch of precipitation. Otherwise, fire danger remains high to extreme across parts of the Intermountain West, although the number of large fires and the number of acres burned remains below the 10 year average.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Karin Gleason</name>
   <affiliation>National Centers for Environmental Information</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
