<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050106</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecasts for the next 5 days (Jan. 5-10) show another vigorous system poised to come on shore in the West bringing with it heavy rains to the California coastal ranges (from San Diego to Eureka) and valley locations (1 to 4 inches) as well as several more feet of snow to the slopes of the central and southern Sierra-Nevada range. Amounts are expected to be somewhat lighter but still beneficial drought-wise in extreme western and southern Nevada (&gt; 1 inch) and northern Arizona and southwestern Utah as well (1 to 1.5 inches possible). The same system could bring good snows to the Rockies from Colorado up to western Montana and into Idaho as well.</p>
   <p>Looking out farther at the 6-10 day period (Jan. 11-15), the forecast calls for above-normal precipitation in southern California and the Southwest and for below-normal amounts in both Wyoming and Montana. In the Plains, above-normal precipitation is possible from the Missouri River Valley up into the Great Lakes region. Virtually the entire western half of the United States from the northern Plains across to the Pacific Coast is expected to see below-normal temperatures during the same stretch.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="From the Rockies to the Pacific Coast">
   <p>Once again, the West was pounded by another major storm system late last week and again over the weekend with heavy rains in the lowlands and several feet of snow in the higher elevations. Most of the I-5 and I-15 corridors in California were inundated with rains of 3 to 6 inches (or more locally) and heavy snows of several feet in the upper elevations of the Sierras (now 150-180% average snowpack water content through January 3) bringing much-needed relief to the dryness in the region. While short-term recovery can be seen in soil moisture levels there is still some ground to be made up on the hydrological side of the drought with regards to reservoir storage levels in the region. The abnormally dry (D0) category has been pushed totally eastward off the coast, out of the valleys and up into the leeward side of the Sierra-Nevadas. With the record warm/dry March of 2004 fresh in our memories though, it wouldnt take much to revert back to dryness given the general drawdown of storage in the regions reservoirs unless this wet cycle continues into the spring.</p>
   <p>Farther east, extreme western and southern Nevada (in and around Reno and down to Las Vegas and points south) shared in the excessive wetness as several feet of snow piled up in the Reno/Lake Tahoe area and several inches fell in the south leading to more flooding issues. Arizona also saw a great deal of the wet stuff in both the north ( Flagstaff area) in the form of snow (1 to 3 feet) and in the central valley reaches ( Phoenix area) by way of 3-6 inches of rain. Some of these rain totals looked more like annual totals with more being expected earlier this week. While flooding caused many problems, the good news is that these totals have finally started to put a dent in the long-term drought that has persisted in this region for the better part of five years. While recovery is by no means complete from a storage stand point (especially up river in the Upper Colorado River Basin), it is a welcomed pattern as we head into the new year.</p>
   <p>As a result of the recent series of storm systems in California and the Southwest, there was generally a 1-category improvement across the board for all parts of California, extreme western and southern Nevada (along with a reduction of the severe (D2) and extreme (D3) areas), central and northern Arizona and extreme southern Utah. In addition, good precipitation over the past 6-months (&gt; 125-150% of normal) in parts of southeastern Idaho has led to a slight trimming of the exceptional drought (D4), but most of this region is still in the grips of extreme drought (D3). While only modest in contrast to the changes seen elsewhere in the Southwest, it is hopefully a signal of better things to come as the critical precipitation months in southeastern Idaho are November-February.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>The D0AH area in northern reaches of the Island of Hawaii remains unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Florida">
   <p>The situation in Florida remains unchanged (D0) from last week even though light precipitation fell over parts of the region. The year ended on a drier than usual note with November-December rainfall in Miami coming in as the 8th driest such period on record going back to the late 1800s. West Palm Beach had their 15 th driest December since 1888 and Fort Lauderdales annual total of 41.46 inches was the 9 th driest on record dating back to 1913.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>Last week was relatively quiet precipitation-wise for most of the dry areas of the region. Modest precipitation totals in north-central Minnesota have led to a slight trimming of the abnormally dry (D0) area that was introduced last week. So far this winter (through January 3), the Minneapolis-St. Paul metropolitan area is experiencing their lowest snowfall total (2.8 inches) on record (114 years).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
