<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050120</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) storm systems and mild temperatures will continue to move into the Pacific Northwest region January 18-20; 2) several weak Alberta Clippers will move across the Upper Midwest and Great Lakes January 18-19, with a much stronger clipper providing more significant precipitation to the dryness areas of Minnesota and Iowa January 21-22; 3) this same clipper will become a more major storm along the East Coast January 22-24 and will provide a chance for precipitation to extend across the dry Southeast and into southern Florida; ) the Southeast will then return to relatively dry conditions during the January 25-29 period; and 5) during that same period, a ridge will develop across the western United States and bring relatively mild and dry conditions to much of the West and Great Plains, although precipitation will begin to move back into the southwestern U.S. by the end of the 10-day period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Florida and the Southeast">
   <p>Although southern Florida did receive some rain during the week, the abnormally dry (D0) category remained unchanged across the region. Meanwhile, the rest of the southeastern United States, particularly along the Atlantic Coast, had another relatively dry and abnormally mild week. In cities such as Charlotte, NC; Columbia and Charleston, SC; and Savannah and Augusta, GA, 90-day negative precipitation departures are building. Columbia, Charleston, Savannah and Augusta are at, or below, 50 percent of their normal precipitation since December 1, 2004. Abnormal dryness (D0) was not added to the region at this time, but may need to be put into place in the upcoming weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>The biggest story across this region during the past week was the arctic cold blast. Embarrass, MN, hit -54F in the morning on Martin Luther King Day. Meanwhile, lake effect snows over the weekend dropped two feet of snow over the Keweenaw Peninsula in Michigans Upper Peninsula. Before the arctic airs arrival, a snowstorm dropped more than four inches of snow across the northeast half of Minnesota, but the heaviest amounts missed most of the D0 area in the state. Dry conditions, and a lack of snow cover, continue to plague parts of the Midwest and Plains. As a result, minor expansions of the D0 area were made in southeast South Dakota and northwest Iowa, and moderate drought (D1) conditions spread across southeast Nebraska and adjacent areas of Kansas, Missouri, and Iowa. As 2005 begins, storage along the Missouri River reservoirs has hit an all-time low of 35.2 million acre feet. Runoff for 2004 was only 66 percent of the long-term average and was the fifth consecutive year with below-normal runoff. The navigation season along the Missouri River could be shortened by 33-61 days in 2005 as a result of the low river levels.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>After a very active period across the southern sections of the western United States during the past several weeks, conditions quieted down considerably for the region. Adjustments resulting from some reassessments removed D0 in parts of southern Nevada and southwest Utah; D1 in parts of northeast Nevada, southwest Colorado, and in the Sangre de Cristo Mountains in south-central Colorado; D2 in parts of central New Mexico; and D3 in parts of northeast Arizona. Meanwhile, a heavy snowstorm in the Bear Lake region of Idaho, Utah, and Wyoming helped improve the D4, D3, and D2 conditions across this particular area. Unfortunately, the northern Rockies continue to be relatively dry. As a result, the extreme drought (D3) category was expanded across the Big Horn Basin in north-central Wyoming. Several storm systems moved into Washington, bringing heavy precipitation to the coasts of Washington and northwest Oregon. The D0 category was pushed inland away from these areas that received the heaviest precipitation by the weeks end, with the precipitation expected to continue into the next week. Unfortunately, the temperatures have been so mild with these storms that a considerable amount of the already-limited snowpack in the Cascades has melted as a result. No changes were made to the D0 category in these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
