<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010322</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: 1) A storm system will continue produce widespread precipitation, including high-elevation snowfall, in the northern Mid-Atlantic States and central Appalachians into Thursday, March 22; 2) Mostly dry weather is forecast to return to the Southeast, including Florida, although a cold front may produce light rain toward weeks end; 3) Light precipitation is possible during next few days across the central Plains, but mostly dry weather is expected elsewhere on the Plains; 4) Generally light precipitation may provide limited drought relief in the Northwest by weeks end; and 5) The NWS 6-10 day outlook for the last 5 days of March calls for below-normal precipitation in drought areas of the Southeast, southern High Plains, and Montana Plains. In contrast, beneficial precipitation is forecast to continue in the Northwest, especially from the Cascades westward.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, significant showers were confined to typically wetter windward locations. However, enough rain recently fell across the eastern part of the Big Island to warrant dropping water conservation notices and change the moderate drought (D1) designation to abnormally dry (D0) in most areas. In Puerto Rico, recent widespread showers brought some improvement in streamflows, although abnormally dry (D0) conditions persisted on southern and eastern portions of the island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Appalachians">
   <p>Generally light precipitation brought little change to hydrologically dry (D0) areas in southern West Virginia and adjacent areas, while locally more than 1 inch of moisture provided limited relief to abnormally dry areas in Pennsylvania and southern New York.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Little precipitation was observed on the Montana High Plains, where severe drought (D2) continued. Hydrological dryness (D0) remained a concern as far south as northwestern Kansas and west-central Iowa. Varying degrees of hydrological dryness (D0 to D2) also continued to affect southwestern Texas and southeastern New Mexico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Torrential rainfall continued to pound the Southeast at regular intervals, leaving topsoils wet despite underlying subsoil moisture and water-supply shortages. As a result, hydrological drought persisted across most of the Southeast, remaining at extreme (D3) proportions in western North Carolina. Despite some lingering long-term moisture deficits in southeastern Louisiana and coastal Mississippi, recent heavy rains warranted the elimination of abnormally dry (D0) conditions. Farther north, abnormally dry and moderate drought conditions (D0 and D1) expanded northward across the Mid-Atlantic region. According to preliminary data from the National Climatic Data Center (NCDC), October 2000 - February 2001 was the driest such period on record in West Virginia, Virginia, North Carolina, and Florida.</p>
   <p>On March 15, the South Florida Water Management Districts Governing Board voted to implement Phase III water restrictions in portions of the Lower East Coast and Lake Okeechobee service areas. The more stringent restrictions, which will limit the typical homeowner to lawn watering once per week, are scheduled to take effect on March 28. The average surface level of Lake Okeechobee fell to 10.16 feet on March 18, then rose slightly the next day, but remained at a record low for this time of year. The all-time record-low lake level of 9.75 feet was established on July 29, 1981. The years most significant rainfall, locally in excess of 5 inches, overspread Florida on March 19. The heaviest rain fell in two bands, the first just north of a line from Tampa to Orlando, including Ocala and Daytona Beach, and the second in a corridor roughly from Ft. Myers to West Palm Beach, including Lake Okeechobee. March 19 rainfall of 2.07 inches in Ft. Myers and 5.05 inches in West Palm Beach accounted for more than half of the cities respective year-to-date totals.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A weather pattern change brought a sustained period of dry weather to the Sierra Nevada for the first time in 2 months. According to the California Department of Water Resources, the water content of the Sierra Nevada snow pack climbed to about 22 inches during the 2-month wet spell, up from 5 inches in early January. However, the snow packs water content stood only slightly greater than 80 percent of normal for mid-March, leaving lingering summer water-supply (D0) concerns in areas fed by the Sierra Nevada spring runoff. Meanwhile in the Northwest, light precipitation provided limited drought relief, primarily from the Cascades westward. Slight expansions of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) were noted in northern Utah and southeastern Oregon, respectively. A new area of severe drought (D2) was added in southern Oregon due to meager snow packs and poor spring runoff prospects. According to USDAs SNOTEL network, mid-March snow pack water equivalents generally ranged from 45 to 75 percent of normal in key watershed areas from the Cascades to the northern Rockies. According to NCDC, October 2000 - February 2001 was the second-driest such period during the 106-year period of record in Washington and Oregon. Going back further, NCDCs Northwest Region, comprised of Washington, Oregon, and Idaho, experienced its second-driest March-February period on record, with a 12-month precipitation total slightly less than two-thirds of the long-term average. Only March 1976 - February 1977 was drier in the Northwest.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
