<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040527</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The last days of May 2004 may bring excessive rainfall to at least part of the D1 area in western Arkansas and southeastern Oklahoma, where 4.0 to locally 6.3 of rain are forecast. Elsewhere, moderate to locally heavy precipitation (1 to 4 inches) is anticipated across western sections of Washington and Oregon, northeast Oregon, northern and central Idaho, western and south-central Montana, southeastern Idaho and adjacent Wyoming and Utah, the northern and east-central Great Plains, north-central and northeastern Texas, and the dry areas in North Carolina and Tennessee. In contrast, little or no precipitation is expected in most of the Southeast and across the southwestern quarter of the contiguous states.</p>
   <p>Over the first 5 days of June, wet weather is favored in east-central and upper southeastern Alaska, and across the Southeast except in southern Florida. Meanwhile, deficient precipitation is favored throughout the western half of the country. At the same time, warm weather appears most likely from the central and southeastern Rockies westward to the Pacific Coast, and across Florida and adjacent southeastern Georgia. Cool conditions are favored in upper southeastern Alaska and over the northeastern quarter of the contiguous states.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Periodic precipitation finally eradicated dryness in central Alaska, but D0H conditions persisted farther to the east, where Northway has received just over half of its normal precipitation during the past year. Farther south, short-term dryness has developed in southeastern Alaska and on Kodiak Island. The last 30 days brought 1 to 3 inches of precipitation to most locations in these regions, which is less than half of normal. D0A conditions were introduced because longer-term near- to above-normal precipitation totals precluded any hydrologic concerns.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Moderate to heavy rains (2 to 4 inches) fell on most locations in northern Missouri, southern Iowa, west-central Illinois, northeastern Indiana, and northwestern Ohio, eliminating former D0 to D1 conditions. It should be noted, however, that groundwater levels remained a cause for concern in the old D1 region in northwestern Missouri, and will be monitored closely for signs of dryness or drought re-development. Meanwhile, heavy rainfall evaded northwestern Indiana, keeping D0 conditions intact</p>
   <p>Heavy rainfall of 3 to 6 inches eliminated dryness in northeastern Nebraska, areas near the Minnesota/Iowa border, and southeastern Minnesota. Somewhat lower totals (1 to 3 inches) similarly eradicated former D0 conditions in north-central North Dakota and east-central Minnesota. Meanwhile, moderate to heavy totals (1 to locally 4 inches) improved conditions to D0 or D1 in the rest of southern Minnesota while 1- to 4-inch totals were more scattered across the rest of the northern Plains, resulting in patches of 1-category improvement and keeping other areas from deteriorating. Topsoil moisture in particular benefited from precipitation during this and the previous week. On May 25, 26% of South Dakota topsoils were short or very short of moisture, compared to 72% just 2 weeks earlier. Both North Dakota and Nebraska observed substantial but lesser declines.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, areas across the central and southern Plains experienced a hot and dry week, especially from southern Kansas and eastern Colorado southward through central Texas and western Arkansas, where most locations reported no measurable precipitation and 7-day average temperatures around 4F above normal. These conditions created an environment conducive to rapid surface water loss, and consequently D0 conditions expanded rather dramatically into south-central Kansas, all but northeasternmost Oklahoma, western Arkansas, and much of northern and western Texas. In addition, an area of D1 was introduced in southeastern Oklahoma and adjacent Texas and Arkansas, where longer-term precipitation deficits are extant. Across Oklahoma, the proportion of topsoils short or very short of moisture shot up from 39% 2 weeks ago to 74% on May 25.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Scattered precipitation totals of 1 to 3 inches were observed last week, most commonly in southern and southwestern North Carolina, northern Georgia, and eastern Alabama. Meanwhile, rainfall was scarcest from northern Florida northward through upstate South Carolina and in northwestern Alabama, where most sites recorded below-normal rainfall, if any.</p>
   <p>Rainfall was not strikingly deficient last week, but in combination with unseasonably hot weather (weekly averages 2F or more above normal north of the Gulf Coast), efficient evaporation and transpiration led to drought persistence or intensification. D2 was introduced in most areas assessed as D1 last week, and D1 expanded to cover most of South Carolina, all of central and southern Georgia, and part of northern Florida. Meanwhile, D0 extended westward to encompass all of Alabama, part of the northern Florida Peninsula, and areas near the Appalachians in North Carolina and Tennessee.</p>
   <p>Since late February, precipitation deficits in excess of 7 inches have accumulated in part of central Georgia and much of central and southern Alabama, with 90-day shortfalls between 4 and 7 inches noted over the remaining areas of D1 and D2 conditions. As a result, topsoil moisture was assessed as short or very short across more than half of both Georgia and South Carolina, and in at least 30% of both Alabama and North Carolina, according to the National Agricultural Statistics Service, USDA. In addition, streamflows were among the lowest 25% of all measured levels for this time of year at nearly 80% of observing sites across Georgia and South Carolina on May 25, with one-half to one-third of all sites among the lowest 10% of historic seasonal occurrences, according to the United States Geological Survey.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>Copious precipitation fell on most areas of drought and dryness from the northern Rockies to the Pacific Northwest while heat and deficient precipitation covered areas farther to the south. Exceptional precipitation totals of 3 to 6 inches doused northeastern Oregon and much of the Idaho Panhandle, erasing former D0 conditions. On May 21, Spokane, WA measured almost 2.2 inches of precipitation and recorded 0.4 inch of snow, marking both their all-time wettest single day and latest spring snowfall since records began in 1889.</p>
   <p>Farther east, precipitation totals of 1 to locally 4 inches were fairly widespread across the western half of Montana. Since May 10, over 2.5 inches has fallen on Great Falls, MT, topping the amount they recorded during the previous 6 full months (about 2.2 inches, their second-driest October-April period on record) and breaking their string of 12 consecutive months with below normal precipitation, their longest such stretch since 1936-1937. However, only slight reductions in the extents of D0 to D4 conditions were introduced this week. Montana topsoils markedly moistened up, with short or very short topsoil moisture evident across 44% of the state on May 25, compared to 81% on May 11. However, 72% of Montana subsoils remained short or very short of moisture, and it will take considerably more precipitation to significantly ease the entrenched hydrologic drought, which has resulted from several years of persistently below-normal precipitation and deficient cold-season snowfall.</p>
   <p>From Wyoming, Utah, Nevada, and California southward to the Mexican border, only scattered light precipitation was observed since last Tuesday, generally keeping dryness and drought intact, though conditions deteriorated in a few areas. D1 expanded a bit into the southern Sierra Nevada, D2 conditions filled in most of lower northern Utah and extended across northern Colorado, and D3 pushed into parts of western and southern Nevada, central and southeastern Wyoming, and northern Colorado. Streamflow levels declined through most of these areas last week, especially in Wyoming, where on May 25, 86% of observing sites reported streamflow levels among the lowest 25% of historic measurements for this time of year, with 58% of sites at or approaching record low levels for late May. Only 2 weeks earlier, just over one-third of sites were among the lowest 25% on record for early May, and only 18% were anywhere near record seasonal lows.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
