<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20110113</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (January 12-16), temperatures over the eastern half of the United States look to be well below normal, with the upper Midwest 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit below normal.  The western U.S. will be above normal, with temperatures 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal from Colorado to Washington.  Precipitation is projected to be widespread from the Great Lakes down to the Ohio River Valley and into the Gulf Coast, with the greatest amounts over the Great Lakes and the Ark-La-Tex region.  A strong system will come onshore in the Pacific Northwest, bringing heavy precipitation along with it from Washington and Oregon and into northern Idaho and Montana.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (January 17-21) shows a broad area of cold air over the eastern half of the United States, with below normal temperatures over the entire region down to the Gulf Coast.  The best chances for above normal temperatures are projected over the desert Southwest and the Alaskan coast.  Above normal precipitation is projected over the Southeast and below normal precipitation chances are best over the south from Texas to southern California.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes were made this week for Alaska and Puerto Rico.  Hawaii had some decent rains over Maui and the Big Island during the last week, but improvements were minimal.  Some minimal improvements were made on Maui in the Upcountry regions, improving the D0/D1.  The dry slopes on Maui are starting to green up, but are still short on moisture.  On the Big Island, the D0 in the Kona district was removed and the D2 in the South Kahala District was improved to D1.  No changes to the D3 on the west slopes of Mauna Kea as ranchers in the area are still hauling water.  D0 was expanded on the northeast side of the island as December rainfall totals were 50 percent of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>A significant winter storm impacted the region, bringing with it cold air and record-breaking snow amounts throughout the region.  Florence, Alabama, recorded 11.0 inches of snow and Killen, Alabama, had 10.5 inches of snow while northern Georgia had several reports of 10+ inches of snow. Much of the area was left unchanged this week, with an expansion of D0 and D1 in the Carolinas and an expansion of D2 in northern Florida and D1/D2 expansion in southern Florida as the only changes this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>The same winter storm that impacted the Southeast brought rain and snows to many areas in the southern Plains and Gulf Coast.  Significant improvements were made in Texas as the short-term dryness that was impacting the area was diminished with widespread heavy rain.  Areas that did not record as much precipitation and had both short- and long-term dryness did see a bit of degradation as D2 was expanded in northeast Texas and D1 was brought into northwest Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid Atlantic">
   <p>Short-term dryness in the region is widespread.  A few areas have received significant snow events along the eastern seaboard in recent months, but most have not.  Being in the middle of winter, impacts are going to be minimal, but an area of D0 was expanded into southern Pennsylvania, Maryland, Delaware and Virginia this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>As assessment of conditions in the western United States allowed for the removal of all the remaining D0 in Nevada and California.  No lingering impacts were being reported in this region and precipitation values, especially since the start of the water year, allowed for the removal.  D0 was also improved slightly in Wyoming while D0/D1 was improved in the Four Corners region.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
