<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080313</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (through March 17), an active weather pattern is taking shape for most of the United States, with models in disagreement on exact storm tracks.  Temperatures look to be 3 to 6 degrees Fahrenheit below normal for much of the country except Texas and the Gulf Coast, where temperatures should be 3 to 6 degrees Fahrenheit above normal.  Precipitation looks to be shifting to the north a bit, with storm tracks through the central Plains and Midwest.  Maxima for precipitation during this time are expected over the Pacific Northwest, through Nebraska and Kansas and into Missouri and Kentucky.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6 to 10 day outlook for March 18-22 shows below normal temperatures over Alaska, Great Plains, and into the Great Lakes region.  Above normal temperature should be expected over the Southeast.  Below normal precipitation over Alaska and the High Plains as well as southern Florida should not improve drought status in those regions.  Above normal precipitation over Great Lakes, New England and Ohio River Valley should be observed.  Models at this time are not in good agreement with differences in several large scale features.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>D0 was expanded to include all of the Hawaiian Islands this week.  Continued short-term dryness plagues the entire island chain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Another dry week for the region, except for portions of Oklahoma and Texas.  With the continuing dry winter, D1 conditions were expanded to the southeast in Nebraska and now include extreme northeast Colorado as well as the southwestern portions of Nebraska.  This area was labeled AH in response to the problems with low flows as well as impending dryness for agricultural producers in both the Republican and Platter River valleys.  Texas continues to have a clear delineation line showing where precipitation events have and have not taken place.  Roughly, areas west of Interstate 35 are where dryness continues.  D3 conditions in south Texas were expanded to the southwest this week, with a slight expansion of D2 as well.  The drought status gradient was tightened and shifted to the west as some areas did receive several inches of rain in south central Texas.  Cedar Creek, Texas, recorded 2.54 inches of rain, Somerville Dam 2.59 inches, Refugio 2.30 inches, Coleto Creek Reservoir 2.21 inches,  Danevang 3.05 inches, Edna 3.21 inches, Victoria 3.85 inches, and West Columbia 3.24 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeastern and Mid-Atlantic States">
   <p>Several rain events brought welcomed relief to the region.  Several inches of rain and even snow in higher elevations allowed for widespread improvement to the drought status this week.  The heaviest rains were recorded in a band from northeast Georgia into western North Carolina.  Bryson City, NC, recorded 3.92 inches of precipitation, Buck Forest 3.32 inches, Bent Creek 3.18 inches, Enka 3.45 inches, Hendersonville 4.22 inches, Robinsville 3.23 inches, and Waynesville 3.13 inches.  The precipitation allowed for a categorical improvement of all drought categories in North Carolina, and with the removal of D4 from the state, this is the first time since August 2007 that there is no D4 in North Carolina.  In Georgia, D3 was improved in the northeast corner of the state and D4 was improved in the northwest.  The drought categories in central Georgia were all shifted to the north in response to continuing improvements there.  Northern portions of Florida continued to see precipitation, allowing for the removal of D1 in the area and a reduction of D0 conditions as well.  In southern Florida, conditions along the Kissimmee River were improved to D0 following seasonal changes in regulation levels and consistent rains over the last few weeks.</p>
   <p>Tennessee saw the removal of D3 status in the eastern portions of the state.  Even with the improved conditions in eastern Tennessee, long-term hydrological problems still linger. In Kentucky, D1 conditions were pushed south, almost completely out of the state, while some improvements were also made to the northern extent of the drought status in Virginia.  In Maryland, several inches of rain pushed the D0 and D1 conditions to the south, leaving much of northern Maryland drought free.  Dalecarlia Reservoir in Maryland recorded 3.03 inches, Stevensville 2.17 inches, Smithburg 2.72 inches, and Williamsport 2.92 inches of rain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A dry week in the west with cool temperatures allowed for no changes this week.  The cool temperatures were welcomed as they allow for maintaining current snowpack levels.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
