<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061005</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next five days (October 4  9, 2006), precipitation totals of 1 to 2 inches are forecast for a few small areas currently experiencing dryness or drought, specifically western Colorado, adjacent portions of Utah and Wyoming, and northern Wisconsin. Totals should exceed 0.5 inch in central Idaho, parts of southern and western Montana, the northern and central Rockies, southern Texas, and portions of the central Great Plains, upper Midwest, and Great Lakes regions. In contrast, little if any precipitation is anticipated across the Southeast, the southeastern Great Plains, parts of the northern Great Plains, northern Montana, and most of Washington. For the ensuing 5 days (through October 14, 2006), the odds favor above-normal precipitation in a swath from much of New Mexico eastward to the Atlantic Coast, with below-normal amounts expected in an area extending from northern California and the Pacific Northwest eastward through the central and northern Rockies, the northern half of the Plains, and most of the Great Lakes region and upper Midwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Heavy rains fell on parts of the archipelago last week, but managed to evade the areas currently experiencing dryness and drought. No changes were introduced.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Overview">
   <p>Little or no precipitation fell on those parts of the country classified as D0 (abnormally dry) or worse on the Drought Monitor. According to data compiled by the National Weather Service River Forecast Centers, only about 2.5 percent of these regions received more than 0.5 inch of precipitation for the 7-day period ending Tuesday morning (October 3, 2006). Consequently, there were relatively few changes in the Drought Monitor map this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Between 1 and 3 inches of rain fell on the easternmost parts of the island and on the northwestern fringes of the D0 area, but little or no rainfall was the rule for most of this region. As a result, D0 was expanded into central and east-central Puerto Rico, where rainfall deficits on several time scales (30 days to 6 months) are now similar to the D0 areas farther south and east that were introduced last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Precipitation totals for the week topped 0.5 inch in parts of northwestern North Dakota, northeastern Minnesota, central Wisconsin, the eastern Upper Peninsula of Michigan, and isolated locations in southern Texas, with amounts locally topping 1 inch in small parts of central Wisconsin and the extreme eastern Upper Peninsula. Little or no precipitation fell on the remainder of the dry areas in the Great Lakes region, the upper Midwest, and the Great Plains. No improvements were made to the Drought Monitor map because of the weeks precipitation, but a re-assessment of recent heavy precipitation in the northern Plains led to the removal of D0AH conditions from part of northeastern South Dakota, and to a small reduction in the extent of D3AH conditions near the border separating Nebraska from South Dakota. In contrast, D1AH conditions expanded into many of the former D0AH areas in Missouri and Arkansas, and D3AH conditions pushed into part of central Texas, most notably in the Austin, TX, metropolitan area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, West, and Southwest">
   <p>More than 0.5 inch of rain fell on small portions of central Montana, southwestern Wyoming, and northwestern Colorado, but little if any precipitation was observed in most areas. This essentially left dryness and drought conditions intact, except in the western half of Wyoming, where D1AH to D3AH conditions expanded northwestward in response to poor rangeland conditions, declining stock pond levels, and markedly below-normal precipitation totals over the last 12 months.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Gulf Coast, and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Rainfall totals exceeding 0.5 inch were restricted to the Atlantic Coast of northern Georgia and adjacent South Carolina, and to scattered areas in south-central and southeastern Tennessee, northeastern Alabama, and northern Georgia. Amounts exceeding 1 inch were limited to parts of the northern Georgia and adjacent South Carolina coastline. Little or no rain fell elsewhere. As a result, D0 and D1 (moderate drought) conditions expanded along the southwestern tier of South Carolina, eastern and southern Georgia, and northern Florida. In addition, with surface moisture on the decline, former D0H to D1H areas were reclassified as D0AH to D1AH in Georgia, northern Florida, southern Alabama, and a few adjacent areas. Farther west, growing short-term moisture deficits prompted the re-introduction of D0AH conditions in southwestern Louisiana. Improvement in the region was limited to south-central Tennessee, where light to moderate rains appeared sufficient to eliminate D1H in favor of D0H.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
