<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020418</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Expected weather conditions that may affect abnormally dry or drought areas during the next 5 days (April 18-22) include: 1) General troughing across the northwestern U.S. should bring cool and unsettled weather to the Pacific Northwest and north-central Rockies, including Wyoming; 2) Scattered showers and thunderstorms should develop in the northern Plains and upper Midwest, and eventually the central Great Plains and middle Mississippi Valley, as a storm system tracks northeastward from the central Rockies into Ontario; 3) By the weekend, the cold front is predicted to stall across the Southeast, bringing a good chance of rain and lower temperatures to the Tennessee and Ohio Valleys, and possibly eastward into the mid-Atlantic; 4) The Southwest is forecast to remain dry, with temperatures warming after the weekend.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6-10 day (April 23-27) outlook calls for above-normal precipitation from the northern Plains southeastward into the Carolinas, subnormal totals across southern Alaska, in the Pacific Northwest, along the Gulf Coast, and in the southern Plains, with seasonable amounts elsewhere. Temperatures should remain below-normal in the north-central states and throughout Alaska, warmer than normal conditions are predicted across the southern tier of states, and seasonable readings elsewhere.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>A relatively dry week throughout the Hawaiian Islands, except at windward locations of the Big Island, maintained D0(W) across western Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Two slow-moving storm systems, an upper-air low over the eastern Gulf and a cold front that stalled and then weakened east of the Appalachians, produced widespread showers and thunderstorms east of the Mississippi River. The greatest totals (more than 2 inches) were reported in the lower Ohio River Valley, along the western Gulf Coast, and from the Florida Panhandle northeastward through the Appalachians into western New England. These rains further eased drought and dryness in western Georgia, southeastern Alabama, northern and western Florida, and western and northern drought areas of the Northeast. In the latter area, above normal precipitation since February has gradually raised river and reservoir levels, but wells have been slower to respond, thus maintaining the severe hydrological drought in some New England areas.</p>
   <p>However, amounts rapidly decreased east of the Appalachians (&lt;0.5 inches), and with temperatures averaging 8 to 12F above normal, and evaporation and transpiration rates increasing, extreme drought increased in central Virginia. According to an April 10 report by the Virginia state climatologist, 6-month departures have currently stabilized at very low levels that are slightly less severe than the major droughts of 1930 (the modern Virginia drought of record) or the mid-1960s. Compared to a week ago, 7-day average (ending April 15) USGS stream flows remained at or further declined to near-record lows (&lt;10%ile) in NJ (88%), DE (84%), VA and SC (55%), MD (49%), NC (39%), and GA(33%). Additionally, building short-term deficits and rapid spring growth prompted the northward retreat of the Hydro(W) line into central Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Scattered, locally heavy thunderstorms dropped 1-3 inches of rain on parts of the southern Great Plains, western Corn Belt, and upper Midwest, providing some improvement in south-central Texas (the second straight week with 1-2"), southwestern and central Oklahoma (1.5-3"), and northeastern Iowa (1-1.5"). However, the remainder of the Plains and Midwest recorded much lower totals. Additionally, the week was also very warm and windy, with departures +8 to +15F and highs in the 80's and 90's from Texas northward into South Dakota and Minnesota. As a result, 30 and 90-day precipitation has averaged between 25 and 75% of normal in most of the northern and central Great Plains and western Corn Belt, with deficits between 1 and 4 inches. With both short (30-day) and medium-term (3-4 month) shortages, moderate drought developed over eastern North Dakota, northwestern Minnesota, and western Missouri. The unseasonable warmth and little or no rain expanded D2 into eastern Colorado and extreme western Nebraska, and D1 edged eastward into the western Dakotas. In the northern High Plains, long-term drought and continued poor winter and spring conditions kept the most recent Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) below -3 in much of Montana and Wyoming, reflected in the expanded D2 and D3 drought areas. The NASS/USDA rated 60% of Montanas winter wheat in very poor or poor condition, while Wyomings pasture and range was rated 52% very poor or poor, and topsoil moisture 79% very short or short.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Above normal temperatures contributed to melting snow almost everywhere. Unsettled weather brought moderate to heavy precipitation (2 to 6 inches) to the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies, increasing cumulative precipitation by 1-5%, but little or no precipitation occurred in the remainder of the West. In the Southwest, very warm weather (temperatures averaging more than 10F above normal, widespread highs in the 70's and 80's) further depleted or melted the meager snow pack in Arizona, New Mexico, and the southern halves of Utah and Colorado. The April 1 SWSI further declined in many central and southern Western states, while some improvement was noted in northwestern states. The A,F,W lines were modified to reflect changing impacts as the growing season commenced. The West was broken into three impact areas. The northern 1/3 remained in long-term, hydrological (W) drought from last seasons near-record dryness, although the recent precipitation kept this years cumulative totals and April 15 snow water content at adequate or surplus levels, and improved some areas (e.g. north-central Idaho, northeast Oregon, northwest Montana). In contrast, short-term precipitation deficits in north-central Oregon and south-central Washington has adversely affected the winter wheat and pastures, thus A was added. Main impacts in the southern 1/3 were related to poor pasture and rangeland (A) conditions (over 70% very poor or poor in AZ and NM, according to NASS/USDA) and high wildfire danger (F) due to a near-record dry Oct01-Mar02, but hydrological concerns (W) are less (so far) thanks to a wet October 2000-April 2001. The middle 1/3 impacts are a combination of the other two areas, namely subnormal precipitation this wet season and last, thus all three impacts (A,F,W) were shown.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, the latest March statistics indicated that seasonal (October 01-March02) precipitation was less than 70% of normal across east-central sections of the State, including some areas under half of normal. In addition, mountain snow pack in east-central sections were similarly below normal (50-70%) as of April 1. As a result, D0 encompassed these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
