<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010503</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 5 to 10-day period (May 2-11) that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country: 1) A stationary front draped over the northern Plains states this coming weekend (May 4-6) will bring with it the potential for heavy rains (3 to 6 inches possible in southeast Nebraska, southwest Iowa, northeast Kansas and northwest Missouri), but it appears most of this will skirt north of the drought-affected areas in the Midwest. Temperatures over the same period are predicted to remain at or above normal across much of the Midwest and the Southeast. Only the southern half of Florida seems likely to see any modest precipitation amounts (1 inch or less) in the short term (May 2-7); 2) Looking out further, the 6- to10-day forecasts (valid May 8-12) indicate that temperatures will likely be above normal in the Plains, Midwest, Ohio and Tennessee Valleys and the Northeast. The only area showing a likelihood for above-normal precipitation appears to be centered over Oklahoma and extends north into Kansas and south into most of Texas; 3) In the West, the next 5 days should be cooler and wetter, bringing some relief to parts of the Intermountain ranges and the Rockies. Over the May 8-12 period, a quieter pattern seems to be on the horizon, with temperatures and precipitation near normal except in northern California and Oregon which could see below-normal precipitation; 4) Projected weather patterns over the Hawaiian Islands in the near future dont seem to indicate that any major relief is on the way, which will allow the drought to continue its grip on the leeward areas of the state.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Below-normal rainfall was reported once again across most leeward island locations last week. As the state heads into their dry season, substantial improvement in drought conditions is unlikely unless they see an abnormally wet dry season. Western Molokai seems to be in the worst shape. Although rainfall during the past few weeks has stabilized the situation somewhat, Extreme Drought (D3 A,F) conditions persist in the county.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Appalachians, Ohio Valley and Tennessee Valley">
   <p>Most of the states in these regions saw normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation for the week. Seasonal rainfall and year-to-date deficits continue to accumulate for many areas. Moderate Drought (D1) now encompasses all of Kentucky and continues to push into portions of Tennessee, Ohio, Illinois, Indiana, Missouri and Arkansas. Kentucky is now heading into the growing season riding eight consecutive weeks (March-April was at 57% of normal) of below-normal precipitation while April alone ended up being the seventh warmest and tenth driest on record. Abnormally Dry (D0) conditions have also begun to push out from the D1 core. The expanding Moderate Drought (D1) is now defined to the west along the Missouri/Arkansas border, and the eastern edge intrudes into western Virginia and the Carolinas. The drought has continued to slowly push its way north into the southern reaches of Ohio, Indiana, Illinois and Missouri as well. Soil moisture and streamflow levels have continued to deteriorate rapidly across the entire region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Much warmer temperatures (+5 to +10F) swept into most of the northern Plains states last week, accompanied by very windy conditions. The winds have actually played a favorable role in that they have helped to rapidly warm up and dry out the soggy soils that have been prevalent across the region. The winds have also brought with them an increased risk for wildfires even in areas that may only be experiencing a short-term dry period.</p>
   <p>Cooler temperatures prevailed last week across most of Oklahoma and Texas. Parts of extreme south-central and west Texas also saw above-normal rainfall. For areas south of San Antonio and north of Brownsville, this is the second week in a row of above-normal precipitation in the month of April. In changes of note, Abnormally Dry (D0) conditions are now depicted from the Trans-Pecos to the lower Rio Grande region in west Texas. The average storage from 1996 to present for both Falcon and Amistad reservoirs in west Texas along the Rio Grande is the lowest on record since they were originally filled.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>All but Florida experienced another dry week and most areas along the Atlantic coast from Florida to the Carolinas actually saw cooler-than-normal readings. Although a few places in southern Florida did see above- normal rainfall this past week, April rainfall readings across the state were still below normal, and year-to-date totals also came in below normal (-3 to -6 inch deficits) over most of the state. Districtwide, the South Florida Water Management District reported only 23% of average rainfall (.57 inches) for the month. The recent rains have also done little to dampen fire risk in the state as most of the state remains vulnerable. In addition, the Moderate Drought (D1) area in the Southeast has now joined with the D1 areas in the Ohio and Tennessee Valleys (see below).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>After a short reprieve, a quick return to abnormally warm (+5 to +10F) temperatures across most of the West led to a rapid depletion of snowpack. Precipitation was below normal as well in all but some parts of the Pacific Northwest (Washington, Oregon, the Idaho Panhandle, and northern California). The snows and rains seen in the Pacific Northwest have helped, but have not led to a substantial increase in seasonal precipitation or snow water equivalent readings in most basins. One area of dryness that seems to be expanding is found in eastern Montana, where both Abnormally Dry (D0) and Moderate Drought (D1) conditions have pushed eastward toward Fort Peck Lake as a result of below- normal precipitation and above-normal temperatures this spring. Following on the heels of a dry winter, this has led to a depletion of soil moisture and streamflow levels in many parts of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
