<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030925</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) the remnants from Hurricane Marty that hit Baja California will bring some welcome rains up to 1.0 inch to parts of southern Arizona September 23-25; 2) a storm system could bring heavier rains to northern New England September 27-29; 3) a highly amplified ridge/trough pattern September 30 through October 4 will bring generally above-normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation to the western half of the country and below-normal temperatures in the eastern half; 4) however, unsettled weather may bring above-normal precipitation to a small area of California, Nevada, Utah, and Arizona during this same period; and 5) the easterly trades will continue to remain limited across Hawaii, keeping conditions generally dry on both the windward and leeward sides of the islands through the period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Dryness (D0) continues around the Northway region in southeastern Alaska, although the area did have some showers during the past week. Across Hawaii, the week was generally mild with only scattered windward showers in some locations. No changes were made to the drought classifications for the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Long-term hydrological dryness and moderate drought still persist across much of Maine, as well as stretching across northern New Hampshire, Vermont, and New York. Twelve-month precipitation departures run more than 8.0 inches below normal across the region, with 12.0 inch departures in northern Vermont, and are reflected in the low streamflows in these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Great Lakes">
   <p>Heavier rains for the past week fell across portions of eastern North Dakota, Minnesota, western Wisconsin, western Illinois, Iowa, and Missouri. As a result, dryness (D0) conditions were improved in central Missouri and west-central Illinois, moderate drought (D1) conditions were improved in northern Minnesota and northeastern North Dakota, and severe drought (D2) conditions improved in east-central Minnesota and northwestern Wisconsin. Meanwhile, most of Michigan except for the extreme eastern portion of the state missed Isabel's rains, and moderate drought (D1) was expanded to cover most of the Lower Peninsula. Long-term dryness is affecting the streamflows in southwestern and west-central Missouri and a new D0 (H) area has been established. Joplin, MO, for example, has a 14-month precipitation departure from normal of 18.15 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Much of the western United States had a very quiet, uneventful week last week. Several cold fronts moved across the region, keeping it cooler than normal for this time of year, but these fronts did not provide much precipitation. The only exception to this was an area of moderate rain across north-central Montana. Choteau, MT, northwest of Great Falls, received 1.39 inches for the week. As a result of this precipitation event and longer-term precipitation totals near normal, the D4 drought area was reduced in size slightly in the area around Choteau, and minor improvements were made to the D3 and D2 areas in the north-central part of the state. Meanwhile, in the Southwest, reservoir levels continue to decline. This includes Lake Powell on the Colorado River, as well as the Salt and Verde River Basins that provide water for the Phoenix metropolitan area.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
