<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20131031</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next five days (October 31-November 4) the trend is for a wetter pattern over the eastern half of the United States.  As a strong cold front moves eastward, showers and thunderstorms will develop.  The greatest precipitation is expected over the Ark-La-Tex region, with amounts up to 4 inches, and through the Midwest, with amounts of 2-3 inches from Missouri up into the Great Lakes.  Temperatures will be at to slightly above seasonal normal for most of the area east of the Rocky Mountains, with departures of up to 3 degrees Fahrenheit above normal.  The area to the west will be right at normal to slightly below.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (November 5-November 10) continues with the best chances of above-normal temperatures over the eastern half of the United States and Alaska while the West has good chances of being below normal.  Precipitation chances are projected to be the greatest over the Mississippi River Valley as well as portions of the southern Plains.  Drier-than-normal conditions can be expected in New England and the Mid Atlantic coast as well as in the southwestern United States.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The Big Island of Hawaii did receive some heavy rain and thunderstorm activity on 10/26-10/27 which may have helped local conditions, but the events were spotty and it may take some time to see improvements.  Oahu recorded heavy rains as well on 10/27 but these mainly fell on areas not being impacted by drought currently.  Precipitation missed the drought areas of Alaska and no changes were made this week.  The lower elevations are lacking snow with one of the warmest Octobers on record in the state.  The sub-surface remains dry and the fire danger is still elevated over much of the state.  Puerto Rico did not have any changes this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>A fairly dry but cool week over the Midwest did not allow for any degradation this week.  Improvements to D0 conditions were made in the northern sections of the lower peninsula of Michigan as well as in northwest Minnesota along the border with North Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South">
   <p>Some heavy rains on 10/26 brought enough precipitation to show some improvements in southeast Oklahoma, the Oklahoma panhandle, eastern Texas and into southwest Arkansas.  A category improvement was made over the areas recording the most rain.  Along the Mississippi River between Arkansas and Mississippi, a reassessment of conditions allowed for improvements to the D0 and D1 in both southeast Arkansas and western Mississippi.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>After a wet summer, much of the fall has been drier than normal over a large portion of the region.  As the dryness is developing, the long-term conditions are still quite wet, while the recent 60-90 days have been below normal.  In response to the dryness, D0 was expanded in Alabama, Florida, Georgia, South Carolina, and North Carolina this week and as far north as Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Continuing dryness over the last 2 months is beginning to have an effect as areas of southern New England have received 50 percent or less of normal precipitation since September.  As the dryness continued this week, D1 conditions were expanded to include more of Long Island and the New York City metro area as well as southern Connecticut.  A new area of D1 was also introduced in Massachusetts and Rhode Island and D0 conditions were shifted to the west.  In western New York, recent precipitation allowed for the removal of D0 along Lake Erie.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>It was mainly a dry week on the Plains.  Some improvements were made in North Dakota, eliminating some D0 in the eastern portion of the state.  Rain at the end of the current U.S. Drought Monitor period in Kansas allowed for slight improvements to the D0 in the southern portion of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Some precipitation was recorded in New Mexico and into Colorado this past week but for the most part the area was dry and status on the United States Drought Monitor was unchanged for the week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
