<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20071220</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (December 20-24), the Rocky Mountains and locations to the east should see temperatures above normal.   Temperatures will range 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal over the lower Mississippi Valley, compared to 3-6 degrees Fahrenheit below normal in Colorado.  Several storm systems will influence precipitation in the United States as well.  The Pacific Northwest will continue to record heavy precipitation, especially along the coast.  A storm system approaching the Sierra Nevada Mountains will drop several feet of snow in some locations.  The northern Rocky Mountains area is also projected to record above-normal precipitation.  A wide swath of precipitation is expected from the Great Lakes down to the Gulf Coast.  Heaviest amounts are projected over Louisiana and Mississippi, the Upper Peninsula of Michigan and throughout New England.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlook (December 25-29) shows that above-normal temperatures should dominate much of the country, with the warmest over the northern Plains and Great Lakes.  Below-normal temperatures should be expected over the West, far South, and Southeast.  Above-normal precipitation should continue over the Pacific Northwest and northern California.  Above-normal precipitation is also projected over the Mississippi and Ohio River valleys.  Below-normal precipitation over Alaska, northern Plains, and the Southeast should be expected during this time.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, a categorical improvement to the drought categories was made.  All the D1 was removed form Maui, leaving a small area of D0.  No changes were made in Alaska or Puerto Rico this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>A continued favorable storm track through the region brought some relief to the drought areas.  In New England, the D1 was removed from Connecticut, Rhode Island, and Massachusetts, leaving a small area of D0 behind.  This area is still showing lingering hydrological impacts, but the recent precipitation has allowed for the improvements.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and South">
   <p>With two weeks of widespread precipitation, improvements to the drought status in Kansas, Oklahoma, Texas and Arkansas were again made this week.  All of the D0 was removed from the Trans-Pecos region of Texas, while improvements to the D0 and D1 were made in the Texas Panhandle, Oklahoma and Kansas.  Several weeks of ample precipitation allowed the removal of almost all the D0 in Arkansas.  D0 was expanded to include the southeastern portions of Louisiana. Recent dryness along with dryness on longer time frames showed that D0 conditions were influencing the area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, and Midwest States">
   <p>Rains in the region were welcomed, but did not allow for any improvements this week in the Southeast.  Pasture conditions in Georgia were 71 percent poor to very poor, compared to 69 percent last week.  Topsoil moisture in Georgia was also reported 69 percent short to very short throughout the state this week.  The Mid-Atlantic continued to see widespread precipitation, both rain and snow. The northern tier of the Mid-Atlantic recorded precipitation amounts up to 2 inches with the latest storms.  This allowed for the drought categories to be pushed farther south, with improvements to the D0, D1 and D2 regions of Kentucky, Virginia, West Virginia and Maryland.  The D1 and D0 regions in Missouri and Illinois were improved further this week as a full assessment of the recent precipitation in the area was made as well as the lack of impacts being observed during the winter months.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Continued snows in the San Juan Mountains of southern Colorado allowed for D0 conditions to be pushed into the foothills of eastern Colorado this week. With a good start to the snow season, several wet snows have allowed the abnormally dry areas to recover.  Drought intensified in eastern Montana, with drought categories expanding to include almost all of the state.  D0 was expanded through much of the eastern portions of the state while D1 and D2 categories were expanded in central Montana.  Some improvements to drought were made in western Montana with improvements to D1 and D2 conditions.  No other changes in the West were made, as long-term precipitation deficits are still problematic over much of the region.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
