<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010802</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) heavy rains associated with the same easterly wave that moved across Puerto Rico on Sunday, July 29, will fall across central and southern Florida August 1-2; 2) this easterly wave will likely continue to produce generous rains across the Gulf Coast region and potentially into the Lower Rio Grande Valley in southern Texas, with above-normal precipitation associated with this tropical moisture possible for all the Southeast August 7-11; 3) hot and dry weather associated with an upper-level ridge will continue to deteriorate drought conditions across the southern and central Plains, as well as parts of the Midwest throughout the period; 4) little precipitation is expected across the D0 and D1 areas in the eastern Great Lakes and northern New England through August 6; and 5) remnants from Tropical Storm Dalila will pass over the Hawaiian Islands early in the weekend, August 3-4 and provide the potential for moderate to heavy rains on the windward sides and light rains on the leeward sides of the islands.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico and Hawaii">
   <p>Abnormal dryness has occurred along the southern coast of Puerto Rico since June 1. As a result, the region has been placed into the D0 category. A vigorous easterly wave did pass over the island on Sunday, July 29, but rainfall totals in the D0 regions from this system are not yet known. No changes occurred during the week in the drought areas of Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Central Plains">
   <p>Heavy rains fell across parts of northern Kansas during the week, ending the abnormal dryness (D0) there. Rains also reduced dryness in southern and northern Minnesota, and in northern Wisconsin. In contrast, the abnormal dryness (D0) category was expanded in central Minnesota, west-central Iowa, Illinois, southeast Wisconsin, and southern Michigan. Dryness has continued in the northeastern part of Michigans Lower Peninsula, which was placed into the moderate drought (D1) category. Hot and mainly dry weather has also increased D0 across parts of eastern and central Nebraska, where rainfall totals are about 60% of normal for both the 30- and 60-day periods.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Long-term dryness over northern New England became very evident in the streamflow records for the region this past week. Burlington, VT, with 0.77 inches of rain in July, experienced their driest April through July period on record (6.22 inches for the four-month period, which is 48% of normal). As a result, D0 (abnormal dryness) was extended across northern New York, Vermont, and New Hampshire. The moderate drought (D1) in western New York was expanded along the south shore of Lake Erie from Buffalo to east of Cleveland. Rainfall in Buffalo for June and July was only 1.86 inches compared to a normal two-month total of approximately 6.63 inches.</p>
   <p>Abnormal dryness (D0) was also extended to include north-central Maryland, which missed out on the heavier rains that passed just to the south.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Generous rains during the past week fell in the drought and abnormally dry areas from northern Georgia through Virginia. As a result, the extreme drought (D3) in western North Carolina improved to D2. Abnormally dry conditions (D0) were eliminated in eastern Virginia and North Carolina, as well as in central Kentucky and Tennessee. In spite of these rains, long-term hydrological concerns continue in parts of Georgia, South Carolina, and eastern Tennessee. For South Carolina, statewide total rainfall for June and July was slightly below normal. In Florida, the past week had generally normal to below-normal rainfall statewide, but the overall drought situation continues to show some recovery, especially along the lower southwest and southeast coasts. The D0 category was dropped south and east of Fort Myers, while the D2, D1, and D0 categories were improved south and east of Lake Okeechobee.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Mid-South">
   <p>Hot and dry weather continued for most of this region for the week. As a result, expansion took place in the D3, D2, and D1 drought areas of Texas and Oklahoma. Fort Smith, AR, finished July with only 0.07 inches of rain (-2.92 in. below normal) with 13 days of 100F or above. Wichita Falls, TX, recorded only a trace for the month (-1.72 in. below normal) with 27 days of 100F or above. As of July 20, four reservoirs within the extreme drought area in West Texas were below 10% of the conservation storage capacity: Twin Buttes (3.4%), O. C. Fisher (5.0%), Champion Creek (6.0%), and J. B. Thomas (9.2%). Flows along the Rio Grande continue to be extremely low. The Amistad Reservoir held 34.7% and the Falcon Reservoir held 10.1% of their conservation storage capacities, while the city of Matamoros, Mexico (across the border from Brownsville) cannot pump enough water from the river for its population of more than 1.25 million people.</p>
   <p>Moderate drought (D1) and abnormal dryness (D0) expanded southwards across northeast Arkansas, western Mississippi, and northern Louisiana. Tunica, MS, has had 38% of normal rainfall since June 1, and 56% of normal since March 1. Meanwhile, heavy rains fell across southeast Missouri, southern Illinois, southern Indiana, and western Kentucky, improving the drought conditions in these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Alaska">
   <p>The major change from last week for the western continental U.S. was an expansion of D3 (extreme drought) across the basins in southern Idaho as a result of rapidly diminishing irrigation supplies and deteriorating range conditions. Drought conditions also deteriorated in north-central Wyoming. Extreme drought (D3) now extends across the entire Wind River Basin, and the severe drought category (D2) includes the east slope of the Bighorn Mountains in Wyoming. Meanwhile, along the Cascades and the Oregon and Washington coastlines, the main drought concerns continue to be hydrological at this time.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, rain and cooler temperatures helped eliminate the abnormal dryness in the Tanana Valley. Anchorage, AK, established a new record-high rainfall total for July of 4.57 inches (normal is 1.71 in.).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
