<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20160707</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>A stationary front located over the central U.S., along with several systems dropping southeastward out of the Canadian Prairies, triggered widespread moderate to heavy (2 to 6 inches, locally up to 10 inches) showers and thunderstorms from eastern Colorado eastward into Kentucky. The wet and cool weather quickly dashed any thoughts of a possible July flash drought in the central Plains and Midwest. Decent rains (1-3 inches) also fell on parts of the north-central and south-central Plains, along the Gulf and Atlantic Coasts, the central Appalachians, parts of northern New England, and in southeastern Arizona as the monsoon commenced. Temperatures averaged much below normal (4 to 10 degF) in the Midwest, and subnormal in most of the Northeast, northern half of the Plains, and the Four Corners region. In contrast, seasonably dry and warm conditions enveloped the Far West, while portions of the southern Plains, Delta, and Southeast received little or no rain. Similarly, most of the upper Midwest, north-central Great Plains, Great Lakes region, and coastal New England saw minimal rainfall. Elsewhere, conditions were wet in interior Alaska, the windward sides of the Hawaiian Islands, and eastern Puerto Rico.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (July 7-11),  moderate precipitation (more than an inch) should fall along the northern tier of States (Washington-Oregon eastward to New England), and in the northern and central Great Plains, Midwest, Tennessee and Ohio Valleys, and Appalachians. The greatest totals (more than 2.5 inches) were forecast for North Dakota, the western Corn Belt, the Tennessee Valley, and northern New England. Little or no precipitation was expected for the southwestern quarter of the Nation, the southern Plains, and Florida. Temperatures should average below-normal in the West, northern Plains, upper Midwest, and New England, with above-normal readings in the southern Plains and along the southern and mid-Atlantic Coast States.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for July 12-16 favors above-median precipitation along the U.S.-Canadian border, the Midwest, Tennessee Valley, southern Appalachians, and northern Alaska, with sub-median rainfall probable for most of the West and Rockies, south-central Plains, along the Gulf Coast, and in New England. Temperatures are likely to be subnormal in the northwestern quarter of the nation, while the odds favor above-normal readings in most of the eastern half of the U.S., southern Plains, and Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, wet weather during May continued into June, especially on the windward sides that saw significant rains. This included a few windward sites that measured record-breaking June rainfall while several others had their wettest June since 1998, the end of the last strong El Nino. On the Big Island, the Kona slopes continued to improve with FSA reporting that pastures along the lower elevations were in good condition. Based upon rainfall, VHI, and FSA reports, D2 and D3 on the Big Island’s southeast side shrunk based upon rainfall data, and D1 improved to D0 on the lower slopes of Kona and Kau Districts except for the lower southeastern portion of Kau near South Point. This narrow band of D2 and D3 remained based upon reports and photos from ranchers. In Kauai, D0 was expanded westward to Mana but the D0 and D1 gradient was reduced farther down the slope while the eastern portions of D0 and D1 was decreased. Unfortunately, May’s wetness did not persist into June on the leeward areas as most locations were dry. On Maui’s leeward side, persistent dryness and a brush fire in the Maalaea area burned 5000-6000 acres over the weekend, causing significant impacts to road travel during the holiday weekend. The rest of the islands were unchanged.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, widespread moderate to heavy rains (1-5 inches) fell on the southwestern to east-central interior, including around the Fairbanks and Bettles areas that were in D0. With 7-day USGS average stream flows in the above normal range, the southern lobe of the D0 area was removed. To the north and west, however, a dry week and rather dry June (totals under an inch), plus 7-day average stream flows running much below normal, justified the existing D0 in the north while expanding it westward into the Seward Peninsula.</p>
   <p>In Puerto Rico, heavy rains (more than 4 inches) fell on eastern portions of the island, but less than 0.5 inches fell on the D1 area. USGS 7-day average stream flows were mostly in the near normal range, except for above normal in eastern sections. With only a small part of the eastern D0 edge receiving surplus rains, a slight reduction of D0 was made where more than 4 inches was reported. The section just to the west of the D0-D1 area has been deficient the past 60-days, accumulating deficits of 6-10 inches, thus D0 was expanded slightly westward over this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="California and the Great Basin">
   <p>Little or no rain fell on California and much of the Great Basin, except for light monsoonal showers in eastern Nevada and western Utah. Since much of this region is climatologically dry and warm during the summer months, any drought degradation or improvement is highly unlikely in this region when dry is the norm, and any rain that falls quickly evaporates. Not surprisingly, no changes were made to the drought in California and the western Great Basin.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Widespread, beneficial rains (2-6 inches, locally to 10 inches) fell on the central Plains and the middle Mississippi and lower Ohio Valleys, quickly ending speculation about a possible July flash drought developing in the Nation’s mid-section. With D0 and D1 expanding last week during critical crop growth stages, ample rains quickly erased the abnormal dryness across much of eastern Kansas, Missouri, southern Illinois, and western Kentucky, and shrunk some of the D0 in central Nebraska, western Iowa, and central Indiana as showers were more scattered in these areas.  Where D0 and D1 remained (southern Nebraska, southeastern Iowa, western Illinois, northern Indiana), amounts were not great enough to make improvements, but were also not severe enough for degradation. An exception was in central Iowa (Story and Marshall Counties) where little or no rain and increasing deficiencies were enough for D1. In contrast, the past few weeks have been quite dry in the upper Midwest (central and northern Minnesota) and north-central Great Plains (northeastern South Dakota and southeastern North Dakota). With low stream flows and 90-days indices justifying additional dryness, D0 expanded into north-central and east-central Minnesota, D1 increased into southwestern North Dakota and west-central Minnesota, and D2 stretched into Grant and Douglas Counties. However, a localized thunderstorm dropped 4-5 inches of rain on Stevens County, diminishing the D1 there. In addition, the worsening conditions in Michigan were covered in the New England and eastern Great Lakes region summary.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England and eastern Great Lakes region">
   <p>Another week of subnormal temperatures, along with periods of scattered showers early, mid-, and late in the period, provided enough moisture (an inch or more) to prevent major deterioration to the entire region. In fact, enough rain fell on portions of northern New England (2-4 inches, locally to 6 inches) that D0 was removed in extreme northern New Hampshire and far western Maine, along with some of the small D1 area in western Maine. Meanwhile, the moderate rains in eastern Pennsylvania, New Jersey, central New York, Long Island, and southern sections of New York, Connecticut, Rhode Island, and Cape Cod prevented deterioration, but was not enough for any improvement.</p>
   <p>Still, several areas missed out on the beneficial rains, including the eastern Great Lakes region (lower Michigan, northern Ohio, western Pennsylvania, western New York) and coastal New England (southern New Hampshire, central Massachusetts). The subnormal precipitation has persisted long enough that impacts were being observed across much of the region, along with near- to record low 1-, 7-, 14-, and 28-day average USGS stream flows in parts of eastern New England and the eastern Great Lakes region.  July 3 USDA/NASS statistics for statewide topsoil moisture rated short or very short included 51, 60, 64, 66, 73, 73, and 74% for New York, Connecticut, Rhode Island, Michigan, Vermont, New Hampshire, and Massachusetts, respectively. Subsoil moisture rated short to very short over 50% included Connecticut (56), New Hampshire (57), Michigan (57), Rhode Island (59), Massachusetts (60), and Vermont (71). Several towns in New Hampshire, Massachusetts, and Connecticut have restricted or banned outdoor water use as groundwater levels were low. Many agricultural crops required irrigation, and there were numerous reports of stressed or damaged crops in Michigan and the Northeast from the lack of rain. Even established Christmas trees were experiencing signs of damage in Michigan while newly planted, non-irrigated seedlings had died. Another impact from the dryness was the lack of a fungus that attacks gypsy caterpillars. Without a wet spring, the caterpillars thrived and devastated large stands of oaks in New England. Accordingly, D0 was expanded southward in northeastern Ohio, west-central Pennsylvania, and most of lower Michigan. D1 was increased in parts of lower Michigan, northwestern Pennsylvania, western New York, southern Vermont, and western Massachusetts. A new D2 area was added in southern New Hampshire and central Massachusetts where stream flows were at record lows and 60-, 90-, and 120-day SPIs were at or lower than -2.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northwest and Northern Rockies">
   <p>July and August are normally the driest months of the year in the Pacific Northwest, so changes to the drought depiction are usually minor, if any. Similarly, precipitation typically decreases in the northern Rockies during the summer months, so deterioration is not common. However, the lack of rainfall over the past 30-90 days, along with bouts of above-normal temperatures and an early snow melt in the northern Rockies, has depleted soil moisture and lowered stream flows to much-below normal levels. As a result, D0 was added to portions of south-central and eastern Idaho. In coastal Oregon, although springtime precipitation is much lower than the winter, enough rain typically falls on coastal mountains to provide adequate stream flows. This spring, however, a lack of rain and occasional warmth has led to 90-day deficits of 3-6 inches and very low stream flows, thus D1 was added to coastal Oregon. Similar deficits existed in western Washington, but recent rains and lower temperatures were enough to temper the D1 expansion there for now.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Plains">
   <p>Scattered light showers (generally less than an inch) fell on most portions of the D0-D3 area in western South Dakota, southwestern North Dakota, northern Wyoming, and southeastern Montana, enough to maintain - but not improve - conditions from last week. An exception was in southwestern South Dakota where 2-3.5 inches of rain fell on southeastern Custer, Oglala Lakota, and Bennett counties, improving the area by 1 category. In northern Kansas, enough rain (1.5-2.5 inches) fell on Smith and Jewell counties to erase the D0; however, just to the west, Graham and Rooks counties missed the rain, and with 30-day dryness impacts occurring, D0 was added there. As mentioned in the Midwest summary, surplus rains eliminated much of the D0 in eastern Kansas. In north-central Oklahoma, heavy localized thunderstorms dropped 5-8.5 inches of rain on Osage and Pawnee counties, effectively ending the recently added D0 and D1 there. Farther west, the rains were less plentiful, so most D0 and D1 areas remained. Similarly, locally heavy rains also erased D0 in east-central Oklahoma, but dryness expanded eastward into west-central Arkansas where the rains missed. Drier weather in southern and central Texas during the 30-60 days is currently showing up in the SPIs as mild D0 with a few D1s, but seasonable temperatures have limited evapotranspiration rates across the state. As a compromise, D0 was added along the Rio Grande near Maverick County and immediate area where the indices had indicated as the worst spot in the short-term.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southwest">
   <p>The southwest monsoon kicked into gear around July 1 in Arizona, dropping light to moderate amounts (0.5-2 inches) of rain on southeastern and northwestern Arizona, southern Nevada, southern Utah, western New Mexico, and most of Colorado. With the increased moisture and cloud cover, temperatures also averaged slightly below normal. Since this was the first significant precipitation in southeastern Arizona and the D1 –D2 is long-term, it will take a few more events before any improvement is warranted there. Elsewhere, the rains were enough to prevent deterioration, but not great enough for any improvement. Therefore, no changes were made to the Southwest this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Tennessee Valley, Southeast, and Delta">
   <p>Significant rains fell either to the north, south, east, or west of the area from the lower Delta northeastward to the western Carolinas. Since much of the area from eastern Louisiana to western North Carolina received little or no precipitation and observed above normal temperatures, drought persisted or worsened as short-term deficits continued to accumulate. With many locations measuring 50-75% of normal precipitation the past 60- and 90-days, shortages of 3-6 and 4-8 inches have accrued, respectively. July 3 USDA/NASS reported that statewide topsoil moisture rated short or very short  was at 55, 55, 60, and 64% in Georgia, Alabama, Arkansas, and Mississippi, respectively, while similar subsoil moisture levels were at 52, 52, and 56%  in Alabama, Arkansas, and Mississippi. While widespread, major crop damage was not yet noted in the July 3 USDA/NASS crop progress and condition report (most crops fair to good), there were reports of localized damage where soil moisture conditions were the worst. In northern Alabama (Madison County), dryland corn was severely damaged and may not be salvageable any longer. Dry pastures in western Tennessee (Hardin County) were leading to early cattle sales while water users in Jones County, Georgia were asked to voluntarily conserve water as the dry conditions have increased water demand. USGS stream flows have also dropped to below (10-24th percentile) and much-below (less than tenth percentile) levels from western North Carolina southwestward into central Mississippi. As a result, most D0-D3 areas remained or expanded based upon the largest deficits, lowest SPIs, poor VegDri conditions, and low stream flows. This included D0 expansion in many southern and western areas, including west-central Arkansas; D1 increase in central Mississippi and parts of Tennessee and the western Carolinas; D2 extension into southeastern Tennessee, western North Carolina, west-central Georgia and east-central Alabama, the northern Alabama-Mississippi border, and northern Mississippi; and more D3 in northeastern Alabama and northwestern Georgia, northeastern Georgia, and near the Atlanta, GA, metro area.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
