<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050331</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a storm on Wednesday, March 30, bringing 0.5 to 1.0 inches of precipitation to the Upper Midwest, including the dry areas in Minnesota, with scattered areas of snow across the Rockies on the same day; 2) Pacific storm systems continuing to move across the Pacific Northwest during the next 2 weeks, bringing above-normal rain or snow to the drought-affected region; 3) more heavy rains for the Southeast around April 5-6, resulting in more moisture for the lingering dry area in eastern North Carolina; 4) above-normal precipitation for the upper Midwest during April 5-9 and normal precipitation for the week 2 period, April 7-13.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Continued dry weather across southern Puerto Rico resulted in no change to the D0-D1 situation there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>Up to an inch or more of precipitation benefited dry areas near central Iowa, resulting in some shrinking of the D0 area that extends from southern Nebraska into southwestern Iowa. Precipitation was, overall, too light to have much of an impact on the drought in the western Dakotas, western Nebraska, and northern Kansas. Dry weather persisted over the abnormally dry area in central Minnesota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and West">
   <p>Widespread rain and snow covered much of the West this week, with over 5 inches of rain inundating coastal areas of Oregon and Washington, and over 3 inches of precipitation, falling as snow at higher elevations, covering the Cascades of Washington and Oregon. Snow water content increased by 2-3 inches in the Cascades, although totals remained mostly less than one-third of normal. Precipitation amounts exceeded 2 inches from eastern Washington across northern Idaho and into parts of western Montana. Helena, Montana reported 9 inches of snow on March 23-24, while up to 21 inches fell to the south at a 5500-foot elevation. Great Falls, Montana has set a record for March snowfall, accumulating 27.8 inches by March 25. As a result of the prodigious moisture, there was generally a 1-category improvement in drought levels west of the Cascades in Washington and Oregon as well as over northern Idaho and portions of central and western Montana. The heavy rains eliminated dryness near the immediate coast from Washington into northern Oregon. Despite the heavy rains, some of which set daily records, seasonal accumulations in Seattle and Portland still ranged from 6-8 inches below normal. To the south, additional heavy-mountain snows further reduced drought in Utah. Another 21 inches of snow at Alta on March 29 brought the season total to 575 inches at the ski resort, where snow depth reached 185 inches. Drought levels generally improved by one category in northern Utah, resulting in the removal of long-term dryness from central Utah into the Wasatch Mountains. Southwestern Wyoming and southeastern Idaho also saw a one-category improvement, while the D0 in western Arizona retreated farther eastward.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>Heavy rains swept across the Southeast during the past 7 days, with amounts exceeding 2 inches from Florida northward into the mid-Atlantic region and westward into Mississippi. Over 4 inches soaked an area extending from Alabama to South Carolina. The moisture led to the removal of the D0 in Alabama, Florida, and most of South Carolina, as well as the trimming of the D0 in North Carolina and northeast Texas-southern Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
