<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000413</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Heavy showers across northern Texas April 11-12 improved conditions but drier and warmer weather next 2 weeks will offset much of the benefits. Heavy showers in Florida will reduce dryness, especially in the south. Additional rain elsewhere in the South will offer scattered benefit, but not enough to change drought categories.</p>
   <p>No significant change in the next 2 weeks except for relief from abnormal dryness in the vicinity of North Dakota. The Midwest will see significant rains next 2 weeks, but much of the benefits will be offset by periodic heat.</p>
   <p>No significant change expected in the next 2 weeks.</p>
   <p>No significant changes expected in the next 2 weeks.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought continued leeward areas of Hawaii. Abnormal dryness persisted over the north coast of Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The rain and snow that swept across the region April 6-8 brought some drought relief, though not enough to end drought. Up to a foot of snow boosted soil moisture in Minnesota and northern Iowa, but Iowa statewide precipitation totaled only one-third inch. More rain and snow on Monday, April 10 brought some additional relief to Iowa and surrounding states, but preceding moisture supplies were so low that drought persisted from Nebraska to northwest Ohio. The snows did result in severe drought retreating southward from parts of northern Iowa. Severe drought lingered from eastern Nebraska to central and southern Iowa, central Illinois, northern Indiana and extreme northwestern Ohio, with drought expanding northward into most of Michigan's lower peninsula and central Wisconsin. Severe drought also penetrated northern Missouri.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South-Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>More rains swept across the region April 7-9, but amounts were mostly under 1 inch. With these rains in addition to the heavy rains that pounded the region on April 2-4, farmers' concerns tended to be focused more on excessive water than drought. As of April 8, northeast Louisiana and parts of Alabama had measured 15 inches of rain in 4 weeks. River flooding affected Mississippi. Nevertheless, drought persisted along the Gulf Coast from Texas to Florida, with severe drought lingering in southern Louisiana, southern Georgia, and central and northern Florida. Due to little additional rain, drought (D1) expanded into South Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Drought persisted over southern New Mexico while abnormal dryness remained over southern Arizona and much of Montana. Dryness also penetrated northern Wyoming. Fifty-nine percent of Wyoming was short or very short topsoil moisture, with the main impact to northern pastures.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
