<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030515</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>May 15 - 19 forecast conditions that may impact current areas of dryness and drought include (1) More than 1 inch of precipitation in parts of southern Mississippi, central and north Louisiana, most of Oklahoma, western Arkansas, northern Texas, the northern and western Dakotas, and a small area in central Montana, with 2 to 5 inches anticipated in central Oklahoma, the Arklatex region, northeast Louisiana, and upper southern Mississippi; and (2) light or unmeasureable precipitation in the central and southern Rockies, the Great Basin, the central Plains, south and west Texas, the immediate Gulf Coast, northern Minnesota, the central Great Lakes, and northern New England. The forecast for the ensuing 5 days (May 20 - 24) indicates enhanced probabilities for below-normal precipitation in the Great Basin, the northwestern half of the Rockies, the south-central Plains, the lower Mississippi Valley, the central and northern Gulf Coast region, the upper Ohio Valley, and New England. No current areas of dryness have greater-than-average probabilities for heavy precipitation during May 20 - 24.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Despite some localized areas of moderate precipitation, nothing substantial enough occurred in either state to warrant a change in the D0 to D1AH conditions identified on May 6.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Generally 1 to 2 inches of precipitation fell last week, although slightly lower totals (0.5 to 1.0 inch) were observed across interior Maine. Unfortunately, these amounts did little to change the region's long-term precipitation deficits, which date back a few years in spots, thus D0H to D1H coverage remained unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The central and northern Plains">
   <p>Another week of abundant precipitation brought significant improvement to many of the region's dry areas, especially through the northern and eastern Great Plains, where dryness and drought have not been as long-lived as in the High Plains and western Great Plains. Weekly totals of 1 to 4 inches were common through most of the dry areas identified on May 6, leading to broad areas of 1-category improvement except where dryness has been entrenched for many months to a few years. In addition, a few areas missed the week's heavier rains as amounts of 0.3 to locally 1.0 inch were reported in southeast Montana, east Wyoming, central and west-central Nebraska, northwestern Kansas, parts of the Dakotas, and northern Minnesota. In these areas, dryness and drought persistence was noted, with only localized improvement. Wetness during the last several weeks has left D3 confined to part of north-central South Dakota, and D2 coverage much more spotty than it was several weeks ago. Furthermore, the timing of the recent precipitation has relieved most agricultural and topsoil moisture concerns, thus the "A" qualifier has been removed everywhere in the central and northern Plains except for northern Minnesota, which has missed much of the recent wetness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes, Ohio Valley, and Corn Belt">
   <p>Heavy rains again fell on these regions, with totals of 2 to 6 inches common in the last 7 days. As a result, dryness and drought came to an end for most areas, at least for the time being, with immediate agricultural needs assuaged and no widespread hydrologic concerns. However, D0H was left covering northeast lower Michigan, where lingering long-term precipitation deficits and low groundwater levels were reported. In addition, D0AH and a small area of D1AH persisted to the lee of Lake Erie. In this area, the weeks prior to May 6 - 12 were much drier than in areas farther west, tempering the degree of relief brought by this week's copious precipitation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and interior West">
   <p>Moderate to heavy precipitation (0.5 to locally 2.0 inches) fell from central Montana southward through central sections of Nevada, Utah, and Colorado last week while little or no precipitation was observed farther south. Most of the area that recorded moderate to heavy precipitation showed some evidence of drought relief in the form of topsoil moisture increases and a greener appearance to pastures and rangelands. However, given the long-term nature of the region's drought, and the fact that water supplies are managed on multi-year time scales across much of the area, only scattered 1-category improvements were introduced in this week's Drought Monitor. In fact, some areas that missed the heavier precipitation in April deteriorated by 1 category because of bleak surface water supply assessments, specifically the Bear Basins in southeast Idaho and northeast Utah, which are now at D4H, and north-central portions of Wyoming, which deteriorated to D2H despite a relatively damp week. Farther south, recent dryness and unfavorable water supply assessments seemed significant enough to introduce a 1-category deterioration (to D2H or D3H) in central and northern New Mexico, and adjacent sections of both southeastern Colorado and northeastern Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>Rainfall was not nearly as abundant as in areas farther to the north, so conditions in most of the dry areas identified on May 6 persisted or deteriorated. Little or no precipitation fell on the southern High Plains, the southwestern Great Plains, much of central and northern Texas, and the Gulf Coast from Texas eastward through northern and central Florida. 30-day precipitation deficits now range from 2 to 4 inches across much of Louisiana and some adjacent locales, with 1 or 2 inch shortfalls common from north Florida westward through eastern and central sections of Texas and Oklahoma. As a result, D0A conditions were introduced in much of central and north Florida, where abnormally warm weather has exacerbated short-term dryness, while D1AH conditions expanded into large sections of central Louisiana, central and north Texas, and adjacent Oklahoma where significant moisture shortages date back at least 90 days. Most other areas were unchanged, except in Arkansas and adjacent areas of Oklahoma, Mississippi, and extreme northern Louisiana, where weekly precipitation amounts were considerably higher, more like those observed in the central Plains and Corn Belt. Much of these regions improved by 1 category.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
