<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020131</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) an extensive storm system on January 30-February 1 bringing substantial rain and snow from the southern Rockies to the Eastern Seaboard, with 1 to 3 inches of precipitation forecast from Kansas and Oklahoma through the Ohio Valley to the northern mid-Atlantic states and New England; 2) mostly light rainfall amounts from the above storm south of the Mason-Dixon line; 3) generally normal to above-normal precipitation over the next 2 weeks across the central and eastern states, but below normal over the Southwest; 3) the end to the unseasonable warmth across the East; and 4) continued normal to above-normal rain and snow for the Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>A Kona Low delivered heavy rains to Hawaii on January 27-29. Honolulu, Kahului, and Hilo all set new record daily rainfall records for January 29. Honolulus 2.10 inches obliterated the previous record of .43 inches. The heavy rains of the past 1.5 weeks eliminated D0 dryness from Oahu, Lanai, and eastern Molokai. D2 drought improved to D1 on western Molokai. Little rain fell over southern Puerto Rico again this week, resulting in no change in the dryness depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Heavy rains of 2 to 6 inches or more swept across Tennessee, northern Georgia, and the western Carolinas on January 23-25, ending dryness over most of eastern Tennessee and northwestern Georgia, as well as extreme southwestern North Carolina. Drought improved from D2 to D1 over parts of western North Carolina and extreme northwestern South Carolina as well as parts of eastern North Carolina. In contrast, rainfall totals were much lighter across southern parts of Georgia and South Carolina, permitting severe to extreme drought to persist. Lack of rain caused D0 dryness to expand westward across southern Alabama. To the north, rain and snow amounts were modest over the Northeast during the past week, allowing expansion of D0 and D1 westward in upstate New York and D2 to cover the lower Hudson Valley. Severe (D2) drought extended westward across northern parts of Maryland and southern Pennsylvania. Abnormally high temperatures this week further decreased soil moisture.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Light precipitation totals resulted in little change to the drought extending from southern Kansas through west Texas and into New Mexico. Continued below normal rain and snow caused dryness (D0) to expand slightly in Iowa and to stretch northward into central Minnesota. Dryness also developed in northwestern North Dakota. Much of the Midwest from Illinois to Ohio has had little precipitation for the past 8 weeks, but soil moisture has not declined to D0 levels due to earlier ample rains. A storm system brought widespread precipitation to the central and southern Plains following the January 29 cutoff time for the Drought Monitor depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Ample rain or snow fell across a number of areas, including California, Washington, Oregon, Idaho, western Montana, and northern Utah. As a result, D0/D1/D2 areas further receded across the Northwest. Snow pack continued below normal across most of Montana and Wyoming, allowing extreme (D3) drought to continue over large portions of both states, but D3 decreased in western Wyoming and eastern Idaho. In Nevada, many reservoirs remained at less than 50% of average capacity, so D2/D1 (W) drought diminished only slightly over northern and central sections of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
