<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030703</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecast weather conditions that could have an impact on dryness or drought include: 1) mostly above-normal temperatures and below-normal rainfall over the interior West and west Texas during the next 2 weeks; 2) above-normal rains over the next 10 days in upper coastal Texas; 3) heavy rains of 2 inches or more in northeastern Minnesota during July 2-7; 4) dry weather during July 2-7 in the Pacific Northwest, but normal to below-normal temperatures over the next 2 weeks in Washington and Oregon, with normal to above-normal rainfall in western parts of both states during July 8-16; 5) normal to above-normal rainfall and normal to below-normal temperatures over the Corn Belt during July 8-16.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Scattered showers failed to put a dent in the ongoing drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes, Upper Mississippi Valley, and Upper Midwest">
   <p>Widespread thunderstorms brought significant dryness relief to the upper Midwest on June 23-24, while another shot of rain over the following weekend added to the 7-day totals. The resulting 1-4 inches of rain removed drought from Iowa and most of Illinois, as well as southern South Dakota and northern Nebraska. D1 drought, however, did expand slightly in northeastern Illinois and northern Indiana, an area that missed the bulk of the rains. The moisture also eliminated most of the drought in northeastern Minnesota. Abnormal dryness developed in southwestern Missouri, where little rain has fallen in the past 3 weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>High temperatures offset the benefits of showers in northern New England, so D1 remained in northern Maine, while D0 expanded into northern New Hampshire and toward the Maine coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West, including Alaska">
   <p>Hot, dry weather resulted in expansion of D0 dryness throughout Washington and Oregon. June was a record dry month in several locations in both states. Yakima, Washington, for example, recorded just a trace of rainfall this month, as did Pendleton, Oregon. Cumulative rainfall during the past 60 days has been less than 40 percent of normal in much of Washington and western Oregon, and crops rapidly deteriorated in both states. Negligible rainfall in the Southwest helped to maintain very high to extreme fire danger. There was little change in the overall drought situation in the Rockies, but up to 1 inch of rain in Wyoming reduced D1 in the east and D4 in the southwest. In Alaska, abnormal dryness persisted from the eastern to southwestern portions of the interior. Fairbanks' June rainfall was less than one-half of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains">
   <p>Most of the heavy rains from Tropical Storm Bill missed the areas in need of moisture, but periodic thunderstorms did eliminate the D1 drought from southeast Oklahoma and along the upper Texas Gulf coast. Widespread rains of 1 to 2 inches also removed abnormal dryness from the Texas Panhandle.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
