<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050310</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) beneficial precipitation will continue to fall March 8-9 across parts of Florida; 2) a strong clipper-like system will move into the Upper Midwest March 10 and provide light snows to areas of Minnesota; 3) precipitation will return March 12-14 to the northern Rockies; 4) beneficial rains will spread across a large part of the Southeast March 12-14; and 5) for the March 15-19 period, below-normal temperatures will be common across most of the continental U.S.; above-normal precipitation is expected for the Southwest, central Rockies, and Southeast; and below-normal precipitation is expected for the Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Another dry week occurred across the D0 areas of western and southern Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>Very little precipitation fell across the drought areas of the Midwest and Plains during the past week. Meanwhile, temperatures were considerably above normal across the northern Plains before eventually returning to more normal levels. Officials in several Plains and Midwestern states have been concerned about the potential for wildfires. On March 6, very warm and windy conditions caused a grassfire in Pottawattamie County, IA, that burned more than 4,000 acres. Continued short-term dryness in eastern South Dakota led to expansion of the D0 in that area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and The West">
   <p>Warm and dry conditions continue to plague the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies. Snow water equivalent values of the mountain snowpacks across Oregon, Washington, Idaho, Montana, and Wyoming are either at or near new low levels for this time of year. Statewide snowpack averages include 26 percent in Washington, 53 percent in Montana, and 77 percent in Wyoming. Across Montana, 37 of the 50 river basins where the Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) is applicable are reporting SWSI values in the lowest (extremely dry) category. Officials in each of these states are beginning to grapple with what this means in terms of summer streamflows. As a result of the developing drought situation, the severe drought (D2) category was expanded to cover parts of central Washington and north-central Oregon. Meanwhile, in southwestern New Mexico, recent rains have continued to improve the long-term dryness situation in that area, and D0 was removed from a portion of the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Texas">
   <p>It was a generally dry and cool week across most of the Southeast this past week. Because of dryness that has lingered since last fall, an area of D0 was put into place along the North Carolina and South Carolina coasts. In North Carolina, Wilmington has only had 53 percent of normal precipitation since 1 October 2004, and only 40 percent for the year to date. In South Carolina, Charleston has had 53 percent of normal precipitation since the beginning of September. Savannah, GA, has had eight straight months with below-normal precipitation going back to last July (59 percent of normal), and only 44 percent of normal since the beginning of November. Some precipitation did fall across southern Florida early in the week (Fort Lauderdale, Pompano Beach, Miami, Palm Beach, and Hollywood all had totals exceeding one inch), and across the Gulf Coast states later in the week. No changes were made to the D0 areas in Florida for the week. In Texas, dryness has been developing across both the far southern part and the northeast corner of the state. As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) was added to these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
