<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070830</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Slow-moving storms dumped heavy rain over the eastern central Plains eastward to the mid-Atlantic coast. Rainfall totals (including rains reported on the 21st) of greater than 3 inches with local amounts of more than 10 inches deluged eastern Nebraska, Iowa, southern Wisconsin and Michigan, and the northern portions of Illinois, Indiana, and Ohio.  Both north-central Ohio and southwestern Wisconsin were declared disaster areas due to severe flooding as up to eighteen deaths resulted.  Extreme temperatures, averaging 4 to 10 degrees F above normal, exacerbated drought in the southern Ohio and Tennessee Valley and the Southeast.  Scattered showers and thunderstorms provided some local relief to the region, however.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Weather that could have an impact on dry areas in the next 2 weeks: 1) moist flow from the Gulf will bring normal to above-normal rainfall from Louisiana to Alabama for the next 2 weeks, while normal rainfall should cover the area from Tennessee and western Kentucky into Missouri and Arkansas during days 6-10, September 4-8, with normal rainfall expected across the region from the Carolinas to Missouri during week 2, September 6-12; 2) above-normal rains should affect the Arizona area during days 6-10 and 8-14; 3) mostly dry weather and above-normal temperatures through September 3 will cover the drought area that extends from southern Ohio to Missouri and Arkansas; 4) above-normal temperatures will affect much of the Great Basin and Intermountain region into Montana and Wyoming through September 5.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Little or no rain fell in Alaska's abnormally dry area except along the south central coast where 0.5 to 2 inches was reported.  This resulted in only a small reduction in the southern portion of the D0 area.  In Hawaii, summer rains have been near to above normal on the west side of the Big Island.  As a result, the D1 was removed in the north and D0 along the west central coast.  The County of Hawaii Dept. of Water Supply eased restrictions from a mandatory 25% cut to a voluntary 10% reduction request. All other islands remained unchanged.  Puerto Rico received light to moderate showers but long-term deficits remained for year-to-date, so the abnormally dry (D0H) area was kept with slight modification.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East and Southeast">
   <p>Frontal rains brought relief to the drought areas in Pennsylvania, northern Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware.  D1 was deleted in Pennsylvania and scaled back in Virginia, Maryland and Delaware.  D0 was also trimmed back in the four states.</p>
   <p>In the Northeast, however, D0 was expanded into northern New York and created in southern New England.  Many streams in these two areas are in the lower 10 percentile as reported by the USGS.</p>
   <p>Despite scattered rains of 4 inches or more, much of the Southeast remained hot and dry and crops and pastureland continued to deteriorate.  Topsoil was rated dry to very dry for 92% or more of Alabama, Kentucky, and Tennessee, 85% or more of the Carolinas and Arkansas, and 75% of Georgia.  For crops, 53% or more of the corn was rated poor to very poor in Tennessee and North Carolina, and cotton was 58% or more poor to very poor in Alabama and Tennessee.  Many streams in the Southeast were in the lower 25 percentile.  On the U.S. Drought Monitor map, little change was made to the region.  Exceptional drought (D4) was trimmed to the northwest in southwestern Georgia while D0 expanded southward into northern and eastern Louisiana and D1 and D2 southward into southeastern Arkansas.</p>
   <p>Daily maximum temperatures did drop from the century mark after August 24 across the Southeast, providing some respite from August's persistent extreme heat. Numerous temperature records will be broken when the final August numbers are tallied. Birmingham, Alabama, for example, which endured 14 days with triple digit heat this month, is likely to end up with the hottest month on record. Oak trees on ridges are reportedly dying in the state, and 30 percent of long-term stream gauges were at all-time lows.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Showers and thunderstorms brought moderate to heavy rains (1 to over 5 inches) to much of the central Plains with lighter amounts reported in parts of the northern Plains.  In the southern Plains, south central Oklahoma and much of Texas (except for the rains in the panhandle and southern portions of the state) were dry.  The rains in the northern two-thirds of the Plains eliminated or trimmed back drought categories in the Dakotas and Nebraska.</p>
   <p>Dry conditions again prevailed in the upper Great Lakes, resulting in little change in the drought classifications.  D3 was edged eastward into the upper peninsula of Michigan.  At the end of the period, showers and thunderstorms brought some relief to the dryness.</p>
   <p>The heavy rains in the upper Midwest eliminated most of the drought in eastern Nebraska and Iowa, pushed the D0 and D1 northward across the southern portions of Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan, and edged southward the D0, D1, and some D2 in northern Missouri, Illinois, Indiana, and Ohio.  Southern portions of the Midwest from southeastern Missouri and northeastern Arkansas northeastward across southern Indiana, however, remained hot and dry.  Crops in parts of southeastern Missouri were reported to be dead or at best stunted.  Many corn fields in southern Illinois were reported to be prematurely dead. D2 was edged northward in southern Illinois and southern Indiana and D3 moved into the Boothill of Missouri.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The week was again cooler than average across the Pacific Northwest, but warmer than normal over most of the remainder of the West. Light rain fell across western Washington and light to moderate amounts were scattered over the Rockies, but little or no rain fell elsewhere.  One exception was the Southwest, where the remains of Hurricane Dean contributed locally heavy showers exceeding one inch in parts of Arizona and southern parts of Nevada and Utah. Eastern Montana and Idaho again received only widely scattered amounts of less than an inch as around two dozen major wildfires remained active.  USDA NASS reports indicate that pastures continue to deteriorate with conditions poor to very poor for 67% of Idaho and 37% of Montana.  Only slight changes were made in the drought classifications.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Heddinghaus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
