<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20101209</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>December 8 – 12, 2010 should provide widespread moderate precipitation (0.5 to 1.5 inches) from the Ohio/Mississippi Confluence through parts of the central Gulf Region and eastward to the Atlantic Ocean, unfortunately missing southeastern Georgia and peninsular Florida where drought conditions are more serious than in areas farther north. The largest totals should accumulate in eastern New Jersey and northern reaches of the lower Mississippi Valley. Farther west, areas from northern California northward into southern Oregon should record similar amounts, or perhaps slightly more near the California/Oregon border. Colder than normal conditions are expected from the northern High Plains and southeastern Great Plains eastward to the Atlantic Coast, with above-normal temperatures anticipated farther west.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (December 13 – 17, 2010), dry weather is favored from the Southwestern Deserts and central Rockies eastward through the  central Plains, then southeastward to the Carolina Coastline and all points south, as well as in Alaska. In contrast, wet weather seems more likely across the north-central Plains, the Northwest, and northern California. Regarding temperatures, the odds favor cold weather east of the Mississippi River and in Alaska while above-normal temperatures appear most likely from the central and southern Plains westward to the Pacific Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Relatively light but consistent precipitation across central Alaska has reduced or eliminated deficits on time scales ranging from 1 month to a year, with the most improvement seen over recent periods. This led to the removal of D0 throughout central parts of the state. Farther south, quite a few locations reported moderate to heavy precipitation last week, but with relatively large normals common through the regions receiving the larger amounts, deficits remained significant enough to warrant continued D0 conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Atlantic Seaboard">
   <p>Precipitation totals were below normal east of the Appalachians in the dry areas from southern New Jersey southward and southwestward through southern Georgia and the Florida Panhandle, where only parts of New Jersey received over an inch of precipitation. Increasing moisture deficits led to expansion of D0 toward the southern Florida coast, and D1 into parts of the central Carolinas. More widespread deterioration was introduced through much of peninsular Florida and southeast Georgia, with extreme drought expanded northward from northeast Florida into southeast Georgia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="California and Southern Oregon">
   <p>Moderate precipitation totaling 1 to locally 4 inches led to some dryness and drought retraction in northeastern California and southern Oregon. Farther south, A small area of interior western California southwest of the San Joaquin Valley has recorded consistently below-normal precipitation over the course of the last 6 months. Although much of that period typically receives little precipitation during this period, seasonally increasing normals and slowly growing precipitation shortfalls led to the introduction of abnormal dryness there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Central and Northern Rockies and the Intermountain West">
   <p>Although moderate to heavy precipitation fell on the central and northwestern Rockies, most areas of dryness and drought in this region missed significant precipitation, leaving conditions unchanged there. However, a re-assessment of conditions resulted in small areas where abnormal dryness was eliminated, specifically in central Colorado and in the northern Reaches of areas near the Colorado/Utah border.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Central Gulf Coast States">
   <p>Moderate precipitation locally approaching 2 inches, along with a re-assessment of the impacts from rainfall during recent weeks, led to additional improvements in eastern and northern Alabama and northern Mississippi. D3 conditions were removed from southeastern Alabama, and drought was removed from much of central and northern Alabama, along with northern Mississippi</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Another week of relatively heavy rainfall, especially in windward areas, finally seems to have brought improvement to some areas that have experienced a protracted period of dryness and drought. Exceptional drought finally released its grip on northwestern sections of the Big Island, and D0 to D3 conditions improved  in parts of the southern Big Island, western Maui, eastern Oahu, and northern Kauai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Ohio, Tennessee, and Lower Mississippi Valleys">
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation brought limited improvement to the areas of dryness and drought that have existed for some time through the central Ohio Valley, but little or no precipitation resulted in some localized deterioration in central and western sections of the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern and Central Plains">
   <p>Only isolated light precipitation fell on areas from the central Plains southward through Oklahoma and Texas. No change was made to drought designations across the central Plains, but widespread deterioration occurred through most of Texas and Oklahoma, where very little precipitation during the last few weeks, and smaller areas of precipitation deficits dating back several months, led to rapidly increasing impacts and concerns, especially surface moisture declines and its related impacts on wildfire potential and available livestock feed.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Appalachians Westward Toward the Tennessee and Ohio Valleys">
   <p>Heavy precipitation induced widespread drought improvement, especially along the Appalachians. Most of the central and eastern sections of the region recorded 2 to locally over 5 inches, with the largest totals falling on western North Carolina and part of western Virginia. Farther west, amounts of 1 to nearly 4 inches brought less widespread improvement to areas from eastern Alabama, northern Georgia, and eastern Tennessee northeastward through western Pennsylvania. The result of these changes was the elimination of abnormally dry conditions in all areas from the southern Appalachians and eastern Tennessee northeastward through western Pennsylvania.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Rockies">
   <p>Light precipitation fell on isolated locations last week, with most locations reporting none. In a few areas, modest precipitation deficits date back approximately 6 months, but extremely dry conditions over the past 90 days led to a sharp increase in 3-month precipitation shortfalls. As a result, abnormal dryness was introduced throughout Arizona and through most areas outside central and east-central New Mexico.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
