<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020523</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>For the next 5 days (May 23-May 27), most of the country will still be feeling the Spring chill as below-normal temperatures should remain entrenched across all but the New England states. Precipitation during this same period is expected to be relatively light with the best chances for relief coming to eastern Florida (3 to 5 inches) and northwestern Montana (1 inch or more).</p>
   <p>During the period May 28-June 1, some significant weather pattern changes take place as warm air finally pushes out the cold in all but the Southeast (below-normal temperatures expected in Virginia and the Carolinas) and the Pacific Northwest. Not much relief is expected in Alaska or across the middle two-thirds of the country. Of interest however, is the strong prospect of a vigorous system making its way up the Atlantic Coast during this period bringing with it the potential for high winds, high surf, and heavy rains. As a result, high probabilities of above-normal precipitation are forecasted to affect the entire East Coast (Georgia to Maine).</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Texas and the Gulf Coast">
   <p>After weeks of slow deterioration, a much needed break came in the form of cooler weather and rains, which were welcomed in parts of southern and coastal Texas. While dryness has recently spread eastward along the central and eastern Gulf Coast, some parts of the Houston area welcomed a big drink as rains were locally heavy (4-6 inches is a few spots). This was the exception and not the norm though, as most locations received less than a weeks worth of rain. Evaporation rates are already outpacing that at this time leading to no improvement in coastal region of Texas.</p>
   <p>Further to the east, the dryness seen since the first of the year, and back to October of last year, continues to mount. Scattered moderate rains were seen in the region last week bringing a short reprieve to parts of southern Alabama, southern Georgia, and northern Florida . However, in an area roughly bounded by Montgomery, Mobile and Pensacola, the region has only seen around half of its normal precipitation since January 1, with deficits approaching 7-10 inches or more. Since October 1, 2001, the deficits are in the neighborhood of 12-16 inches or more in some places. Stream flow and soil moisture levels continue to remain quite low.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Northern Plains">
   <p>Rains over the past 4 to 6 weeks has led to the removal of abnormally dry D0 (W) conditions in eastern Iowa. Rains of 1-2 inches also fell across parts of eastern and central Oklahoma leading to slight improvement in conditions there. In the Oklahoma and Texas Panhandles however, conditions continue to worsen as the rain hasnt come.</p>
   <p>Further north, the situation remains bleak in western parts of Kansas, Nebraska, North Dakota and South Dakota. In the eastern Dakotas, improvements in year-to-date and October 1-present precipitation totals have led to the removal of moderate drought (D1) in this area while abnormally dry (D0) conditions have been pushed back to the west.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East Coast">
   <p>Continued relief was felt again across most of the region last week as more beneficial rains worked their way into the region. Amounts varied from 1-2 inches across most of the Mid-Atlantic and up into New England. The severe D2 (W) drought in Maine has now improved to moderate D1 (W) drought as improvement continues. In general, improvement is reflected in this region with a pushing of the drought towards the coast in parts of Delaware and Maryland. Most of New England improved from moderate drought (D1) to abnormally dry (D0) as the slow recovery continues for the regions water supply. Rains were not as heavy or frequent in the southern reaches of the Mid-Atlantic so conditions remain relatively unchanged from Virginia south to South Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Heading into the dry season, concern remains high over the entire region as impacts are ramping up. Secretary of Agriculture Ann M. Veneman designated the entire state of Arizona a drought disaster area on May 17. While some improvement was noted last week in parts of the West, this week was relatively quiet in the drought affected areas. The cards have been dealt as far as water supply is concerned as the snowpack season is nearing its end. Streamflows will be low and reservoir levels will continue to decline in the affected areas. Cooler weather recently has helped to slow the melting, but many areas will see a very early melt-out this year.</p>
   <p>Parts of Alaska continue to see balmy weather with record breaking heat in and around the Fairbanks and McKinley Park areas. The heat, coupled with this Springs dryness, has lead to an elevated fire risk and rapid runoff as snow melt has been accelerated.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, reservoirs in Molokai did not respond substantially to early May rains, so D0 (W) has been reintroduced across the western half of the county.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
