<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20250619</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Active weather east of the Rockies led to significant reductions in drought coverage, especially in Florida, Texas, the northern and central Plains, and the upper Midwest.  Amid early-summer showers, drought-free conditions largely continued from the southern Plains to the Atlantic Coast, excluding parts of Florida.  Meanwhile, a Western hot spell—accompanied by short-term dryness across roughly the northern half of the region—was manifested in rapidly developing soil moisture shortages, declining prospects for summer water supplies, an elevated wildfire threat, a boost in irrigation demands, and increased stress on rain-fed crops.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Active weather will shift eastward during the next couple of days, as a hotter, drier pattern envelops the nation’s mid-section and quickly expands.  Additional rainfall could total 1 to 3 inches across the eastern one-third of the United States, with some of the highest amounts expected from the lower Great Lakes States into northern New England.  However, by the end of the week, any significant precipitation should be limited to parts of the North, with hot, dry weather dominating the remainder of the country.  During the weekend, high temperatures should top 100°F in the western Corn Belt as far north as South Dakota, while readings will reach 95°F in nearly all areas of the Midwest.  By Sunday, however, cooler air should spread as far east as the northern High Plains.  During the transition to cooler weather, showers will develop from the Pacific Northwest to Montana.  In the East, the first major heat wave of the season will persist into the first half of next week, with high temperatures near 100°F expected at lower elevations of the Atlantic Coast States from Georgia to southern New England.  There are some indications that, by early next week, remnant tropical moisture once associated with Eastern Pacific Hurricane Erick could be entrained by a cold front, leading to an increase in shower activity from the southern Rockies into the upper Midwest.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for June 24-28 calls for the likelihood of above-normal temperatures across much of the eastern half of the country, as well as the northern Rockies and environs, while cooler-than-normal conditions will be mostly limited to the Southwest.  Meanwhile, near- or above-normal rainfall can be expected nationwide, with an area stretching from the Southwest into the Great Lakes States having the greatest likelihood of experiencing wet weather.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Caribbean">
   <p>In Puerto Rico, drought-free conditions continued, with the commonwealth having experienced neither dryness nor drought since November 5, 2024.</p>
   <p>It was another dry week for the U.S. Virgin Islands with only trace amounts of precipitation based on CoCoRaHS observations. Groundwater levels continued to drop, with St. John (Susannaberg Dpw 3) and St. Thomas (Grade School 3) wells dropped 2.0 feet and 3.4 feet, respectively, over the past month. Short-term indicators are beginning to show a slight dry signal. Mid- to long-term indicators still show normal or surplus amounts in most locations, as shown by the greenness observed in the Vegetation Health Index (VHI). All islands remain free of drought or abnormal dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="High Plains">
   <p>Rain-related drought improvement dominated the High Plains, although some significant drought-related agricultural problems persisted.  By June 15, statewide topsoil moisture ratings on the High Plains ranged from 19% very short to short in Kansas to 50% in Wyoming, according to the U.S. Department of Agriculture.  Wyoming led the region on that date with 36% of its rangeland and pastures rated in very poor to poor condition, followed by Nebraska at 30%.  Elsewhere, significant rain bypassed a few areas, including northeastern North Dakota, where moderate drought (D1) expanded.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>The drought-monitoring period began with drought covering less than 9% of the Midwest.  Showers and thunderstorms chipped away at existing dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2), although not all areas received significant rain.  Some of the most substantial drought relief occurred in the upper Great Lakes region and parts of the western Corn Belt.  On June 15, Iowa led the Midwest with topsoil moisture rated 27% very short to short, according to the U.S. Department of Agriculture.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast">
   <p>The monitoring period began with just over 4% of the Northeast experiencing abnormal dryness (D0) or moderate drought (D1), and that number fell slightly due to ongoing wet weather, especially in Maryland and southern Pennsylvania.  In fact, too much rain fell in some areas, with deadly flash flooding striking Ohio County, West Virginia, on the night of June 14-15.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Pacific">
   <p>An existing area of abnormal dryness (D0) was removed from south-central Alaska, but two new, small areas of D0 were introduced across the interior, amid the first hot spell of the season and a locally increased risk of wildfire activity.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, seasonably dry weather prevailed.  There were few changes in the Hawaiian drought depiction, although a small amount of abnormal dryness (D0) was added to windward sections of Kauai and Oahu.</p>
   <p>The record wettest year –to date continued for American Samoa, which received decent precipitation this week. In Pago Pago, at least 0.43 inches of rain fell this week. On Siufaga Ridge, 1.63 inches of rain were recorded, and American Samoa remained free of drought or abnormal dryness this week.</p>
   <p>In Palau, Koror recorded 2.72 inches of rain this week and conditions remained free of drought or abnormal dryness.</p>
   <p>The Mariana Islands did not experience much rainfall this week. None of the islands received more than 0.77 inches of rain this week, below the needed 1 inch needed each week. Saipan’s moisture deficit continues to increase, only receiving an average of 1.3 inches in the month of June, leading to further degradation of short-term severe drought (D2-S) to short-term extreme drought (D3-S). Tinian and Rota, while receiving little rainfall, have received more precipitation so far this month, 1.8 inches and 5.34 inches respectively. Tinian remains in short-term moderate drought (D1-S) while Rota was improved to short-term moderate drought (D1-S). Guam, while also recording less than an inch of precipitation, has received an average of 4.56 inches this month leading to greening of vegetation.</p>
   <p>The Federated States of Micronesia (FSM) remained mostly unchanged this week. Western and central Micronesia is seeing the return of beneficial rains after dry months. Yap saw further improvement in condition removing short-tern abnormal dryness after 1.93 inches fell this week, leaving the island at 8 inches already this month. No Drought Monitor depiction was made for Ulithi and Fananu this week due to missing data. In Chuuk, 1.5 inches of rain were reported, and conditions remained free of drought or abnormal dryness. On Lukunor, 1.06 inches of rain were reported, ending the three consecutive weeks with less than an inch of rain. Despite this, short-term abnormally dry (D0-S) conditions were introduced to Lukunor. On Nukuoro and Kapingamarangi, 2.36 inches and 3.52 inches of rain were reported, bring much-needed rainfall to the area. Water tanks on both islands are reported to be mostly full, along with healthy vegetation, indicating no drought or abnormal dryness has developed. On Pohnpei, 1.31 inches of rain were reported, and it remained free of drought or abnormal dryness. On Kosrae, 1.76 inches of rain were reported, and it also remained free of drought or abnormal dryness. Short-term extreme drought continued on Pingelap despite receiving 3.25 inches this week.</p>
   <p>In the Marshall Islands, conditions on Kwajalein remained short-term drought (D1-S) after only 0.37 inches of rain were reported this week. Short-term moderate drought (D1-S) continued on Ailinglapalap, where 0.35 inches of rain were reported. Short-term moderate drought (D1-S) continued on Jaluit, where 1.32 inches of rain were reported. Short-term extreme drought (D3-S) continued this week on Wotje and Utirik, where 0.28 inches and 0.02 inches of rain were reported, respectively. On Majuro, short-term abnormal dryness (D0-S) continued after 0.65 inches of rain fell. On Mili, conditions remained free of drought or abnormal dryness, and 5.76 inches of rain have been reported there so far in June.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South">
   <p>Downpours in parts of Texas, the only state in the region still experiencing drought, delivered significant relief but also sparked flooding.  In fact, deadly flash flooding struck the San Antonio area on June 12, when the official airport observation site received 6.11 inches—the second-wettest June day on record in that location, behind only 6.18 inches on June 3, 1951.  San Antonio also set a one-hour station rainfall record for any time of year, with 3.98 inches falling from 3 to 4 am CDT.  In drought-affected areas where heavier rain fell, some of the water was lost due to runoff, rather than absorption into parched soils.  Additionally, groundwater and aquifer depletion in south-central Texas and neighboring areas has developed over many years—and will require much more than a singular heavy-rainfall event for replenishment.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Drought was eliminated from all Southeastern States, except Florida, as showers and thunderstorms peppered the region on multiple days.  Even most of Florida experienced drought relief, with extreme drought (D3) being eliminated.  However, pockets of severe drought (D2) persisted across Florida’s peninsula, and there was even some expansion of moderate drought (D1) along and near Florida’s east coast, where recent rainfall has been light.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West">
   <p>In contrast to areas east of the Rockies, mostly dry weather dominated the West during the drought-monitoring period.  Rapid surface drying and prematurely melting (or melted) snowpack had led to a variety of agricultural and water-supply issues and concerns.  The Northwest has been especially dry in recent weeks, with topsoil moisture—as reported by the U.S. Department of Agriculture on June 15—rated 65% very short to short in Montana, along with 56% in Oregon and 45% in Washington.  Unlike Oregon and Washington, Montana received some much-needed precipitation in mid-June—but continued to experience agricultural drought impacts.  For example, Montana’s rangeland and pastures were rated 46% in very poor to poor condition on June 15.  Among major production states, Montana led the nation on that date in very poor to poor ratings for spring wheat (28% of the crop) and barley (25%).  Meanwhile, among several early-season Northwestern wildfires was the 3,600-acre Rowena Fire near The Dalles, Oregon, which has destroyed more than 150 structures, including several dozen homes.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Lindsay Johnson</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
