<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060323</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (March 22 - 26), an upper level pattern consisting of a ridge in the west and trough in the east will dominate the Lower 48 States.  Rain and snow will be likely in the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies. The rest of the contiguous U.S. is expected to be drier than normal with some scattered opportunities for precipitation.  Temperatures across the western half of the Lower 48 are forecast to be warmer than normal, with the eastern half cooler than normal.</p>
   <p>Over the ensuing 5 days (March 27 - 31), the outlook calls for temperatures to remain warm in the western half and cool in the eastern half of the country.  Normal precipitation is expected in the Pacific Northwest, while dry conditions will prevail throughout the rest of the country.  A frontal system is forecast to pass through the Lower 48, but expectations for precipitation remain low.  In Alaska, warm and dry conditions are anticipated across most of the state with below normal temperatures in the panhandle. Throughout the period, conditions are expected to remain favorable for potentially excessive rainfall in Hawaii.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>In Hawaii, above-normal rainfall during the last 7 to 60 days eliminated the D0 over the Big Island. The last 7 days were wet over Maui, but below-normal rainfall was prevalent at 30-day and longer timescales, so the D0 was left intact there. March 1 snowpack was below-normal across much of Alaska, especially in the southeastern sections. Precipitation deficits at many stations along the coast from Cordova eastward ranged from 4 to 6 inches for the last 30 days to 12 to 16 inches for the last 90 days. D0 was expanded southeastward to most of the panhandle to account for the dryness of the last 3 months.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley, Gulf Coast, and East-Coast States">
   <p>The southern Plains storm followed the usual storm track across the Southeast, missing the coastal Gulf of Mexico. With month-to-date rainfall deficits up to 4 inches and 90-day departures up to 8 to 12 inches, D0AH was expanded across the southern half of Louisiana and D0A expanded along the Gulf coast into the Florida panhandle. Central and southern Florida have experienced dry weather during the last 90 days, but this is the dry time of year and rainfall deficits were only a few inches. Southern Florida will be an area to watch in coming weeks.</p>
   <p>A band of 2 to 5 inches of rain fell across central and northern Mississippi to northern Georgia as the low tracked east, but amounts decreased considerably by the time it reached the drought areas of the southern Appalachians and mid-Atlantic. The D0A across northeast Alabama, northern Georgia, and part of adjoining Tennessee was pulled back, but no improvement was made to the drought areas of the Carolinas, Virginia, or eastern Kentucky/Tennessee. Many streams across the Carolinas remained at the ten percentile flow level, or lower, and March precipitation deficits were still an inch or more, even with rainfall amounts of 0.5 to 1.0 inch. Precipitation amounts ranged from half an inch or lower across eastern Kentucky into Virginia. D1AH was expanded into extreme southwestern Virginia where precipitation amounts were the lowest.</p>
   <p>A large part of the east coast, from the Carolinas to southern Maine, has been significantly dry during the last 30 to 90 days. There were widespread reports of precipitation deficits of 2 to 4 inches over the last 60 days, 7-day average streamflows were significantly below normal across the area, and red flag warnings for fire potential have been issued. D0A was expanded from Maryland-Delaware northward across southeast Pennsylvania to coastal Maine.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>An intense low pressure system pulled abundant Gulf moisture into the southern Plains late in this USDM period. Many stations in southeast Oklahoma, northern Texas, and southwest Arkansas reported rainfall amounts of 4 to 6 inches, with locally heavier amounts. Weekly rainfall totals exceeded 7 inches at 21 stations in or near Dallas, Arlington, Cooper, Clarksville, and Commerce in northeast Texas, with totals topping 9 inches in the Dallas area. Rainfall reports of 2 to 4 inches were widespread surrounding this heavy rain core into the adjoining sections of these three states. But even with the recent heavy rains, significant long-term deficits remained: 10-inch deficits or more over the last 12 months across much of the southern Plains, with 15 to 20 inch deficits over parts of southeast Oklahoma, southeast Texas, and southern Louisiana. As a result, the D4 oval in northeast Oklahoma was improved to D3 and the D4 oval in southeast Oklahoma was improved to D2, with a large part of D3 across Oklahoma, Texas, and Arkansas improved to D2. In Arkansas and northeast Texas, the D2 and D1 boundaries contracted, with D2 shrinking in north central Oklahoma. The D2 and D1 boundaries in southeast New Mexico and the adjoining Edwards Plateau in Texas were pulled back to conform to the area of one inch or more of rainfall. Deterioration occurred in the western part of the Oklahoma panhandle where long-term deficits were severe, with D3 nudging into counties that received little precipitation from this weeks storm.</p>
   <p>The low pressure system had a northerly component that brought heavy snow to the central Plains. Much of Nebraska received over a foot of snow, with amounts exceeding 2 feet reported at Loretto, Greeley, Chambers, Madison, and Fullerton in east north central Nebraska. Equivalent precipitation amounts from the snow ranged from 1 to 2 inches across most of Nebraska and into northern Kansas. The snowstorm dumped lesser amounts across parts of South Dakota, Colorado and southwestern Kansas, before moving into the Ohio Valley. The D0-D1 boundaries in central, eastern, and north central Nebraska and south central South Dakota were pulled back, and the D2 in eastern Nebraska all but eliminated, as a result of the beneficial short-term moisture. The D1 boundary was contracted westward in eastern Kansas, and the D1 was dented in northwest Kansas and southwest Nebraska.</p>
   <p>With this major precipitation event, a large part of the Plains drought area was designated with the H impacts label to capture areas having wet precipitation anomalies at roughly the 30 to 90 day timescales but dry anomalies at longer timescales. This includes most of Nebraska, the northeast third of Kansas, the southeast third of Oklahoma, most of Arkansas, and northeast Texas. The remaining drought areas in the central and southern Plains retained an AH impacts designation.</p>
   <p>D0A was expanded into northeast South Dakota, west central Minnesota, and most of North Dakota due to unusually dry conditions during the last 30 days to 6 months. The drought areas of Iowa, Illinois, and most of Missouri missed significant precipitation during this USDM period, so the depiction in those areas remained unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Southwest, and California">
   <p>Much of the West received precipitation this week, with most locations reporting a few tenths of an inch. An inch or more fell locally, with a few reports of 3 inches or more, generally not in the western drought areas. The last 30 days have been drier than normal across western Washington state, but well above-normal precipitation has fallen there earlier this winter. Across Arizona and most of New Mexico, generally below-normal precipitation fell during the last 7 days with amounts mostly 0.25 inch or less. With the exception of southeast New Mexico, no change was made to the USDM depiction in the western states this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Liz Love-Brotak</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
