<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030410</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through April 19 which may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: over the next 5 days (April 10-14): 1) dry, warm weather dominating the Plains and Rockies, with little or no rain or snow over the drought areas, and temperatures up to 15 degrees F above normal. For the 6-10 day period (April 15-19): 1) a storm system bringing rain and snow to the Southwest around April 13-14 and to the Rockies, Plains, and Midwest April 15-17; 2) above-normal precipitation across the Rockies and the Mississippi Valley and normal precipitation in the High Plains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Normal precipitation amounts led to diminishing D0 dryness in the southeast. In the southwest, where D0 continued, 12-week precipitation has totaled less than 50 percent of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Moderate showers contributed to the removal of D0 dryness from Oahu, but continued below-normal rainfall caused D1 drought to develop on the western side of the Big Island. D1A continued in the east.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Abundant rain or snow affected the region, but the heaviest precipitation fell south of the drought area in Maine and the D0 area in northern New Hampshire and northeastern Vermont, so the depiction changed little this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Heavy rain exceeding 2 inches fell over northeastern parts of the island this week. With many areas experiencing abundant rains in the past 2 weeks, D0 dryness ended.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>A major snowstorm spread across the Plains, Midwest and Great Lakes Region, leaving beneficial moisture for areas that had been experiencing abnormal dryness since at least last autumn. The storm, which struck during April 6-8, left a blanket of snow ranging from 5 to 10 inches in a wide swath from Nebraska through northern Iowa into Wisconsin and northern Michigan. Amounts of 1 to 5 inches covered a large area just to the south. With liquid-equivalent amounts of 1 to 3 inches over much of the region, severe D2 drought improved to D1 in Michigan, northeastern Indiana, and northeastern Illinois, and D1 drought retreated northward in Illinois and Indiana and disappeared from Ohio. D1 drought also diminished in northern Iowa and eastern Nebraska, as D4 drought disappeared in central Nebraska and D3 diminished. In contrast, precipitation failed to significantly improve the D3 drought area in northwest Missouri, while D2 and D1 drought even expanded eastward in South Dakota and southern North Dakota. An area of D3 drought developed in north-central South Dakota in response to long-term and short-term dryness. Persistent dryness led to the extension of D0 southward in eastern Illinois, and D0 dryness also expanded westward across Arkansas and edged eastward in northern Texas and southern Oklahoma.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Snow and rain spread across the Rockies, Great Basin, and the West Coast from central California northward to Washington, with heavy snow in the Cascades. Liquid-equivalent amounts of 1 to 2 inches across western Montana and northern and central Idaho led to further erosion of drought in these areas, while the improvement in other states was minor. With continued normal streamflows in the area and cumulative precipitation since October near to above normal, the D4 in southeastern Colorado improved to D3. The Southwest remained mostly dry. USDA's National Water and Climate Center noted that the stormy March led to improved water supply volume forecasts in the Southwest, Rockies of Colorado, Wyoming, Montana, and the Columbia basin, but the storms missed the Intermountain West of Utah, Nevada, and southeastern Oregon, with forecast spring and summer streamflows less than 50 percent of average.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
