<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061102</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 5-day period (November 2-6) that may affect areas of dryness or drought include: 1) Heavy precipitation will arrive along the northern Pacific Coast (western Washington to northern California) on November 2 and continue, with only brief interruptions, into early next week; 2) Rain and snow will spread as far east as the northern Rockies, but the heaviest precipitation (locally 5 inches or more) will fall primarily from the Cascades westward; 3) Rain showers may develop during the weekend and early next week across the south-central United States, although amounts will be generally an inch or less; 4) Locally heavy rain will fall during the next few days in Hawaii, especially from Kauai to Maui, where flash flooding may occur; 5) Most other key drought areas, including the northern Plains, the Southwest, and the Southeast, will receive little or no precipitation.  The 6- to 10-day (November 7-11) outlook from the Climate Prediction Center calls for above-normal temperatures and precipitation across most of the contiguous United States.  Warmer-than-normal weather will be most likely from the northern and central Plains into the Northeast, while wet conditions will be most prominent across the interior South, the upper Great Lakes region, and the Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Heavy rain returned to parts of Hawaii on October 30-31, following a brief lull.  On Oahu, 24-hour totals ranged from 5 to 10 inches in several locations, with a maximum of 10.05 inches reported in Maunawili.  On the heels of last weeks rain, mandatory water restrictions over eastern Oahu were changed to a voluntary request for conservation, and moderate drought (D1) was upgraded to abnormal dryness (D0).  Meanwhile, locally heavy showers continued to pepper Puerto Rico, although abnormally dry (D0) areas across the southern and eastern periphery of the island received mostly light rain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>A narrow band of heavy rain spread across southeastern Colorado and much of Kansas from October 25 to October 27, boosting topsoil moisture reserves for pastures and winter wheat.  The central Plains rain, which generally totaled 1 to 3 inches, brought a reduction in the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2).  In contrast, mostly dry weather persisted across much of Oklahomas winter wheat belt, where moderate to extreme drought (D1 to D3) remained entrenched.  On October 29, USDA rated 23% of Oklahomas winter wheat in very poor to poor condition.  Meanwhile, the percentage of the Kansas wheat crop rated very poor to poor stood at just 3%, down from 7% a week earlier.</p>
   <p>Farther north, light snow blanketed much of Montana on October 30, helping to insulate emerged winter wheat from an early-season cold snap.  That snow, along with a reassessment of earlier precipitation patterns, led to a decrease in coverage of severe drought (D2), especially in northeastern Montana.  Although the northern and central Plains drought depiction now carries an H label, for long-term, hydrologic drought, lingering agricultural concerns include limited irrigation reserves and poor pasture conditions.  In northeastern Colorado, along the South Fork of the Republican River, Bonny Reservoir held 10,240 acre feet (just under 3.3 billion gallons) of water on September 30, which was only 30% of average.  On October 29, the percentage of pasture and rangeland rated very poor to poor by USDA included: 31% in Colorado; 35% in Montana; 44% in South Dakota; 45% in Nebraska; 46% in Kansas; 50% in North Dakota; and 63% in Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South-Central States">
   <p>Another round of heavy rain soaked the western and central Gulf Coast States.  From October 25 to October 27, storm-total rainfall locally topped 10 inches in non-drought locations such as Moss Bluff, Louisiana (11.37 inches), and Orange, Texas (10.65 inches).  Farther north, a band of heavy showers (2 inches or more) brought some drought relief to southwestern and central Arkansas.  However, only light to occasionally moderate rain fell in the core extreme drought (D3) areas of the south-central United States, resulting in little overall change in the regions drought depiction.  In south-central Texas, year-to-date rainfall through October 31 totaled just 9.23 inches (54% of normal) in Del Rio and 18.15 inches (64%) in San Antonio.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>While heavy rain brought drought relief to parts of Alabama and Georgia, conditions worsened in east-central Florida.  The former area of moderate drought (D1) was broken in two, with a lingering area of hydrologic drought in south-central Alabama.  In Georgia, moderate drought was pushed to an area south of a line stretching roughly from Columbus to Macon to Augusta.  In contrast, D1 was introduced farther down Floridas east coast to the vicinity of Lake Okeechobee.  Within the southeastern area of D1AH (moderate agricultural and hydrologic drought), October rainfall totals were less than 25% of normal and year-to-date amounts were at least one foot below normal in Florida locations such as Vero Beach and Melbourne.  Elsewhere in the Southeast, there were some general reductions in the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0), especially in areas receiving significant rainfall for the second consecutive week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Upper Great Lakes Region">
   <p>A pesky area of moderate to extreme drought (D1 to D3) remained entrenched across the upper Great Lakes region, especially across northern Minnesota.  Through the end of October, year-to-date precipitation totaled 15.71 inches (72% of normal) in International Falls, Minnesota.  In northern Michigan, Marquette followed its second-lowest June-September rainfall total (8.87 inches, or 66% of normal) with another dry month.  Marquettes October precipitation totaled just 1.72 inches (47% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>An early-season snow storm blanketed the Colorado Rockies with as much as 2 feet of snow on October 25-26.  Snow was particularly heavy across north-central Colorado, where storm-total liquid equivalents topped 2 inches.  As a result, there were some modest reductions in the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2).  Meanwhile in southeastern Idaho, light snow and a reassessment of earlier precipitation totals led to a slight reduction of abnormal dryness (D0).</p>
   <p>It is also worth noting that the 2006-07 wet season is off to a slow start from the West Coast states eastward into the western Great Basin.  In Californias Central Valley, rainfall totals for July-October 2006 totaled just 0.08 inch (9% of normal) in Fresno and 0.26 inch (9%) in Redding.  However, less than 10% of the normal annual precipitation typically falls from July to October in those two locations.  Nevertheless, one effect of the early-season dryness has been poor pasture and rangeland conditions.  On October 29, USDA rated 84% of Californias pasture and rangeland in very poor to poor condition, along with 55% in Oregon and 40% in Nevada.  In addition, Riverside County, California, dealt with the 40,000-acre Esperanza fire, which was set on October 26 and claimed the lives of five federal firefighters before its late-October containment.  Recent dryness was only a contributing factor to the fires initial rapid expansion and destruction of more than 30 homes; primary reasons included a Santa Ana wind event (e.g., blustery winds and low humidity) and a heavy fuel load (e.g., dead or dying trees and summer-cured seasonal vegetation).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
