<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080508</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>An intense, late-spring storm at the beginning of the period dumped heavy snow and rain on the north-central High Plains, easing drought concerns in southeastern Montana, northeastern Wyoming, and western South Dakota.   Later in the period, an upper-level low tracked from the Southwest into the central and southern Plains, triggering scattered showers and thunderstorms and reducing drought conditions in western Texas and southeast New Mexico.   Dryness persisted for the eastern Gulf and southern Atlantic Coasts, while light to moderate rains in the Northeast maintained favorable to abundant moisture conditions.  Light precipitation fell on the Northwest for the 8th consecutive week, and the Southwest remained dry.  Temperatures across much of the lower 48 states averaged below normal, with the greatest departures (less than -4 degrees F) in the Great Basin, central Plains, upper Midwest, and Northeast.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days, an upper-level low moving through the southwestern United States will trigger thunderstorm clusters across the southern and central Plains and Delta on Wednesday, May 7, with additional rain and storms moving into the southeast on Thursday.   Rainfall in excess of 4 inches is forecast for parts of eastern Kansas and central Missouri on Wednesday, with rain transitioning eastward into the Ohio River Valley and Mid-Atlantic by the end of the week.  Scattered precipitation is also expected for the northern High Plains, where drought-affected areas of South Dakota, Montana and Nebraska could benefit from 1-2 inches of rainfall by Friday.  An optimistic forecast for the southeast has rainfall in excess of 2 inches overspreading drought-stricken areas of eastern Tennessee and northern Georgia over the weekend.  Out west, dry conditions are expected to continue for much of California, Arizona and New Mexico, while northern areas of the Great Basin should see light amounts of precipitation (under 1 inch) over the next five days.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 6- to 10-days (May 12-20), cool, wet conditions are expected for the eastern half of the nation, with drier than normal conditions forecast for much of the west, along with temperatures much warmer than normal.  South Florida should see continued warm, dry conditions during this period, and southern and eastern parts of Alaska may see above normal precipitation through May 20, while southern Texas is expected to see increased wetness develop by May 14, after an initial dry period over the next 7 days.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Weekly rainfall totals remained low across much of Hawaii, with just 0.5 to 1 inch reported on Maui, and between 0.5 and 4 inches reported on the eastern slopes of Big Island, keeping D0 and D1 conditions status-quo.</p>
   <p>Drought-afflicted areas of central and eastern Alaska also remained unchanged, due to rainfall amounts generally below 0.5 inches, while much of interior and western Alaska received close to zero precipitation.</p>
   <p>Some improvement was made in D0 coverage across western Puerto Rico after a second wet week brought over 5 inches of rain to the northern and western slopes of the island, eliminating abnormal dryness across the northern two-thirds of the island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>A late spring snowstorm brought blizzard conditions and heavy snow to the north-central High Plains, with liquid equivalent precipitation totals as high as 4.5 inches in southeast Montana, and between 2 and 3 inches in western South Dakota.  A general one-category improvement was made in this area.  The D2 coverage in southeastern Montana was reduced into western North Dakota, where surpluses now exist in both the short and medium term.  In western and northern South Dakota, D0 and D1 coverage was trimmed back as well, and D1 was reduced to D0 in far western parts of the state, along with D0 being cut back in northeast Wyoming.</p>
   <p>While this heavy precipitation brought relief to the north-central High Plains, rainfall amounts between 0.5 and 1.2 inches in the Nebraska Panhandle did little to ease long-term dryness, precluding any changes to the D2H and D3H coverage this week.  Drought blends do show a slight improvement this week, but 30-, 60-, and 90-day precipitation remained below 50% of normal, and Box Butte Reservoir was reported to be at 27% of capacity (49% of normal capacity), though slowly increasing, which is expected at this time of year.</p>
   <p>Further south, heavy showers and slow-moving thunderstorms dumped over 2 inches of rain on southwestern Kansas (across the D1A and D2A areas of Seward, Meade, and Clark counties), replenishing topsoil moisture and prompting a reduction in drought coverage in a localized area of southwest Kansas.  Additional storms in western Texas and eastern New Mexico late in the period brought over 2 inches of rain to western areas of the Brazos and Red River valleys, with much of the D2A in southeastern New Mexico reduced to D1, and the D1 boundary reduced westward into New Mexico.  Areas of northwestern Texas and the Oklahoma Panhandle, however, missed out on this rainfall, and no adjustments were made to the D2A coverage.</p>
   <p>East of the Big Bend and along the Rio Grande Valley, moderate rains over the past two weeks, combined with recent heavy rainfall from thunderstorms, eliminated the exceptional drought (D4) area encompassing Maverick, Dimmitt, and Webb counties.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Unfortunately, D2-D3 areas of eastern Tennessee and northern Alabama missed out on the heaviest rain this week when a powerful storm system dumped 2 to 7 inches of rain on the Delta and the western Tennessee and southwestern Ohio valleys. Weekly totals below 0.5 inches were observed across the D2 areas in southeastern Tennessee and northern Alabama and Georgia, where short-term (30- and 60-days) deficits persisted, ranging from 3-6 inches, and longer-term deficiencies (6- and 12-months) remained between 10-25 inches.</p>
   <p>A strong line of thunderstorms moved through the Gulf Coast region early on Saturday morning, bringing 1-2 inches of rain to southern Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama, while 4 to 8 inches inundated southeastern Louisiana.  Consequently, the D0 and D1 areas were alleviated to the north and west of Lake Pontchartrain, where 30-day deficits (1-3 inches) and 90-day shortages (2 to 6 inches) were erased.  The D2H and D3H regions of central and northern Alabama benefited from 0.5 to 1.5 inches of rain during the week (topsoil moisture), but long-term precipitation deficits and very low stream flow levels suggested that improvements to this area were not warranted yet.  Though eastern D0 areas along the southern Atlantic Coast did receive rainfall exceeding one inch, the drought-stricken western regions of North Carolina, South Carolina and northern Georgia received little or no precipitation, and D3 was expanded slightly into the western counties of South Carolina due to persistently low USGS 7-day averaged stream flow percentiles (2-10th percentile).</p>
   <p>South Florida D0 and D1 coverage was expanded eastward across Palm Beach, Broward and Miami-Dade counties due to the third consecutive dry week, and D2 was introduced into Glades, Hendry and Collier counties owing to decreasing soil moisture percentiles across interior portions of southern Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Much of the Southwest remained dry during this period, with most of California, Arizona, and the Great Basin reporting little or no precipitation.  Light precipitation (0.1 to 0.3 inches) was observed in southeastern Oregon and southwestern Idaho, but an upper-level ridge kept the region rain-free early in the week, offering no drought relief.  More significant precipitation (0.3 to 1.5 inches) fell further north on the drought-free Northwest, especially in the Cascades.</p>
   <p>After an exceptionally wet start to the 2007-08 water year, precipitation in the West has greatly diminished since early February, especially in the Southwest. Precipitation during the past 90-days was well under 50% of normal for much California, Nevada, Arizona, and western New Mexico.  Farther north, precipitation has also been subnormal, but not quite as severe as the Southwest.  However, looking back during the past 7 months, the water year to date (WYTD) basin-average precipitation is surprisingly close to normal for much of the West.   Fortunately, cold conditions since mid-March have limited snow melt, and along with frequent but weak Pacific storm systems and decreasing normal snow water contents, the observed NRCS basin-averaged snow water content (SWC) across the northern half of the West has remained at or above-normal, remaining steady or actually increasing during the past few weeks.  In the Cascades, SWC was between 150-285% of normal.  Farther south, however, an area of concern was in California's Sierra Nevada, where SWC has declined to between 45-77% of normal, and WYTD precipitation averaged between 72-81% of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael James</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC, JAWF</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
