<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070215</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (February 15-19), moderate precipitation (0.25 to 1.25 inches) is forecast for the central Appalachians and parts of the central and northern Rockies. Light amounts are expected in most other areas of dryness and drought, but little or none is anticipated from the northern tiers of California, Nevada, and Utah southward to the Mexican border, and in most of Kansas, Oklahoma, and Texas.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (February 20-24), the odds favor subnormal precipitation in the dry areas of Alaska, central and northern sections of the western Plains, and peninsular Florida. In contrast, wet weather is anticipated for California, Nevada, Arizona, and western Utah.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In the D0 region of Alaska, a few locations reported between one-tenth and one-quarter inch of precipitation, but at most sites amounts were barely measureable at best, allowing D0 conditions to persist.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, decent rains (1 to 4 inches) fell on parts of eastern Hawaii Island, northern Maui, and northern Kauai, but only scattered amounts exceeded 0.5 inch elsewhere, and D0 conditions were maintained throughout the state.</p>
   <p>It was an exceptionally dry week throughout Puerto Rico, though some stations in eastern parts of the island recorded about one-quarter inch of rain. With rainfall deficits continuing to grow, both D0 and D1AH conditions were expanded northwestward. For the last 60 days, only the interior southwestern parts of the island have been wetter than normal, with most other locations (except the northern tier) recording under half of normal. Longer-term dryness is most substantial in central and eastern parts of the island, where some locations are 1 or 2 FEET short of normal rainfall for the last 6 months.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East and Southeast">
   <p>It was another relatively dry week, with scattered precipitation totals of 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches confined to southeastern West Virginia and the southern half of the Florida Peninsula. Little or no precipitation fell on northern Florida and adjacent Georgia, and from northern sections of Alabama and Georgia northward to the Kentucky and Virginia borders.</p>
   <p>On time scales ranging from 30 to 90 days, moisture deficits across northern Alabama, northwestern Georgia, and eastern Tennessee have been more significant than in other dry portions of the East. Anywhere from 10 to 50 percent of normal precipitation fell during the last 30 days in this region, and totals dating back to mid-November 2006 are 8 to locally 16 inches below normal. As a result, a new area of D1AH was introduced here. Only 5 inches of precipitation fell on Chattanooga, TN from December 2006 through January 2007, which was their sixth driest such period in 117 years of record.</p>
   <p>In addition, increasingly dry conditions led to the expansion of D0AH into the northern half of Alabama and western North Carolina, and D0A was introduced in a small area near West Palm Beach, FL that for a while had been better off than other portions of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Although moderate to heavy precipitation fell on a substantial portion of the central United States, very little of it affected areas that have been experiencing dryness and drought. Amounts ranging from 1 to 3 inches ended D0H conditions in most of southwestern Missouri, but in the remaining dry areas stretching from the northern Plains and Great Lakes southward through Texas, weekly amounts exceeding 0.5 inch were limited to central and eastern Kansas and southwestern Oklahoma. As a result, conditions remained unchanged for a vast majority of the area, though there were a few exceptions.</p>
   <p>The last couple of months brought only 25 to 50 percent of normal precipitation to northeastern North Dakota and adjacent Minnesota, prompting deterioration to D2H for the region. Farther east, northern portions of Minnesota remained exceptionally dry. Across the states D3H region, only isolated areas of measurable precipitation have been observed during the last 30 days, and totals for the last 6 months range from 10 inches down to as little as 2 inches, only 5 to 25 percent of normal in north-central Minnesota and in the eastern reaches of the Arrowhead.</p>
   <p>Assessing the severity of dryness and drought has been challenging in the southern half of the Great Plains, with conditions for the past few months differing markedly from those of the previous couple of years. Precipitation totals for the past 60 days were above normal for a vast majority of this region. If you go back an additional month, the last 90 days were below normal for most of the D1H through D4H areas in Texas and in the D2H region of Oklahoma; however, amounts as low as half of normal were limited to a small part of the D4H region. Keep looking back farther and farther, through 2005 in Texas and 2004 in Oklahoma, and both the duration and magnitude of the drought appear progressively worse. During the last 12 months, most of the D3H and D4H regions in Texas recorded 4 to 12 inches less than normal precipitation while 12 to 16 fewer inches than normal were reported across the northern sections of Oklahomas D2H region. Go back an additional year, and since mid-February 2005 precipitation totals range from 1 to 2 FEET below normal across much of the D3H and D4H regions in Texas, with 2-foot shortfalls even more common across central Oklahoma and northern Texas. And keep in mind that these numbers include the above-normal totals observed in most areas for the last 60 days.</p>
   <p>The recent precipitation has boosted topsoil moisture and virtually eliminated significant fire danger. However, subsoils (roughly below 60 cm deep) remain exceedingly dry, and as a result, the substantial precipitation that has fallen this winter has not been particularly effective in increasing base streamflow rates, refilling stock ponds, and boosting reservoir levels because a large proportion of the fallen precipitation gets soaked up by the dry subsoils, leaving less water available to produce tangible signs of drought recovery. For these reasons, the Drought Monitor continues to identify significant areas of moderate to excessive hydrologic drought across the southern half of the Plains.</p>
   <p>Some adjustments were made to the Drought Monitor depiction across Texas, but this was the result of a re-analysis of the long-term indicators. No substantial precipitation fell on the region</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Rocky Mountains">
   <p>Heavy precipitation finally fell on parts of California. Amounts of 5 to 12 inches were fairly common across the southern Cascades, the western tier of the state as far south as the San Francisco Bay area, and the northern and central Sierra Nevada. Between 2 and 5 inches were recorded in the southern Sierra Nevada, and along the western tier from Monterrey southward to San Luis Obispo. Elsewhere, scattered totals of 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches were observed across much of the northern halves of the Rockies and Intermountain West, part of southwestern California, and a few of the higher elevations in Arizona. Meanwhile, most areas from central Utah and Nevada southward through southeastern California recorded a few tenths of an inch at best, and similarly low amounts fell on northeastern Montana and all but the western tier of Wyoming.</p>
   <p>Despite the large precipitation totals in parts of California, its effect on the regions dryness and drought was surprisingly small. D0 was pulled out of interior northern California, and D1A conditions retreated only slightly to the south and east. Despite the wet week, basin-average totals since the start of the water year (October 2006) were only 50 to 60 percent of normal. The storm was a relatively warm one, so its effect on snowpack water content was even less impressive. As of mid-February, there were a few locations northwest of Lake Tahoe that were slightly above 70 percent of normal, but most sites in the central and southern Sierra Nevada were only 35 to 50 percent of normal.</p>
   <p>In fact, precipitation totals since the start of the water year are below normal through many of the mountainous regions of the West, and with temperatures generally averaging above normal, the percent of normal snowpack water content is even lower in most places. As a result, several areas of deterioration were introduced this week. D2A conditions expanded westward in southern California, the D1A boundary was moved northward to include the southwestern one-third of Nevada, and D0 conditions were broadly expanded to include all of Utah and adjacent sections of Idaho and Nevada. Snowpack water content generally ranged from 55 to 75 percent of normal in the new D0 areas despite the fact that actual water year precipitation totals were somewhat above normal in southeastern Utah.</p>
   <p>Finally, with above-normal water year precipitation totals and only slightly below normal snowpack water content, D0 conditions were removed from northern Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
