<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030102</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather conditions which may have an impact on abnormally dry or drought areas during December 31, 2002-January 1, 2003 include an ongoing Southeast storm that is and should drop additional significant rain on the Piedmont. During January 2-6: 1) A quieter (dry) weather pattern should cover most of the country, except for 2) continued unsettled weather in the Pacific Northwest, and 3) in the Northeast, although northern Maine may miss most of the significant precipitation again. Temperatures should average well above normal in the northern and central Plains and upper Midwest, and somewhat below normal in the East.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6 to 10-day outlook (January 7-11) features subnormal precipitation for much of the lower 48 States, except for surplus precipitation in Washington, north-central Rockies, and coastal New England, and seasonable totals in the Great Lakes region, eastern Ohio Valley, mid-Atlantic, and southern Appalachians. Temperatures should be above-normal in the western half of the Nation, with subnormal readings east of the Mississippi River and south of the Ohio River.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Light to moderate scattered showers continued across windward locations of Kauai, Oahu, Maui, and the Big Island (Kona), but little or no rainfall occurred at leeward locations, maintaining dryness and drought in western Molokai, Maui, and western Kona. The Dec. 26-27 showers across northern Maui (0.25-0.5) were not enough to erase the abnormal dryness there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Scattered light showers, generally occurring early in the period, did little to alleviate short-term dryness and growing deficits across most of the island. In the west-central interior, however, locally heavier amounts (1.5-3) removed or prevented dryness. With 7-day average USGS streamflows (ending Dec. 30) at or below the 10-24%ile across the north-central and eastern parts of the island, D0 was expanded eastward.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Another El Nino-enhanced storm system dropped moderate to heavy precipitation on much of the South and East, with 1.5 to 3 inches of rain in the Southeast, 1-2 inches of liquid-equivalent, mixed precipitation to the mid-Atlantic, and heavy snows (1-3 feet) to most of New England. The moderate to heavy rains from Georgia into Virginia further eased or alleviated long-term drought, prompting a drought statement from Georgia State Climatologist that the state's drought was all but over, except for some groundwater (well) levels, but that water conservation is still needed. Similarly, 7-day average USGS streamflow levels (ending Dec. 30) are generally at the 75 %ile or higher from Georgia northward into southern New England. Unfortunately, the Christmas snow storm missed most of northwestern Maine as long-term drought remained.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>Before the Christmas snow storm hit the Northeast, it tracked across the southern Plains, Delta, and Midwest, dropping light to moderate rains (0.5-2.5) on the southern Great Plains and Delta while producing severe weather on Dec. 23 across the western Gulf Coast States. Meanwhile, the northern fringes of the storm (south-central Plains, Ozarks, and western Ohio Valley) were blanketed with 6-12 of snow. In Arkansas and southern Missouri, enough precipitation (1.5 to 3 inches) fell to diminish D0-D1 in the area.</p>
   <p>Farther north, however, the system completely missed the western Corn Belt and north-central Plains, and temperatures averaged 5 to 10F above normal, with highs reaching into the sixties. Very little precipitation has fallen on this region the past 6-7 weeks, with Des Moines, IA reporting no measurable precipitation since Nov. 12, and St. Joseph, MO since Nov. 15. Accordingly, dryness and moderate drought extended northward into central Iowa, while severe-extreme drought covered northeastern Kansas and northwestern Missouri, the latter area accumulating 3-6 inch deficits the past 90 days. In the upper Midwest, a dearth of snow (from a combination of subnormal precipitation and mild weather) resulted in abnormal dryness across northern Minnesota and the Upper Peninsula of Michigan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Another moisture-laden Pacific storm system brought moderate to heavy precipitation to the region, this time somewhat farther north than last week's system, dropping 2-6 inches, locally more than 10 inches, to the northern two-thirds of the West Coast, portions of the Bitterroot and northern Rockies, and Idaho's Salmon River Mountains. Even normally drier areas east of the Cascades (eastern Washington and Oregon) received 0.75 to 1.5 inches, bringing month-to-date precipitation 2 to 3 times of normal in central and eastern Washington, and 150-250% of normal in southern and central Oregon. In addition, with this week's precipitation bullseye (6 to 12 inches) targeting northern California and southwestern Oregon, basin average precipitation (PNP) and snow water contents (SWC) quickly rebounded, with season-to-date PNP now above 70%, and SWC near or above normal (through December 30) in southern Oregon (Rogue, Umpqua, Klamath, Lake County). As a result, D0-D2 was eased across southern and central Oregon and southern Washington. The D3 area in south-central Idaho was slightly shrunk as the basin PNP approached 90%, and SWC topped 100%. In New Mexico, the latest indices and data suggested some drought improvement across north-central areas as average basin PNP and SWC were both 90-130% of normal.</p>
   <p>In contrast, another relatively dry and mild week in central and eastern Montana (temperatures 4 to 6F above normal, highs in the fifties), little or no snow cover, and minimal precipitation since late October or early November (Miles City .07 since Oct. 13; Glasgow .11 since Oct. 22; Havre .07 since Nov. 10; Billings dry since Dec. 5) expanded the D1-D3 areas slightly northward.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
