<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040115</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Conditions expected over the next 2 weeks that could influence ongoing dry areas include: 1) tropical Pacific moisture streaming northward into New Mexico and Texas will bring the heaviest rainfall so far this season to the drought areas of southern and eastern New Mexico and western Texas during January 14-17, with over 1 inch expected across southeastern New Mexico and much of Texas, as well as eastern Oklahoma; 2) abnormal mildness will give way to severe winter cold over much of the Plains and the West starting around January 21, and widespread snow should cover the Rockies and Plains during January 20-24; 3) above-normal precipitation is forecast across the northern Rockies and northern Plains during January 22-28, while drier weather extends across the Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Ample coastal precipitation and above-normal snow packs led to some retreat of the D0 area in southeastern Alaska. Rainfall was mostly light after January 5 across Hawaii, and D0 persisted in western Hawaii and western Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Very little precipitation fell this past week in the drought areas extending from Texas to the Dakotas, Minnesota and Wisconsin. Drought levels stayed the same, except for some expansion of the D1 in eastern South Dakota. Thirty and 90-day precipitation has been less than 75 percent of normal across the region. In west-central Texas, where extreme to exceptional drought continued, 90-day precipitation has been less than 25 percent of normal. As of January 13, Lubbock, Midland, and Childress had reported only a trace of precipitation since December 1.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Temperatures switched from abnormally cold to abnormally mild after January 7 in the northwestern quadrant of the country, while precipitation was generally lighter across the region, as heavy precipitation was mostly limited to the areas outside of the drought zones, including western parts of Washington and Oregon, and northern California. Nevertheless, light to moderate rain or snow, with variable amounts ranging up to an inch, fell from eastern Oregon and Washington across Idaho into western Montana, with over 2 inches in parts of Idaho and northwestern Montana. This was enough to tilt the dryness categories one category to D0 in much of eastern Washington, northeastern Oregon, northern Idaho, and northwestern Montana. Some of the improvement was also based on re-evaluating current conditions in the light of recent snow pack, streamflows, and ground water levels. The improvement from D4 to D3 in southeastern Oregon and southwestern Idaho was mainly based on a re-evaluation based on snow data, as the snow water content has climbed to the 126 to 142 percent of normal range in this area. The D4 area in southeastern Idaho and southwestern Montana diminished slightly in response to updated monthly precipitation data. To the south, continued dry weather in southeastern Arizona led to a slight expansion westward of D1/D2/D3.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
