<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050113</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecasts for the next 5 days (Jan. 12-17) show the prospects for a much quieter pattern than we have seen over the past couple of weeks. While southern California and the Southwest are expected to dry out and warm up to seasonable levels, it looks like much-needed precipitation could come to parts of the Pacific Northwest and Idaho Panhandle, with totals of 1 to 2 inches (liquid equivalent) possible. The real story in this period will be the invasion of very cold arctic air, with readings 10 to 30 degrees below normal expected in the Pacific Northwest, across the northern and southern Rockies and out into the Great Plains and Midwest.</p>
   <p>Looking out farther at the 6-10 day period (Jan. 18-22), the forecast calls for better chances of above-normal temperatures across most of the western United States, with the exception of normal readings in the Intermountain West and Great Basin. As for precipitation, the Pacific Northwest could see above-normal totals while the rest of the West should see less than normal amounts.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="From the Rockies to the Pacific Coast">
   <p>It has become a broken record, same wet song, third wet verse. Without reprieve, the second major storm system in as many weeks invaded California before moving through and pushing into the Southwest, bringing with it more record rains, flooding and several feet of snow to the Sierra Nevada range. Very little is left of the drought/dryness that was once prevalent up and down the California coast. With these early-season historic snow levels and rainfall totals, the short-term precipitation glut has led to significant improvement in the long-term drought that has plagued the Southwest since the late 1990s. Many basins and upper elevation locations are near, or have exceeded, record-high snow water equivalent (SWE) levels (many basins in CA, NV, UT and AZ are &gt;200% of average) for this time of year, based on NRCS/SNOTEL network readings. Early spring and summer streamflow forecasts are now calling for 110-150% of average flows, with plenty of time left in the wet season to add to the optimism. These good rains and snows have once again led to one-category improvements in the depiction within Nevada and Arizona in particular. The extreme (D3) drought has been relegated to only extreme northwest Nevada and the severe (D2) drought has also been scoured away to its current form over the past few weeks.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, not all have shared in the wetness. Even including the recent spell of precipitation last week along the coastal reaches of Oregon and Washington, the Pacific Northwest continues to dry out, with many locations such as Portland (-5.69 inches/64% of norm), Eugene (-11.89/47%), Salem (-7.79/56%), Pendleton (-1.99/56%), Seattle (-5.71/65%), Olympia (-7.65/66%), and Spokane (-2.16/65%) all well below normal since the water year began back in October. As a result of the slowly accumulating deficits, the abnormally dry (D0) region has expanded and pushed to the coasts and eastward through Oregon and Washington into the Idaho Panhandle and northwest Montana. Many of the basins in this region are showing snowpack levels below 50% of average to date and most of the upper elevation SWE readings are in the driest 5% of those recorded over the past 20 years. Although the dryness has not resulted in any real immediate impacts, if it persists, a significant reduction in expected spring and summer streamflows will follow.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>The abnormally dry (D0 AH) area on the Island of Hawaii has now been removed because of steady improvement over the past several weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Florida">
   <p>The situation in Florida remains unchanged (D0) from last week, with the continuing dryness leading to elevated fire danger levels.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>The storm that spilled out onto the Plains last week avoided the drier regions for the most part before dumping rain and snow on the Ohio Valley. Some minor relief in northwestern Missouri and central Iowa is shown via a slight reduction in the abnormally dry (D0) conditions that exist there.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
