<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000420</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Light to moderate rains are forecast for the northern tier of the region during April 19 - 24, but little or no rainfall is anticipated in the Gulf Coast and southern Atlantic states, including the current D2 areas. The ensuing 5 days (April 25 - 29) are expected to be dry across most of Florida, the central Gulf Coast, and the interior Southeast, with near-normal totals anticipated elsewhere. Temperatures are forecast to be near normal for the next 5 days, then rise above normal west of the Atlantic Seaboard for April 25 - 29.</p>
   <p>Moderate precipitation (1 to 3 inches) may provide some drought relief in eastern Wyoming, much of South Dakota, and areas from the Mississippi Valley eastward across the northern Ohio Valley and southern Great Lakes region during April 19 - 24. However, totals are forecast to remain below 0.25" in western Iowa and eastern Nebraska. Meanwhile, temperatures are expected to range from near normal across the southeastern half of the region, to well above normal in the northern and west-central Plains. The ensuing 5 days (April 25 - 29) are forecast to bring above-normal rainfall to much of central and eastern Nebraska, which would provide some drought relief, while near-normal amounts are anticipated elsewhere. Above- to much-above-normal temperatures are expected throughout the region during this period, possibly counteracting some potentially positive effects of the forecast rainfall.</p>
   <p>April 19 - 24 could bring more than 0.5" of rain to northwestern Wyoming while 0.25" to 0.5" is anticipated along the southern and western tiers of Montana. Farther south, little or no rain will dampen the dry areas across western Texas, New Mexico, and Arizona. During the ensuing 5 days (April 25 - 29), subnormal precipitation is anticipated in all of the dry areas. Meanwhile, above- to much-above-normal temperatures are forecast for these regions during April 19 - 29.</p>
   <p>No substantial changes are expected in Hawaii, Puerto Rico, or Guam during the next 10 days.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, Puerto Rico, and Guam">
   <p>Following a few dry days, daily showers dropped light to moderate rain on windward sections of Hawaii, but rainfall remained very light and isolated in leeward areas. As a result, D1(A,F) conditions were introduced in leeward sections of Kauai and Oahu while classifications were unchanged elsewhere. Meanwhile, scattered showers early this week dropped beneficial moisture on northern Puerto Rico, but not enough to erode D0 conditions along the northern tier of the island. No measurable rain fell on Guam during the past 7-days, and only 0.85" fell during April 1 - 19 (38% of normal). The island has received about 15.5" less rain than normal since August 1, 1999.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Two storm systems affected the D2 region in the last 7 days, but precipitation totals were lower than expected, so only a few areas experienced tangible relief. Between 0.7" and 2.0" fell near the Iowa/Nebraska border, in the Chicago, IL area, and on scattered sections of eastern Illinois and southern Indiana. Elsewhere, amounts ranged from a few tenths to locally 1 inch. In addition to the damp conditions, abnormally cool weather kept evaporation rates relatively low, preventing any significant drought deterioration. However, D0 conditions were introduced across the central South Dakota and northwestern Nebraska in response to subnormal precipitation for the last 30 days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South-Central States, Central Appalachians, and Southeastern States">
   <p>Rain fell on most of the region during the past 7 days, but precipitation was generally not sufficient to reduce drought categorizations. Exceptions included part of southern Florida, where 2 to locally 6 inches ended abnormally dry (D0) conditions; the northeastern Texas and western Louisiana coastline, where another 1 to 3 inches followed several relatively wet weeks, improving D2 (severe drought) conditions to D1 (first-stage drought); and eastern sections of the central Appalachians, where 1 to locally 4 inches eliminated D1 conditions and reduced the extent of D0 dryness. Despite increased rainfall across north-central and northeastern Texas, water use restrictions remain in place for 78 public water systems, and one municipal authority has imposed mandatory water rationing. Elsewhere, 7-day rainfall totals below 0.2" were measured across central and northern Georgia, the central Florida panhandle, and southeastern Louisiana, causing intensification to D2 conditions in central Georgia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Light precipitation and warm weather kept D0 conditions intact across interior Montana and allowed similar conditions to expand into northwestern Wyoming. Farther south, little or no precipitation fell from western Texas westward through the southern half of Arizona, allowing dryness to persist. According to the Southwest Area Coordination Center, approximately 200,000 acres (over 30% of the national total) have been scorched by wildfires in New Mexico. This is more than the statewide total for any full calendar year since 1994, and exceeds the 3-year total acreage burned during 1997 - 1999.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
