<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20031218</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may have an impact on abnormally dry or drought areas during the next 5 days (Dec. 18-22) include: 1) Strong ridging (high pressure) in the West and troughing (low pressure) in the East will create mostly dry and mild weather for the West and Plains, maintaining or possibly deteriorating drought conditions in both regions. Only the Pacific Northwest, northern California, and northern Rockies should receive some light precipitation during this period. The mild air should eat away at the snow cover, along with decreasing the basin average snow water content in the West; 2) A few weak systems (Alberta clippers) should drop southeastward out of the Canadian Prairies and drop light snow on the northern Great Plains, upper Midwest, and western Corn Belt, with temperatures remaining below-normal in the eastern third of the Nation; 3) An upper-air low over the Gulf of Alaska will move inland, bringing precipitation to much of southern and southeastern coastal Alaska; 4) A weak cold front should bring only light, scattered showers to Hawaii.</p>
   <p>The 6- to 10-day outlook for December 23-27 calls for above-normal precipitation along the Pacific and southeastern Alaskan Coasts, and the eastern third of the Nation. Unfortunately, drier-than-normal weather should encompass the northern two-thirds of the Rockies and Plains, western Corn Belt, and upper Midwest. Unseasonable warmth is forecast for the northern two-thirds of the U.S., with subnormal readings limited to the Gulf Coast and western Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>After two weeks of heavy showers (14-day totals ending 8 am HST, Dec. 9 included: 35.06" at Wilson Tunnel and 29.03" at Luluku, Oahu; 28.51" at West Wailuaiki, Maui), much drier conditions returned to the islands, maintaining D0 and D1 on Lanai, western Molokai, and the leeward sides of Maui and Kona. In Alaska, mild conditions overspread much of the state (weekly temperatures averaged 5 to 14F above normal), except for readings slightly below normal in extreme southeastern sections. While much of the northern three-quarters of Alaska was dry, moderate to heavy precipitation (1 to 4 inches) fell along the south-central coast, ending dryness on the Kenai Peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>The weekend storm system that dropped mixed precipitation on the mid-Atlantic and heavy snow on interior New England also generated widespread, heavy showers and occasional thunderstorms across the Southeast, including 1 to 3 inches of rain at central Florida locations. The rains were enough to alleviate most of the abnormal dryness, except in extreme north-central Florida where totals were less than an inch, and the Keetch-Byrum Drought Index (KBDI), a wildfire potential indicator, remained high (between 500-600, max=800).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Early in the period, a strong storm system tracked northeastward from the southern Great Plains into New England, dropping light to moderate snow on the south-central Plains, western Corn Belt, and western Great Lakes region, and heavy rain (more than 2 inches) on the lower Missouri and middle Mississippi Valleys. Lighter rainfall amounts (0.5-1.5") dampened the Red River Valley and Delta. The precipitation was enough to improve conditions by 1-category in northeastern and southern Wisconsin, northern Illinois, eastern Iowa, and northern Missouri, while the overall areal extent of D0-D1 shrank in the south-central Great Plains. Large year-to-date deficits still remained, however, in southeast Oklahoma and northeast Texas (more than 12 inches) and northwest Missouri (8-10 inches), and since mid-July in southeast Minnesota (8-10") and western Wisconsin (6-8").</p>
   <p>In contrast, another week with little or no precipitation in the upper Midwest (0.1-0.3"), northern Great Plains (&lt;0.1"), and southern High Plains (&lt;0.1"), or 25-50% of normal since mid-September (past 90-days), expanded moderate to severe drought into northern Minnesota, western North Dakota, and the Texas Panhandle. To further dramatize drought in the latter area, a strong but dry cold front kicked-up a large dust cloud across eastern New Mexico and western Texas on Monday, and it was quite visible on satellite images. The dust was transported well northeastward, with a red deposit reported around the Chicago area and lower Michigan after raining.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>The Pacific jet stream remained active, bringing several fast-moving systems into the Far West during the week, even southward into southern California. As a result, moderate to heavy (more than 2 inches, locally up to a foot) precipitation fell along coastal sections of central and northern California, Oregon, and Washington, and on the Cascades, Sierra Nevadas, and northern Rockies. In Californias Sierra Nevada basins, the storm increased season-to-date precipitation from 67-80% of normal on Dec. 10 to 86-96% of normal 5 days later, and increased snow water content from 72-108% (Dec. 10) to 109-133% (Dec. 15). This wet weather pattern has persisted since early October in the Pacific Northwest and extreme northern Rockies, producing above-normal water year-to-date (since Oct. 1) basin average precipitation across Washington, northern Idaho, and northwestern Montana, as well as near to above-normal basin average snow water content (on Dec. 15). Accordingly, another slight eastward retreat (improvement) of the western-most drought area was made in central Washington, western Oregon, and northeastern California, and in the Idaho Panhandle, to reflect this Falls persistent wetness in this region. Heavy precipitation (2-3.5") also fell around theYellowstone Park area, increasing both basin averaged season-to-date precipitation and snow water content by 10 percentage points in 5 days to above-normal values.</p>
   <p>Farther south and west, precipitation was much lighter, but temperatures generally averaged near or below normal, maintaining or slightly decreasing the basin averaged snow water content (on Dec. 15) in the Southwest and southern Rockies from 5 days prior. December 1 reservoir storage as a percent of capacity (via NRCS/USDA) was updated for Utah and Nevada; Utah was 24% (normal=67%, with 25 of 28 reservoirs reporting), and Nevada was only 9% (normal=45%, with all 7 reservoirs reporting). In Utah, Bear Lake storage was amended due to a settlement agreement so that the new lake bottom is now 2 feet higher than last year, meaning that water users no longer have access to about 130,000 acre feet of water. In other words, Bear Lake storage went from 142,000 acre feet to 12,000 acre feet, or about 1% of the total new capacity of 1,302,000 acre feet. In Nevada, an ever-shrinking Lake Mead has forced the Southern Nevada Water Authority to impose, effective January 1, much tougher mandatory water conservation laws, affecting the Las Vegas area.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
