<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070705</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather that could have an impact on dry areas in the next 2 weeks: 1)Maximum daily temperatures averaging as much as 12 degrees F above normal during July 3-8 over the interior West followed by continued above-normal heat through week 2 and minimal rainfall; 2) normal to above-normal rainfall the next 2 weeks over the Midwest, Northeast, and South.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Moderate to heavy rains in the eastern interior basin fell mostly outside of the D0 area, resulting in no change to the depiction of abnormal dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Generally light showers fell in the drought areas, resulting in no change to the depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Light rainfall resulted in continued D0H conditions in southeastern Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Frontal passage on Friday, June 29 brought beneficial rains to the Midwest and Ohio Valley. The moisture removed most of the D0 in Illinois and further reduced D0 in western Indiana. D1 retreated southward in eastern Indiana but persisted in southern Ohio. In contrast, dry weather led to expansion of D1 in central and southern Minnesota and D0 across western Iowa and parts of eastern Nebraska and southeastern South Dakota. Rainfall has been under 40 percent of normal in this region during the past 30 days, leading to rapid drying of soil moisture.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Continued below-normal rains and low streamflows led to the introduction of D1 in western New York. Very low streamflows and low farm pond levels led to D0 development in western New England.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>A cold front that swept across the region during this period led to helpful showers across the southern drought area, although much more rain is needed. The core of the drought remains in northern Alabama, which still stays at D4 status. But the recent rains, which reached 2 to 5 inches locally in Alabama, have begun to eat away at the drought area, and resulted in a slight shrinking of the D4. The moisture even brought some streams up to normal levels in northeastern Alabama, at least temporarily. The impact of the drought on farmers remains extremely serious, with Alabama corn still rated 88 percent poor to very poor, and soybeans at 85 percent poor or worse. Heavy rains reduced the D3 in northern Tennessee and also D2 and D1 in western Kentucky. The scattered showers scaled back slightly the D3 in parts of Georgia and the D2 in western South Carolina, with rainfall totals up to 4 inches pulling back the D1 in central South Carolina. The rains also reduced D1 in south-central North Carolina and the D0 in central Virginia. Heavy rains along the Florida southeast coast removed the D2 and D1 from the coast. West Palm Beach has recorded 14.85 inches of rain since June 1. To the west, however, D2 severe drought remained entrenched over Lake Okeechobee, which dropped to record lows this period. The depiction was re-analyzed this week to reflect the deficient river flows coming into the lake from the north, D1 now extending northward into interior central Peninsular Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and High Plains">
   <p>Across the interior West, above-normal temperatures and little rain led to persisting drought from the Southwest desert region northward to the northern Rockies and Intermountain region, with D2 and D1 drought expanding northward in eastern Oregon and D1 drought migrating into southern Idaho. Dropping soil moisture levels due to hot, dry weather led to introduction of D3 drought in western Nevada and adjacent areas of the California Sierra. High temperatures also contributed to some expansion of the D0 dry area in northern Colorado and southeastern Wyoming. Triple-digit heat reached from Colorado into Wyoming on July 2. Dry weather and temperatures averaging close to 4 degrees F above normal led to expansion of D0 northward into southwestern North Dakota from western South Dakota. Drought also extended slightly eastward in southwestern South Dakota. Thirty-day rainfall less than one-half of normal led to D0 in far western Kansas. Flooding rains hit eastern Kansas and Oklahoma and Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
