<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001026</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During October 25 - November 4, the following features may impact current areas of dryness: (1) Near- to above-normal precipitation and near- to below-normal temperatures across the Intermountain West and southern Rockies; (2) Additional moderate to heavy precipitation through most of the Great Plains and the southern High Plains; (3) Continued warm and dry conditions through the end of October in areas south and east of the Ohio and Mississippi Rivers; and (4) the chance for increased rainfall from the lower Mississippi Valley eastward through the central Gulf Coast and Tennessee Valley during the first few days of November.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Long-term dryness and drought continued to affect leeward parts of all islands in Hawaii, where only light rain was observed last week. Severe drought (D2), primarily for agricultural and wildfire-related concerns, covers the leeward sides of Maui and the Big Island, and all of Molokai.</p>
   <p>In Puerto Rico, moderate rains eliminated residual D0 conditions along the northern coast, though long-term rainfall totals remained below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>In contrast to areas farther east, many locations across the central and southern Plains experienced another week of moderate to heavy precipitation. Between 6 and 11 inches of rain doused sections of central and southwestern Oklahoma and part of east-central New Mexico, bringing significant drought relief but also localized flooding. Meanwhile, at least 2 inches soaked much of central and northern Texas, most of Oklahoma, northeastern New Mexico, parts of central and southern Kansas, and a few sites in northern Kansas and southwestern Nebraska.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, other areas missed most of the precipitation. Scattered totals approached 2 inches in the remainders of Nebraska, Kansas, and Texas, and across parts of Iowa and northern Missouri, while little or no precipitation was observed in the rest of the northern Plains and Great Lakes regions.</p>
   <p>Despite the recent wetness in many areas, 90-day precipitation totals were still 4 to locally 8 inches below normal in central Minnesota and over much of a broad area from western Iowa and eastern Nebraska southward through Louisiana and the northern half of Texas. As a result, dryness improved in many areas, but was not eradicated. Many of the D0 to D2 areas from western Nebraska and central Kansas southward through Texas improved by 1 category, with heavy rains and localized floods prompting improvement from D2 to D0 in small parts of southwestern Oklahoma and the Texas and Oklahoma panhandles.</p>
   <p>In contrast, moderate to heavy rains evaded most of the D3 areas in (a) western Texas, where only a modest reduction in extent was noted, and (b) eastern Nebraska and adjacent locations, where a slight expansion occurred. Short-term drought indices were returning to near normal in much of central and southern Texas, but many of the areas reservoirs remained unfavorably low, so D1(W) was introduced. Farther north, short-term dryness led to an expansion of D0 into most of the northern Great Lakes region, and to the introduction of D1 in parts of Michigans upper peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>Another week with little or no precipitation was observed from the lower half of the Mississippi Valley eastward through the southern Atlantic Coast, allowing dryness to persist or increase. For the 30 days ending October 23, precipitation totals were 2 or more inches below normal across much of western Virginia, the Carolina Appalachians and Piedmont, parts of eastern Tennessee, eastern South Carolina and adjacent Georgia, most of central Florida, and both the northern and southern reaches of the central Gulf Coast states. In parts of northern Mississippi and Alabama, 90-day rainfall totals were 7 to 10 inches below normal.</p>
   <p>The increase in short-term precipitation deficits eliminated the disproportionate hydrologic impacts previously affecting the southern Atlantic Coast. On October 1, short or very short topsoil moisture was reported in less than 10% of the 5 southern Atlantic coastal states (from Virginia to Florida), according to the National Agricultural Statistics Service. By October 22, however, this had increased to over 60%.</p>
   <p>The most significant changes to the regions drought categorizations occurred in the North Carolina Appalachians and part of central Florida, where new areas of extreme (D3) drought were noted, and in a swath from east-central Arkansas through part of northern Alabama, where exceptional (D4) drought developed. In addition, severe (D2) drought expanded through eastern Tennessee.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Beneficial precipitation fell on many areas once again, but was not as widespread as last week. Heavy rains (1 to 6 inches) fell on broad sections of Arizona, engendering localized flash flooding, while scattered moderate amounts (0.5 to locally 2.0 inches) dampened southern Nevada, central and southern Utah, central and western New Mexico, central and southwestern Colorado, and the northern Intermountain West.</p>
   <p>The precipitation allowed areas of D0, D1, and D2 to recede in northwestern and southwestern reaches of the interior West, and eliminated the small D2 area near the central Utah and Arizona border. However, the northern High Plains, central Rockies, and central Great Basin missed most of the recent precipitation, and increasing moisture deficits led to the introduction or expansion of D0 to D1 conditions in these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
