<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000518</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Expected mid-week precipitation (1-4 inches in some areas) from a vigorous low pressure system tracking across the Plains and into the lower Great Lakes region may lead to some improvement in existing drought conditions here but will likely not be enough to erase the 9 months of dryness some parts of the region have seen going back into1999. Further out, the 6-10 day outlook is showing better chances for above normal precipitation across most of the Great Plains and the Midwest. Temperatures look to be near or above normal for the most part through the period ending May 25.</p>
   <p>No immediate relief is seen on the horizon for most drought affected areas in the Deep South and Southeast. Some rains may reach the region by the weekend but only nominal amounts are expected, especially in areas currently experiencing first stage (D1), severe (D2) and extreme (D3) drought. The 6-10 day forecast isn't any more promising with conditions over the entire region looking to be warmer and drier than normal except for an area covering northeast Texas, Arkansas, northern Louisiana and northern Mississippi where there is a chance for above normal precipitation.</p>
   <p>No relief is seen coming for fire fighters in the coming week. Although temperatures are expected to be at or around normal throughout the Southwest, significant precipitation isn't really expected, as is the norm this time of year. Dry thunderstorms (lightning risk) and continued high winds will only worsen fire danger in parts of Texas, New Mexico and Arizona.</p>
   <p>No real significant weather pattern changes are expected over the Hawaiian Islands anytime soon. As average daily temperatures continue to climb across the state, leeward areas currently in first stage (D1) drought are at risk to worsen and fall into severe drought (D2) in the coming weeks.    For Puerto Rico, generous showers and scattered strong thunderstorms may bring relief (as much as 2-4 inches of rainfall) to many parts of the island during the latter part of this week (5/17-19) due to the encroachment of a rather vigorous trough.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>First stage drought (D1) conditions are firmly in place across most of the island chain. Conditions have now deteriorated enough to warrant bringing severe drought (D2) into the leeward areas of Molokai, Lanai, Maui, and the northwest portion of the Big Island. Impacts across all sectors will continue to be felt until a sustained change in the circulation patterns occurs over the islands.</p>
   <p>Abnormally dry (D0) conditions persist along the northern side of Puerto Rico but a more favorable (unstable) weather pattern has emerged recently giving hope for more rain in the near future which would alleviate some of their water concerns on the island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Insignificant rains and warm temperatures once again plagued the western Corn Belt. Winter wheat, alfalfa and pastures are all feeling the effects of this drought. According to Nebraska's Ag Statistics figures this week, statewide soil moisture values in Nebraska show 70% of the topsoil rated as short/very short and subsoil readings are showing 80% as short/very short. Extreme drought (D3) would appear to be on the doorstep in parts of eastern Nebraska and western Iowa unless favorable weather arrives soon.</p>
   <p>The eastern half of the Corn Belt (from eastern Iowa over to western Ohio) saw a very warm week as well, but they had some beneficial rains (but not overly plentiful) across the northern reaches of Illinois and Indiana. These rains, however, haven't really put a dent into the 9-month deficits that have accrued since last fall. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions have now spread to encompass the Upper Peninsula of Michigan. Surface and ground water levels continue to fall and reach record or near-record lows in many parts of the region. As such, the core region of severe drought (D2) found in the Midwest continues to be a persistent feature that doesn't look to go away anytime soon.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>As expected, most locales here experienced a very warm and dry week leading to the expansion of drought conditions in the Southeast. Evapotranspiration totals are already reaching impressive numbers for this time of year. In response to this continuing pattern, the areas of first stage (D1) and severe drought (D2) have expanded across all of the Gulf Coast region. Severe drought (D2) conditions have now pressed across the Savannah River from Georgia into parts of South Carolina. Rainfall deficits this year are already running close to 10 inches in Atlanta and over 6 inches around Augusta, GA.</p>
   <p>In addition, the extreme drought (D3) area of Louisiana has now expanded eastward to include the southern coastal areas of Mississippi, Alabama, the Florida Panhandle and southwest Georgia. Many locales within this region are running precipitation deficits of around 10 inches this year alone. This doesn't take into account the dryness some of these areas have seen going back 12 or more months. Impacts are being seen in almost all sectors at this time with the heat of summer still on the horizon. Of note recently has been the outbreak of wildfires in Florida and other states in the Southeast.</p>
   <p>After a wet week last week, most of abnormally dry (D0) eastern Texas missed out on moisture this week but continued to see well above normal temperatures. A rapid depletion of topsoil moisture will continue and could easily lead to this area falling back into first stage drought (D1) conditions in the coming weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Western States">
   <p>Hot, dry and windy weather continued for the most part last week across many parts of the Desert Southwest. Areas of first stage (D1) and severe (D2) drought advanced into northern and western New Mexico and into eastern Arizona. The most obvious and immediate threat is found in the form of extreme fire potential that exists across both states. Lack of moisture the past two winter seasons in these two states has really led to some favorable fuel conditions. In addition, severe drought (D1) is now being seen in a small portion of west cental Montana in an area bounded roughly by Bozeman, Lewistown, Great Falls, Helena and Butte.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
