<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060706</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Current and forecast weather that may have an impact on dry or drought areas in the next 2 weeks include: 1) heavy rains over Louisiana and Florida during July 5-10, as well as New Mexico, Colorado, and parts of Oklahoma, Kansas, and Missouri; 2) a tilt toward above-normal rainfall for the South during July 11-15, accompanied by below-normal temperatures; 3) above-normal warmth across the northern Plains and Upper Mississippi Valley for the next 2 weeks, but a tilt toward above-normal rainfall in Minnesota and eastern North Dakota during days 6-10.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Gulf Coast and South">
   <p>Heavy rains exceeding 3 inches for the week eased lingering dryness along the Texas coast as well as the southwest coast of Florida. Dry weather across most of Mississippi and Alabama caused northward expansion of D1 in both states. In Alabama, 63 percent of the corn was in very poor or poor condition. D2 drought edged eastward in Floridas Panhandle.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Outlying Areas">
   <p>D0 conditions abated from Homer, Anchorage, and Talkeetna westward in south-central Alaska. Many locations in this region recorded 0.5 to locally 1.5 inches of precipitation last week, and both 30-day and 90-day precipitation totals are now near normal. In addition, 1 to locally 4 inches of precipitation during the last two weeks ended abnormal dryness in east-central Alaska. Meanwhile, only a few tenths of an inch of rain at best fell on southeastern Alaska, keeping D0 conditions intact from near Fairbanks southward and southeastward, where fire weather indices ranged from high to extreme by July 4. Farther north, similar surface moisture shortages and enhanced fire danger have been noted across part of interior northeastern Alaska, where D0 conditions were introduced this week. There was no change in the depiction for Hawaii, where leeward areas of the northern islands remained abnormally dry.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>The beginning of the weekly valid period included the last stages of the deluge that brought flooding to the mid-Atlantic and northeastern states. To the south, the recent rains failed to erase long-term deficits, and D1H drought persisted from northwestern South Carolina into western North Carolina. Streamflows and some reservoirs remained below normal in this area.  D1 drought continued across much of Georgia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Little rain over the Dakotas resulted in expansion of D1 drought northward into much of North Dakota and expansion of D2 drought into southern North Dakota. Topsoil moisture rated 31 percent very short in North Dakota, according to the latest report from USDA. In South Dakota, the area of D3 and D2 expanded slightly, while D0 dryness extended farther southward in Minnesota and Wisconsin. D1 drought developed across northwestern Wisconsin where 30-day rainfall has been less than one-half of normal. D1 drought also developed in northwestern Minnesota and adjacent northeastern North Dakota. Farther south, welcomed rains eased drought in eastern Colorado, shrinking parts of the D3 areas there, but D3 drought expanded slightly westward in northern Colorado. Denver has recorded its driest start to the year on record, measuring just 2.72 inches of precipitation from January through June. This is one-third of normal. With dry weather continuing, part of northeast Texas, including the Dallas-Fort Worth area, saw D2 drought degrade to D3. Precipitation since last October has been as little as 50 percent of normal. In contrast, up to 3 inches of rain reduced the D4 in south Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West">
   <p>An early start to the monsoon eased wildfire danger across the Southwest. Rainfall totals exceeding 1 inch resulted in some retreat of the drought areas in Arizona. Relief was less substantial in New Mexico, where there was little change in the overall drought picture. Persistent dryness led to D1 intensifying to D2 in south-central Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Heddinghaus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
