<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070816</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather that could have an impact on drought areas in the next two weeks: 1) Tropical Storm Erin will make landfall along the lower Texas coast on August 16.  Rainfall associated with Erin will not directly affect any U.S. drought areas, although the storm's remnant moisture may be drawn into a ring of showers encircling a large ridge of high pressure parked over the Southeast; 2) however, hot, mostly dry weather will persist for at least the next week in the Southeast; 3) monsoon moisture will continue to move northeastward from the Four Corners States and interact with a series of cold fronts crossing the northern Plains and the Midwest; 4) the fronts will contribute to locally heavy showers in the upper Midwestern and Great Lakes States; 5) the NWS 8- to 14-day outlook for August 23-29 calls for a return to cool weather across the central one-third of the U.S., while hot weather will persist in the East and Far West.  Meanwhile, above-normal rainfall across much of the southern half of the U.S. will contrast with drier-than-normal weather across the North.  Elsewhere, Hurricane Dean, currently located east of the Lesser Antilles, will soon enter the Caribbean Sea and may threaten the U.S. Gulf Coast sometime next week.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Conditions in Alaska and Puerto Rico did not warrant changes to the depiction of abnormal dryness (D0).  Currently, dryness covers less than 30 percent of Alaska and about 10 percent of Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Rapidly weakening Hurricane Flossie passed less than 100 miles south of the southern tip of the Big Island on August 14.  However, effects on Hawaii's areas of dryness (D0) and drought (D1 and D2) were rather limited.  On the Big Island, 24-hour rainfall totals for the period ending the morning of August 15 totaled no more than 1 to 2 inches at most reporting stations.  Elsewhere, most leeward locations remained especially dry; through August 14, year-to-date rainfall totaled 2.73 inches (27 percent of normal) in Honolulu, Oahu, and 4.08 inches (34 percent) in Kahului, Maui.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>An historic heat wave arrived across the Southeast in early August, following relatively cool, favorably showery weather in July.  Frequent temperatures near 100 degrees F were noted as far north as the southern Corn Belt, while impressive strings of triple-digit heat were reported farther south.  As a result of the intense heat and minimal rainfall, along with severe stress on pastures, livestock, and immature summer crops, all categories of dryness and drought were broadly expanded across the Southeast and the lower Midwest.  For example, two areas of exceptional drought were joined, leaving a continuous swath of D4 stretching from Tennessee through Alabama and western Georgia.</p>
   <p>Montgomery, Alabama, reached or exceeded the 100-degree mark on at least 10 consecutive days (August 6-15), easily surpassing its record of 7 days established in 1881, 1954, and 1990.  Farther west, Evansville, Indiana (100, 102, and 100 degrees F from August 7-9) achieved triple-digit heat for the first time since August 18, 1995.  Other locations reporting their first 100-degree reading of the decade included Roanoke, Virginia, Paducah, Kentucky, and Cincinnati, Ohio (all three cities reached 100 degrees F on August 8).  Roanoke, Paducah, and Cincinnati all last observed a high of 100 degrees F or greater in 1999.  Even the overnight hours provided little heat relief, as locations such as Roanoke (79 degrees F on August 9); Atlanta (82 degrees F on August 8); and Wilmington, North Carolina (83 degrees F on August 9), set all-time records for their highest minimum temperature.</p>
   <p>However, some of the most impressive heat-related records were the all-time-record highs established across the Southeast.  Greenville-Spartanburg, South Carolina, tied its all-time-record high of 104 degrees F on August 8 and 9, then erased that standard with a high of 105 degrees F on August 10. Elsewhere in South Carolina, Columbia reached 105 degrees F on August 8, representing its highest reading since July 10, 1990 (also 105 degrees F).  Later, however, Columbia attained 106 degrees F on August 9 and 107 degrees F on August 10.  Columbia's August 10 reading tied its all-time high of 107 degrees F, previously achieved on August 21, 1983, June 27, 1954, and July 23, 24, and 29, 1952.  Meanwhile, Augusta, Georgia (108 degree F on August 10), also tied its all-time record, previously set on August 21, 1983.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>In contrast, an impressive band of 2- to 4-inch rainfall totals, with locally higher amounts, fell in the Midwest, especially from eastern Nebraska to Lake Erie.  In fact, drought was nearly cut in two across the Midwest, with a lingering area of moderate drought (D1) arcing across the region at the Indiana-Ohio-Michigan triple point.  However, parts of the upper Midwest and the upper Great Lakes region continued to miss out on the rainfall.  As a result, extreme drought (D3) was introduced in parts of central Minnesota and expanded in the upper Great Lakes region.  In Michigan's upper peninsula, May to July was the driest such period on record in Newberry (4.49 inches, or just shy of 50 percent of normal) and Ontonagon (5.10 inches, or 52 percent).  From June 1, 2006, to July 31, 2007, Ontonagon's precipitation of 29.54 inches was just 73 percent of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Favorably cooler weather overspread the West in early August, while monsoon showers continued from the Four Corners States northeastward into parts of Wyoming.  Despite the spell of cool weather, wildfires remained active and difficult to contain across the northern Rockies and northern Intermountain West.  By August 15, year-to-date wildfires across the U.S. had charred 6.0 million acres of vegetation, 134 percent of the 10-year average.  Many of the currently uncontained wildfires were located in western Montana and central Idaho.  In the latter region, severe drought (D2) was downgraded to extreme drought (D3), due to a variety of impacts.  In contrast, showers continued to chip away at dryness and drought across southeastern Arizona and neighboring areas.  Despite the summer showers, many Western reservoirs remained unusually low, signaling ongoing hydrological drought.  At the end of July, reservoir storage stood at 82 percent of average for this time of year in Arizona.  Storage ranged from roughly two-thirds to three-quarters of average in several other Western states, including Idaho, Oregon, Utah, and Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
