<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080320</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (through March 24), the forecast calls for good rains in the southern Plains and across the Southeast and Mid-Atlantic regions. Some of the better totals are expected to fall within some of the core D3-D4 drought areas in the Southeast as well as the D1-D3 core in southern Florida. As for temperatures, they are expected to be 3 to 6 degrees Fahrenheit below normal for the entire eastern two-thirds of the United States. The exception can be found in the extreme southern tip of Florida, where they are looking at normal, seasonal-type temperatures. It's looking to warm up in the west. Specifically, the Southwest is looking at 3 to 6 degree Fahrenheit departures on the warm side during this time frame.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6 to 10 day outlook for March 25-29 shows that cooler temperatures are likely in Alaska and for the entire eastern half of the United States (east of the Mississippi River). Above-normal temperatures are expected in the Desert Southwest, the Intermountain West, and southern California. As for precipitation, below-normal totals are likely across Alaska, the Desert Southwest, southern Rockies, southern Plains, and southern Florida.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>A relatively quiet week weatherwise across Hawaii results in no changes to the Abnormally Dry conditions (D0) found there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>A break in the dry pattern occurred early this week as heavy late-period rains (2-4 inches) fell across west-central Texas and up into Oklahoma, bringing widespread relief and a general one-category improvement along the western and northern edges of last week's D2 core in west-central Texas. To the west of San Angelo and Del Rio, however, the rains failed to materialize, and D1 has advanced across all of western Texas and D0 now covers the entire Texas Panhandle. Drought has also pushed east across all counties within the OK Panhandle. In addition, above-normal temperatures returned in earnest to the region after a brief hiatus. This, coupled with the dryness in west Texas, has again raised grass fire fears.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeastern and Mid-Atlantic States">
   <p>Slow but steady erosion of the D4 core continued last week following back-to-back weeks of good rains (1 to 3 inches) in and around the Cumberland Plateau of Tennessee and across northern Georgia and the western Carolinas. In fact, the D4 has been removed from Georgia as a result. This is the first time Georgia has been D4-free since July of last year. The return of moisture and warmth led to some severe weather across the region, signaling that the high demand season is just around the corner. The rest of the region remains in a holding pattern this week, with no changes to the drought depiction as widespread long-term (since October 1) deficits (10-20 inches/50-75% of normal) are still entrenched across the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The recent warmth and dryness has led to the introduction of D1 in southeastern New Mexico. Elsewhere in the West, status quo is the story as a drier March-to-date (for the Southwest, Great Basin, and Intermountain West) is being aided by a cooler March in the upper elevation thus far, preserving the good early pack. However, recent warmth has started to erode the lower level snows. The cooler temperatures have helped to temper flood fears thus far.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
