<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20140522</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>This US Drought Monitor week was dominated by a weather system that moved across the Southern Plains and Midwest and through the South and Mid-Atlantic.  The system brought damaging wind and hail throughout the impacted area and tornadoes in the Southeast and Mid-Atlantic.  Widespread areas of three to four inches of precipitation fell while areas of eastern Texas received over seven  inches.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the May 21-26, 2014 time period, precipitation is expected across the Plains, from South Dakota to northern Texas, and into eastern Colorado and Wyoming.  Additional precipitation is expected around the Great Lakes and into the Mid-Atlantic and Northeast.  Precipitation is estimated to approach two inches in select locations during this time period.  At the same time, below normal temperatures are expected in the Southwest, east of the Rockies and into the Southern Plains.  Above normal temperatures are expected along the West Coast, through the Central US, and into the Southeast.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (May 27-31, 2014), the odds favor normal to above-normal temperatures across the entire contiguous US and southern Alaska, with the exception of the western Gulf Coast.  Below-normal temperatures are favored in northern Alaska and along the aforementioned area around the Gulf of Mexico.  Above-normal precipitation is likely across the Eastern half of the US and in the far Northern Plains and northern Alaska.  Below-normal precipitation is expected in the Southern Plains, the Pacific Northwest, as well as in southern Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>A lack of trade winds has kept windward sections of the Big Island of Hawaii drier than normal.  The existing area of Abnormal Dryness (D0) expanded eastward on the island and a new area of Abnormal Dryness (D0) was added near Hilo because of those rainfall deficits.  No changes were made in Puerto Rico or Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Areas of Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormal Dryness (D0) continue to impact the Midwest.  No changes were made to the area this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>A strong system moved through the area on the 15th and following, dumping rain as it went.  Locally heavy rain exceeded four inches in locations throughout western Maryland, West Virginia, and Virginia.  This greatly decreased the area of Abnormal Dryness (D0) along the Appalachian Mountains in that area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Locally heavy rain came to the South early in the Drought Monitor week.  Areas of Texas, Louisiana and Arkansas benefitted.  Areas of Abnormal Dryness (D0) were removed from southern and eastern Texas, northern Louisiana into southern Arkansas, and northern Arkansas into southern Missouri.  Mounting deficits saw degradation of drought conditions in western and central Texas.  Areas of Exceptional Drought (D4) expanded in central Texas where lake and stream levels are exceptionally low, water supplies are dwindling, and water restrictions are the norm. With some places going months without appreciable precipitation, degradation was in line in most locations in Oklahoma, with the exception of the extreme southeast part of the state.  Areas of Exceptional (D4), Extreme (D3), Severe (D2), and Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormal Dryness (D0) expanded eastward this week in Oklahoma.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Conditions remain very dry across the West as much of the West moves into its dry season.  Areas of Extreme Drought (D3) expanded in western and eastern New Mexico, as did Exceptional Drought (D4) in eastern New Mexico as precipitation deficits mount. The state overall experienced its seventh driest Year-to-Date (January to April) and 12th driest Water Year (October 2013 – April 2014) on record.  The rest of the West remained unchanged.</p>
   <p>Wildfires remain a problem in parts of the West.  According to the US Forest Service, the current large incidents are all in California, Arizona, and New Mexico.  The fires around San Diego, CA resulted in at least one death, approximately 125,000 evacuees, and millions of dollars in property damage.  So far this year nationwide, there have been 22,863 fires that have burned 471,875 acres which is below the 10-year average (2004 – 2014 average, year to date,  is 27,895 fires and 1,053,217 acres according to the National Interagency Fire Center).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
