<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020228</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through March 9 that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) very cold air following a cold front pushing through Florida and off the East Coast February 27 will bring freezing temperatures to many parts of the South February 26-28; 2) cold conditions will remain across the northern and eastern United States through the period; 3) a storm system developing in the middle of the country will bring snow to the lower Great Lakes and widespread rain to much of the East Coast March 1-3; and 4) relatively quiet conditions will persist in the West, with a return to a more active weather pattern by the end of the 10-day period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, long-term moderate drought (D1) conditions still exist on western Molokai, causing some hydrological impacts. The southern Puerto Rico coastline, meanwhile, continues to experience abnormal dryness (D0). However, San Juan, Puerto Rico, located on the northern coast, has had above-normal precipitation since December 1 (+6.42 inches).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Following another generally dry week with above-normal temperatures, drought and abnormally dry conditions continue to gain attention along the East Coast. Severe drought (D2) was expanded to include all of eastern Massachusetts and Rhode Island, including the Boston and Providence areas. Precipitation departures from normal in the mid-Atlantic states for the 90-day period since late November range between -4.0 and -6.0 inches, and the area of extreme drought (D3) was extended into northern Virginia to accommodate deteriorating drought conditions there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>A snowstorm in the Midwest February 19-20 helped improve dryness (D0) in eastern Minnesota. Otherwise, the dry and drought areas of the Midwest and Plains received little precipitation during the past week. As a result, parts of Iowa, South Dakota, Nebraska, and southern Texas were included in the D0 areas, while moderate drought (D1) conditions have developed in the western Sand Hills region in Nebraska. In spite of the dry week, drought conditions in the extreme drought (D3) area in western Texas have improved in recent weeks, and the northern edge of this area was improved to the D2 (severe drought) classification.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Continuing dryness caused deteriorating drought conditions across many parts of the Southeast during the past week. As a result, the area of extreme drought (D3) expanded in northern South Carolina and into southern and southeastern North Carolina. Areas of severe drought (D2) increased in North Carolina, South Carolina, and southern Georgia. The area of abnormally dry conditions (D0), resulting from much below normal winter season precipitation, was increased to include northwestern Georgia, eastern Tennessee, and eastern Kentucky. Concerns about wildfire danger and agricultural impacts, in addition to the long-term hydrological impacts, are increasing rapidly across the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Ski resorts in Colorado and Utah received several rounds of welcomed snow during the past week, and snowpacks across much of the West increased slightly, compared to normal. The dryness continued in the Southwest, however, and snowpacks did decrease significantly with warmer weather in Arizona. The continued dryness in southern Arizona has caused D0 (abnormally dry) conditions to push to the Mexican border and include the Nogales, Tucson, and Sierra Vista areas, with the major concern involving the threat of wildfires. Conditions have also deteriorated in eastern Wyoming, and severe drought (D2) expanded into this region. Wyoming officials imposed water restrictions this week along the North Platte River in the southeastern part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
