<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20091217</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Early in the Drought Monitor period, beneficial precipitation again fell on Texas, helping to ease drought conditions there.  The same storm produced precipitation all along the East Coast and was followed by a second storm dropping precipitation along a similar path.  Late this period, a storm brought beneficial rain and snow to areas of drought-stricken California and western Nevada.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Warmer than normal temperatures through much of the central part of the country early in the December 17 – December 21, 2009 period will give way to below normal temperatures from the Plains to the East Coast later in the period.  Near-normal temperatures are expected to dominate the western US.  Precipitation is expected along the northern West Coast, along the Gulf of Mexico coast, and from the northern Midwest to the East Coast.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (December 22 – 26, 2009), the odds favor cooler-than-normal conditions over most of the eastern US and across the states bordering the Gulf of Mexico up into the Midwest.  The West, mostly from the Rockies westward and particularly in the extreme Southwest, is likely to see normal to above normal temperatures.  Normal to below normal precipitation is expected from the Midwest through the Ohio Valley and into the Southeast.  Above normal precipitation is expected in the Northwest, the Northeast, and along the western Gulf Coast.  Odds favor near-normal temperatures and above normal precipitation for much of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought conditions remained unchanged across the Hawaiian Islands and in Puerto Rico this week.  In Alaska, the abnormal dryness expanded into the central part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Two storms affected the East Coast again this week.  They eliminated areas of abnormal dryness (D0) from northern Florida and the southwest Pennsylvania - West Virginia area.  Lingering eastern drought and dryness is limited to south Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Most of the drought-affected areas of the region saw little to no precipitation this week.  Continued long-term deficits resulted in unchanged drought classification in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Mississippi River Delta">
   <p>In Texas, the impact of recent beneficial precipitation continues.  Areas of extreme drought (D3) were removed from the southern part of the state as shorter-term wetness has mitigated many of the negative impacts of the long-term drought.  Areas of severe (D2) and moderate (D1) drought and abnormal dryness (D0) were also reduced near the Gulf Coast.  In western Texas, moderate drought (D1) was reduced while abnormal dryness (D0) near the Mexico border expanded.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A series of storms this Drought Monitor period brought rain and snow to many areas in the West, particularly the Sierras and the Rockies.  Precipitation along the southern coast of California led to reduction in moderated drought (D1) from Monterey down to Los Angeles.  This storm also reduced severe drought (D2) in interior southern California.  Conversely, the area of severe drought (D2) in northern California and northwest Nevada increased as did the abnormal dryness along the northwest California and southwest Oregon coast, as this area largely missed the beneficial precipitation.  Southern Nevada saw improvement in severe drought (D2) as did western Arizona.  Extreme drought (D3) was also reduced slightly in central Arizona.   Small expansions of abnormal dryness (D0) expanded in the north-central mountains of Colorado and in southern and western Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
