<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070111</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The next 5 days (January 11-15) show a developing arctic outbreak with a large gradient of temperatures across the United States as the first big push of arctic air funnels south.  Temperatures are expected to be 10-20F below normal over the western two-thirds of the country and 5-15F above normal in front of the cold air.  Precipitation is also expected to fire up along the frontal boundary, with the greatest amounts positioned to be centered over Arkansas with lesser amounts in the Rocky Mountains and in the southwest.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (January 16-20), a large trough and cold air are expected to dominate the weather pattern, with the trough centered over the Great Lakes.  Below-normal temperatures will cover much of the continental United States while Alaska will be above normal.  Precipitation is expected to be above normal east of the Rocky Mountains and onto the Plains, along the Gulf Coast and up the Atlantic Coast.  Below-normal precipitation is likely over the Pacific Northwest and California and in the upper Midwest and Great Lakes regions.  Alaska should continue to see above-normal precipitation as well, especially along the coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>D0 conditions were improved along the Alaskan coast because of recent precipitation, while D0 was expanded over most of the Hawaiian Islands because of recent dryness in the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>With small amounts of precipitation recorded this week, the drought designation remained unchanged for almost the entire region.  In South Dakota, the D1 designation in the north-central part of the state was shifted to the east.  This region was hard hit last summer and is slow in recovering.  There was also a slight expansion of the D0 in Kentucky this week in response to the short-term dryness in the region, where only 50-75 percent of normal precipitation has been observed.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Appalachians">
   <p>Heavy rains over northeast and east Texas and into Arkansas allowed for the improvement of the region.  D3 conditions were removed in northeast Texas as other drought categories were improved.  Over the past week, 1.5 to 2 inches of rain fell over much of northeast Texas.  This precipitation along with the recent wet pattern has allowed for conditions to improve.  The D0 in Arkansas was reduced greatly and removed completely along the Gulf Coast from Louisiana to the Florida panhandle.  The recent precipitation has improved conditions even though long-term deficits exist.  In Georgia and Florida, the D1 area was reduced in size in response to the recent heavy rains in the area.  D1 was expanded in Florida to the Gulf Coast, coinciding with the announcement of water restrictions in the area.</p>
   <p>D0 conditions in Pennsylvania and into West Virginia were reduced.  This area continues to be on the fringe of short-term dryness, and improvements were warranted this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Rocky Mountains">
   <p>Heavy rain in the Pacific Northwest was the main feature in the region this week.  Some snow in the central to northern Rocky Mountains has helped to improve snowpack conditions for the region.  In Wyoming, drought categories were expanded because of low snow totals so far this year as well as reservoir and water supply concerns.  D3 was expanded in central Wyoming and D2 was expanded to the northwest into Montana. The D1 region in southern Colorado was removed as precipitation deficits have improved and current snowpack is above average.</p>
   <p>In Arizona, D0 was improved in north-central Arizona, while D2 was expanded from southwest Arizona to the north and west to include southern Nevada and extreme southeast California.  Winter precipitation is crucial in the expanded D2 region, and the water year has started off very badly in this region.</p>
   <p>D0 was expanded along the California and Nevada border and along the coast of California.  Some agricultural impacts on grazing lands have been reported in California, as pastures have not provided adequate forage for many producers in the region.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
