<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030529</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Several storm systems will bring locally heavy rainfall to the East Coast May 29 through June 2. Heavy precipitation is also expected during this period in the Great Lakes region into the Middle to Lower Mississippi Valley. Colorado in particular can expect to see some relief as several storm systems move through the state. The central Great Plains is expected to receive light to moderate precipitation with most of the West Coast remaining dry. Above normal temperatures are expected from the West Coast inland over the majority of the country with cooler than normal temperatures in the Northeast.</p>
   <p>The ensuing 5 days (June 3 - 7) will continue to bring heavy rainfall to much of the East Coast, especially the Northeast, with cooler than normal temperatures as well. The central Great Plains can expect to see above normal precipitation with average to below normal temperatures. The West Coast inland to the Rocky Mountains will have below normal precipitation with above normal temperatures.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico, Hawaii, and Alaska">
   <p>Several stations along the southern coast of Puerto Rico received light precipitation (a fourth of an inch to an inch) while most others received several inches of rain. A drying trend in 4-week totals was observed at a few stations, but streamflows were near to above average across the island, so no drought is depicted. In Hawaii, 2 to 3 inches of rain fell at a few stations on the Big Island early in the week, with half an inch falling at a few other stations later in the week. But most stations reported little or no rainfall, with streamflow gauges averaging below normal for the week, supporting the maintenance of the D0 to D1 depiction in Hawaii. Alaska SNOTEL stations reported above average melting of snowpack in most basins during the week, due to above average temperatures. Precipitation reports were mixed, with many below-normal reports. A sliver of D0 was extended into southeastern Alaska to correspond with enhanced fire weather vulnerability, otherwise there was no change to the drought depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes and Northeast">
   <p>Locally heavy rains, up to 1 to 3 inches, from low pressure and frontal bands brought improving conditions to the drought areas in the central and eastern Great Lakes. The D0H over Lower Michigan and D1 along Lake Erie were eliminated and the Lake Erie D0AH was changed to D0H and contracted. Heavy rain at the end of the period broke a drying trend that had been developing along New Jersey to southern New England. Light precipitation prevailed elsewhere, keeping the Maine and northern Minnesota drought areas intact.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The northern and central Plains">
   <p>The nose of D2 in central Nebraska was shaved back beneath a band of 1 to 2 inch rains. Light to moderate rains fell over the drought areas from southeast Nebraska to northwest Missouri, but not enough to warrant improving the drought depiction there. In eastern Nebraska, even with decent rains less than 48 hours prior, farmers preparing fields for soybeans were raising dust behind their tractors. Light to no precipitation fell across the drought areas elsewhere in the region. D0 was expanded slightly in southeast South Dakota in an area of persistent (30 to 90 day) dryness. Otherwise, the coverage and severity of D0H to D3H conditions were unchanged relative to last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and interior West">
   <p>Widely scattered showers and thunderstorms occurred along the Rockies from northern Idaho to New Mexico, but rainfall amounts were mostly half an inch or less. Little or no precipitation fell elsewhere. Warm to extremely high temperatures brought rapidly melting snowpack and above-normal flow to many western streams by the end of the week. Except for the Sierra Nevada and some basins in the Pacific Northwest, mountain snowpack was below seasonal norms with only stations above 10 thousand feet having any snow left. Fire vulnerability indicators remained high from the Desert Southwest to parts of the northern Rockies, and reservoir levels continued below average in many states. D1 was pulled back in southeast Wyoming due to three consecutive days of afternoon thunderstorms which improved soil moisture conditions and contributed to flooding along the Laramie River. Otherwise, the drought depiction for the West was largely unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>Showers and thunderstorms brought locally heavy rain to parts of south central Oklahoma and north central to western Texas and adjoining areas of New Mexico, as well as much of the Southeast from the southeast tip of Mississippi to Florida and the Carolinas. Precipitation amounts of 3 inches or more along the Red River in south central Oklahoma and adjoining Texas, and 1 to 2 inches toward west central Texas, resulted in the pullback of D1 and the H-AH boundary toward the Caprock (east of an Amarillo to Lubbock line), and the shaving of D2 in west central and north central Texas. Hydrological conditions remained severe in southwest Oklahoma, where reservoir storage was near 50% below conservation capacity at two small lakes and farm ponds were in very bad shape. A second week of 1 to 3 inch rains in northwest Florida significantly improved conditions, lifting the state Keetch Byram Drought Index in the area to near-normal values and resulting in the elimination of the D0A. However, southeast and south central Texas missed out on the beneficial rains. The Twin Buttes and OC Fisher reservoirs that supply the San Angelo area had a combined storage of 9 thousand acre feet as of late April, compared to a conservation storage capacity of 297 thousand acre feet. The Crop Moisture Index and satellite Vegetation Health Index showed deteriorating conditions from southern Texas to Arizona over the last several weeks. According to May 25 USDA reports, 70% of New Mexico pastures and rangelands were described in "poor" or "very poor" condition, as were 53% of ranges and pastures in Arizona and 42% in Texas, an increase of 2 to 4 percent from last week. As a result, the central Texas D2 snaked westward toward Del Rio and San Angelo, avoiding pockets of moderate rainfall in the area, to reflect the persistent dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
