<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041111</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (November 11-15), weather that may affect areas with dryness or drought include: 1) a cold front and associated low pressure center will track across the eastern half of the Nation early in the period, but at best, only light precipitation should fall on the Great Lakes region, with dry weather and moderating temperatures by the weekend; 2) two upper-air Pacific lows should affect the Southwest: early in the period, a low should track across the Sierra Nevada and northern Great Basin and weaken; by the weekend, a second low should move into southern California and trek east, providing additional precipitation to the Southwest; 3) the Northwest and northern halves of the Rockies and Plains are expected to be mostly dry and mild; 4) significant precipitation should fall along the southeastern Alaskan Panhandle, with more snow for interior and eastern Alaska; 5) Hawaiian trade winds returning, producing scattered showers on the windward portions of Maui and the Big Island.</p>
   <p>The 6- to 10-day outlook (November 16-20) calls for: 1) above-normal precipitation in California, from the southern Rockies northeastward to the upper Midwest and all points east (except New England), and along the southern and southeastern Alaskan Coast; 2) below-normal precipitation in the Pacific Northwest, northern Rockies and Plains, and New England; 3) colder-than-normal conditions are forecast for the Far West and Southwest, with unseasonably mild weather in the northern Plains, Midwest, Great Lakes region, western New England, and southern and eastern Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>In Hawaii, a very dry October across the western and northern parts of Maui (Kahului 0%, Lahainaluna 28%, Kula Branch 29%, Pukalani 37%, Waikapu CC 39%, Haiku 40%, Mahinahina 67%) was somewhat tempered by scattered light to moderate showers (0.5 to 2 inches) during November 5-7, but it was not enough to erase accumulated 45-day deficits, maintaining the D0(A). On the Big Island (Kona), near- to above-normal (98-147%) October rains in southeastern Kona (at Hilo, Piihonau, Mountain View, Waiakea Uka, Pahoa), plus relatively quiet November weather, failed to remove 3-month rainfall deficiencies on the windward (east) side, keeping eastern Kona status-quo (D0). An exception was near Pali 2 (southern Kona) where 7.5 inches of rain during October (nearly 300%) alleviated abnormal dryness.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, frigid Arctic air enveloped much of the State, with temperatures as much as 18 oF below normal in interior Alaska, lows dropping to -35F at Bettles, and significant precipitation (1 to 4.5 inches) confined mainly along the southern and southeastern sections. In the southeastern Panhandle, autumn precipitation (since Sep. 1) has been close to normal; however, with summer (June-August) rainfall only about half of normal, large deficits since June 1 remained (up to a foot at Yakutat and Petersburg). Farther north, although observed and satellite-derived data indicated a good start to the cold season snow cover (during October) across northern and eastern Alaska, the extremely dry and warm summer (with record wildfire acreage burned) required a decent snow pack by this spring to offset the warm seasons drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Great Plains">
   <p>Early in the period, a series of slow-moving systems brought widespread precipitation (0.5 to 2 inches, locally up to 4 inches in the Southeast) to the south-central Plains and central Corn Belt eastward to the Atlantic Coast, including unseasonably heavy snow (up to 9 inches) to the Texas Panhandle. Unfortunately, most of the significant precipitation fell on non-drought areas, except in east-central Kansas (0.8-1.2 inches), southeastern Missouri (0.5-0.8 inches), and southeastern Michigan (0.6-1.4 inches) where abnormal dryness was alleviated. In contrast, another dry week, temperatures averaging 4 to 8F above normal, and 7-day average USGS stream flows (ending Nov. 8) in the lower 25 th percentile expanded D0(A) into north-central Kansas, eastern Nebraska, and southwestern Iowa. The rest of the Midwest and Plains observed tranquil and mild weather after a couple of wet weeks, maintaining conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies">
   <p>A trough of low pressure anchored over the West kept the storm track (and significant precipitation) in the Pacific Northwest, along the Pacific Coast, and in the Southwest. Although most of the Rockies recorded little or no precipitation this period, the previous 2 weeks brought surplus precipitation, including high-elevation snows, thus maintaining status-quo. Even with this weeks tranquil weather, the NRCS SNOTEL sites basin average precipitation (since October 1) remained above-normal in the north-central, central, and southern Rockies. A slower start in the northern Rockies (Bitterroot Range) and parts of Montana and New Mexico has dropped only 65-90% of average basin precipitation. A mostly good start to the 2004-05 wet season in the West was encouraging, but with several years of drought creating well-below normal reservoir storage capacities in the Rocky Mountain States, continued stormy weather will be needed to ensure above-normal snow pack and spring runoff.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southwest, Great Basin, and California">
   <p>Another in a series of upper-air lows dropped southward along the Pacific Coast and into the desert Southwest and southern Great Basin, bringing additional unseasonably heavy precipitation (more than 0.5 inches) to coastal and far western California, eastern Arizona, southern Nevada, and southern Utah. The greatest totals fell during November 7-9, with 1 to 3 inches measured in semi-arid areas of western Arizona, extreme southern Nevada, and southwestern Utah. Since the Western storms started on October 17, 23-day amounts exceeding 4 inches were common along coastal California (up to a foot), in the Sierra Nevada (8 to 12 inches), central and northwestern Arizona (6 to 10 inches), southern and eastern Nevada (2 to 6 inches, locally 16 inches at Mt. Charleston), and southern and northern Utah (10-14 inches at higher elevations). According to NRCS SNOTEL sites, basin average precipitation since October 1 in the Southwest is running an encouraging 150 to 250% of normal (up to 485% in southwestern Utah), but it is still very early in the wet season.</p>
   <p>The early wet season precipitation has eased dryness and drought in California the most where long-term drought was not as severe as the remainder of the West, and reservoir levels were close to normal; however, the record-setting late October and early November precipitation in parts of the Southwest has somewhat dented the drought (soil moisture-wise) in semi-arid regions of western Arizona, extreme southern Nevada, and southern Utah, where a one-category improvement was made to areas with the greatest 23-day precipitation as compared to lowest cold season (October-March) normals. For example, October-March normal precipitation ranges between 3 (Las Vegas, NV) and 9 (Grand Canyon and Prescott, AZ) inches; this area generally received between 3 and 10 inches since October 17, or approximately one cold seasons worth of precipitation in 3 weeks. It should be noted, however, that the November 1 state-wide reservoir capacities in these Southwestern States (except California) were still well-below normal, with long-term hydrological drought still intact. The recent precipitation has greatly boosted topsoil moisture and range/pasture conditions, but exceptional future wet season(s) and mountain snow pack(s) are still required to gradually fill the reservoirs and erase long-term drought.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
