<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20090806</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (August 6-10), some relief should come to the Pacific Northwest in the form of below-normal temperatures. The cooler weather is also expected across most of the West. A strong ridge will build into the Plains and bring above-normal temperatures with it. The warmer-than-normal readings are also expected in the Midwest and Mid-Atlantic. The best bet for beneficial rains will be confined to the northern tier states from Montana to the east across the northern Plains, upper Midwest and Mid-Atlantic.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day forecast (August 11 – August 15) calls for a greater likelihood of below-normal temperatures in the Pacific Northwest and the southeastern island chains in Alaska. The real story is seen in the ridging in the country’s mid-section, where temperatures are expected to be well above normal for this period across the Plains, Midwest, Southeast and Mid-Atlantic. Precipitation is likely to be below normal across the same areas seeing above-normal temperatures, so this isn’t a good combination. Above-normal precipitation is likely for the Pacific Northwest and the Gulf Coast states.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Alaska saw another good week of rains, and streamflows have responded as well, leading to a reduction of D0 in the southwestern Aleutian chain. The D0/D1 found in the southeast remains unchanged, though.</p>
   <p>The past few weeks have brought more favorable trade wind rains across the eastern sides of the islands in Hawaii and improvement is noted in the removal of D1 across eastern Kauai, eastern Maui and the eastern side of the Big Island. This also led to the removal of D0 across the far eastern region of the Big Island.</p>
   <p>Puerto Rico remains unchanged and drought free this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Relatively seasonal weather, both in terms of temperatures and rainfall, results in very little change this week across most of the region for the second consecutive week. Exceptions are noted in Alabama where heavy rains (3-5 inches) fell in the southwest and east-central regions of the state, which led to the removal of some D0 in these parts. The rains didn’t come to west-central Georgia and seasonal and yearly deficits are slowly climbing again. D0 has expanded in this area. Rains in the northern part of the state were simply enough to hold serve against summer demand.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>The heaviest rains last week fell mostly north of the D0/D1 areas in Louisiana and Mississippi. However, the past two weeks have brought enough rain to the region to continue the improvement trend this week as both abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) have once again been pushed southward in both of these states. D1 was also reduced in west central Louisiana where it was connected to D1 in Texas last week. These recent rains have not been enough, however, to offset the overall dryness of the past few months, so a core of D0/D1 still extends from central and southeastern Louisiana up into southern Mississippi.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Good rains (2 to 5 inches or more) covered parts of eastern Ohio, Pennsylvania and New England last week. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions have improved in eastern Ohio but have expanded west and north this week into northwestern Ohio, northeastern Indiana and southwestern Michigan, where 90-day rainfall totals are 3 to 6 inches below normal (50-75% of normal). Heavier rainfall (3-5 inches) in the southern Appalachians across eastern Tennessee and western North Carolina leads to the retreat of D0 to the east this week. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions were also trimmed in south-central North Carolina as well after a few consecutive weeks of beneficial rain along the coastal plains.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>The northern Plains didn’t see much rain last week, but it was much cooler than normal, with temperatures running 6 to 12 degrees below normal. These cooler temperatures have played a large mitigating role in keeping impacts in check, given the deficits that have been slowly building throughout the growing season. This duration component is now beginning to show in areas that don’t see timely rains each week. As a result, both central Nebraska and South Dakota show an increase in the D0 conditions. In addition, the D1 in south-central Nebraska has also pushed north and east this week. Crops in these areas are seeing stress now, especially in the sloped areas and those fields with less heavy soils and lower water holding capacity. Abnormally dry conditions have also expanded a bit in North Dakota this week. It should be noted that these areas are labeled as “A” for shorter-term agricultural impacts as the longer periods are showing no stress and streamflows are generally running well above normal.</p>
   <p>The storm pattern in the southern Plains was a little more active, with a good bit of it centered over central and northwestern Oklahoma. After degradation just last week in northwestern Oklahoma, this week’s rains of 2-5 inches brings improvement, with widespread 1-category improvement in the northwest and Panhandle as well. Some D1/D2 remains in the northwestern part of the state, where seasonal deficits are still quite impressive at 6 to 9 inches below normal (25-50% of normal) since the beginning of May.</p>
   <p>In Texas, the storm track set up once again across parts of the southern Panhandle and the north, bringing 2-5 inches on the heels of good rains last week. This leads to more reduction of D0-D2 in these regions and tightens the gradient between the core of D3/D4 and the D0-D2 in the south. The bridge of D1 depicted last week between Texas and Louisiana has been removed this week as well after another round of 2-4 inches of rain. This led to some reduction in D0 as well. Temperatures across the northern half of Texas were below normal last week, but the thermostat was still blasting away above normal across the southern half of the state. This was generally coupled with very little rainfall, leading to a slight push east of the D3/D4 core in southern Texas and an expansion of D3 to cover the entire Rio Grande basin. Some recent rains and relatively better (when compared to those of D4) streamflows on the southwestern flank of D4 in Texas led to a slight respite this week, in the form of D4 reduction to D3.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The recent cool and wet pattern across northern Montana brings more changes for the better on this week’s map, with a general 1-category improvement and reduction of D0-D2, although small cores of D0-D1 remain across the north and south-central portions of the state. Streamflow readings are running above normal virtually statewide, and below-normal temperatures were reported in all but the extreme western reaches.</p>
   <p>The Pacific Northwest is another story as it has been extremely warm (8 to 15 degrees above normal) with no rains to help offset it. Expansion is noted this week in the form of D1 across the northern Olympic Peninsula. An expansion of D1 and a new pocket of D2 are also introduced this week in north-central Washington state. The entire region is feeling the effects of this recent weather pattern. Streamflows in the D0-D2 areas are running well below normal for this time of year. Forage and water for livestock are both running low in north-central Washington state as reports from the field come into USDA.</p>
   <p>The sluggish start to the monsoon season across Arizona, coupled with above-normal temperatures, has led to the expansion of D0 across most of the state this week. Precipitation is only running at about 5-25% of normal as we reach the peak of the monsoon. Pasture land is burning up and livestock producers are concerned about culling herds if the monsoon remains quiet. USDA is reporting 61% of the state’s pasture and range land as poor or very poor. This is having an impact on wildlife in the region as well.</p>
   <p>The monsoon has been much kinder to eastern New Mexico, where rains of the past several weeks have led to more removal of D1 in the northeast. The picture in the western part of the state is about the same as Arizona’s, with little monsoonal moisture and above-normal temperatures leading to some D0 in the northwestern corner of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Upper Midwest">
   <p>Temperatures were cooler than normal once again, but for the most part, the region was left wanting rain. Stress is beginning to occur in the agricultural sector given the length of the dryness, and deficits are found at both the short- and long-term scales back to 12 months or more, so even those isolated pockets that saw an inch or two last week are simply treading water and aren’t seeing a reversal of the trend or a break in the drought. This combination of dryness across both short- and long-term scales leads to the introduction of extreme drought (D3) this week across northwestern Wisconsin and extreme east-central Minnesota, where deficits for the year now stand at 6-10 inches (50-70% of normal and worse in some places). USDA is reporting this week that 44% of the state’s pasture and range land is poor or very poor.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
