<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20011108</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) above-normal temperatures continue to be expected for the duration of this period over most of the nation; 2) the next few days will be quiet in the Pacific Northwest, but several storms are expected to progress across the area beginning by the upcoming weekend, November 10-11; 3) the northern Plains, Midwest, and Northeast are expected to have below-normal precipitation throughout the next 10-day period; and 4) above-normal precipitation is expected in Florida and the southern Plains November 13-17.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Effects of the long-term drought continue to occur on all islands of the Hawaiian chain. The leeward side of Molokai continues to experience some of the driest conditions in the state. On Puerto Rico, dryness for the past two months or longer has prompted the establishment of D0 for the eastern, northern, and southern parts of the island. September and October are the wettest months for many stations, and 8-week rainfall in these regions is running 33-68% of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic States">
   <p>As a result of another dry week across the region, drought conditions deteriorated in some areas, and more impacts from the drought were experienced. Severe drought (D2) expanded across New Hampshire and southeastern Vermont. Moderate drought (D1) expanded to cover southwest Vermont, Massachusetts, New York City, Long Island, and parts of Connecticut. On November 6, 9 counties in south-central Pennsylvania were placed into the Drought Warning status, and 10 counties were added (46 total) to the Drought Watch list for the state. Delaware River Basin storage for New York City also fell on November 6 into the Drought Warning category. Meanwhile, a Drought Watch was declared for all of New Jersey on November 1. As for precipitation during the month of October, it was the third driest October ever for Connecticut and New Jersey; the fourth driest for Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Delaware, and Virginia; and the fifth driest for Maryland.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Drought conditions continue to deteriorate in western Texas, and an area of extreme drought (D3) was added in the Trans-Pecos Climate Division of Texas, as well as the southeastern corner of New Mexico. Continued dryness that began during the summer months allowed an expansion of D0, D1, and D2 into other parts of New Mexico. The week was warm and dry across most of the Plains and Midwest. There was a slight increase in the D0 area in north-central Iowa and in southwest and south-central Kansas. Several other areas across the Plains will be watched for additional D0 development in the next several weeks. The only improvement in drought conditions resulted from locally heavy rains in northeastern Oklahoma around Tulsa, reducing D1 to D0 in that area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Following a dry week, severe drought (D2) was expanded across eastern North Carolina and central Georgia. Moderate drought (D1) expanded into parts of western Virginia and west-central Georgia. Wildfire danger remains high across most areas in the Southeast, streamflows are very low, and water restrictions continue to be enforced across many parts of Georgia. Hurricane Michelle gave Key West and south Florida only a glancing blow as it moved through the Straits of Florida from Cuba to the Bahamas on Monday, November 5.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>With changing seasons and a diminishing concern about wildfires and agricultural impacts, the hydrological drought designation was expanded for parts of the Northwest and northern Rockies, particularly in areas where precipitation has been near normal to above normal so far this fall. This transition will likely continue in following weeks in the West. In the meantime, wildfire potential is still above normal for all of California and normal for Nevada through November 20, according to the National Interagency Fire Center.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
