<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20071011</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Behind a frontal system moving off the East Coast, a reinforcing cold front will bring an end to the record temperatures in the East early in the period. While many locations on the Eastern Seaboard received more than 1 inch of rain with the passage of the front, high pressure will continue to dominate during the upcoming week and although temperatures will be seasonable, conditions will remain largely dry. The exception may be upstate New York and New England where a developing low may move southward into the region near the start of the weekend. In the Northwest, the active pattern of recent weeks continues. Pacific moisture will be plentiful in many of the same areas impacted in the past several weeks. The movement of systems eastward will also bring rainfall to the Plains, but moisture is expected to be limited by the blocking ridge in the East and lack of inflow from the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
   <p>The National Weather Service outlook for October 15-19 indicates the presence of a ridge of high pressure centered over the central U.S. separating troughs off the New England coast and over the Gulf of Alaska. The pattern will support normal to above normal temperatures for much of the country, with the exception of coastal California which will have normal to below normal temperatures due to the presence of the Gulf of Alaska trough. With the presence of the ridge of high pressure, near average to below average precipitation is likely over much of the eastern U.S. Precipitation in the Pacific Northwest and parts of the central and northern Plains will be average to above average.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Trade wind weather continued on the Hawaiian Islands with windward areas receiving generally higher amounts of rainfall. However, drought-affected areas on the Big Island and Maui received less than 0.50 inch of rain, light amounts also fell in areas of drought on Molokai and Oahu, and there was no change to the drought status on the islands this week. Precipitation was below average in many parts of Alaska during the past week, but near term and year-to-date precipitation totals for much of the state remain near to above average. D0(AH) conditions from the northeast Arctic Plains of Alaska southward across the Brooks Range reflect the continuing effects of below average precipitation. In Puerto Rico, the persistence of long-term deficits was reflected by a continuation of D0(H) across parts of southeastern Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Continued lack of rain and temperatures that were 10 to 20 degrees warmer than average led to an expansion of D0(AH) and D1(AH) conditions in New Jersey and Pennsylvania. In New Jersey, and neighboring areas of Pennsylvania, D1 was expanded to encompass areas with 90-day precipitation totals less than 50% of average. D0 and D1 were also extended westward across areas of northern Pennsylvania where large 3- to 6-month precipitation deficits were present. Low CPC soil moisture and USGS streamflow also reflected the very dry conditions. Farther north, rainfall totals of 1.0 to 1.5 inches south of Lake Ontario led to a 1-category reduction of D2(A) conditions in Monroe and Wayne counties. In upstate New York and northern Vermont, 1 to 2 inches of rain returned streamflows to near average and resulted in a removal of D0(A) conditions. In areas to the south extending into southern New England, a 1-category degradation reflected the accumulating effects of continued drier- and warmer-than-average conditions. D1(AH) was extended on all sides to encompass more of western Massachusetts and Connecticut and now stretches across Rhode Island and Massachusetts to the Atlantic coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>The greatest amount of precipitation during the week occurred with the movement of an upper low and passage of a frontal system through the Plains during the latter half of the period. The greatest rainfall amounts fell in eastern areas of the Plains unaffected by drought. More than 1.5 inches of rain in central South Dakota, along and to the west of the Missouri River, resulted in a slight westward reduction of D0(AH) and D1(AH) conditions. But in northwestern South Dakota and southwestern North Dakota where little precipitation fell and 30-day precipitation is 25% of average, D1(A) was extended northward from Meade county, South Dakota, across the border of North Dakota. While much of the rain in North Dakota fell in southeastern parts of the state unaffected by drought, rainfall in the northwestern corner of the state allowed for a small reduction of D2(A) along the Canadian border. In central Kansas, rainfall during the past week exceeded 1.5 inches in many locations, but lighter amounts, farther east in areas where 90-day deficits exceeded 4 to 5 inches, did not prevent a small westward expansion of D0(A).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, Ohio and lower Missouri Valleys">
   <p>Easterly flow around a high pressure area off the Southeast coast brought showers to parts of the region early in the period. The heaviest rainfall amounts (3 to 6 inches) occurred in southeastern Georgia and northeastern Florida where drought conditions were absent, but a westward retraction of D0(H) was made from central Georgia to central Florida. Enough precipitation fell in upstate South Carolina and the Appalachian Mountains of North Carolina to delay the westward extension of D4(AH) conditions in North Carolina. But in other places, a continued lack of precipitation and much warmer than average conditions led to an expansion of drought. A 1-category degradation was made on the coastal plain of South Carolina and along the Savannah River in Georgia. Temperatures during the past week reached the upper 80s and low 90s, and rainfall totals for the past 30 to 60 days were less than 50% of average in many places. USGS 7-day to 28-day streamflow levels were below the 5th percentile in many places and CPC soil moisture in much of the region was extremely low. The return of hotter and drier than average conditions in recent weeks in much of Georgia and Alabama produced agricultural and other short-term impacts, supporting the return of AH conditions to the region.</p>
   <p>In three counties of upstate South Carolina and neighboring areas of North Carolina, where precipitation early in the period was largely absent, D3(AH) was downgraded to D4(AH).  Continued lack of precipitation and warmer than average temperatures also led to a 1-category degradation in western Alabama and eastern Mississippi. In eastern Virginia, D1(AH) was replaced with D2(AH). Some locations in the area have not received measureable rainfall in more than 30 days and many locations are under voluntary or mandatory water restrictions. In eastern Kentucky, southern West Virginia, and along the Ohio River, a 1-category degradation was made to the north and east where much warmer than average temperatures and one to three month rainfall totals have been less than 50% of average in many places.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Upper Mississippi Valley and western Great Lakes Region">
   <p>The major feature for the week occurred late in the period when a deep low moved northeastward through Minnesota and Wisconsin. Combined with rainfall early in the period, there were widespread accumulations greater than 3 inches from southwestern Minnesota to northern Wisconsin and the Upper Peninsular of Michigan. More than 7 inches fell in some locations. This system affected many of the same areas that received higher than average amounts the past two to three weeks and contributed to widespread reductions in drought severity. A 1-category improvement was made from northern extremes of the Upper Peninsula of Michigan to parts of central and northern Minnesota. However, a sharp gradient remained in central Minnesota, reflected by a small area of D2(H) and D1(H).</p>
   <p>Increased inflow to Lake Superior resulted in a small rise in the lake level from the record September low reached last month. At the end of September, Lake Superior, the biggest and deepest of the Great Lakes, was about 20 inches below its long-term average level, 1.6 inches below the previous low for the month reached in 1926. Levels of all the Great Lakes remain below average as part of a decline that began in the late 1990s.</p>
   <p>The active pattern that eased drought conditions in Minnesota and Wisconsin remained to the west of Michigan. Rainfall throughout northern Michigan was below average during the past 3 months, with 90-day accumulations less than 50 to 70% of average. Combined with recent record and near-record temperatures, conditions deteriorated to D2(AH) in northwest Michigan, while D1 was extended across northern Michigan to Lake Huron.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The Northwest was affected again by an active storm track and fast-moving Pacific storms that brought rain and snow to many parts of the region. Western Washington from the coast to the Cascades received the most precipitation with several locations receiving more than 3 inches. Lighter amounts fell elsewhere but in sufficient totals to provide areas including western Oregon, the northern Rockies, and much of the plains of Montana and Wyoming with wetter than average conditions for the week. The additional precipitation combined with recent weeks of above average totals led to the removal of D0(AH) along the coast of Oregon and an eastward nudge of D0(AH) along the Cascades. In eastern Washington and the western edge of the Idaho Panhandle, D0(AH) and D1(AH) were moved eastward to reflect improving conditions from several weeks of precipitation. Additional improvements will likely occur during coming weeks if the pattern remains active as forecasted. In south-central Montana, D1(H) conditions improved to D0(H) to reflect the benefits of the 2-4 inches of precipitation that has fallen in the past month. Improving conditions in western Wyoming led to the removal of a small area of D3, and the D0(H) line was pushed farther south in central Wyoming. Although parts of central Wyoming along the North Platte River received unusually heavy rainfall in recent weeks, D1(H) conditions were left in place due to the effects of eight years of well below average inflows that have left two main storage reservoirs at less than 30% of average for this time of year.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Jay Lawrimore</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
