<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20031002</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During October 1-October 5, an unseasonably cool but predominately dry air mass will encompass the eastern half of the United States. Exceptions to the generally dry regime will be across Florida, where tropical moisture will enhance rainfall across the Sunshine State and in the vicinity of the Great Lakes where the unseasonably chilly air will enhance rain and even some snow showers across Michigan and downwind areas of Lakes Erie and Ontario. Across the West, unseasonably mild and dry weather will continue during this period, with scattered showers and thunderstorms bringing limited relief to portions of the southern Rockies and Intermountain region. Looking ahead to the period October 6-10, a cold front will significantly increase rainfall potential for Pacific Northwest by the 7th. Odds will also favor above average precipitation from west Texas and into the Four Corners region. In the East, normal to below normal rainfall will coincide with continued cool temperatures, while wetter weather is expected across Florida as well as the Northeast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>There was no change in the D0, D1 or D2 areas throughout Hawaii. The agricultural impact in southeast Alaska was removed but the D0 was left in place since rainfall has not been substantial enough to help the long-term deficit.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Maine received 1-3 inches of rain during the monitoring period, improving the drought situation from moderate drought (D1) to abnormally dry (D0), with long-term hydrological dryness being the primary concern across much of the state. The D0 areas across northern New Hampshire, Vermont, and New York remained intact to reflect the long-term deficit in the area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Great Lakes">
   <p>The Great Lakes region had improvement across Michigan, which picked up 2-4 inches of rainfall during the period. This alleviated dryness throughout the Upper and Lower Peninsula, enabling a depiction change from moderate drought (D1) to abnormally dry (D0), as well as some shaving of pre-existing D0. Farther to the west, parts of extreme southeastern Minnesota continued to be dry and the drought depiction worsened from severe drought (D2) to extreme drought (D3). Central Texas had improvement over the past week with many areas receiving 1-3 inches of rain. All drought classifications (D0, D1 and D2) were reduced one category and shifted to the northwest. However, in the southern portion of the Texas panhandle severe drought (D2) was extended eastward. In southwestern Oklahoma, the recent lack of rain resulted in a joining of D0 areas, while farther north in northwestern Oklahoma, showers and thunderstorms shrunk the existing D1 region that had been in place.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Due to the remnants of Hurricane Marty, southern Arizona received moderate to heavy rainfall early in the monitoring period bringing limited relief to the far southern areas of the state. The majority of the West remained dry with slightly above normal temperatures. There were no changes made in these regions with the exception of southern Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
