<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010906</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The following forecast features during September 5 - 10 could impact areas currently experiencing moisture shortages: (1) Moderate to heavy rainfall (1 to locally 3+ inches) across Florida, much of Michigan, northern and southeastern Nebraska, southern and eastern Iowa, Illinois, Missouri, most of Arkansas, northeastern Oklahoma, and parts of central and eastern Texas; (2) light to moderate precipitation (up to an inch) in the rest of the southwestern and west-central Great Plains, the Ohio Valley, the lower Northeast, New York, the Carolinas, much of the northern and central Rockies, and southeastern Idaho; (3) little or no precipitation in New England, southern Minnesota, South Dakota, eastern Wyoming, the central and southern High Plains, and the remainder of the western states; (4) significantly below-normal daily temperature maxima in the central and upper southern Plains, the northern Intermountain West, and the west-central Rockies.</p>
   <p>For September 11 - 19, the odds slightly favor above-normal precipitation across the southern tier of states (except peninsular Florida), the mid-Atlantic and lower Northeast, the central and northern Great Lakes region, and the western half of the Plains. Meanwhile, below-normal totals are expected in the Northwest, Idaho, the northern Great Basin, and northern California. Slightly enhanced chances for above-normal temperatures cover areas from the central and northern Great Plains eastward to the Atlantic coast early in the period, and areas from the central and northern High Plains westward to the Pacific coast later in the period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Another week with only scattered light to moderate rains (up to 0.8 inch) kept dryness and drought intact across much of the island chain. These areas will continue to be monitored for signs of deterioration as the drier time of year approaches for many areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Plains and Midwest">
   <p>oderate rains (locally 1 to 4 inches) ended D0 conditions in central Minnesota, but continued below-normal totals in areas to the south prompted a substantial expansion of D0 into much of Iowa, northern and central Illinois, parts of Nebraska, and the eastern half of South Dakota. These areas received little or no rainfall in the last 7 days, except for scattered totals of 0.5 to locally 2.0 inches along the Missouri River. Because of the increasing prevalence of short-term dryness, the W qualifier that had existed in southwestern Nebraska was eliminated. In addition, some increase in D1 extent seemed appropriate in southwest Iowa and adjacent Nebraska, where subnormal precipitation has been somewhat more marked.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>A strong cool front brought much-needed rainfall and lower temperatures to parts of the dry region, but a few areas that missed the rains deteriorated a bit. Between 1 and 4 inches fell during the week across much of Ohio, northern and western sections of Pennsylvania and New York, and the northern half of Maine. Meanwhile, 0.5 to 2.0 inches fell on most of southern Maine, Vermont, New Hampshire, central New York, central and northeastern Pennsylvania, and central sections of Michigans lower Peninsula. Only isolated amounts exceeding 0.5 inch fell on other parts of the dry region, specifically southern New England, the lower Northeast, northwestern Ohio, southern Michigan, and the northern Great Lakes region. As a result of this precipitation pattern, dryness ended in parts of northeast New York, and northeast and southwest Pennsylvania. D1 to D2 conditions generally improved by one category in other dry areas that received moderate to heavy rain, such as northern Maine and western sections of New York and Pennsylvania. In contrast, the dry week prompted expansion of D0 conditions across Michigans Upper Peninsula, southeastern Pennsylvania, much of New Jersey, and the New York City area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Moderate to heavy rains (1 to locally 4+ inches) ended dryness in eastern South Carolina, western Georgia, and at least temporarily in eastern Tennessee. In addition, the extent of D1 and D2 conditions declined along the Carolinas border, though drought remained acute in areas near Charlotte, NC where less rain fell. Light to moderate rains were observed across most of Florida, but normals are high this time of year, and with decreasing groundwater levels noted in some areas (particularly southeastern parts of the state), the extent of D0(W) and D1(W) conditions was increased in central Florida, and D0(W) was introduced into southeastern Florida. A few wells were near or at record low levels in Dade County, a marked decline from the more-favorable conditions observed with heavy July and early August rains.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Mississippi Delta">
   <p>Heavy to excessive rains fell on much of this region last week, causing severe localized flash flooding, but also substantially improving many dry areas. Between 12 and 16 inches of rain deluged parts of central Texas near San Antonio and Austin, the west side of greater Houston and Galveston, and part of southwest Louisiana. Meanwhile, 8 to 12 inches fell on much of a broad swath from central and lower eastern Texas eastward through south-central Louisiana, and the dryness and drought that had been covering parts of these regions (D0 to D2) were alleviated. Elsewhere, D0 to D2 conditions improved in the wake of 2 to 8 inches of rain across the rest eastern Texas, southern Texas, the remainder of Louisiana, northwestern Mississippi, and southern Arkansas. Farther north and west, however, substantial rainfall was less widespread, and thus relief from recent dryness and drought was not as robust, if it occurred at all. Rains of 0.5 to locally 4.0 inches in western Texas eliminated D3 and reduced the extent of D2 while only scattered showers across most of Oklahoma, central and northern Arkansas, southern Kansas, and eastern New Mexico kept improvement limited, and in fact allowed D0 to D2 conditions to expand in a few areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Another hot, dry week kept D0 to D3 conditions essentially intact across much of the West. Little or no precipitation was observed in most areas, with scattered totals of up to 0.5 inch recorded in the Rockies, the eastern Great Basin, and western Washington. A few locations in extreme northwest Washington received 1 to 4 inches, but climatology is also increasing seasonally in this region, so the rains offered only superficial relief. In addition, continued above-normal temperatures in northern and western parts of the region aggravated the continuing moisture shortages. A few areas deteriorated enough to merit a one-category increase in drought severity classification, specifically eastern Montana (where D0 to D3 conditions crept eastward), northern Idaho and northeastern Washington (which dropped to D3, matching neighboring Montana), and the Salmon River basin in western Idaho (where a new D3 area was introduced). The region-wide warm, dry weather kept streamflows below normal and allowed high to extreme fire danger to persist, although the acreage consumed by fires to date has been comparable to most other years.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
