<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050224</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During February 23-28, 2005, widespread precipitation is expected in the Southeast, ranging from 1 to 6 inches for the period. The majority of the nation is forecast to receive an inch or less of precipitation with the exception of the Pacific Northwest, and the northern Rockies to the northern Great Plains, which are forecast to receive none. Temperatures are expected to be warmer than normal in the above mentioned dry areas with below-normal temperatures for the rest of the nation. The weather pattern for the ensuing five days (March 1-5) will consist of an upper-level ridge over the western portion of North America and a cold trough over the east. This will result in above-normal precipitation for the southwestern third and northeastern quarter of the country, and the western two-thirds of Alaska.  Below-normal precipitation is expected for the Pacific Northwest and the northern Rockies and Great Plains. Normal conditions are progged for the rest of the country.  Above-normal temperatures are forecast for the Pacific Northwest and adjoining parts of California and Nevada, plus southern portions of Alaska.  Below-normal temperatures are expected beneath the trough, from the Great Plains to the Atlantic Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>The lack of rain during this monitoring periods week prompted the expansion of D0 in the northwest and south central areas of the island. Less than 0.25 inch of rainfall (less than 30 percent of normal) has occurred over these areas so far this month, with 5-inch deficits (rating at 30 percent of normal) common for the year to date. There have been no reports of agricultural impacts, however an A label was added to the Puerto Rico D0 areas to indicate the short-term timescale of the dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Half an inch to an inch of moisture fell across southeast Minnesota, just outside of the D0 area in the state. Very little precipitation occurred elsewhere, at most a quarter of an inch over the Plains and Midwest drought areas. Even though this is their dry season, D0A was added to the Plains of east central Colorado to reflect well below normal precipitation for the last 6 months. The impacts designation for the drought area of northeast Colorado, northwest Kansas, and extreme southwest Nebraska was changed from H to AH to reflect dryness at both the short- and long-term scales.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and The West">
   <p>This week saw a continuation of the pattern of wet weather in the southern half of the region and dry conditions persisting in the north. An inch or more of precipitation fell across much of California, into west central and southern Nevada, across much of central Arizona, and over parts of northern Utah, central New Mexico, and western Colorado. Local amounts of 6 to 9 inches of precipitation and some flooding were reported around Los Angeles, with 2 inches or more reported in central Arizona, the Salt Lake City area, and the Las Vegas, Nevada area. This winter (December 1, 2004-February 22, 2005), at 6.51 inches, ranked as the wettest winter on record in Las Vegas. Higher amounts fell in the southern California mountains, including 22.13 inches at Opids Camp in Los Angeles County and 18.68 inches at Old Man Mountain in Ventura County (through February 22). A few stations in southern Idaho, and the southern Cascades of Oregon, received half an inch of moisture, with three-fourths of an inch reported at Roseburg. The rest of the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies states ( Montana and Wyoming) had little or no precipitation.</p>
   <p>Record to near-record low snowpacks and 7-day streamflows were reported all along the Washington and Oregon Cascades, with some ski areas having to close. Record low snowpacks were also observed from northeast Oregon into Idaho, western Montana, and Wyoming. In Washington, D0 was expanded into the Puget Sound area, where Seattle reported a 2.24 inch deficit for the month so far, and a 7.30 inch deficit (68 percent of normal) since October. Olympia was down 3.98 inches so far this month. D1 was expanded across northwest Oregon and southwest Washington, and D2 was introduced into the Cascades of southern Washington and northern Oregon to the west central coastal mountains of Oregon. D2 was expanded from the east into central Washington and north central Oregon. Precipitation has been well below normal for much of the Pacific Northwest for the last four months. The impacts line separating Pacific Northwest AH drought from the H drought to the south was moved toward the Nevada state line to accommodate short-term dryness in southern Oregon and southwest Idaho.</p>
   <p>D2 was expanded in northwest Montana to encompass the Kootenai and Flathead river basins. As of February 22, snowpack was at 56 percent of average over the Flathead basin, which is the third lowest snowpack on record. The Kootenai basin snowpack was at 57 percent of average, ranking sixth lowest. D2 was expanded in north central Montana with a thumb of D3 encompassing the Bear Paw Mountains, where snowpack was at a record low level.</p>
   <p>D1 was pulled back in north central Arizona where recent precipitation has resulted in net surpluses back 12 to 24 months. D2 was retracted in east central Arizona and D1 edged back in southwest New Mexico to reflect improving conditions. Local reports indicate improvement along the Salt River Project, with SRP reservoirs up to 81 percent of capacity this week and SRP water deliveries to be restored to pre-drought levels. However, long-term precipitation deficits continued out to 24 to 60 months across much of eastern and southern Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>It was another dry monitoring period over most of Florida. D0 was expanded into the north central counties where rainfall deficits averaged 2 to 4 inches for the month to date and 4 to 8 inches over the last 60 days. The KBDI forest fire indicator for this area was greater than 500, indicating dry conditions. Gainesville has had only 0.27 inch of rainfall for the month to date, 2.23 inches below normal. The KBDI is over 500 across the southern third of the state and over 600 in the Broward and Palm Beach county area. Month to date precipitation was considerably below normal in this area, totaling only 0.05 inch at Miami (1.46 inches below normal), 0.04 inch at Ft. Lauderdale (2.03 inches below normal), and a trace at Naples (1.65 inches below normal). Groundwater conditions were normal and Okeechobee lake levels were still in the normal range, so an A impacts indicator was added to indicate short-term dryness.</p>
   <p>A vigorous weather system brought 1 to 2 inch rains over much of the Carolinas and Georgia. In spite of the rain, 90 day deficits were 5 inches or more over a large area of the Southeast. D0 was not expanded due to the wet weather this week, but the entire Southeast will continue to be monitored for any signs of deterioration, especially as the growing season approaches.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
