<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000622</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Features to watch in the next 10-day period include: 1) heavy rains June 19-21 across Missouri and drought-affected areas in west-central Illinois will bring additional relief to this region; 2) heavy rains June 19-21 will continue to benefit the remaining D0 region in northern Minnesota; 3) additional beneficial rains appear possible during the next 10-day period over the D3, D2, and D1 drought areas in the Midwest; and 4) normal to above-normal precipitation is forecasted June 27-July 1 for the entire eastern two-thirds of the United States, which includes above-normal precipitation for large parts of the drought regions in the Southeast and the Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Long-term drought continues in Hawaii. Extreme drought (D3) concerns involving agriculture and wildfire potential exist for Maui and a small part of the Island of Hawaii. The abnormally dry conditions continue along the northern coast of Puerto Rico as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Beneficial rain fell in most of the drought areas in the Midwest during the previous week. The exception to this occurred in western Nebraska and the western half of Kansas. As a result, drought conditions intensified some in these regions. Heavy rains in the Red River Valley and northern Minnesota allowed D1 conditions to improve, and only a small area of D0 remains in northern Minnesota. D0 was eliminated across the rest of northeastern Minnesota. A second major rain event in 10 days helped remove extreme drought (D3) from most of southeastern Nebraska. Missouri, southern Illinois, and most of Indiana also saw drought conditions improve during the week. In Missouri, D3 conditions in the south-central part of the state improved to D2, while large areas of west-central and central sections improved from D1 to D0. Most of the D0 category in southeastern Illinois, Indiana, and northern Kentucky was eliminated by rains during the week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeastern States">
   <p>Afternoon thunderstorms became more common across the southern and southeastern United States, a pattern that is typical during the humid summer months. Precipitation for the week was lowest in the D4 (exceptional drought) region of Georgia and Florida, and the region expanded to include west-central Georgia. Drought conditions intensified in western North Carolina, allowing an expansion of D2 (severe drought).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Western States">
   <p>A generally dry week occurred across most of the western United States. Abnormally dry conditions (D0) now exist over all of Colorado and most of Utah. Seasonal thunderstorms were beginning to become more common across southern Arizona, New Mexico, and western Texas. The main threat in the western states remains the high wildfire potential, although there are some agricultural concerns in most of the region as well.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
