<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061207</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch over the next 2 weeks that could affect current dry or drought areas include: 1) mild weather for most of the nation following Arctic chill that persists through about December 10; 2) mostly dry weather for existing drought areas through December 11, except for moderate to heavy rains in South Texas, followed by 3) normal to above-normal precipitation through week 2 in the Mississippi Valley and the Southeast; and 4) generally below-normal precipitation over the High Plains and the Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Summary">
   <p>The main story this week was the major storm system that left a swath of snow and ice from northern Texas through Oklahoma, Missouri, Illinois, Wisconsin, and Michigan. The low center tracked northward from Missouri into Michigan during November 30 to December 1. Snowfall amounts from 7 to 12 inches and greater were common near the storms path. Heavy rains fell in the warmer air south and east of the storm. Cumulative melted precipitation of 2 to 5 inches brought significant improvement to dry and drought areas extending from northern Texas into western Illinois. A general one-category drought improvement took place, with 2 categories in some locations. As a result, drought was reduced across Missouri, southeast Iowa and western Illinois, while drought diminished in southern and eastern Oklahoma and parts of northern Texas. D0H dryness lingered in parts of Missouri and in southeast Iowa due to long-term precipitation deficits and low pond levels. Dryness and drought levels from D0 to D4 were scaled back from the east in Oklahoma, and portions of the D3 retreated southward in northern Texas. In contrast, abnormally dry conditions (D0) extended eastward to the central Texas Gulf coast in response to continued below-normal rainfall.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, light to moderate precipitation in the Upper Midwest was not sufficient to result in improving conditions for the extreme drought over northern Minnesota and the D0 to D1 dryness/drought over the Dakotas and Nebraska. Persistent dry weather even led to some expansion of D0 in eastern Nebraska and northeastern Kansas, while D1 edged northward toward central Kansas.</p>
   <p>In the West, continued light to moderate rain or snow contributed to a pullback of D3 drought in northern Wyoming. In California, rainfall this season continued well below normal across the south. Water supplies are in good shape thanks to last winters storms, but soil moisture is low and, as a result, D0 dryness extended across southern California. In Riverside, rainfall since July has measured 0.05 inches, versus a normal of 1.60 inches. Downtown Los Angeles has seen 0.50 inches versus a normal of 2.08 inches. The dry conditions have contributed to the high fire danger in southern California. D0 also expanded northward into southwestern Nevada, where the season is also off to a slow start.</p>
   <p>Light to moderate rains maintained the dryness/drought status quo over central and northern Florida and southeastern Georgia. D0 dryness expanded slightly northward in Georgia and Alabama in response to low rainfalls and abnormally low stream flows.</p>
   <p>Heavy rains in eastern Puerto Rico led to some retreat of the D0 there.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Heddinghaus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
