<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20031106</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Most current areas of dryness and drought are forecast to receive some precipitation during November 6 - 10, except for the central and northern High Plains, the southern Rockies, the desert Southwest, and eastern Washington. Totals of less than 0.5 inch are anticipated in most areas, but more is expected (up to 1.7 inches) in central and western Arkansas, the southeastern half of Oklahoma, and northern Texas from the Red River and the southern Panhandle southward. In addition, amounts exceeding 0.5 inch are forecast for southwestern Oregon and most of California from the Sierra Nevada and Los Angeles northward, with 2.0 to 3.5 inches expected in the central and northern Sierra Nevada. During the ensuing 5 days (November 11 - 15), the odds favor above-normal rainfall through the southern half of the Mississippi Valley and the south-central Plains, but below-normal precipitation appears more likely across the Dakota and Montana Plains, most of Idaho, the northern Great Basin, and from central Washington southward through northern California.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>No precipitation was reported in southeastern Alaska last week, allowing D0AH conditions to persist. Meanwhile, near- or below-normal rainfall across most of Hawaii kept last week's areas of dryness and drought intact. Furthermore, unusually dry conditions during October and the beginning of November induced D0A conditions across the eastern half of the Big Island. At Hilo, 0.34 inch of rain during the first 3 days of November followed a 14-day spell with no rainfall that closed out October, a time when rainfall is typically on the increase. Because of the heavy precipitation normally recorded at Hilo, the accumulated departure from normal was below -6.5 inches for the 17-day period (about 5% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region, Mississippi Valley, and Plains">
   <p>Heavy rains finally brought some significant drought relief to areas from the central Plains northeastward through most of the Great Lakes region. Generally 4.0 to 6.5 inches drenched a swath from extreme southeastern Nebraska northeastward across the middle of Iowa and southern Wisconsin, with 1.0 to locally 4.0 inches recorded in areas surrounding the heaviest band. As a result, last week's D1AH to D3AH conditions from southeastern Nebraska to Lake Michigan generally improved 1 category and at least temporarily resolved any surface moisture shortages, resulting in D0H to D2H conditions as of November 4, 2003. However, in spite of the exceptional rainfall totals, accumulated 90-day precipitation reached only near- or slightly-below-normal levels, even in the wettest areas, and the rain-induced record high streamflows reported in parts of Iowa had dropped back more than halfway to previous levels only 24 hours after peaking.</p>
   <p>Farther east, 1.0 to locally 5.0 inches of precipitation fell on most of lower Michigan, eliminating D1 conditions in west-central parts of the Peninsula and leaving D0H conditions restricted to a swath through the middle of the region. Elsewhere, moderate precipitation (0.5 to 1.5 inches) engendered 1-category drought improvements in part of northwestern Wisconsin (to D0AH), central Nebraska (to D1AH), and southwestern South Dakota (to D0AH or D1AH).</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, less than 1.0 inch of precipitation fell on other parts of the Great Lakes region, Mississippi Valley, and Plains last week, with most locations reporting little or none. As a result, D0 to D3 conditions remained generally unchanged from last week, with some deterioration noted in southwestern Nebraska and adjacent Colorado (to D3AH), central and southeastern Arkansas (to D0A), extreme northeastern Texas (to D0AH), parts of the Red River of the South Valley (to D1AH), and northwestern Texas just south of the Panhandle (where D2AH and D3AH expanded eastward). Rainfall totals for the last 30 days were at least 2.0 inches below normal throughout the Red River Valley, central and southern Arkansas, and northern Louisiana, with some 4.0-inch deficits observed near the ArkLaTex region. In addition, 90-day rainfall totaled more than 4.0 inches below normal in northeasternmost Texas, northwestern Texas south of the Panhandle, and southeastern New Mexico. Farther north, similar deficits were reported across northern and southwestern Iowa, central and northeastern Wisconsin, and the Mississippi Valley in Minnesota, where D1AH to D3AH conditions persisted.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Cooler and damper conditions covered the western U.S. this week. Between 1.0 and 4.0 inches of precipitation fell on parts of the Colorado and adjacent Wyoming Rockies while a broken pattern of 1.0- to 3.0-inch amounts was observed across northeastern Utah, northern and western Wyoming, western and parts of central Montana, northeastern Idaho, and scattered sites across southwestern Oregon and the Sierra Nevada.</p>
   <p>Because of the protracted nature of the drought conditions in the Rockies and Intermountain West, the only improvements noted that justified a 1-category drought severity reduction occurred across northwestern Colorado, where D0H and D1H now prevail, and a small portion of northeastern Idaho and adjacent Montana, where a tight gradient from D1AH to D3AH exists.</p>
   <p>In the West Coast states, however, dryness and drought does not date back as far, so this week's precipitation produced more tangible improvements there. Most notably, the 0.5 to 2.0 inches of precipitation observed in much of central and western California, along with cooler and more humid conditions throughout the state, helped contain the devastating wildfires that had plagued some locales. D0A conditions were eliminated in central and west-central California, in addition to part of the southwestern coastline north of Los Angeles. In addition, conditions improved to D0A in the southern reaches of the Sierra Nevada. Farther north, similar precipitation totals in southwestern Oregon left only a small area of D0A west of the Klamath Basin.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
