<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020221</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a storm system currently working its way across the Midwest and Great Lakes February 19-20 has brought beneficial precipitation (rain and heavy snow) to the Great Lakes; 2) as this system moves to the East, generally light precipitation is expected in the Southeast and along the East Coast February 20-21; 3) another storm system will brush the Pacific Northwest February 21-22, but most of the nation will be dry during the February 20-25 period; 4) arctic air will push into the middle of the country and dominate the nations weather for the 6-10 day period (February 26 through March 2), a reminder that the winter season lasts for a couple more weeks; and 5) a potential upslope snow event in the eastern Rockies of Colorado and Wyoming and the central High Plains could provide very beneficial moisture during this 6-10 day period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>A second straight quiet week occurred across Hawaii. No changes were made to the map for the islands, and only western Molokai has a D1(W) designation. In Puerto Rico, the past eight weeks have been generally dry, with below-normal precipitation across most of the island. Abnormal dryness continues to be depicted along the southern coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Drought concerns continued to escalate along the East Coast during the past week. As a result of deteriorating drought conditions, an area of extreme drought (D3) now is located across most of New Jersey, southeastern Pennsylvania, northern Delaware, and northern Maryland. This includes both the Philadelphia and Baltimore metropolitan areas. Severe (D2) and moderate (D1) drought expanded to cover more of central Pennsylvania and eastern West Virginia. According to the USGS, streamflows are below normal at 87% of the gaging stations in Maryland and Delaware, and 100% of the groundwater observation wells in the two states are also below normal. In addition, streamflow entering into Chesapeake Bay is at the second lowest level for February since 1937. Precipitation in Washington, D.C., has only been 35% of normal (a deficit of 10.28 inches) since September 1, 2001. The New York City Delaware River Basin storage, meanwhile, has risen since the beginning of the year, although levels still remain in the Drought category, according to their terminology, and have not been this low in February since 1981.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The biggest drought-related news item in the Midwest continues to be the low lake levels in the Great Lakes. Although not captured on the Drought Monitor map, the low lake levels will have increasing impacts as spring approaches. The past week was dry across the entire Great Plains. The Fargo and Grand Forks areas in North Dakota, for example, are at 21% and 6% of normal, respectively, for the year-to-date precipitation. No changes were made to any of the drought or abnormally dry areas in the Midwest or Plains.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Very little precipitation occurred across the southeastern United States during the past week. As a result, agricultural and wildfire concerns are increasing and the line delineating hydrological impacts was moved north to northeastern Georgia. An area of abnormal dryness (D0) was added to southeast Alabama, southern Mississippi, and southeastern Louisiana. New Orleans has a year-to-date precipitation departure of -4.20 inches (54% of normal). In addition, recent dryness expanded the abnormally dry (D0) region into eastern Kentucky and Tennessee.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Little precipitation fell in the western United States during the past week. Concerns about the low snowpack levels are increasing in the Rockies as the winter season progresses toward spring. As a result, D1 (moderate drought) expanded to include southwestern Wyoming, western Colorado, and eastern Utah. Snowpack levels in Utah, for example, ranged from 35% to 75%.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
