<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010426</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period (April 25-May 5) that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country: 1) Except in the Pacific NW and the Southeast, high pressure should dominate most of the country over the next two weeks leading to a pushing of the jet stream well north. This should allow well above-normal temperatures to spread northward toward Canada over the period, with some areas of the High Plains seeing temperature departures of +15 to +20F; 2) In addition, the aforementioned ridging means that most of the U.S. can also expect to see below-normal precipitation over the same time frame, which should bring a rapid drying out and warming up of soils in the soggy Plains and upper Midwest; 3) In contrast, the Pacific NW and parts of the Southeast (especially Florida) can expect a cooler and wetter pattern to persist over the next ten days, bringing some welcome relief to the snowpack situation (or at least a delay in any rapid melting) in the Northwest along with beneficial rains to the Deep Southeast; 4) High pressure should dominate the weather pattern over the Hawaiian Islands in the near future which should only help the drought continue its grip on the state.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>A very dry week returned to the islands, with only windward Hilo recording substantial rains of more than 2.5 inches, and that is still well below normal. Drought conditions over the islands remain unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Appalachians and lower Ohio Valley">
   <p>No real relief came to most of this region last week. Like the Southeast, they shared in a much cooler and drier week after experiencing near-record highs the week before. Year-to-date precipitation totals remain very low along the Ohio River from Ohio down to the Mississippi River confluence. As a result, Moderate Drought (D1) has spread westward into the Bootheel region of southeast Missouri and into northeastern Arkansas as well. In addition, this same area of Moderate Drought (D1) has also pushed into the southern portions of Indiana and Illinois.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>An active storm pattern continued over much of the Plains. The real story has been too much rain, which has been causing all sorts of flooding and planting delays in the region. These recent storms have led to a retreat of Abnormally Dry (D0 W) conditions back north and west into Wyoming as areas in the southeast part of the state have benefitted the most. Streamflow and snowpack conditions are generally in much better shape here. Relief continues in the Nebraska Panhandle as Abnormally Dry (D0 W) conditions are now confined to the extreme southwest corner of the state, where streamflow and reservoir levels remain low.</p>
   <p>Although rainfall was plentiful in much of central Texas, most of the rain continues to miss areas up and down the Rio Grande River. This is a region that continues to bear watching as the hot season is just around the corner. The immediate impact, or benefit, of recent scattered heavy rains around Brownsville, TX (3 to 5 inches), will be monitored as some improvement in drought conditions (D0, D1) in the area may be warranted in the coming weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>In contrast to last weeks active weather pattern, most of the region experienced a much drier and cooler (5 to 9F below normal) week, with most of Alabama, Georgia, Florida and the Carolinas seeing very little (&lt; .25 inches), or nothing, in the way of precipitation. Soil moisture conditions continue to decline in Florida, where statewide topsoil condition reports from USDA show 91% rated in the short-very short range. In South Carolina, 50% is rated at short-very short. In Florida, the persistent drought and recent drier and cooler air actually helped fuel several wildfires as low relative humidity and dew point levels, accompanied by brisk winds, led to a quick spreading of these fires. The resultant smoke has led to road closings again as part of U.S. Highway 1 was shut down going into and out of the Florida Keys. Already this year, more than 2,200 fires have burned over 170,000 acres. Fire risk remains a concern across other parts of the Southeast and will continue to increase if forecasts for above- normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation hold true over the next two weeks (see Looking Ahead section below).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Warmer and wetter conditions returned to much of the West and Southwest last week. California welcomed the wetness but most parts of the state also saw cooler than normal temperatures. The cooler temperatures are beneficial in that they help to delay melting of low snowpacks. Again, without the benefit of deeper self-insulating packs, the rapid melting of snows continues to be of concern as the hotter summer months approach. In the Pacific Northwest, very little improvement resulted from the relatively meager snow showers that frequented the region over the past week, assuring that snowpack levels (and water equivalent totals) in most parts will remain among the lowest recorded.</p>
   <p>The only drought condition change of note in the region is shown where we have Abnormally Dry (D0 W) conditions continuing to pull back out of the extreme southeastern corner of Wyoming as a result of heavy snows from a strong spring storm a week ago. This same spring blizzard came out of Wyoming and the Rockies and proceeded to dump almost two feet of snow in Rapid City, SD, and the Black Hills. All in all, though, snowpack levels and snow water content levels remain very low across much of the West. In addition, Montana is rating 52% of their top soil (upper 6 inches) moisture as short-very short while New Mexico reports 49% falling into the same category. Fire risk remains high over the Four Corners region and in north-central and northeastern Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
