<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20140403</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>This U.S. Drought Monitor week saw an active weather pattern across much of the West coast and northern Rockies as a series of disturbances moved through the region delivering rain showers to the lower elevations and mountain snow showers to the higher elevations. Scattered snow showers were observed in higher elevations of the Intermountain West while the Southwest remained in a warm and dry pattern. Across portions of the South and Southeast, scattered rain showers were observed while locally heavy rain and snow showers fell across much of New England. In the Northern Plains and Upper Midwest, the pattern of below-normal temperatures and snow showers persisted. Across the Southern Plains and western portions of Texas, dry and windy conditions continued to deplete soil moisture levels. On this week’s map, slight improvements were made in northern California and northeastern Oregon, while conditions deteriorated in southern Colorado. Moving eastward, conditions in the southern Plains, western Texas, and the lower Midwest deteriorated while New England saw improvements.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>The NWS HPC 7-Day Quantitative Precipitation Forecast (QPF) calls for moderate-to-heavy precipitation accumulations (two-to-six inches) across the lower Midwest and moderate accumulations (two-to-three) in the South and Southeast. The Upper Midwest, New England, central Rockies, and Pacific Northwest are forecasted to receive accumulations of less than two inches. The 6-10 day outlooks call for a high probability of above-normal temperatures across the West while below-normal temperatures are forecasted across the South, Midwest, and Eastern tier. A high probability of above-normal precipitation is forecasted across portions of the Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, New England, northern Plains, and Pacific Northwest while the remainder of the West, southern Plains, and western portions of the South are expected to have below-normal precipitation.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>On this week’s map, conditions remained status quo in Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico. In the Hawaiian Islands, temperatures during the past week were generally near-normal and precipitation was slightly above-normal on the windward slopes. In Alaska, the northern half and Aleutians experienced above-normal temperatures while the eastern portions of Southcentral were well below-normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>The Mid-Atlantic remained drought-free on this week’s map. In the mountain region of western North Carolina, an area of Abnormally Dry (D0) expanded in response to below-normal streamflow activity and short-term precipitation deficits. Otherwise, the eastern portions of North Carolina and Virginia received rainfall accumulations ranging from one-to-two inches. According to the National Weather Service, the month of March ended as the coldest on record at Washington Dulles Airport, breaking the previous record set in 1984. Overall, temperatures were well-below-normal during the past seven days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>During the past week, precipitation was generally light across the region with rain in the Lower Midwest and some locally heavy snow showers in the Upper Midwest. Liquid accumulations were generally less than an inch with slightly greater accumulations in central Wisconsin, the Upper Peninsula, and northern Michigan. Short-term precipitation deficits, pockets of dry soils, and below-normal streamflow activity led to expansion of Abnormally Dry (DO) in southern Illinois and southeastern Missouri while the remainder of the region remained unchanged on the map. According to the NWS National Operational Hydrologic Remote Sensing Center, the total area covered by snow in the northern Great Lakes region was 56.2% as of April 1, 2014. Temperatures across the region remained below-normal during the past week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>The Northeast remained drought-free on the map with the exception of two small areas of Abnormally Dry (D0). During the past week, coastal areas from New Jersey to Maine received precipitation accumulations ranging from two-to-five inches while locally heavy snowfall accumulations were observed across the Alleghany Plateau, Interior Lowlands, and Adirondacks of New York as well as northern portions of Maine. According to the NWS National Operational Hydrologic Remote Sensing Center, the total area covered by snow in the Northeast region was 82.6% as of April 1, 2014. This week’s precipitation events led to the removal of areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) in Connecticut, Massachusetts, and New York. During the past week, well-below-normal temperatures persisted in New England.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>As with most of the northern tier, the northern Plains experienced below-normal temperatures and areas of snowfall including blizzard-like conditions early this week in the Dakotas. According to the NWS in Bismarck, North Dakota, record daily maximum snowfall (8.1 inches) was observed in Bismarck on Monday. In the southern Plains, continued short-term precipitation deficits, declining range and pasture conditions, and areas of below-normal streamflow activity led to expansion of areas of Moderate Drought (D1) and Severe Drought (D2) in the eastern half of Kansas and central Oklahoma where areas of Severe Drought (D2) pushed eastward. Temperatures were generally near-normal to slightly above-normal in the southern portions of the Plains during the past week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>During the past week, some moderate to locally heavy precipitation (two-to-four inches) fell across the southern halves of Alabama and Mississippi, eastern and northern Louisiana, and east Texas leading to improvement in areas of Abnormally Dry (DO) in northern Louisiana and areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) and Moderate Drought (D1) in East Texas. Moving westward in Texas, conditions continued to deteriorate as short- and long-term precipitation deficits and declining reservoir levels raised concern. According to Water Data for Texas, San Angelo Area reservoirs are currently 7.9% full while the Panhandle Planning Region reservoirs are currently 1.7% full. On this week’s map, expansion of areas of Extreme Drought (D3) were made in the Hill Country and portions of West Texas while the Panhandle saw slight expansion of areas of Exceptional Drought (D4) as dry and windy conditions continued to spark dust storms. Temperatures were near-normal to slightly below-normal for eastern portions of Texas to Alabama while the western half of Texas was above-normal during the past week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>The Southeast received some shower activity during the past week, but most of the significant rainfall was restricted to drought-free areas in Florida. One-to-two inches of rainfall fell over isolated pockets of southwestern Georgia and coastal South Carolina, while northern Georgia received less than half an inch. Continued short-term precipitation deficits in northern Georgia and Alabama led to slight expansion of areas of Abnormally Dry (D0) as streamflows remained below normal. During the past week, average temperatures were four-to-seven degrees below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>During the past week, a series of disturbances pushed on-shore from the Pacific delivering much-needed rain and snow to northern California and Oregon. In northern California, liquid precipitation accumulations ranged from two-to-six inches in the northern coastal mountains while the northern Sierras received three-to-eleven inches. In the northern half of the Central Valley, precipitation accumulations were less than one and a half inch. Despite short-term gains, the long-term deficits across the region remained substantial. According to the California Department of Water Resources, California’s snowpack has increased since the first snow survey on January 3rd, but the latest survey results show California’s snow-water equivalent is only 32 percent of the average April 1st measurement when the snowpack is generally at its peak level prior to spring melt. In light of this week’s significant precipitation accumulations in the northern Sierra, a one-category improvement from Extreme Drought (D3) to Severe Drought (D2) was made to reflect short-term gains over the areas of greatest precipitation accumulations ranging from four-to-eleven inches. In northeastern Oregon, a one-category improvement from Moderate Drought (D1) to Abnormally Dry (D0) was made to reflect near-normal snowpack conditions in the Blue and Wallowa Mountains. In the Southwest, a warm and dry pattern continued across the region leading to slight deterioration of conditions in southwestern Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>David Simeral</name>
   <affiliation>Western Regional Climate Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
