<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20071129</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The key weather system over the next few days will be a storm moving from the Four Corners region to the Great Lakes States.  Locally heavy rain and snow will overspread the Southwest on November 30 - December 1.  Precipitation will develop across portions of the Plains on December 1, and the storm's cold front will sweep into the East on December 2-3.  Heavy snow and high winds may accompany the system from portions of the central U.S. into the Great Lakes region, and bitterly cold air will trail the storm into the Midwest and Northeast.  Dry weather will prevail nearly nationwide in the storm's wake, except for persistent rain and snow showers in the Northwest.</p>
   <p>The outlook for December 6-12 calls for colder-than-normal weather across the eastern one-third of the U.S., while warmer-than-normal conditions will prevail in most areas from the High Plains westward.  Meanwhile, most of the nation will receive below-normal precipitation.  Near-normal totals will be confined to the Far West and the nation's northern tier.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Conditions did not warrant any changes to the drought depiction this week in Alaska and Hawaii, while Puerto Rico remains free of abnormal dryness and drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes and Ohio Valley">
   <p>A pair of storm systems produced widespread precipitation across the Ohio and middle Mississippi valleys, as well as the lower Great Lakes region, resulting in reductions in the coverage of dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2).  The most significant changes occurred in southern Ohio, southeastern Michigan, and north and northeast of St. Louis, Missouri.  In particular, D0 was erased from southeastern Michigan by precipitation totals of at least 1 to 2 inches.  More than 2 inches soaked much of southern Ohio.  In contrast, a continuation of dry weather resulted in a slight expansion of D1 in west-central Michigan and D0 and D1 in northern Wisconsin.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Significant precipitation also fell in much of the Northeast, shaving the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) in central Pennsylvania and erasing it from western New York.  However, only light rain (mostly less than 1 inch) fell in southern New England, where low streamflows and precipitation deficits at various time scales continued to support some moderate drought (D1).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Gulf Coast States">
   <p>Light snow fell in many locations on the Plains, but liquid totals were generally less than one-quarter inch except in Montana and south of Lubbock, Texas.  For the most part, snow prevented further intensification of the dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) that has developed this autumn on the High Plains.  In Texas, the percentage of the winter wheat crop rated very poor to poor by USDA rose from 29 percent on October 28 to 53 percent on November 25.  During the same 4-week period, Oklahoma wheat rated very poor to poor increased from 18 to 30 percent, while Kansas and Colorado wheat rated very poor to poor climbed from 10 to 15 percent.  By November 25, topsoil moisture rated very short to short in Kansas stood at 100 percent in the southwest, 86 percent in the south-central region, 82 percent in the west-central region, and 72 percent in the northwest.  (The Kansas state average was 53 percent very short to short on topsoil moisture.)  Wheat was struggling to grow on the southern High Plains, where Texas' emergence stood at 70 percent on November 25, compared to the 5-year average of 85 percent.  Similarly, Oklahoma's wheat was 83 percent emerged, compared to the 5-year average of 95 percent.  Another complication of the Plains' dry autumn has been a rash of grass fires.  During the week ending November 23, the Aetna fire burned 5,000 acres of vegetation in southern Kansas, while the Wild Hog fires (two separate incidents) charred at least 3,400 acres in northern Texas.</p>
   <p>Some minor changes occurred on the northern Plains, including the introduction of severe drought (D2) in parts of western South Dakota.  Farther south, significant precipitation fell south of the primary winter wheat belt, but soaked (or blanketed) areas from western Texas to the lower Mississippi Valley.  In Midland, Texas, the normal annual snowfall of 5.2 inches was surpassed November 22-25, when 6.2 inches fell.  El Paso, Texas, received 5.3 inches of snow on November 24-25, representing its heaviest November snowfall since 1976, when 6.7 inches fell on the 27th and 28th.  Farther east, the former area of abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) covering more than 70 percent of Texas was cut in two.  D0 persisted across southern Texas, while a slight expansion of D1 was noted across north-central Texas.  In contrast, the area of moderate drought covering parts of northeastern Texas, northwestern Louisiana, and the southwestern corner of Arkansas was eliminated by 1 to 3 inches of rain.  Meanwhile, heavy rain dented dryness and drought in western Florida and southern portions of Alabama and Mississippi.  Mostly dry weather persisted, however, across Florida's peninsula, where moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) expanded to the west.  Naples, on Florida's Gulf Coast, received just 34.06 inches of rain (68 percent of normal) from January 1 to November 27.  Southern Florida's Lake Okeechobee remained unusually low for this time of year, with the November 27 average surface elevation of 10.29 feet being about 5 feet below the late-November historical average.  The lake has rebounded less than 18 inches from the all-time record low of 8.82 feet set on July 3.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>The historic and intense drought that has been affecting the Southeast for much of the year seems to be shifting eastward in recent weeks.  Since mid-October, periodically significant rains have been falling across the western slopes of the Appalachians, particularly from western and central Tennessee into the interior Northeast.  As a result, the latest storm system to pass through the region brought some further reductions in the coverage and intensity of drought as far east as Kentucky, Tennessee, northern and southern Alabama, and far southwestern North Carolina.  Nevertheless, some exceptional drought (D4) persisted in central and northeastern Alabama, southeastern and northeastern Tennessee, and southwestern Virginia.  Farther east, a continuation and slight expansion of D4 was noted from northern and western Georgia into parts of North Carolina.  Through November 27, year-to-date precipitation deficits were in excess of 20 inches in locations such as Anniston, Alabama (28.33 inches below normal; 40 percent of normal), Tuscaloosa, Alabama (28.27 inches below normal; 45 percent of normal), and Greenville-Spartanburg, South Carolina (20.09 inches below normal; 56 percent of normal).  Meanwhile, soil moisture shortages, meager streamflows, and both long- and short-term precipitation deficits supported the expansion of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) across the Mid-Atlantic coastal plain.</p>
   <p>Although hydrological impacts were dominant in most drought-affected areas, some serious agricultural drought effects were still evident in the middle and southern Atlantic coastal plain.  According to USDA, 81 percent of North Carolina's pastures were rated in very poor to poor condition on November 25.  Six weeks ago, on October 14, North Carolina's number stood at 93 percent.  Elsewhere on November 25, pastures rated very poor to poor stood at 75 percent in Virginia, 74 percent in South Carolina, and 71 percent in Georgia.  Since mid-October, pasture conditions improved slightly in Virginia and South Carolina, but deteriorated (from 55 to 71 percent very poor to poor) in Georgia.  Another drought-related agricultural impact was delayed emergence of winter wheat.  Wheat planting was ahead of the 5-year average in Georgia and North Carolina, while emergence trailed the normal pace.  In South Carolina, half of the wheat was planted (vs. the 5-year average of 58 percent) by November 25, but the crop was only 19 percent emerged (vs. the average of 43 percent).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A mostly dry week resulted in few changes to the drought depiction.  Dry weather returned to areas from Oregon to Montana, where previous rain and snow had resulted in some drought reductions.  In north-central and northeastern Arizona, however, a continuation of dry weather and a reassessment of long-term conditions in various watersheds, including the Little Colorado River basin, led to a broad deterioration from abnormal dryness (D0) to moderate drought (D1).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
