<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020425</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During April 25-29, a cold front will sweep across the eastern states early in the period, providing some beneficial rains to drought stricken areas of the Mid-Atlantic and Northeast states. A developing storm system across the plains during the weekend will provide some relief with scattered rainfall expected from Oklahoma northward into South Dakota. This system will reach the Eastern Seaboard by early next week, along with more opportunities for scattered showers and thunderstorms. Out west, an upper level trough of low pressure will provide relatively cool and unsettled conditions, with rain and mountain snow expected across parts of the Great Basin, from Nevada and Utah eastward into western Colorado. Little or no precipitation is expected across the desert Southwest, deep south Texas, and the extreme Southeast. The NWS 6-10 day forecast for April 30-May 4 calls for above normal precipitation from the Tennessee Valley eastward through the Mid-Atlantic states. Wetter than average conditions are also anticipated across parts of the northern Rockies eastward into the northern Plains, along with below normal temperatures. Relatively warm and dry weather is forecast from New Mexico and Texas eastward along the Gulf Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Mainly dry weather persisted across most of the Hawaiian islands, except for locally heavy windward precipitation over Oahu and Kauai. Otherwise, there were no changes to the existing D0 designation across western Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>A slow moving frontal system that bisected the Mid-Atlantic states during the weekend of the 20th-21st brought locally heavy but beneficial rains from West Virginia eastward across northern Virginia and Maryland. Weekly rainfall amounts exceeding 2 inches allowed for a reduction in D0 to D2 depiction across eastern West Virginia into the Shenandoah Valley of Virginia. Elsewhere across the Northeast and Mid-Atlantic, little overall change in drought conditions was observed as record warm temperatures combined with more scattered precipitation amounts to maintain existing long-term dryness. Across the Southeast, a strong early season Bermuda high pressure system resulted in relatively dry and very warm conditions across the region, with precipitation amounts scattered and light. The lack of rainfall along with accelerated evaporation rates prompted the expansion of D0 across much of Alabama, as soil moisture declined abruptly during the past week. Hydrological drought designation was also shifted farther to the north, as soil conditions continued to dry out across much of the Carolinas and Georgia with a notable absence of significant precipitation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Gulf of Mexico moisture intersected a frontal boundary that resided over the central Plains to produce clusters of showers and thunderstorms from central Kansas eastward through Missouri. This effectively eradicated D0 dryness throughout much of this area. Farther north, chilly rains and even a late season snowfall over parts of Minnesota allowed for a reduction of D0/D1 across northwestern areas of the state as the cold airmass further squelched evaporation rates. Precipitation that has been only 25 to 50 percent of average during the last 3 months prompted the expansion of D2 drought levels across western Kansas and parts of eastern Colorado. Across deep south Texas, triple digit heat teamed with strong winds and another rainless week to warrant the introduction of D3 in the Brownsville area. Hot, dry weather also promoted a northward expansion of D0 into central Texas, despite mixed signals from various drought indicators.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation was near to or above average from the Pacific Northwest and throughout the northern Rockies as a frontal system traversed the region during the first half of the period. High elevation snowpack gains across northwestern Wyoming eased drought conditions with a depiction reduction from D2 to D1 in areas that included Yellowstone National Park. While increases in snow water equivalent maintained D0 across northwestern Utah, much of the remainder of the Beehive State experienced worsening drought conditions with plunging reservoir levels, and D2 was expanded from the south as well as along the Bear River bordering Wyoming. In neighboring Colorado, D2 was expanded northward and D3 (extreme drought) was introduced across the southern half of the state as a lack of winter precipitation and insufficient snowpack continued to heighten drought concerns. Colorado Governor Bill Owens released emergency funds for firefighting in anticipation of an active fire season and requested an emergency statewide drought declaration from the U.S. Department of Agriculture. Additionally, D3 was expanded into northern New Mexico and northeastern Arizona, and various indicators suggest that a continued expansion of extreme drought depiction may be required in the weeks ahead.</p>
   <p>Although weekly precipitation across Alaska was generally above average, subnormal seasonal precipitation and snowpack across east-central areas maintained abnormally dry (D0) conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
