<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080110</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather conditions that could affect dry or drought areas over the next 2 weeks include: 1) a cold front on January 10-11 and coastal low on January 13-14 bringing widespread rain to the Southeast, resulting in 5-day forecast amounts during January 9-14 exceeding 1 inch in Alabama, northern Georgia, coastal areas of the Carolinas, and much of Virginia, Delaware, and Maryland; 2) Pacific weather systems spreading rain and snow across the Northwest during the first 5 days, with over 1 inch of liquid precipitation in the higher elevations, but the Southwest mostly dry and the forecast storms hitting the Northwest much weaker than the recent storms; 3) the 6-10 day and week 2 forecasts indicating below-normal precipitation for most of the West and the mid-Atlantic region, but above-normal rains for southern Texas.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Additional moderate to heavy rains eliminated remaining D0 areas in Hawaii. There was no change to the D0 area in Alaska, as snowfall amounts were modest.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast">
   <p>D0 dryness lingered over southern New England as wells remained low in parts of the tri-state area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Continued dry weather led to merging of the D1 drought areas in southern Texas and expansion of the D0 in southwestern Texas and along the central Texas coast. Farther north, D2 drought expanded in southwestern North Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Rainfall totals less than 1 inch resulted in little change to the drought status across the Southeast as well as the mid-Atlantic. Preliminary rankings issued by the National Climatic Data Center show that in 2007 North Carolina experienced its driest year in 113 years of record-keeping. Tennessee had its second driest year, Alabama its third, and Georgia its fourth.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A series of fierce storms battered the West this period during January 3-6, with additional rain and snow on January 7 and 8. The storms inflicted the greatest impacts on California, with powerful and damaging winds, heavy rains, and impressive mountain snows. Although the extreme weather adversely affected millions of people, the moisture dramatically improved California's available water. Weekly precipitation totals ranged from 5 to over 10 inches in the Sierra and coastal mountain ranges, with over 2 inches in the northern Central Valley. Four to 6 feet of snow piled up in the Sierra Nevada, with local accumulations as high as 11 feet. The snows resulted in California's snow water equivalent jumping to 111 percent of normal. Big improvements in snow pack have also taken place in Oregon. For the 31-day period from Dec. 9 to Jan. 9, snow water equivalent (from NRCS SNOTEL) in the Willamette Basin of Oregon increased from 45 percent to 159 percent of average, the Rogue/Umpqua basins in SW Oregon from 32 percent to 130 percent of average, and the Klamath Basin east of the Cascades to 109 percent of average from only 24 percent a month ago. Heavy mountain snows and valley rains also affected Arizona, northern New Mexico, Nevada, Utah, and Colorado. Over 2 inches of moisture fell in central Idaho and the Yellowstone area of Wyoming. Drought intensity levels improved by one category in much of southern California, coastal central sections of California, western Nevada, central and southern Utah, and northwestern Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
