<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20110120</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (January 19-23), cold air will entrench the United States east of the Rocky Mountains.  Temperature departures of 12-15 degrees Fahrenheit below normal will be common through the Great Lakes and Upper Midwest regions.  Temperatures will be above normal over the western United States, especially California, with departures 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal.  Precipitation chances will be widespread, especially over the Plains and the northern tier of the country.  The greatest precipitation amounts are expected over east Texas, Florida and the Pacific Northwest.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (January 24-28) has temperatures remaining below normal over the United States for most locations east of the Rocky Mountains.  Temperatures are projected to stay above normal for southern Alaska, the western United States, and the northern Rocky Mountains.  Dry conditions are expected over the Midwest, Pacific Northwest, and Great Basin.  The best chances for above-normal precipitation can be expected over the Gulf Coast and along the eastern seaboard as well as southern Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes for Alaska, Hawaii or Puerto Rico this week.  In Hawaii, even with the return of moisture, many of the Islands are not showing immediate improvements to drought conditions as the long-term drought has definitely impacted many, especially agricultural and water supply interests.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Dryness continued in southern Missouri and southern Illinois.  D1 was expanded out of Arkansas and into southern Missouri while D0 was pushed farther north to include all of southern Missouri.  D0 was expanded to include the southern reaches of Illinois.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Precipitation was minimal over most of the region, with Florida being the anomaly.  Several stations reported well over an inch of rain, with close to 3 inches in the Tampa Bay area. Tarpon Springs, Florida, recorded 2.86 inches for the week.   This allowed the drought status in Florida to remain unchanged this week.  D0 and D1 conditions expanded in North Carolina.  Low inflows into reservoirs as well as low streamflows, for this time of year, throughout the region are being observed.  D0 was also expanded in western North Carolina, extreme western South Carolina and northeast Georgia as dry conditions continue in the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>Widespread rain through east Texas allowed for continued improvements to the drought status.  Categorical improvements were made in most areas as the rains continued to improve upon the dryness in the region. In south Texas, precipitation over the last two weeks has allowed for more improvements, with just a few small pockets of D1 remaining.  West Texas remains dry even for the dry season.  D2 was introduced this week as the short-term dryness continues to worsen.  In Alabama, the drought-free pocket in the central portion of the state was filled in with D0 and D1 expanded to the north out of southern Alabama.   In Arkansas, D2 was expanded in the north-central part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid Atlantic">
   <p>Most of the region ended the week with below-normal precipitation, continuing the pattern observed for most of the winter.  Coastal regions were impacted by a storm delivering several inches of snow.  D0 expanded this week in Virginia as the Mid Atlantic remains dry.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>No changes were made in the western United States this week.  Above-normal snow pack over most of the region is ongoing.  In Wyoming, the upper elevation snow amounts are good, but the lower elevations remain dry in the D0 region.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
