<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000803</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may affect some of the nations dry or drought areas include: 1) Diurnal showers and thunderstorms are forecast to continue moistening topsoils and denting long-term drought in the Southeast, especially from western Florida and southeastern Alabama northeastward to the southern Appalachians and adjacent piedmont areas; 2) Mostly dry weather is forecast to persist in the south-central United States, including Texas, accompanied by near-normal temperatures; 3) Scattered showers will provide only limited relief to dry or drought-affected areas in the northern and central High Plains and westernmost Corn Belt; and 4) Cooler air is forecast to arrive in the Northwest, accompanied by isolated showers, but hot, mostly dry conditions will persist elsewhere in the West.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Alaska, cool and occasionally showery weather persisted for a third consecutive week, eliminating the abnormally dry (D0) area previously affecting portions of southern and interior Alaska. In Hawaii, a relatively quiet week (light, scattered showers and near-normal temperatures) in leeward areas resulted in little change in conditions that range from first-stage to severe drought (D1 to D2) from Maui westward, and first-stage to extreme drought (D1 to D3) on the Big Island (Hawaii County). Overall, July rainfall brought slight improvement from extreme to severe drought (D3 to D2) in Upcountry Maui. At the valid time of this summary (the morning of August 1), Tropical Storm Daniel was passing just north of the Hawaiian Islands, but heavy rainfall associated with the system remained mostly north of the center and away from the islands. In Puerto Rico, long-term abnormal dryness or first-stage drought (D0 or D1) continued across northern and eastern portions of the commonwealth, although recent showers totaled as much as 1 inch or more in the latter area. Nevertheless, year-to-date rainfall in San Juan through July stood at 13.99 inches, or 55 percent of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northern and Central Plains">
   <p>Beneficial rainfall, totaling an inch or more in many areas, fell across the eastern two-thirds of Nebraska and southwestern Iowa, stabilizing or improving conditions that range from abnormal dryness (D0) to severe drought (D2). A pocket of extreme drought (D3) persisted in southwestern Nebraska, while abnormal dryness and first-stage drought (D0 to D1) continued to affect the remainder of the northern and central High Plains. Drought intensification was noted in Montana, where temperatures soared to near or slightly above the 100 F mark on July 29 and 30. An area of severe drought (D2) was introduced in central Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Beneficially cooler weather overspread the region, accompanied by widespread, locally heavy rainfall in the interior South and the southern Atlantic States. Two to four inches of rain, with locally higher totals, soaked Peninsular Florida, the southern Appalachians, and the Carolinas. The rain resulted in a slight reduction of drought that ranges from mostly first-stage or severe (D1 to D2) along the southern Atlantic Coast, to extreme or exceptional (D3 to D4) in the southernmost Appalachians. More than 2 inches of rain also fell in the lower Ohio Valley, producing a slight reduction in abnormally dry (D0) to first-stage drought (D1) conditions. Some of the rain fell at such an intensity, however, to maximize runoff and reduce the effectiveness of moisture absorption into the soil profile. For example, Greenville-Spartanburg, South Carolina, netted 2.74 inches of rain in just 90 minutes on July 28, and Paducah, Kentucky, received 4.43 inches of rain on July 29. In contrast, mostly dry weather persisted from southern Texas eastward to western Alabama, resulting in slight intensification and west- and northward expansion of first-stage to extreme drought (D1 to D3). Despite the beneficial rainfall in parts of the Southeast, more than 20 percent of the more than 240 USGS river gauges in the South Atlantic-Gulf Basin (southeastern Mississippi to the Carolinas) measured record-low flows for the date on July 31, the 28th consecutive such day. As a result of major impacts on agriculture and the hydrologic cycle, exceptional drought (D4) continues from southeasternmost Louisiana to western Florida, much of central and southern Alabama, and central Georgia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Increasingly hot and continued mostly dry weather fostered the spread of dozens of wildfires in the 11-state region. Scattered thundershowers were primarily confined to the Four Corners region, where the benefits of localized soil moisture improvements were offset by lightning-sparked blazes. According to the National Interagency Fire Center, wildfires scorched approximately 3.5 million acres in the U.S. during the first 7 months of the year, more than 180 percent of the 10-year average. On July 31, more than 50 active wildfires were reported in the West, including a 77,000 acre complex near Salmon, Idaho, and blazes of more than 60,000 acres apiece near Wells, Nevada, and Kernville, California. Dead fuel moisture remained extremely low at the end of July, according to USDAs Forest Service. For 10-hour dead fuels, moisture was 2 percent or less from southern California and western Arizona, northward through the Great Basin, and into southeastern Oregon and southern Idaho. For 100-hour dead fuels, moisture was less than 5 percent in parts of each state in the West, including all of Nevada and Utah. Temperatures across the region soared in recent days under the influence of a dominant ridge of high pressure. On Sunday, July 30, all-time-record high temperatures were noted in locations such as Burley, Idaho (107 F); Tooele, Utah (106 F); and Eureka, Nevada (101 F). As a result of the continuing wildfire threat and increasing irrigation requirements, the D0(A,F) was retained across much of the Intermountain region and expanded slightly northwestward across Nevada and into southeasternmost Oregon. First-stage drought was also expanded slightly in the Intermountain West, now affecting several areas from the northern Rockies to near the Four Corners.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
