<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030612</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>For the drought areas depicted on this week's map, June 11 - 16 is expected to be wet throughout most of the Great Plains, with 1-3 inches called for in the northern and central Plains and 2-4 inches or more in southern Oklahoma and northeastern Texas. Louisiana is also expected to receive on the order of 1-2 inches statewide as well. With the dry season into full swing before the onset of the monsoon, the West is expected to see little, if any, precipitation during this time period. As for temperatures, some relief is in store for the West, with normal readings expected. However, some parts of the Intermountain West will again feel above-normal temperatures (NV, ID, WY and UT). On top of the rain in the Plains, it is also expected to remain cool here, with readings expected to be a little below normal for this time of year.</p>
   <p>The next 5 days (June 17 - 21) are expected to bring normal temperatures in the West along with normal to below-normal precipitation. In the northern Plains, above-normal temperatures are expected to return along with normal precipitation. One area that could see above-normal precipitation in this period is in eastern Montana, northeastern Wyoming and the western Dakotas. These areas could really use it, too. The southern Plains are expected to see cooler-than-normal temperatures coupled with normal precipitation. This period looks to be warm and dry for Maine. Alaska is forecast to see better chances of below-normal temperatures along with above-normal precipitation.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico, Hawaii, and Alaska">
   <p>Hawaii remains in a relatively dry pattern as only light rains visited the island chain. As of June 8, Hilo had accumulated a 28-inch deficit (49% of normal) for the year. As such, no changes are depicted this week. High pressure is expected to build into the area this week, bringing moderate trade winds with rains limited to the windward locations. Conditions in Alaska (D0) remain unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes and Northeast">
   <p>Isolated pockets of good rains (1.5-2") fell in northern Maine last week, leading to subtle short-term improvement. Long-term impacts remain as ground water levels remain low in some parts. Most of Maine stays in a DOH/D1H, or hydrological drought, as it continues its slow recovery. The better rains primarily fell to the west of the dry areas in the arrowhead of northern Minnesota, leaving conditions there unchanged for the most part.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The northern and central Plains">
   <p>All but the southern Plains saw a pleasantly cool week with many areas also receiving heavy rains because of active thunderstorms in the region. Amounts on the order of 2-4 inches were seen in eastern South Dakota, eastern Nebraska, and western Kansas. The cool, wet weather led to one-category improvement over most of these areas as the favorable weather pattern continues to bring long-overdue relief to large areas of the Plains. One area that has worsened is western Nebraska, where low soil moisture reserves and the heat of two weeks ago has led to concerns for the winter wheat crop there. Timely rains will be essential for those who can't irrigate. As a result, an "A" impact designation has been added to the pre-existing "H" in this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and interior West">
   <p>Virtually the entire West was left not only "high and dry", but also hot! An early season heat wave gripped most of the West, bringing rapid early melting of even the higher elevation snows. Actually, the abnormally warm temperatures can be traced back over a month now as unseasonably warm weather has plagued the region. Some SNOTEL snow measuring stations in central Idaho were melting at a rate of more than 2 inches a day on the warmest days. Normal melt rates in early June are usually around 1 to 1.5 inches a day.</p>
   <p>The gradual melting of the winter snowpack in the spring and summer is why the snow is so important in producing steady streamflow in the West, especially with most of the western areas receiving less than 1 inch of precipitation during the summer months. Some places are a good month ahead (or more) on their "melt out" while others didn't have much snow to melt to begin with. The downside of melting so much snow so quickly and early is that there will be less snow (if any now) to melt in late June and July in order to sustain summer streamflow levels.</p>
   <p>Changes of note in the region include a small addition of exceptional drought (D4H) in extreme southeast Utah and northeast Arizona in and around Navajo and Hopi Nation lands. El Nino didn't bring nearly enough in the way of relief to offset several sub-par years now in the Southwest as water supply concerns remain a stark reality. Restrictions are in place in several communities here and reservoirs are very low with virtually no inflow to speak of.</p>
   <p>Extreme drought (D3H) has spread eastward along the Idaho and Montana border as groundwater levels have dropped some 20 feet in some of the basins here. Farther north in Montana, the severe (D2H), moderate (D1H) and abnormally dry (D0H) conditions have again spread westward toward the continental divide.</p>
   <p>Some improvements were warranted in parts of eastern Montana and Wyoming where good rains fell. One-category improvements were seen in eastern Wyoming (to D1H and D0H) and in the northern Black Hills region (to D0H) of South Dakota as a result of good rains over the past few weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>South central Oklahoma welcomed heavy rains as 2-4 inches fell last week. Even heavier amounts (4-6"+) fell in the Texas Panhandle (severe drought (D2) eliminated here), Big Bend, and west central regions of Texas as well. To the south and east, not nearly enough rain came to offset the continued dryness along the coastal areas as severe drought (D2) has pushed eastward and merged with the existing D2 area in Louisiana. Although short-term relief in both temperatures and precipitation has been welcomed, there are still many pockets of dryness remaining throughout the region.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
