<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070607</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (June 7-11), a strong storm system crossing the northern Plains at the beginning of the period will spread drought-easing rains into Montana eastward into the Dakotas, where additional improvement in dryness is expected to continue. This same storm will bring showers to the western Great Lakes region, with potential improvement in areas of Minnesota, Wisconsin and Michigan. Outside of the northern Rockies and Cascades, the remainder of the West will generally remain devoid of significant precipitation. In the South and Southeast, only isolated to scattered showers and thunderstorms are expected, with perhaps some modest improvement possible in Florida where the frequency and coverage of daily thunderstorm activity may be somewhat higher.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlook (June 12-16) suggests a continuation of wetter than normal conditions from the northern Rockies eastward to the Great Lakes where embedded drought areas may be positively affected. Overall, somewhat cooler than average weather is expected in much of the West, while warmer weather relative to normal is expected throughout most of the East. Scattered to numerous showers and thunderstorms could slowly modify drought conditions in parts of the Southeast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Locally heavy windward showers during the past week erased D0 classification in extreme eastern Puerto Rico. Otherwise, no there were no changes to existing drought status across Alaska and Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Ohio Valley To The Gulf Coast">
   <p>Well west of Tropical Storm Barry's rain shield, this area experienced worsening conditions after another week of spotty, lackluster rainfall. Exceptional drought classification (D4) was introduced in areas of northern Alabama, while D0/D1 areas were expanded northward across the Ohio River into most of the Ohio Valley. Short-term dryness continued to expand westward into Arkansas and extending into southeastern Missouri and eastern Illinois.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Upper Midwest and Western Great Lakes">
   <p>A storm system tracking out of the northern Rockies brought additional rainfall to areas of northern Minnesota over the weekend, allowing for a continued slow improvement in conditions around the periphery of the western Great Lakes drought area. Rainfall brought a notable erosion of D0/D1 in the eastern sections of Michigans Upper Peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Tropical Storm Barry developed on the traditional start of the Atlantic hurricane season, forming on June 1 and moving across Florida then up the Atlantic Seaboard over the weekend. Heavy rainfall on the order of one to three inches fell across much of Florida, southeastern Georgia and portions of the coastal plain of the Carolinas. Locally, more than six inches of rain fell in southeastern Georgia. One-category improvements were common in these areas, although the progressive movement of Barry prevented excessive rainfall, and thus the storm failed to eliminate drought. Severe long-term hydrological drought concerns remained, as evidenced by sluggishly responding streamflows and lake levels. As of June 5, the level of Lake Okeechobee was at 8.98 feet, up slightly from the record-breaking level of 8.94 feet set last week on May 31. Elsewhere in south Florida, low well levels and lingering water supply concerns continued the socioeconomic drought in this part of the Sunshine State.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A northern storm track through the Pacific Northwest eastward into the northern Rockies continued to bring beneficial precipitation to this part of the country, lessening drought concerns across areas of Montana eastward through northeastern Wyoming and the Dakotas. Abundant precipitation in North and South Dakota virtually eliminated short-term drought concerns in the western part of these two states, although a footprint of longer-term hydrological drought remained. Elsewhere throughout the region, a seasonal lack of precipitation continued the ongoing drought classification.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
