<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070412</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecast weather that could have an impact on dry conditions during the next 2 weeks: 1) a storm system bringing widespread snow to the northern Plains on Tuesday-Wednesday, April 10-11, after the cutoff time for this weeks Monitor; 2) heavy showers in the Tennessee Valley and Southeast on Wednesday from the same storm; 3) heavy showers over the Florida Peninsula on Tuesday after the cutoff time; 3) forecast heavy showers from a second frontal system on April 14-15 across the Southeast; 4) normal to above-normal rainfall over the Southeast during week 2 (April 19-25).</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Precipitation was light in Alaska, allowing D0 dryness to persist. Snow pack in the D0 area was generally less than 70 percent of normal on April 1. Hawaii rainfall was light and below normal, allowing D0 to persist and even expand to all areas. Up to 2 inches of rain hit southwestern Puerto Rico, improving D1 to D0. D1 lingered in the southeast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>The frontal system that heralded the leading edge of the cold air coming out of Canada triggered a massive severe weather outbreak across the Tennessee and Lower Mississippi valleys on April 3. The rainfall totals of 0.5 to 1.0 inch benefited dry areas, but were not enough to change drought categories. Drier weather even led to some expansion of D2 westward into Mississippi and D1 into northern Louisiana and southeastern Arkansas. D1 drought also expanded northward from Georgia into coastal South Carolina. In Florida, widespread showers on Monday, April 9, left up to 0.27 inches of rain on the central Peninsula, but amounts were lower to the south, where D2 drought expanded westward into the Fort Myers area. Naples had seen just 1.24 inches of rain since January 1 through April 9, 5.56 inches below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>An historically cold high pressure ridge dominated the region, with temperatures averaging more than 16F below normal in the northern Plains, and snow falling as far south as central Texas. Outside of Texas, precipitation totals generally totaled less than 0.5 inches, although higher amounts in the form of snow blanketed northeastern Minnesota at the start of the period. The Texas precipitation led to a slight shrinking of the lingering D1 and D0 area in southern Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Much of the West saw above-normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation. Thermometer readings averaged up to 12F above normal in the Great Basin, while California, Nevada, and Arizona experienced light and below-normal precipitation. The result was little change in the overall drought picture, with further expansion of the drought in California, D1 drought extending northward past Redding and D2 spreading northward past Bakersfield. D3 drought persisted over much of southern California and western Arizona. The April 1 snow pack was the lowest for that date since 1988 in California. D0 dryness expanded slightly in eastern Oregon and southern Idaho as snow pack decreased. Rain or snow deposited an inch or more of liquid in parts of Utah and Colorado, but amounts were not enough to change the D0 to D1 conditions in western Colorado and D1 in Utah. Light to moderate precipitation over southern and eastern Montana and northern Wyoming contributed to a D1 to D0 improvement from eastern Montana into north-central Wyoming, as did a re-evaluation of the impacts from the late-March snow storm. Low snow pack led to development of D0 in northwest Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Heddinghaus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
