<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100513</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Precipitation this week fell mainly in the Southeast and in western New England.  Much of the South, the West, and the mid-Atlantic were dry.  A May 10 tornado outbreak impacted 16 counties in Oklahoma, including the Oklahoma City area, based on preliminary reports.  Five people were killed in the storms.  The tornadoes were accompanied by very large hail, in some locations reaching the size of softballs (about 4.25 inches in diameter).</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Precipitation is expected to move across the Midwest, into the Great Lakes, and across New England early in the May 13-17, 2010 time period.  Later in the period, the South and Southeast may see areas of precipitation. The West is expected to be dry.  Above normal temperatures will dominate much of the Southeast and areas of the Northwest during this time, while below normal temperatures are expected through the Plains, the Midwest, and into the Northeast.  Hawaii can expect a mostly dry period with the exception of some light windward showers.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (May 18-22, 2010), the odds favor cooler-than-normal conditions In the Pacific Northwest and in the Northeast.  Warmer-than-normal conditions are expected from the Rockies, across the central and northern Plains, and into the Midwest and parts of the Southeast.  The odds of above-normal precipitation extend from the Pacific Northwest, across the northern Plains, through the Missouri and Mississippi River valleys and into the Southeast, extending to the Gulf of Mexico.  Odds favor below-normal precipitation in the upper Midwest and into the mid-Atlantic and Northeast.  Odds favor above normal temperatures and below normal precipitation in most of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought conditions remained unchanged across Alaska and Puerto Rico this week.  While parts of Alaska did receive 200 – 300 percent of their normal precipitation this week, that amounted to only a few tenths of an inch and had little impact on the larger deficits there.  The lingering effects of the El Nino are still being felt in Hawaii.  No changes were made except on Kauai where improved pasture conditions resulted in a slight pull-back of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1).  Evergreen vegetation in the exceptional drought (D4) region of the Big Island has been described as looking like a Christmas Tree on New Year’s Day.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Precipitation across New York and into most parts of non-coastal New England alleviated moderate drought (D1) and abnormally dry (D0) conditions along the Great Lakes.  The mid-Atlantic and much of the Southeast saw little precipitation.  As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) increased through the Carolinas and extended up into southern Virginia.  Areas of southern Alabama and Georgia, and northern Florida saw heavy rains with some areas receiving over six inches, or 800% of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Some of the drought-affected areas of the region received beneficial precipitation this week.  Precipitation fell in central and west-central Wisconsin and across northern Michigan.  Some areas received upwards of two inches, which is 200 – 300 percent of normal.  However, continued long-term deficits resulted in unchanged drought classifications in this region.  Rains in the eastern Great Lakes, especially in New York, resulted in drought improvement.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>For the most part, the northern Plains experienced areas of normal to above normal precipitation while most of the central and southern Plains received below normal precipitation this week.  Parts of extreme northwestern Missouri saw upwards of 3 inches of rain.  Conversely, most of Louisiana and Texas saw little or no precipitation.  This resulted in increases in the extent of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1), with moderate drought (D1) now covering most of Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Storms dropped precipitation across much of the Northwest Coast, from northern California to western Washington, as well as through eastern Montana and much of Wyoming.  This improved conditions in Montana with abnormal dryness (D0) disappearing from most of the eastern part of the state.  Improvements in abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) were also evident in southwest Oregon and central and western Idaho.  This area is still dominated by below normal streamflow and snowpack, and overall water-year precipitation deficits.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
