<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000113</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Parts of this region are expecting their first significant snow event of the winter later this week as a relatively strong system pushes out into the Northern Plains and across the Great Lakes, the Ohio River Valley, and into the Northeast. Incredibly, many spots in the Northeast haven't even seen snow yet this winter. The outlook for the next 6-10 days generally calls for warmer temperatures and little if any precipitation across most of this region. The continued dry and warm winter has once again elevated concerns of wild fires in Nebraska and surrounding states.</p>
   <p>A very strong jet stream has settled in across northern California, which will bring changes to the drier northern tier states here over the next week. A strong system was bringing plenty of rain, to the lower elevations, and snow to areas of the central Sierras and points both northward into Idaho and eastward into Wyoming as of 1/11 and 1/12. This pattern looks like it will hold over the next week or two as moisture from the Gulf of Alaska clashes with the warm air from the south bringing mild temperatures and plenty of moisture and snow to northern California, Nevada, Utah, southern Idaho, Oregon and much of Washington. Most of the Southwest and Four Corner states can expect to see no change in their luck as temperatures should remain well above normal and no precipitation is expected through late January.</p>
   <p>Hawaii should experience gradual improvement over the next few months as seasonal rains continue.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>D1 (first stage drought) conditions persist across many parts of the central and eastern Hawaii Islands. The only significant precipitation seen last week was isolated on the northern side of the Big Island (Hilo). Very little was seen across the rest of the island chain.</p>
   <p>Parts of northern and western Alaska are also seeing low snowpacks at this time with the Koyukuk Basin showing just 56% of normal accumulated precipitation from October 1,1999 to present.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Eastern States">
   <p>The entire eastern half of the U.S. enjoyed another very warm week. Temperature departures varied anywhere from 6 to 15 degrees above normal across the region. Differences, however, were seen in the amount and distribution of precipitation that fell over the last seven days. A generous storm system brought 1-4 inches of rain to parts of SE Texas on a line northeastward up into Maine.</p>
   <p>For the most part, core areas experiencing severe drought (D2) at this time weren't in the path of the systems producing the needed precipitation. Conditions have continued to deteriorate in central and western Nebraska where many areas have received less than 25% of normal precipitation since September 1 while also experiencing a very warm winter to this point. As a result, both the areas of first stage (D1) and severe (D2) drought have slowly pushed westward. The exceptions to this pattern's stranglehold is found in SE Texas where some relief came last week to the severe drought (D2) there but it is too early to tell if any significant recovery will occur just yet. Also, parts of Alabama, Georgia (severe droughtD2) and the Carolinas welcomed beneficial rains. Recovery continued in areas affected by first-stage drought (D1) as rains fell on the affected parts of southeast Missouri, southern Illinois, western Tennessee, northern Kentucky, and southern Indiana and Ohio. As a result, the first stage drought (D1) has receded back off of the Ohio River. On the whole, average streamflow levels in the regions currently seeing dryness or drought remained quite low.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>Precipitation last week across the West was limited to the higher elevations and coastal regions of Oregon and Washington. The higher elevations in Idaho, Utah and Wyoming also saw light amounts of precipitation. Colorado continues to hope for a change in this pattern, which would lead to a boost in snowpack there. For most of the states in the West, it has been another very slow start to the snowpack season. Concerns have elevated recently from northern California eastward into Colorado, but there are still three months to go in the snowpack season and things can change in a hurry.</p>
   <p>Abnormally dry conditions (D0) expanded to cover most of California, the western half of Nevada, southern Utah and most all of Arizona and New Mexico in what is being seen as a repeat so far to the winter of 1998-99. Unlike last winter however, the dryness has been felt further north into the Sierra Nevada and Cascade ranges, which saw a bumper snowpack season in many places just a year ago. Snowpack levels are generally well below 70% in most basins across the West, but fears have been tempered somewhat by above average reservoir storage in these same areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
