<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070614</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (June 13-17), moderate to locally heavy rains are expected in most areas from southern Florida northward to the central Appalachians and Piedmont, across the northwestern Great Lakes region and adjacent Plains, and along part of the central Gulf Coast. Normal precipitation, at best, is expected in other areas of dryness and drought across the lower 48 states, with little or no precipitation anticipated in most of the dry areas from the Rockies westward, and in the dry areas across much of the upper South, Tennessee Valley, middle and lower Ohio Valley, and adjacent Midwest.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (June 18-22), the odds favor surplus precipitation in the Great Lakes region, along the central Gulf Coast, and in the lower Mississippi Valley while below-normal precipitation seems more likely in central and southwestern sections of Alaska. In other parts of the nation, the outlook for this period is uncertain, with neither wetter nor drier than normal conditions favored.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Generally 1 to 3 inches of precipitation ended D0 conditions in east-central Alaska and northeastern Puerto Rico, but lesser precipitation amounts elsewhere allowed D0 conditions from last week to persist.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Continued below-normal precipitation and increasing water supply concerns prompted the introduction of D2 conditions in parts of southern Maui and northern sections of the Big Island while D1 was expanded to cover the remainder of the Big Island, more of central Maui, and western Molokai. D0 to D1 conditions persisted across the rest of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern and Eastern United States">
   <p>In the broad area of dryness and drought that has come to encompass a large section of the southern and eastern United States, heavy rains brought relief to some areas on the western, northern, and southeastern fringes of the area (across western Arkansas, eastern Oklahoma, southern Missouri, parts of northeastern Ohio and west-central Pennsylvania, and the Florida Peninsula) but conditions persisted or intensified elsewhere. Moderate to heavy rains fell on scattered sections of southwestern Georgia, southeastern Alabama, and Louisiana as well as isolated sites elsewhere (primarily from the Appalachians eastward), but only light rain was reported across the vast majority of the region. As a result, D0 expanded northward to include central and southern Illinois, and the coverage of each drought intensity level from D1 through D4 expanded (primarily northward and southward) from the central Gulf Coast northward through most of the Ohio Valley. With the last two months being the driest such period since 1988 in many areas, reports of water restrictions and crop stress are reaching northward past the Ohio River as far as central Indiana. Farther south, dry conditions date back much longer, and as a result, agricultural impacts and water supply concerns are more common. According to the U.S. Department of Agriculture, corn and soybeans have yet to be severely affected throughout any given state, although almost one-quarter of Tennessee corn is in poor or very poor condition; however, some other crops, pasture conditions, and streamflows all reflect serious regional drought impacts. In Alabama, 68 percent of the cotton crop, 48 percent of peanuts, and 78 percent of pastures are in poor or very poor condition, as are 60 percent of Florida peanuts and 35 percent of Georgia cotton. The proportion of pastures in poor or very poor condition ranges from almost half to more than three-quarters in six southeastern states (MS, KY, TN, FL, GA, and AL) while four additional adjacent states (WV, IN, SC, and NC) report at least one-quarter of pastures in poor or very poor condition.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Broad-scale moderate to locally heavy precipitation abetted drought relief in many areas across the northern Intermountain West, the northern Great Basin, the central and northern Rockies, and parts of the northern High Plains. Numerous locations across southern Montana, the lower Idaho Peninsula, adjacent sections of Wyoming and North Dakota, and a few sites near the Great Salt Lake recorded 2 to 4 inches of precipitation, with locally higher amounts. As a result, former D0 to D1 conditions improved across much of the Dakotas, parts of southern Montana, and portions of northern Wyoming. Farther south, only light precipitation fell on the central tier of the West, and little or no rain was reported from the lower elevations of California and central sections of Nevada, Utah, and western Colorado southward to the Mexican border.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western Great Lakes">
   <p>Scattered moderate to locally heavy precipitation fell primarily on northwestern parts of the region while most sites received only light amounts. Declining drought-related impacts brought on by recent precipitation led t the elimination of D3 conditions in extreme northern Minnesota, improvements from D2 to D1 conditions across interior northeastern Minnesota and northwestern Wisconsin, and generalized 1-category improvements to the D0 to D2 conditions in northwestern Minnesota. In contrast, drought classifications persisted or worsened farther to the south and east, with D0 conditions encompassing the Twin Cities area, and conditions on the Keweenaw Peninsula in northwestern Michigan deteriorated to D2.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
