<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20071115</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather that could affect dry or drought areas over the next 2 weeks includes: 1) ongoing rains from a frontal system tracking eastward through the East, resulting in 0.5 to 1 inch of rain during November 14-16 from northern parts of Alabama and Georgia through Tennessee and Kentucky and Virginia. More than 1 inch is forecast from Pennsylvania to New England. 2) Over 1 inch of rain during November 14-19 in Idaho and western Montana, with slightly lower totals in eastern Oregon and central Montana. 3) Abnormally dry, warm weather over the Southwest and Colorado during November 14-19, but above-normal precipitation forecast for the Rockies and central states during November 20-24 and for the Great Plains to the Ohio and Tennessee valleys for November 22-28.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drier weather took hold over most of Hawaii following the heavy rains of the prior week, but moderate rains over the Big Island contributed to the D1 drought pulling back to northern parts of the island. A reassessment shows that a sliver of D1 remains over east Oahu due to ongoing mandatory restrictions for users of irrigation water from the Waimanalo system.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Over one-half inch rain fell in southern New England and western Pennsylvania, but this was not enough to significantly affect the dry areas, although the moisture reduced some of the western flank of the D0 area in Pennsylvania. D1 drought lingered in southern New England.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Short-term dryness resulted in southward expansion of D2 drought in western North Dakota. Continued dryness also led to some expansion of D2 and D1 in the Nebraska Panhandle and D0 in eastern Colorado, northwest Kansas, and southwest Nebraska. With many locations reporting less than 25 percent of normal rainfall during the past 60 days, D0 dryness expanded into southern and central parts of Texas. Soil moisture is a concern with the winter wheat crop there. Southeast of the Panhandle, for example, the Northern Low Plains area reported topsoil moisture at 62 percent very short. Temperatures in the High Plains averaged 4 to 8 degrees or more above normal for the week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, Ohio and lower Missouri Valleys">
   <p>This was a mostly dry week over the D4 (Exceptional) drought areas in the Southeast. In fact, Alabama, Georgia, and South Carolina have been virtually rainless so far this month. With temperatures below normal in the Southeast, and little evaporation, the lack of rain did not have a major impact on the drought, but drought intensity did expand by about one category over southern parts of Alabama and Georgia due to dropping stream flows. In addition, the D4 area increased in western South Carolina, and the D2/D3/D4 areas expanded slightly in North Carolina. Nearly 60 percent of the streams in Georgia reported record lows for this time of the year on November 13. More than one-half of the streams in South Carolina measured record lows, as did more than one-third in Alabama. In North Carolina, 283 water systems are under restrictions - nearly 80% of the state population, the most since record-keeping began. Due to low streamflows, D1 drought expanded into central Virginia. D0 and D1 also edged westward in Mississippi.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation spread across much of the West outside of the arid Southwest and the mountains of Colorado. Temperatures averaged 4 to 8 degrees or more above normal over the interior West. With 60-day precipitation well above normal, D3 drought was eliminated from eastern Idaho. D2 transitioned to D1 in north-central Idaho. D2 receded in eastern Oregon. The moisture eliminated the D3 areas in Montana, and D1 improved to D0 in southwestern Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
