<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070315</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>For March 14-19, a strong upper-level ridge will become entrenched over the western U.S. with a trough over the East.  Pacific storm systems will be deflected into the Pacific Northwest and British Columbia coast, leaving most of the western U.S. warm and dry.  Cooler-than-normal temperatures will dominate the eastern third of the country.  A couple of storm systems will move across the eastern third of the country, bringing an inch or less of precipitation to most areas.  An inch or more of precipitation is expected along part of the Gulf Coast, the Northeast Coast, and the central Appalachians, but rainfall amounts are not believed to be significant enough to erase long-term deficits, or even deficits back only 30 days.</p>
   <p>For March 20-27, warmer-than-average temperatures are expected to spread across the Lower 48 States, with Alaska remaining colder than normal.  Dry weather is forecast for much of the West, the East Coast, and western Alaska, with wetter-than-normal conditions from the southern Plains to Great Lakes and southern Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Much of interior Alaska continued dry this week.  D0 was expanded to the north, east, and west in the Yukon Basin to better match the pattern of low snowpack and precipitation deficits of the last 3 to 6 months.  As of March 12, snow water equivalent was 42% of average over Koyukuk Basin and 55% of average over Chena Basin, with water year cumulative precipitation at 60% and 54%, respectively.  In Hawaii, several stations received an inch or more of rain during the last 7 days, but 30-day and longer departures are still significantly negative, so the D0 was left unchanged.  Vegetation was turning brown due to the persistent dryness over Puerto Rico.  But showers this week helped abate the recent spate of wildfires, so the Puerto Rican depiction remained unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Rainfall in recent weeks across much of the Southeast has not been sufficient to relieve the deficits that have accumulated over the last 60 days to 12 months.  Low streamflows and soil moisture will be further stressed as temperatures and evapotranspiration rise, and wildfires had flared up over parts of Florida, the southern Appalachians, and Gulf coast.  This week saw an expansion of D0 across central Georgia, western Tennessee, northeastern Kentucky, southern Alabama, all of Mississippi, and southern West Virginia.  D0 moved up the South Carolina coast, across most of North Carolina and much of Virginia and the Delmarva Peninsula, and into the Florida panhandle.  D1 expanded into southwest Virginia, western North Carolina, much of Alabama, and southern Mississippi, mainly into areas that had the greatest precipitation deficits.  These areas had deficits of 4 to 12 inches at 90 days, and even more at longer periods.  Deficits were even as great as 3 to 6 inches for the last 60 days, and some areas were 4 to 6 inches below normal for the last 30 days.  D1 also expanded across much of southern Florida, and a spot of D2 was added over Martin and St. Lucie counties in Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States and Southern Plains">
   <p>Heavy rains fell from a surface and upper low which slowly rotated across the southern Plains, with some stations reporting over 5 inches.  Most of the rain fell to the east of the D3 extreme drought area in south central Texas.  But D3-D2-D1-D0 were eroded where 2 inches or more of rain fell.  D0 in the northern Low Rolling Plains of Texas retreated under 2-inch rains.  Heavy rains also cut into the D2 in central Oklahoma.  D0 was added to south central Oklahoma near the Red River, which has persistently missed the recent rains, bridging the D0 areas in Oklahoma and northern Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The rainy season across much of the Southwest has been very dry.  By March 8, the driest rain season to date was reported at several stations in southern California, including downtown Los Angeles (2.42 inches of rain, down 9.13 inches), Long Beach airport (1.59 inches, down 8.70 inches), Los Angeles airport (2.18 inches, down 8.31 inches), and Burbank airport (2.33 inches, down 10.82 inches).  The extreme dryness was coupled with hot temperatures and very windy conditions which prompted Red Flag/Fire Weather warnings for southern California, where two large wildfires and several smaller blazes threatened homes in Orange and Riverside counties.  The above-normal temperatures caused many river flows to increase because of early melt of the below-normal snowpack.  In spite of the below-average precipitation this water year, especially in southern California, reservoir levels were near average across the Golden State due to a combination of above-average precipitation last year and good water management decisions since then.  As of March 11, the projected median April-July snowmelt runoff for Californias water supply basins remained low, ranging from 85% (Shasta Lake inflow in the north) to 46% (Kern River in the south).</p>
   <p>An area of D3 was introduced into southern California and adjacent Arizona where the deficits were greatest.  D2 was expanded in southern California and Arizona, and a spot of D2 was added in Nevada near Reno.  D1 grew in Arizona, central Nevada, northern California, southern coastal California, and extreme southern Utah.  D0 nudged into southwest New Mexico.  Slight adjustments were made to the D0-D1-D2 boundaries in Montana to better reflect the short- and long-term moisture conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
