<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040805</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include... 1) refreshing Canadian air will settle in and give us a taste of fall over much of the eastern half of the country, leading to a much cooler weather pattern while warmer-than-normal temperatures are expected west of the Rockies over the next seven days; 2) precipitation over the same period is expected to be most likely across the Texas Panhandle, eastern New Mexico and southern Colorado, where amounts could reach or exceed 1 to 2 inches; 3) looking out over the next 10 days, we can expect below-normal temperatures to persist east of the Missouri and Mississippi Rivers, while above-normal temperatures will once again frequent the High Plains all the way over to the Pacific coast as a result of classic ridging over the Rockies and troughing over the East; 4) precipitation over the same period should bring a mixed bag of results, with improvement likely in the southern Plains (from Nebraska down to the Gulf Coast). Otherwise, dryness would still seem to be in the cards for the Southeast, the High Plains and most of the West, save for southern Arizona and parts of extreme southern New Mexico, where precipitation is forecasted to be above normal.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Some nice rains were reported last weeks over parts of the abnormally dry (D0) area in the interior, but they arent enough to reverse the 90- to 180-day deficit accrual, so the situation remains the same.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England and The Southeast">
   <p>All in all, it was a relatively uneventful week in the New England area. The light rains that fell across parts of the region and along the coastal areas of Maine werent enough to erase the long-term abnormally dry (D0 H) conditions that exist there.</p>
   <p>Down the coast into the Mid-Atlantic, the rains of Hurricane Alex brought a lot of wind but not much rain. Most of the better rains (2 inches plus) were being reported along northern coastal North Carolina around Cape Hatteras and up the Virginia coast. These rains were enough to stave off introduction of abnormally dry conditions, which are most noted between Wilmington to Cape Hatteras along the North Carolina Outer Banks.</p>
   <p>A hot, dry week in central Georgia (and Alabama) has led to the expansion of abnormally dry (D0) conditions there as it again pushes south and west into central parts of the state and into east central Alabama as well. In fact, July was quite dry, with many locations across Georgia seeing less than half their normal amount of precipitation (Atlanta, 2.2" or 43% of normal and Augusta, 1.54" or 38% of normal). Macon, GA, reported just .67" on the month, leaving them with their second driest July on record. Some streams, crops and the top soil moisture levels are beginning to feel the effects of this dryness, making this an area to keep an eye on for drought development as we move into late summer.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Far Western States">
   <p>On the heels of recent improvement in New Mexico and Texas, the effects of an ill-tempered monsoon have been disappointing up to this point for most, especially in the Southwest. While areas on the eastern fringes have benefitted to a degree, many have been left high and dry instead. July was generally cool from New Mexico up to eastern Montana, which has helped ease the situation, given the lack of moisture. In fact, Great Falls, MT, broke its July record of consecutive days of non-measurable precipitation with 24 straight to close out the month. An even greater emphasis will be put on the upcoming winter as we wind down what is looking to be another very dry water year for most everyone in the West. In addition, for the Pacific Northwest and Great Basin states the heat has been on for most of the past month or so with departures of 2 to 5 degrees F above normal (or more in some places) for the month being reported from northern Nevada and California up into Oregon, Idaho and Washington.</p>
   <p>Very little in the way of the drought depiction has changed from last week as the region is basically in its dry season (except for those monsoon states), but some deterioration has been noted on this weeks map. This can be seen mostly in the form of an expansion of moderate (D1), severe (D2), and extreme (D3) drought in northern New Mexico and southwestern Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The High Plains and Central States">
   <p>Spotty rains avoided most of the drought areas in this region last week. In addition, the last week saw a return of the heat across most of the Plains and Midwest. After a very unseasonably cool July (2 to 5 degrees F cooler than normal), August was ushered in with a wave of near-triple digit temperatures across the Plains. In short, nothing has changed to reverse the slowly eroding situation in the western Plains from the Nebraska Panhandle northward up into the Badlands and up the front range of the Rockies into Wyoming and Montana as well. On top of the long multi-year drought that has plagued western Nebraska, Wyoming and Montana, short-term dryness (last 60 to 90 days) has once again reared its ugly head as most of this region has only seen 40-60% of normal precipitation dating back to last October. As a result, a slow general eastward expansion of abnormally dry (D0), moderate (D1), severe (D2), and extreme (D3) drought has been reflected in Nebraska and the Dakotas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
