<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000615</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Features to watch in the next 10-day period include: 1) thunderstorms moving across the Midwest and Mid-Mississippi Valley early in the period will bring beneficial rains to the D3 and D2 areas in the region, except in central and western Nebraska; 2) likewise, beneficial rains will occur in the Red River Valley of North Dakota and Minnesota early in the period; 3) continued dryness over much of the Southwest and West through the period, including the D3 region in Texas and New Mexico; 4) the Climate Prediction Center (CPC) releases its Climate Outlooks for July and the July-September period on Thursday, June 15; and 5) CPC also releases its Seasonal Drought Outlook on Friday, June 16.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Long-term dryness continues to occur across all of Hawaii. As a result of deteriorating conditions, a region of D3 (extreme drought) for agricultural and wildfire related impacts now exists on the leeward sides of Maui and the Island of Hawaii. Intensification to D2 (severe drought) conditions occurred on parts of the Islands of Kauai, Niihau, and Hawaii. D1 and D0 conditions remain in the rest of the state. In Honolulu, a 40-inch deficit has built up since November 1, 1997, which is 33% of normal for the 31-month period. In Puerto Rico, abnormally dry (D0) conditions continue along the northern side of the island. More than an inch of rain fell in San Juan during the week, but deficits remain for June and an 8-inch deficit (59% of normal) exists for the year-to-date.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>The pattern bringing rainfall across Minnesota, northeastern Iowa, northern Illinois, southern Wisconsin, and the Lower Peninsula of Michigan continued as in previous weeks. North and south of this region, it remained dry for most of the week, with thunderstorms becoming more numerous over the weekend in most of the Midwest. Hot, dry, and very windy conditions occurred in the western Corn Belt June 6-9, with temperatures nearing and exceeding 100F. As a result, drought conditions intensified westward into southwestern Nebraska and western Kansas. Statewide values in Nebraska for the conditions of winter wheat, corn, soybeans, sorghum, and pastures all decreased significantly over the week. An area of first stage drought (D1) also now exists along the Red River Valley in North Dakota and Minnesota. An area of extreme drought (D3) has emerged in south-central Missouri.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>Another dry week took place across most of the Southeast, except in southern Florida, where there was some relief from the drought conditions. Even though temperatures averaged below normal for the week, the drought intensity was increased to D4 (exceptional drought) for a large part of Georgia, extreme southeastern Alabama, and parts of northwestern Florida. Streamflows in this region are exceeding all-time lows. Year-to-date deficits and their corresponding percentages of normal in five cities across the South include New Orleans (18.37 in., 32%); Baton Rouge (17.31 in., 36%); Mobile (12.51 in., 56%); Pensacola (15.33 in., 41%); and Macon (10.86 in., 52%).</p>
   <p>Residual moisture from Tropical Depression #1 streamed into Texas, generally over regions that have already seen drought eliminated during the past month. Some additional relief occurred in the north-central part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Western States">
   <p>Little precipitation fell during the past week across the western United States. Regions of drought exist in Arizona, New Mexico, and Montana. In addition, abnormally dry areas exist in Wyoming, Colorado, and Utah. Wildfires are the main concern across these regions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
