<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100812</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (August 12-16) above normal temperatures will continue to dominate most of the country in a typical August weather pattern.  The warmest temperatures are expected over the Ohio River valley and in the Pacific Northwest, with departures from 9 to 12 degrees Fahrenheit above normal.  Cool conditions will continue along the Pacific coast of California and in the upper High Plains states.  A tropical depression is projected to arrive along the Gulf Coast and move inland over Mississippi, bringing with it significant amounts of rain.  Much of the High Plains and eastern United States are looking at widespread precipitation over the period, with the greatest amounts over Iowa and Minnesota, Kansas and Kentucky.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (August 17-21) shows a cool down over the central plains, and below normal temperature expected to continue over the California coast and western Alaska.  Temperatures are showing the best chances to be above normal over the Great Basin, East Coast and Gulf Coast regions.  The best chances for above normal precipitation are projected to be over the East Coast and western Alaska and below normal over the Great Basin.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes were made in any of these regions this week, but conditions in Hawaii were not improving and drought related impacts are being felt over many of the Islands.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="High Plains">
   <p>In response to the heat and dryness over the last few weeks, an area of D0 was introduced into north central South Dakota as local reports of stressed crops with yield losses are becoming abundant in this area.  Many areas in Nebraska and South Dakota are being impacted by the heat and dryness over the last 2-4 weeks and some areas are seeing agricultural impacts developing rapidly.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>North Carolina had a mix of areas with significant rainfall and those who missed out completely or were below normal this week.  The northern coastal plain of North Carolina had D1 shift to the east, all the way to the coast, while D0 was extended south along the coast and into South Carolina.  Georgia had the area of D1 in the western portions of the state extend into Alabama and join the D1 in southern Alabama.  Also in Georgia, D0 and D1 were extended across the southern part of the state and into northern Florida.  The D0 in southeast Georgia was connected to the D0 along the Atlantic coast in Florida and the D1 was also extended along the Florida coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>Temperatures remained well above normal throughout the region and most places were dry over the last week.  In Alabama, D0 and D1 were extended in the southern portion of the state, bringing D0 all the way to the southern coast.  D0 was extended in Mississippi, bridging the two previous D0 areas in Alabama and western Mississippi.  For Texas, D0 was improved in northeast Texas in response to rains over the last several weeks and D0 was extended to the southwest in the eastern portions of Texas as this area continued to miss out on the rains while observing significant heat.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Scattered precipitation helped keep drought from intensifying in the region.  Some degradation did take place, as D1 was introduced in Maine because soil moisture and streamflow indicators are in the lower percentiles.  In northeast Pennsylvania, D0 and D1 were extended to the north, with D0 reaching into southern New York as this area remained dry. Temperatures that are well above normal are rapidly changing conditions in the region, and without rain, the drought is going to persist and maybe intensify.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>D0 was introduced in north central Montana in response to recent dryness and hydrological concerns being felt in the region. Improvements to the D0 in western and southern Montana were made as the abnormally dry conditions have subsided.   Improvements were made in Arizona this week; D1 was eliminated from Apache County and categorical improvements were made to the D1 and D2 in Navajo County as the monsoon rains have eased drought related impacts in this part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
