<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040708</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas  experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) the western United States will remain mostly dry through the period; 2) the monsoon in the Southwest may become established across New Mexico and Arizona late in the period (July 13-17), or about a week and a half later than normal; 3) temperatures and precipitation amounts should remain seasonable across Alaska, providing some potential relief for firefighters battling wildfires burning in the eastern part of the state; 4) upper air disturbances will move across the northern Plains and Great Lakes July 9-13, providing opportunities for precipitation across northern Minnesota; and 5) a system moving into the Northeast July 7 could provide generous precipitation in eastern Maine July 8-9.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Temperatures remained above normal across the state along with little precipitation, although conditions moderated as the week ended . The D0 region was expanded westward toward the Fairbanks area. Since June 1, Fairbanks has only received 0.31 inches of precipitation (19% of normal). Meanwhile, it was also the second warmest June on record. Currently, seven large fire incidents are occurring across east-central Alaska. Thus far during 2004, the state has experienced 350 fires that have burned a total of 1.98 million acres.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Seasonably normal precipitation totals fell across Maine during the past week. However, long-term precipitation deficits remain and no changes were made to the D0 area covering the eastern part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Long-term dryness continues across northern Minnesota. In spite of some precipitation during the past week, abnormally dry (D0) and Moderate Drought (D1) conditions expanded into the northeastern corner of the state. Duluth had its 6th driest June on record (1.88 inches, 44% of normal) and International Falls had its 7th driest June (1.55 inches, 39% or normal).</p>
   <p>Across the High Plains, frequent thunderstorm activity and cooler-than-normal temperatures during the past week were welcomed in much of the area. As a result, there was some improvement in drought conditions across southeastern Wyoming, western South Dakota, western Nebraska, and northwestern Kansas. Rain amounts greater than 4.0 inches fell in northwest Kansas and the Extreme Drought (D3) classification was removed from the area. Agricultural conditions have improved in western Kansas and Nebraska, but serious long-term hydrological impacts remain. In contrast, the week was dry across North Dakota, and drought conditions deteriorated somewhat in the southwestern part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Generous precipitation amounts fell across Georgia and South Carolina for another week, further improving drought and dryness conditions. Augusta, GA, received a record high 10.59 inches of precipitation during June. The Moderate Drought (D1) classification was completely removed from both states. In southern Florida, however, conditions remain dry. Key West has only received 2.41 inches of precipitation since June 1, which is only 47% of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>Generally, little precipitation fell across the western United States during the past week. Meanwhile, temperatures for the week were well above normal in Washington. This combination helped cause an expansion of Moderate Drought (D1) conditions in north-central Washington.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
