<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001228</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The strong negative North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) weather pattern should continue into early January as the blocking regime over the North Atlantic holds. Consequently, temperatures are forecast to remain below-normal across the eastern two-thirds of the Nation while above-normal temperatures persist in the West. Systems predicted to affect the Nations drought areas include: 1) During Tuesday-Thursday, low pressure may bring significant precipitation to the southern Plains and Southeast, including rain in central and northern Florida. 2) A second storm system may develop in the Southwest and reorganize over the western Gulf of Mexico early next week, bringing more precipitation to the southern Plains and Gulf Coast states. 3) In the interim, a strong disturbance is predicted to affect the central Plains, bringing more snow to parts of the Corn Belt Thursday and Friday, and weekend lake-effect snows in favored Great Lakes locations. 4) The thermal boundary set-up in the north-central Rockies may produce light snow in the central Rockies and High Plains over the weekend. 5) With high pressure persisting, no immediate relief is expected in Hawaii and Puerto Rico.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>High pressure and trade winds prevailed during most of the week, except during December 20-21 when light showers (generally 0.25 to 1 inches) broke a several week dry spell across abnormally dry areas of Molokai, Lanai, western Maui, and the northwestern part of the Big Island. The showers stabilized the dryness, but were not enough to provide any significant relief. In Puerto Rico, high pressure north of the island produced easterly trades and widely-scattered light showers that kept abnormal dryness intact across southwestern and north-central areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley and Mid-Atlantic, and Appalachians">
   <p>After light snow (liquid equivalent 0.2-0.5 inches) fell on eastern areas Tuesday, Arctic air enveloped the entire region, producing fair and very cold conditions (single-digit lows and double-digit negative departures). In the southern Appalachians, streamflows dropped from above-normal levels after mid-month storminess back to near-record low levels on Tuesday after just one relatively dry week, highlighting the endurance of the long-term drought. With tranquil weather following a wet week, drought remained unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Arctic air (sub-zero lows and temperatures averaging 10 to 20F below normal) and storm systems continued to frequent the Midwest and Great Lakes region, dropping light to moderate snows on parts of the western and central Corn Belts (liquid equivalent 0.2-0.7 inches), while moderate to heavy lake-enhanced snows (liquid equivalent 0.5-1.8 inches) whitened the Upper Peninsula of Michigan. With 1-2 feet of snow covering much of Iowa (an average of 19.8 inches has fallen statewide through the 21st, already making this the snowiest December ever), and 2-3 feet blanketing northwestern Michigan, enough moisture is in the bank to provide future drought relief in central Iowa and around the Keweenaw Peninsula region of Michigan once thawing occurs.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>With the exception of a minor mid-week Gulf Coast system and a developing storm in the southern Great Plains by weeks end, dry and cold weather (temperatures averaging 10 to 18F below normal, freezing as far south as Lake Okeechobee) prevailed across the Southeast. With yet another dry week across most of Florida (0 to 0.1 inches), continued record or near-record low streamflows, reports of dropping lake and well levels, and even a 2600 acre wildfire near Haines City, severe to exceptional drought (D2-D4) slightly increased across north-central portions of the state. In contrast, additional rainfall (0.5 to 0.8 inches) on top of moderate totals the previous week alleviated dryness or eased drought in parts of Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama, while changes in southeastern Georgia were made to better represent long-term drought indicators. Farther west, a winter storm dumped moderate precipitation (between 0.3 and 0.8 inches) on central New Mexico and western Texas, providing some relief from drought or abnormal dryness, but southern Texas remained mostly dry.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West:">
   <p>A ridge of high pressure persisted over the Southwest, veering most Pacific storm systems northeastward into British Columbia and then southeastward into the Rockies. More snows blanketed the northern and central Rockies (liquid equivalent 1-2 inches), further decreasing dryness in western and southern Wyoming and southwestern Montana as both 3-month SNOTEL basin precipitation and December 25 basin snow water content approached normal. In the Oregon Cascades, enough snow fell to boost December 25 basin snow water content to 85-95% of normal, but mild and mostly dry weather in the Sierra Nevada dropped snow water contents to or below half of normal. After an unseasonably wet October, November and December have been quite dry, but the majority of the Far West wet season still remains.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
