<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070201</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (February 1-5) cold air is going to settle in over much of the United States.  Average temperatures are forecasted to be below normal for most locations except for south Florida and the Pacific Northwest.  Departures from normal will range from 15-20F below normal over the Plains to 3-6F below normal over the East Coast.  Precipitation amounts are expected to be greatest over the southeast portion of the United States and continued dry through much of the West.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (February 6-10) a long-wave ridge over the west and a trough over the central and eastern United States are expected to maintain cold air over much of country with the coldest temperatures in the northeast.  Temperatures should remain above normal for much of the West and Alaska.  Precipitation during this time period is expected to be varied, with below-normal precipitation over the Southeast, New England, the Southwest and the northern Plains as well as in Alaska.  The shift of the long wave ridge to the east should also allow above-normal precipitation over much of California, the northern Rocky Mountains, and the Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="The Midwest, High Plains and Appalachians">
   <p>A dry week over the region has resulted in little change to the drought status.  Temperatures were seasonal for the Midwest and Appalachians, with above-normal temperatures for much of the High Plains and average temperatures 5-10F above normal.  Short-term dryness continues to plague much of the region, but little impact has resulted so far.  D0 was extended in Kentucky, covering more of the eastern part of the state and into western West Virginia and the Maryland Panhandle.  D3 conditions were extended in northeast Wyoming where low snowpack and water concerns are prevalent.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>Precipitation remains ample along the southern jet stream, bringing continued relief along the Gulf Coast.  In Texas, 3-5 inches of rain this week has allowed for further improvements to the region.  D0 conditions were removed along the coast and moved inland.  D1, D2 and D3 conditions in south Texas were all improved, pushing the gradient farther to the west.  In Oklahoma, D0 was extended into the southwest portion of the state.  There has been very little hydrological response in this region to the recent rains, with many lakes still at historical low elevations. Lake Altus is still at 18% of capacity, with Lake Tom Steed and Lake Waurika at 40% and 79% of capacity, respectively.  In north-central Oklahoma, there has been a positive response to recent precipitation, and this has allowed for some improvement to the drought designations in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Rocky Mountains">
   <p>A dry week over much of the West and Rocky Mountains.  Temperatures recovered from the arctic blast over much of the region, with most areas normal to slightly below normal.  In Montana, conditions continue to worsen in the southern part of the state.  Low snowpack is raising some concern.  D1 and D2 conditions shifted farther to the north, leaving much of the southern part of Montana in D2.  In the north-central part of the state, conditions have improved enough to reduce the D1 area to D0.</p>
   <p>The dry winter continued in Nevada and California.  Abnormally dry (D0) conditions were migrated to the east, now covering most of Nevada.  Dryness continued as well over the Sierra Mountains and into California.  Low snowpack in the Sierra Mountains along with very dry conditions in California has allowed for expansion of D1 conditions into the central valley and along the coast.  A very wet 2006 water year has allowed ample water storage in the states reservoir systems, thus lessening the impacts of the current dryness.  The water in storage has allowed for water deliveries to irrigators to continue as planned, with only a few reductions announced at this point.  The short-term dryness has also increased fire danger for much of California, with counties spending extra money to have crews on stand-by during high fire danger conditions.</p>
   <p>Rain along a portion of the southern California coast this week allowed for a small reduction of the D1 conditions along the south coast drainage region.  Ojai, California, reported 4.49 inches of precipitation this week, while Santa Paula recorded 4.49 inches.  Santa Barbara reported 2.55 inches, and Oxnard had 2.34 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
