<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050407</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: 1) two storms affecting the Plains and lower Mississippi Valley in the next 6 days, including the April 5-7 event, which has already brought significant rains to Kansas, Oklahoma, and Iowa, followed by another storm on April 9-12, which should bring rain to much of the Plains region, all resulting in totals of 1-3 inches for parts of Colorado, Nebraska, and Kansas; 2) more storms hitting the Pacific Northwest during the next 5 days, as totals reach 1-2 inches or more over western Washington and Oregon, with lighter amounts eastward into the northern Rockies; 3) drier weather over Washington and Oregon during week 2, April 14-20, but above normal precipitation forecast for the northern and southern Plains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Heavy showers hit northern and central parts of the island. The bulk of the rains missed the area of D0-D1 dryness across the south, but the moisture did reduce the D0 area in the far west.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>Up to an inch of precipitation trimmed the eastern portions of the D0 area in central Minnesota, but continued dry weather resulted in some expansion of D0 dryness in eastern South Dakota. Light rain contributed to reduced dryness in northern North Dakota. Over an inch of rain benefited central and southern parts of Nebraska. Although the moisture had little impact on the overall drought situation in western and southern Nebraska, there was some diminishing of the D0 and D1 conditions in central Nebraska. Farther east, with drier weather and low streamflows, D0 dryness expanded slightly in east-central Nebraska. Warm, windy, dry weather resulted in expansion of D0 dryness into south-central Oklahoma. A storm system brought significant rains to the Kansas-Oklahoma region following the Tuesday morning cutoff time for this weeks Drought Monitor. D0 dryness also expanded into southeastern Arkansas and persisted in South Texas. Falcon Reservoir, which serves the Lower Rio Grande Valley, saw decreasing storage in the past week due to heavy water demand for irrigation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and West">
   <p>Another week of mountain snows and valley rains further benefited drought areas in much of the West, although excessive rains hampered farmers in coastal parts of Washington and Oregon. Storms dumped 1 to 5 inches of precipitation across western Washington and Oregon, with significant snows in the Cascades. As a result, dryness further retreated from coastal areas, but continued below-normal snowpacks kept the Cascades and most of central and eastern Washington and Oregon mired in D2 drought. Moderate precipitation did benefit soil moisture across central and eastern Washington and Oregon and into Idaho, but D2 drought expanded slightly northward in central Washington due to near-record low snowpacks. Rain or snow also trimmed the eastern portions of the D3 and D4 area in southeastern Idaho, but reservoirs across central and southern Idaho remained below average levels and the water supply outlook in Idaho remains gloomy. Recent rains brought minimal improvement to northern Idaho and western Montana as snowpack levels stayed near record lows. Rain and snow continued to bring gradual improvement to remaining dry areas in southwestern Wyoming, much of Utah, and southwestern and eastern Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast:">
   <p>The storm system that inundated the Gulf Coast with up to 14 inches of rain on March 31-April 1 brought beneficial amounts of 0.6 to 1.5 inches to eastern North Carolina, resulting in the elimination of the D0 area.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
