<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050623</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2-week period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) below-normal rainfall and above-normal temperatures from Missouri and Illinois eastward through the Northeast and mid-Atlantic region, with the exception of near normal temperatures for the first 5 days in the mid-Atlantic region; 2) hot and dry weather over Texas, Louisiana, and Arkansas for June 22-27, but above-normal rainfall during June 28 to July 6 in coastal Texas and much of Louisiana accompanied by normal to below-normal temperatures; 3) above normal rainfall in the Northwest but generally normal to below-normal rainfall in the Southwest, notwithstanding widespread showers across the Southwest, central Rockies, and eastern Great Basin observed during June 21-22. Looking farther out, the U.S. Seasonal Drought Outlook released on June 16 indicated the potential for drought to expand across northern and central Texas, with drought conditions persisting northward from Texas into Illinois.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Ample showers during the past 2 weeks resulted in a one-category improvement, leaving D0 over the Big Island and western parts of Maui and Molokai and no remaining areas of drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Heavy rains fell across New York, with 1-2 inch totals common and isolated totals exceeding 3 inches. The moisture eliminated D0 over New York, but lesser amounts of rain and unseasonably low streamflows led to D0 remaining in the New York City area, Long Island, and southern Connecticut, and D0 expanding into eastern and central Pennsylvania and northern New Jersey. To the south, D0 developed in eastern North Carolina and adjacent parts of southern Michigan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Moderate rains over northern Wisconsin and Michigans Upper Peninsula reduced D0 dryness in those areas, but mostly dry weather prevailed farther south from Iowa and southern Wisconsin southward into Missouri and Illinois and Michigans western Lower Peninsula. As a result, D1 expanded into extreme eastern Iowa and also into east-central Illinois and across far northwestern Indiana. D1 lessened in northern parts of Michigans UP but expanded southward in western areas. D0 also expanded eastward toward central Ohio and farther south in central Kentucky. Persistent dryness led to the development of D2 drought in north-central Illinois, where some locations have seen less than 40 percent normal rainfall in the past 60 days. USDA reported that 74 percent of Illinois farmland is short topsoil moisture.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Spotty heavy rains hit areas from Kansas northward to the Dakotas, but the remaining drought areas missed most of the heaviest rains, so there was little change in the depiction this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Thunderstorms late last week tore through Oklahoma, southern Arkansas, and parts of Louisiana, dumping over 2 inches of rain in some locations. As a result, there was a general one-category improvement in Oklahoma and in central Arkansas, with D2 in Oklahoma now limited to areas near the Texas border. Severe D2 drought continued in northeastern Arkansas into southern Missouri as well as portions of southern Arkansas. Rainfall amounts were much lighter in eastern Texas, allowing D1 drought to expand into the Houston area. Houston has measured only 0.08 inches so far this month. The all-time June record was set in 1934, when only 0.12 inches fell. Southward, the D2 drought in the Lower Valley expanded northward, as did D1.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Montana saw another week of wet weather, with many areas recording over 1 inch of rain. This led to removal of D3 in northwestern Montana and improvement to D0 across some northern and central parts of the state. The rains eliminated dryness in parts of northeastern Montana. The moisture also led to the removal of D3 on the border of Idaho and Montana. Although wet weather affected the Pacific coast from northern California to Washington, near-record low streamflows for this time of year resulted in slight expansion of D1 and D2 drought in northern Washington. D1 to D2 drought persisted in Idaho and Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
