<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040722</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The general circulation pattern over the next 10 days will consist of a ridge over the western part of North America and a trough over the eastern part of the United States. The resulting precipitation and temperature patterns will be dictated by these circulation features. Embedded within this circulation pattern will be a number of upper level weather systems that will move over the drought areas. The Southeast, southern Great Plains, and northern High Plains can expect above normal precipitation amounts with below normal temperatures. Below normal precipitation and above normal temperatures are forecasted for much of the Far West and Northeast. The north central U.S. can expect below normal precipitation with near to below normal temperatures. Above normal temperatures are forecasted for Alaska. Wetter than normal weather is expected along the southern coastal areas with dry conditions continuing over the southeastern panhandle as well as in the interior drought areas.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>A new area of D1 was introduced in the eastern section of Alaska during this drought monitoring period. The placement of D1 in this area was determined by SPI indices of 1-, 2-, 3- and 6-months as well as numerous fires that have been burning for the better part of this month. As of July 20th, 11 fires were still active in Alaska. Also in Alaska, D0 was expanded further northwestward to reflect low precipitation and the continuing fires that have been reported in that area. No changes were made to Hawaii this monitoring period. Although several stations reported well above normal year-to-date rainfall totals, this may be an area to watch in upcoming weeks as recent totals have been a little below normal with above normal temperatures.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Rainfall totals ranging from 2 to 8 inches fell in New York this week, which was adequate rainfall to justify complete removal of the D0 in the state. An area of D0 remains in far western portions of Connecticut and Massachusetts as only small amounts of precipitation ranging from 0.25 to 0.50 inch fell during this drought monitoring period. Although Maine did receive rainfall, it was not substantial enough to constitute the reduction of the D0 that was expanded last period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Based on 7-day stream flow reports and percent of normal precipitation maps for several time frames, D0 was introduced this week into Wisconsin as well as north central Texas to account for the dryness that has developed there. Elsewhere in the central US, tongues of D0A expanded eastward across the northern and southern edges of Nebraska into adjoining parts of South Dakota and Kansas. These new areas of abnormally dry conditions are based upon 7-, 14- and 30-day percent of normal precipitation plus soil moisture readings from Mead and Indian Cave State Park. Also in Nebraska, temperatures have been well into the nineties during this drought monitoring period causing soil conditions to dry out quickly. In Missouri, the western edge of the D0 was slightly shaved back due rain that fell this period based on radar estimates as well as station reports of 1 to 4 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Heavy rainfall in central North Carolina lead to the retraction of D0, leaving a tongue of D0 right above the South Carolina border. Radar estimates indicated as much as 8 to 10 inches of rain fell in the Piedmont Triad region of the state on July 17th and 18th. Florida has been in a wet pattern for the majority of the drought monitoring period, with amounts of 1 to 2 inches from radar estimates in some areas which were enough to warrant the reduction of the D0 in the southern part of the state. Local reports indicate Lake Okeechobee has already begun to rise with this weeks precipitation across south central Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>In Montana the southeastern D4 drought area was expanded westward based upon 7-, 30-, 60-, 90-day and 6 month percent of normal precipitation as well as 6 and 12 month SPI indices. The exceptional drought in eastern Wyoming was slightly trimmed away on the western side of the drought area. This change is to reflect recent rainfall and positive responses seen in vegetation as well as higher stream flows being reported in the area. Also in Wyoming, a doughnut hole of D1 was cut into the D2 in the western part of the state, based on local feedback and 30-, 60-, 90-day and 12 month percent of normal precipitation. In spite of recent rains this drought monitoring period, Mackay and Magic reservoirs in Idaho ran out of water which is indicative of long-term water supply problems, although no changes were made to this area. In the Pacific Northwest, the D0 in western Washington was extended east as well as southward into Oregon, based on soil moisture deficits, 14-day and 30-day percent of normal precipitation maps. In west central Nevada, D2 was expanded westward into California based upon percent of average precipitation, as well as 30-, 60-, 90-day percent of normal precipitation. In Arizona, fissures as big as 5 feet wide and 12 feet deep erupting at the surface have been reported by the media near Willcox. Local experts note that this is a result of long-term pumping of groundwater which reflects long-term impacts of socioeconomic drought. However, in view of scattered areas of rainfall due to the start of the monsoon season, the drought depiction was unchanged in this area.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
