<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030814</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may have an impact on dryness or drought areas during the next 2 weeks: 1) little rainfall is expected during August 13-18 across the Plains and Upper and Middle Mississippi Valley, but temperatures will be below normal from Texas into southern Oklahoma; 2) scattered thunderstorms may leave over 1 inch of rain locally in the Southwest during the 5-day period, but little rain is expected over the western Great Basin, the Northwest, and the northern Rockies; 3) during August 19-27, most of the West should see below-normal rainfall and above-normal temperatures, with normal rainfall forecast for Arizona; 4) normal to above-normal rainfall is on tap for the central states from Minnesota through Missouri and into eastern parts of Kansas, Oklahoma, and Texas.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>There was little to no change in the D1 to D2 drought over Hawaii and the D0 dryness in southeastern Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region and Middle Mississippi Valley">
   <p>One-half to 1-inch rains dampened parts of northern Illinois, northern Iowa, and northern Missouri, but most of the region from Minnesota south to central Missouri recorded under one-half inch during August 6-12. As a result, D0 dryness and D1/D2 drought expanded eastward and southward in Missouri and D1 drought developed in southwestern Wisconsin and south-central Minnesota. The combination of severe short-term dryness and persistent long-term rainfall deficits resulted in the development of extreme D3 drought in northwestern Missouri. USDA reported that 41 percent of Missouri's corn crop is in poor to very poor condition, making this the second consecutive year the state has endured serious crop problems. There are numerous reports of empty farm ponds, wells drying up, and major crop losses in northwestern Missouri. Farther north, D0 dryness expanded northward in Minnesota, leaving over three-quarters of the state abnormally dry. D0 dryness covered much of Iowa, where soil moisture was rated short to very short over 63 percent of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Another 1 to 3 inches of rain further reduced the D0H area in Maine. Excessively wet conditions persisted across the eastern one-third of the nation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Two-inch rains allowed D1 drought to improve to D0 in western Oklahoma east of the Panhandle, and cooler weather and an outbreak of thunderstorms kept drought from progressing into eastern Texas, but hot, dry weather further worsened drought in western and central Texas, as D2 expanded eastward and southward. In Kansas, showers prevented further deterioration in most eastern and western areas, but lack of rain resulted in D2 drought extending southward into south-central Kansas and persisting across most of the northern one-half of the state. D2 drought continued across large parts of Nebraska and into western South Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>There was little change to the overall drought situation, although showers left one-half inch or greater rainfall totals on parts of Montana, Colorado, and northern New Mexico. Amounts were very light to negligible in the Great Basin-Intermountain region, allowing extreme to exceptional drought to continue. Severe to extreme drought expanded in southern New Mexico while severe drought edged eastward into southeastern Colorado. Temperatures for the week averaged below normal over the Pacific states, but 4 to 8 degrees F above normal in the Rockies and eastern Great Basin.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
