<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050922</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) Hurricane Rita was forecast to strike the Texas coast late Friday night, September 23, as a major hurricane, based on the official forecast issued on September 21 at 5 p.m. EDT. The storm will bring torrential rains to Texas, resulting in a major impact on existing areas of dryness both in that state and, to some extent, Louisiana as well. The exact path of the storm will determine how much rain falls over existing D0 to D3 drought areas. 2) Based on frontal passages and enhanced moisture from the remains of Rita, the 6-10 day forecast issued on September 21 indicated above-normal rainfall from the Plains through the Midwest to the Northeast, but persisting dry and warm weather for the Southeast. 3) The week 2 forecast for September 29-October 5 indicates more heat and dryness for the Southeast and more wetness for the Great Lakes region, and above-normal rains for the drought area in the Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Rain falling late in the period was not sufficient to affect the D0 dryness area in the eastern interior basin of Alaska. Windward areas of Hawaii measured as much as 7 inches of rain, but totals in the D0 dry areas mostly ranged from 0 to 1.6 inches for the week ending on the 18 th, resulting in little change in the dryness status.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Hurricane Ophelia dropped 4 to 8 inches of rain on the southern and central coasts of North Carolina on September 14-15, eliminating abnormal dryness. Rainfall tapered off rapidly to the west and north. Not only did interior sections of the state remain in D0 dryness, but D1H drought developed across central portions of the state, as dry September weather continued over much of the Southeast. In response to the persisting warm and dry weather, D0 expanded to include most of South Carolina, while D1A drought developed across central and eastern parts of Virginia, most of Maryland, and western and eastern Pennsylvania. Drought continued in Delaware, New Jersey, and southern New York despite scattered thunderstorms. September rainfall to date has totaled under one-half inch over a large swath of the nation extending from Pennsylvania to Georgia. Many locations have seen less than a tenth of an inch so far this month, including interior portions of the Carolinas and the Washington DC area. Heavy rains exceeding 2 inches doused southeastern Massachusetts, ending D0 dryness. Lighter amounts resulted in some retreat of D1 drought in Connecticut.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>Several bouts of thunderstorms improved moisture conditions over the Midwest, with 1 to 4 inches of rain causing D2 and D3 drought to retreat in Illinois. Nevertheless, an area extending from eastern Iowa across northern Illinois into extreme southeastern Wisconsin still posted year-to-date precipitation deficits exceeding 10 inches, and D3 drought remained. In Illinois, rainfall deficits since March 1 in Moline, Chicago, and Peoria still exceeded 1 foot. More relief took place in Missouri, which saw 7-day rainfall totals through September 20 of 3 to 5 inches over central and southern locations. This was enough to end drought and dryness over most of the state. Showers exceeding 1 inch fell over Wisconsin and southern Michigan, but amounts were not enough to significantly erode existing D1 to D2 drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>The rains from Hurricane Rita affected southern Florida by the end of the valid period, but the west coast of Florida north of Naples continued a dry pattern that has persisted all month. With streamflows near record lows for this time of the year and soil moisture diminishing, D0 dryness developed across the west-central areas of the peninsula centered near Tampa. Rainfall this September through the 20th totaled a meager 0.02 inches in Tampa. Farther west, severe droughtD2developed in south-central Louisiana. Areas just west of the Katrina-affected locations in southeastern Louisiana have been unusually dry for much of the year. The year-to-date rainfall departure in Lafayette, Louisiana totaled 21.86 inches as of September 20. In east Texas, hot weather with only sporadic rainfall resulted in D1 drought expanding westward from Louisiana. To the north, heavy rains eased drought in northern, central, and western parts of Arkansas, with up to 5 inches of rain removing dryness in the northwest, and 1-3 inches shrinking the D1 and D2 areas, as well as the D3 in the southwest.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation amounts were generally light this week, although western Montana picked up over an inch of rain. D3 drought developed east of the Cascades in Washington southward to northern Oregon, as recent dry weather compounded the effects of the abnormally dry winter. Streamflows are near record lows in the D3 area.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
