<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060316</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>March 15  20, 2006 looks generally cool and wet across the lower 48 states, with some dry areas forecast to receive heavy precipitation. Over an inch of precipitation is anticipated in central Arizona, part of northern Wyoming, much of the central and southern Great Plains, and the lower Mississippi Valley, with 3.0 to 4.5 inches forecast in southern Arkansas, southeasternmost Oklahoma, and northeastern Texas. Among the currently-dry areas, precipitation totals under one-quarter of an inch should be restricted to the lower mid-Atlantic, most of North Carolina, northern South Carolina, central Illinois, southeastern Iowa, northeastern Missouri, southwestern Wyoming, central and southern New Mexico, and southeastern California. Temperatures are expected to average below normal everywhere but the Gulf Coast region, southern Texas, and the Florida Peninsula, with temperatures averaging 9 to 19 degrees below normal from Oklahoma and Arkansas northward through the Dakotas, southern Minnesota, and the lower Great Lakes region.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (March 21  25, 2006), the odds favor a return to below-normal precipitation in the Southwest, the Rockies, the northern Intermountain West, and the D0 area in Alaska. Meanwhile, surplus precipitation is favored from central and eastern Texas eastward through the southern half of the Atlantic Coast. Widespread below-normal temperatures are again anticipated for the contiguous 48 states from the Rockies to the Atlantic Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>A few tenths of an inch of precipitation fell on most of the D0 area in Alaska, keeping abnormally dry conditions intact. Farther south, heavy to excessive rains fell on parts of Hawaii, but missed the abnormally dry areas. West-central portions of the Big Island received 1 to 2 inches of rain, but the remaining D0 areas recorded only light amounts, leaving D0 conditions unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley and East-Central States">
   <p>Severe weather, flooding, and 6.0 to 9.5 inches of rain doused southern sections of Indiana and Illinois and small adjacent areas in southeastern Missouri and western Kentucky, bringing an abrupt end to D0AH conditions.</p>
   <p>For the region as a whole, precipitation totals declined from west to east, with 2 to locally 6 inches falling on southern Ohio, 1 to 3 inches falling on much of eastern Kentucky and Tennessee, 0.5 to 2.0 inches dampening the central and southern Appalachians, and little or none observed along the Atlantic coastal plain. As a result, there was a net eastward shift of D1AH conditions into easternmost Kentucky, and similar conditions expanded into south-central Virginia. Meanwhile, the wet week eradicated D0AH conditions in southern Ohio and northwestern West Virginia, but drier conditions farther east led to D0 expansion into much of the mid-Atlantic region, central South Carolina, northern Georgia, northeastern Alabama, and southeastern Tennessee.</p>
   <p>During the last 90 days, precipitation totals were 4 to 8 inches below normal for most areas from the Delmarva Peninsula southwestward into northern Georgia and adjacent sections of Tennessee and Alabama. This, in conjunction with substantial longer-term precipitation deficits, led to daily record low streamflows at numerous sites from north-central South Carolina northward into south-central Virginia, according to the U. S. Geological Survey.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Beneficial rains of 1 inch or more fell on a broad swath from southeastern Oklahoma northeastward through the southern Great Lakes region, including most of Arkansas, Missouri, Illinois, and Indiana. Parts of this region recorded much larger amounts, with 4 to 6 inches reported in southeastern Missouri and 2 to 4 inches observed at many locations in east-central Oklahoma, northern Arkansas, south-central Missouri, central Illinois, and a swath from eastern Iowa eastward through southwestern Michigan. As a result, areas from east-central Oklahoma northeastward through central Illinois generally improved by 1 category, including former D4AH conditions in east-central Oklahoma. It should be noted, however, that 6-month precipitation totals are still 8 to 12 inches below normal in many of these areas, with deficits of 12 to 16 inches observed in parts of eastern Oklahoma and adjacent portions of Arkansas and Texas.</p>
   <p>Farther north, the wet weather helped bring at least a temporary end to short-term precipitation deficits and surface moisture shortages across southern and east-central Iowa, central and northern Illinois, and the adjacent Great Lakes region, with precipitation totals now near to above normal on time scales going back as far as 90 days. However, continuing long-term precipitation deficits, low groundwater levels, and deep soil moisture shortages led to only spotty 1 category improvements and a broad reclassification of conditions as D0H to D2H, dropping the A impact designation. Precipitation totals for the last 12 months remain 8 to 16 inches below normal at many locations in this region, and groundwater levels in east-central Iowa, though at their highest level since July 2005, remain almost 2 feet below the average of all prior measurements since 1941, according to the U. S. Geological Survey.</p>
   <p>To the west, moderate to heavy snow fell on some of the D1H areas in western South Dakota and adjacent Wyoming, especially in and near the Black Hills, but precipitation totals were not large enough to warrant any drought classification changes.</p>
   <p>Across the central and western Great Plains, the High Plains, and southern Texas, precipitation totals last week were once again unfavorably low. Totals of a few tenths of an inch were common, with little or no precipitation falling on areas from central Kansas and eastern Colorado southward through the southwestern Great Plains, the southern High Plains, and the southwestern two-thirds of Texas, including the Panhandle. Portions of the Texas Panhandle and interior southern Texas have recorded less than 25 percent of normal precipitation during the last 6 months, and 90-day totals are below 5 percent of normal in an area extending from central Kansas southwestward into central New Mexico.</p>
   <p>These conditions prompted expansion of D4AH in southern Texas while D3AH conditions pushed northward along the southeast Texas coast, edged slightly westward in central Texas, and expanded into the western Red River Valley and most of the Texas Panhandle. In addition, D2AH stretched into west-central Texas, central New Mexico, and southeastern Colorado while D1AH enveloped central and west-central Kansas and adjacent Colorado.</p>
   <p>The southern Plains drought, in conjunction with above-normal temperatures, low humidity, and gusty winds, led to an outbreak of wildfires. According to the Texas Forest Service, over 1.1 million acres have been burned in that state alone, taking a few lives and prompting local disaster declarations for 50 counties.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Southwest, and California">
   <p>Substantial precipitation finally fell on parts of the Southwest and the southern Rockies, though not nearly enough to pull water-year precipitation totals (since October 2005) to anywhere near normal levels. Many locations in southwestern California, central and east-central Arizona, north-central New Mexico, southwestern Colorado, and southwestern Utah reported over an inch of precipitation for the week, with 2 to locally 5 inches recorded at scattered sites, particularly in central Arizona and southwestern Colorado. This precipitation eliminated D0 conditions in part of southwestern Colorado and southwestern California, prompted improvement to D2 in a sizeable portion of central Arizona, and led to 1-category improvements for a few other small areas, including the southwestern Sierra Nevada.</p>
   <p>Phoenix, AZ reported over an inch of precipitation during March 11  12, breaking their string of 143 consecutive days without measurable precipitation. Farther north, more than 29 inches of snow fell on Flagstaff, AZ during March 10  12. This was 10 times the total for the previous 160 days, yet seasonal snowfall totals increased only to 40 percent of normal.</p>
   <p>As of March 14, the higher elevations from southern sections of Colorado and Utah southward through New Mexico and Arizona reported less than 75 percent of normal water-year-to-date precipitation, and under 60 percent of the typical snowpack water equivalent for mid-March, according to the Natural Resources Conservation Service. High elevation stations across Arizona and all but northernmost New Mexico have recorded just 30 to 50 percent of normal precipitation since October 1, 2005.</p>
   <p>Farther north across the central and northern Rockies, most locales received a few tenths of an inch of precipitation, with only a few isolated sites reporting over an inch. As a result, drought conditions were essentially unchanged. In southeastern Idaho, groundwater levels remained among the lowest 4 percent of all measurements taken since 1951 despite above-normal snowpack and water-year precipitation totals.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
