<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060406</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather that could have an impact over ongoing dry or drought areas during the next 2 weeks: 1) a low pressure system crossing the Plains on Thursday April 6, bringing rain to the central Plains and then the Ohio Valley; 2) low pressure developing April 8 spreading widespread rain over the dry areas of the Southeast; 3) more storm systems in the next 2 weeks spreading precipitation eastward from the West, resulting in above-normal rainfall for the West, northern Plains, and upper Midwest; 4) below-normal rainfall over the South and East Coast beyond the first 5 days of the period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Abnormally dry conditions in the Panhandle and interior basin persisted.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East Coast">
   <p>The same frontal system that brought the deadly tornadoes to the Midwest on Sunday brought much-needed rain to the East Coast on Monday. The one-half inch measured in the DC area was the best moisture there since the February 11-12 snowstorm. Nevertheless, rainfall since March 1 at DC has been just 16 percent of normal, and streamflows and many wells remain below normal, resulting in continued D0 around the capital and the mid-Atlantic region. D1 to D2 drought persisted despite the showers across southern Virginia into North Carolina. Farther north, enough rain fell to remove D0 and improve streamflows in southern Vermont and the northern Berkshires in Massachusetts, but surface water conditions remained abnormally dry to the south and east, with D0 even expanding westward into central Pennsylvania and adjacent New York state based on unseasonably low streamflows and groundwater despite the recent rains.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Two storm systems crossed the region, bringing severe weather to many states, including a major tornado outbreak on Sunday, April 2. Widespread precipitation fell across the region, with 1-3 inch rainfall amounts common from eastern Nebraska into the Ohio and Tennessee Valleys. In Iowa, the week ending April 3 was the wettest week in 11 months. The moisture resulted in a general 1-category drought intensity improvement in Iowa, with D2 replaced by D1 in the south. The area of D2 diminished in northern Illinois, now mostly confined to an area from Peoria to De Kalb. The remaining D2 is consistent with locations that still sport 12-month precipitation deficits of 1 foot or more and where subsoil moisture remains a concern. The rains also reduced D1 drought in eastern Kansas, northwestern Missouri, and eastern Nebraska, but D1 expanded into eastern Colorado, as this area missed significant rain or snow this past week. The heavy rains that fell on March 28 resulted in some reduction of the D3 drought in southern Texas, but weekly amounts were generally too scattered to significantly ease drought over the remainder of the southern Plains. In contrast, moderate precipitation and a re-assessment based on USDA soil moisture reports led to reduction of the D0 in North Dakota and the D1 in southwest South Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Southwest, and California">
   <p>More Pacific storms slammed into the West, bringing widespread valley rains and mountain snows from the Continental Divide to the coast. The heaviest precipitation fell in areas outside of ongoing drought concerns, although up to 1 inch of precipitation fell in northern Arizona. The area of D2 to D3 drought remained intact in Arizona and New Mexico, as large snow and rain deficits persisted. Flagstaffs total snowfall this season of 42 inches was 57 inches below normal. To the north, in contrast, enough rain and snow fell in western Montana to erase the lingering D1 area there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Rainfall deficits exceeding 12 inches since early October have resulted in D1 drought development over southern Louisiana, southern Mississippi, and southern Alabama. Deficits exceeded 16 inches in southeastern Louisiana, and rainfall has been less than one-half of normal since October into coastal Alabama. D0 dryness expanded northward and eastward from southern Alabama across Georgia and continued over Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
