<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20011025</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) a cold front this weekend should bring some light to moderate rains across the northern Ohio River valley and into parts of New England; 2) looking out past October 29th, warmer and drier weather is expected for all but Florida in the eastern half of the country as we head into November; 3) cooler and wetter weather is expected in the Pacific Northwest over the same time frame.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Not much in the way of relief was seen over the islands last week. Although windward Hilo did see more than 2 inches of the wet stuff, most of the other islands reported very little rain while reports of impacts due to the long-term drought have picked up recently. Even though Hilo is above normal for the month and season, they are still staring at a - 41.00 inch deficit since January 1st of this year.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic area">
   <p>After last weeks heavy rains, the region saw a much quieter weather pattern overall. Although seasonal rainfall has been well below normal for areas south of New England, October has been markedly dry up and down the Atlantic Coast from the Carolinas up to Maryland, Massachusetts and into New England and Maine as well, with many stations reporting less than 25% (-2 to - 4 inches) of their normal rainfall. This has led to an expansion of D0 (abnormally dry) across most of this region with the prospects for future downgrading if rains continue to stay away. In Maine, New Hampshire and Vermont, D0 (abnormally dry), D1 (moderate) and D2 (severe) conditions have slowly expanded.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Last week brought continued drier and cooler weather across the Dakotas as D0 continues to creep eastward. Recent short-term relief has been seen in southwestern Nebraska, leading to the addition of a hydro (W) delineation in this region. While the moisture has led to better agricultural conditions (winter wheat, pasture and range), the long-term picture here is still of concern.</p>
   <p>Further south in Oklahoma and Texas, conditions have continued to dry out, leading to an expansion of D0 (abnormally dry) into the Tulsa, OK, area. The D1 (moderate) drought has pushed eastward in Texas (to points in and around Abilene and Wichita Falls, TX) and north as far as the Canadian River in the Panhandle. Seasonal deficits in the cities of Abilene and Wichita Falls since September 1st are -2.11 inches and -4.56 inches, respectively. Long-term deficits over much of western Texas arent any better, as D2 (severe) drought has now spread east and south down the Rio Grande river basin into the Del Rio and Brownsville areas. Unseasonably warm weather has been felt here recently as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>All but the southern tip of Florida saw little if any rainfall last week in the region. As deficits continue to accumulate as we move further into fall, we are seeing an expansion of D0 (abnormally dry), D1 (moderate), and D2 (severe) conditions in parts of Georgia and the Carolinas. This area of dryness has begun to move northward into parts of Virginia and the Washington, D.C., area over the past 4-6 weeks. After turning the drought relief corner earlier this summer, things have turned dry again in many parts of Georgia and South Carolina, where they cant seem to shake the drought that has plagued them for the past 3 years. D0 conditions have also pushed back into eastern Tennessee. The entire region needs a beneficial fall/winter recharge period if they are to begin the road to recovery.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Most of the West remained warm and dry last week, with the exception of northwestern Washington. Although recent short-term rains and snows have been welcomed, it is too early in the season to get excited or panic. Even in the areas seeing the precipitation, seasonal departures (Sept. 1 to date) still exist, with deficits of 1.5 to 2 inches, or more, commonly seen. Temperatures were also above normal last week except for areas in northern Washington, Idaho and Montana. As a result, drought conditions and our depictions remain unchanged across the West as we wind down October and a sluggish start to the new water year.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
