<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030403</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through April 12 which may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: Over the next 5 days (April 3-7): 1) a couple of low pressure systems bringing widespread precipitation to the West, Plains and eastern United States, with over 0.5 inches in the northern Plains and over 1 inch for the Great Lakes area and Mississippi Valley; 2) unfavorably dry and warm weather for the southern Plains, including much of Texas and Oklahoma. For the 6-10 day period (April 8-12): expect a return to mostly dry weather across the northern Plains but above-normal rainfall in the southern Plains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation amounts failed to end the dryness across southern Alaska. March precipitation in Anchorage was around one-half of normal and snowfall since January 1 has been one-third of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Many parts of Oahu and Maui picked up over an inch of rain this week, but this was not enough to significantly affect the areas of D0 and D1 drought. Lesser amounts left drought intact on the Big Island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Heavy rain exceeding 2 inches fell over central and southern parts of the island this week, resulting in the D0 area retreating to northern and eastern areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and New England">
   <p>A coastal low pressure area brought rain and snow to the Northeast on March 30-31, with liquid amounts reaching over an inch in parts of northern New England. The resulting moisture caused a shrinkage of the D0 and D1 areas in northern New England.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>A major storm crossed the Midwest on March 27-28, dumping more than a foot of snow in northern parts of Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan, and over an inch of rain elsewhere in the upper Midwest. Additional rain and snow fell on the 31st. The moisture resulted in the elimination of D1 drought from southern Minnesota, central and northern Wisconsin, and Michigan's Upper Peninsula. Precipitation amounts were less to the west and south, and severe drought remained from northern Missouri and southern Iowa into Michigan as well as across the Plains from northern Kansas to western South Dakota. D0 dryness developed in southeastern Missouri and across northern Arkansas, where March rainfall was less than 50% of normal. D0 dryness expanded eastward along the Oklahoma-Texas border, where 60-day rainfall has been less than 40% of normal. The recent dry weather has caused an outbreak of wildfires across the south-central United States.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Although there were no major storms comparable to that affecting Colorado and Wyoming in mid-March, a number of weather systems did bring significant rain and snow to the Rockies, northern Great Basin, and Pacific Northwest. Liquid equivalents exceeded 1 inch over much of northern Wyoming, western and northern Idaho, western Oregon, and parts of western Montana. With snow water content near or above normal across northwestern Wyoming, D2 conditions improved to D1, and D4 and D3 areas to the south and east receded. Drought extent also diminished slightly in Oregon, Idaho, and Montana. In contrast, continuing dry weather in south-central California resulted in expansion of D0 dryness to the coast south of San Francisco.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
