<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20200102</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>An area of upper-level low pressure entered southern California by December 26 and then progressed east across the Four Corners region. This upper-level low resulted in heavy rain and high-elevation snow from southern California east to southwest Colorado and New Mexico. A surface low developed across the south-central Great Plains on December 28 with a subsequent track northeast to the upper Mississippi Valley and Great Lakes. Heavy snow fell to the northwest of this low pressure system, while moderate to heavy rainfall accompanied the cold front as it shifted east from the Great Plains to the East Coast. Following the heavy precipitation across the Pacific Northwest during mid to late December, precipitation average below normal during the final week of December. Enhanced onshore flow resulted in periods of heavy precipitation along the Alaska Panhandle, but longer-term precipitation deficits persist. A low pressure system and trailing front brought locally heavy rain and damaging winds to parts of the Hawaiian Islands this past week.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (January 2 to 6), another surface low is forecast to develop across the southern Great Plain
on January 2. This surface low and trailing cold are likely to bring heavy rainfall (1 to 3 inches) to the lower
Mississippi Valley and Tennessee Valley with more modest amounts (1 inch or less) along the East Coast. A low
pressure system with onshore flow is expected to bring rain and high-elevation snow to the Pacific Northwest,
beginning of January 4. Although rainfall of around an inch is forecast along the Texas Gulf Coast during the next
week, dry weather is likely across the remainder of Texas. Mild temperatures are forecast to prevail across the
continental U.S. during the first week of January 2020, while bitterly cold temperatures persist throughout Alaska.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day extended range outlook (January 6 to 10, 2020) indicates a slight tilt in the odds for above normal precipitation across much of the central and northeastern U.S. Below normal precipitation is favored for the Southeast along with California and the Southwest. The highest confidence in the temperature outlook exists across Alaska where below normal temperatures are likely to persist into the second week of January. Below normal temperatures are favored for the Great Basin and Rockies, while a warming trend is anticipated across the south-central and eastern U.S.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Multiple low pressure systems with onshore flow resulted in frequent daily precipitation along the Alaska
Panhandle. Despite the good start to the water year, long-term deficits persist with consecutive poor water years in
2017-18 and 2018-19. Therefore, no changes were made to the ongoing long-term D0 and D1 areas in Alaska.</p>
   <p>A low pressure system tracked west of Hawaii during late December. The trailing front, associated with this low
pressure system, resulted in locally heavy rainfall (especially in Kauai). However, much of the rainfall occurred
outside of ongoing drought areas. Any changes will be made in subsequent weeks after a more thorough analysis
of rainfall observations and NDVI.</p>
   <p>During the past week, locally more than 2 inches of rainfall occurred in southern Puerto Rico. However, an inch
or less of rainfall was observed across the ongoing moderate (D1) drought area in eastern Puerto Rico. Coinciding
with this D1 area, 28-day stream flows are generally near or below the 20th percentile and 90-day precipitation
deficits exceed 8 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="High Plains">
   <p>A low pressure system developed across the southern Great Plains on Dec 28 and then tracked northeast to Iowa and Minnesota. Along and northwest of the surface low track, beneficial precipitation (0.5 to 1.5
inches) fell from the western half of Kansas north to southern and eastern Nebraska. This recent precipitation
prompted a 1 to 2-category improvements to the short-term drought areas in Kansas. A 2-category improvement
was justified where more than 1 inch of precipitation occurred and 90-day precipitation is either at or above
normal. However, severe drought (D2) continues west of Garden City and Liberal, Kansas. In contrast to the
improving conditions for Kansas, abnormal dryness (D0) was extended north across western Wyoming where 90-
day precipitation deficits are 2 to 6 inches. Drought impacts were modified to long-term only in southwest
Colorado due to recent snowfall. Snow water content is running 125 to 135 percent of normal as of December 29,
but 6-month SPI values support the severe drought (D2) category in southwest Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>A low pressure system and trailing cold front brought widespread rain and snow to this region on December 29 and 30. Abnormal dryness (D0) was added the previous week to parts of central Indiana based on 90-day precipitation deficits of 2 to 4 inches and 28-day stream flows below the 30th percentile. This D0 area was decreased slightly where more than 0.5 inch fell. Elsewhere, 90-day precipitation averages 150 to 200, or more, percent of normal across Kentucky, Michigan, Wisconsin, Minnesota, and the northwest two-thirds of Iowa.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast">
   <p>Precipitation (0.5 to 2 inches) overspread this region on December 29 and 30. Heavy snow (6 to 12 inches) was reported in northern New England, while freezing rain accumulated up to one inch in extreme northern New York. A small area of abnormal dryness (DO) remains designated for parts of southern Delaware and the eastern shore of Maryland based on: 6-month deficits of 4 to 8 inches and 7-, 14-, and 28-day stream flows in the 10-24th percentile. Elsewhere, precipitation averaged at or above normal for the 30- to 90-day period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Pacific Islands">
   <p>During the Northern Hemisphere winter, the North Pacific subtropical high, and the low latitude Inter-Tropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ), migrate south toward the equator. The seasonal migration brings drier subtropical trade winds to the northern portions of Micronesia and ITCZ rainfall to the southern regions. The weather conditions across the U.S.-Affiliated Pacific Islands (USAPI) during this USDM week (1/1/20-1/7/20) reflected this seasonal pattern. The ITCZ, a near-equatorial trough with trade-wind convergence into it, continued across southern portions of Palau and the Federated States of Micronesia (FSM) for much of the week. The convergence and trough extended at times into the Marshall Islands (RMI). Tropical disturbances and weak circulations developed within the trough and convergence zone. Meanwhile, a dry trade-wind pattern remained entrenched across the Marianas, briefly interrupted by weak shear lines or frontal remnants which occasionally extended as far south as the northern FSM and northern RMI. The ITCZ crossed the equator south of Kosrae State, extending southeastward in the Southern Hemisphere as the South Pacific Convergence Zone (SPCZ). The SPCZ (monsoon trough) extended northeastward past the Samoan Islands, then migrated southwestward across the islands later in the week.</p>
   <p>Satellite-based estimates of 7-day precipitation (QPE) showed areas of 2 to 4+ inches of rain across southern portions of Palau to southwest Yap State, southern Pohnpei State, and parts of the RMI. These bands were enveloped by 0.5- to 2.0-inch totals across most of the remaining FSM and RMI. No widespread precipitation was picked up by the satellite QPE over the Marianas. A huge swath of 1 to 2 inch rains, with locally much more, was indicated northeastward from the Samoan Islands, with 0.5 to 1.0 inch touching the islands of American Samoa.</p>
   <p>In the Republic of Palau, December rainfall at the international airport was 9.86 inches, which was above the 8-inch minimum to meet most water needs. However, much of the rain fell in early and mid-December and was followed by a drying trend. During the first 7 days of January, the National Weather Service office (WSO Koror) received rainfall totaling just 0.33 inch. If drier-than-normal conditions persist across the Republic of Palau, short-term dryness could soon develop.</p>
   <p>In the Marianas, it was the driest December during the 72-year period of record at the international airport on Guam, with a total of 1.46 inches. It was also very dry on Rota, where 1.54 inches fell. Saipan fared a little better, with a December total of 3.64 inches. The mostly dry weather has continued through the first 7 days of January, with less than one-quarter inch of rain falling at all major observation sites. With Guam and Rota failing to meet the 1-inch weekly minimum for 5 consecutive weeks, D0-S was introduced. However, recent reports from the Marianas indicate that impacts from the short-term dryness are muted, at least at this early stage.</p>
   <p>In the FSM, D0-S was introduced for Kapingamarangi, where rainfall has failed to meet the 2-inch weekly minimum for 4 consecutive weeks. December rainfall on Kapingamarangi totaled 6.55 inches. In contrast, December totals topped 10 inches at Kosrae and Lukunor, while 21.17 inches soaked Pohnpei. Currently, insufficient rainfall data is available to provide an analysis for Fananu. Several other locations, including Yap, Woleai, and Ulithi, have received little rain the last 2 weeks, following appreciable precipitation during the week ending December 24, and will be monitored for the need to introduce D0-S in the near future.</p>
   <p>In the Republic of the Marshall Islands, D0-S was retained for Majuro. Despite Majuro's December rainfall total of 13.03 inches, drier weather arrived late in the month. As a result, reservoir storage on Majuro fell to 22.904 million gallons by January 7, just 64 percent of the 36 million gallon capacity. Storage below 80 percent of capacity is indicative of drought concerns. In the 19-day period from December 19 – January 6, rainfall on Majuro totaled just 1.48 inches. Elsewhere in the RMI, there is neither dryness nor drought. Mili remains especially wet, following a December total of 17.94 inches. Not enough data is available at this time to provide an assessment for Utirik.</p>
   <p>American Samoa remains wet, following a December rainfall total of 17.93 inches at the international airport. The weather has trended slightly drier in recent days, but the airport's January 1-7 rainfall of 1.21 inches still met the 1-inch threshold for most water requirements.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South">
   <p>As an upper-level trough ejected from the desert Southwest, a surface low developed over the southern Great Plains. Beneficial rainfall (more than 1 inch) resulted in improving conditions across the eastern Oklahoma Panhandle and northwest Oklahoma. Moderate (D1) to severe (D2) drought continues across southwest Oklahoma and adjacent areas of the Texas Panhandle and northwest Texas which received lighter rainfall amounts (0.75 inches of less). Changes to the drought depiction across the remainder of Texas included a slight reduction in D0/D1 in central and southwest parts of the state, based on recent rainfall and lack of short-term dryness. Although it was a dry week across deep southern Texas, a reassessment of indicators supported a slight reduction of severe (D2) drought. A small area of severe (D2) drought was added to Burleson County, based on 120-day indicators. On December 29, a cold front crossed the lower Mississippi Valley where 0.5 to 2 inches of rainfall occurred. The heaviest rain fell to the north and east of the ongoing D0 to D2 areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Following a very wet week which eliminated much of the lingering drought across the Southeast, drier weather returned to the region. The abnormal dryness (D0) area in northeast North Carolina was extended slightly more north in southeast Virginia. Otherwise, no other changes were needed after the major revision during the previous week. Based on 90-day percent of normal precipitation, moderate drought (D1) and abnormal dryness (D0) continues from the Florida Big Bend north to southwest Georgia. The current depiction of D0 and D1 across the Florida Peninsula is based on 90-day precipitation deficits along with 28-day stream flows.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Virgin Islands">
   <p>The U.S. Virgin Islands (USVI) have entered the traditional winter dry season, but unusually heavy showers have developed in many locations in recent weeks. Typically, about 40 percent of the annual precipitation in the USVI occurs from September to November, while just 12 to 15 percent falls from January to March. During December, rainfall across the USVI generally ranged from 2 to 6 inches, based on available data. Some of the highest amounts were noted across the northern islands of St. Thomas and St. John.</p>
   <p>Durante diciembre, hubo una gran variedad de precipitaciones totales en St. Croix, donde persistió la sequía moderada (D1-SL). El aeropuerto de Rohlsen recibió 1.78 pulgadas (60 por ciento de lo normal), mientras que el observador cooperativo en Montpellier anotó 4.81 pulgadas (138 por ciento). Con la lluvia reciente, los niveles de agua subterránea en el pozo USGS Adventure 28 comenzaron a responder levemente, pero la profundidad del agua permaneció aproximadamente 4.5 pies más baja que la misma hora hace un año. Si las lluvias benéficas de invierno continuaran en St. Croix, la designación "SL" podría cambiarse a "L" en el futuro cercano, para reflejar los impactos de la sequía a largo plazo, como la reducción de los suministros de agua subterránea.</p>
   <p>Beneficial showers continued across St. Thomas in late December and early January. King Airport ended December with a monthly total of 4.93 inches (167 percent of normal), with more than an inch falling on the 31st. A CoCoRaHS observer near Anna's Retreat reported 1.52 inches of rain in a 24-hour period on January 1-2. The USGS Grade School 3 well continued to exhibit a groundwater response to the winter rains, indicating that neither dryness nor drought is present.</p>
   <p>On St. John, the depth to water at the USGS Susannaberg DPW 3 Well has decreased to its lowest level (highest water table) since February 2019. A volunteer observer at Windswept Beach recorded 6.52 inches of December rainfall, representing the wettest December in that location since 2013. Based on the December rainfall data and groundwater response, abnormal dryness (D0-L) was removed from St. John. Unusually heavy showers continued during the first 6 days of January, with the Windswept Beach observer recording 1.18 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West">
   <p>A vigorous upper-level trough crossed southern California and the desert Southwest from December 25 to
27. Widespread moderate to heavy rain and high-elevation snow (0.5 to 2 inches, liquid equivalent) accompanied
this upper-level trough. Snowfall amounts exceeded two feet in the mountains of southern California, while 4 to
12 inches was recorded in the higher elevations of Arizona. This recent precipitation along with support from
longer-term SPI values resulted in a 1-category improvement to Dx levels in parts of Arizona and southwest Utah.
180-day precipitation deficits remain the largest (more than 6 inches) across southwest Colorado.</p>
   <p>Drier weather returned to the Pacific Northwest during the final week of December. Following the period of
heavy precipitation during mid to late December, no changes were made to the ongoing abnormal dryness (D0)
and short-term moderate drought (D1) areas. Water year to date (since October 1) precipitation deficits of more
than 12 inches, 28-day stream flows in the lowest 10th percentile, and basin average snow water content less than
50 percent support the short-term moderate drought (D1) across parts of Oregon and Washington.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Pugh</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
