<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030710</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may have an impact on abnormally dry or drought areas during the next 5 days (July 10-14) include: 1) A cold front will track from the northern Plains on Wednesday to the East Coast by Saturday, triggering widely-scattered thunderstorms with locally heavy rains ahead of the front. After the front passes, cooler conditions will cover the northeastern quarter of the U.S.; 2) All Gulf Coast locations will be monitoring the path of Tropical Storm Claudette; 3) A ridge of high pressure should keep most of the Rockies and Far West warm and dry.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlooks (July 15-19) have odds that favor above-normal rainfall in the western halves of Washington and Oregon and along the Gulf Coast, with subnormal precipitation from the central Plains eastward through the Midwest, mid-Atlantic, and New England. Unseasonable warmth is most likely for the northern two-thirds of the Rockies and Plains and the northeastern quarter of the country, while subnormal readings should be limited to Florida and the coastal Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>In Hawaii, near-normal June rains (4-10 inches) plus ample trade wind showers during the first week of July (2-5 inches) improved eastern Kona (Big Island) by one category to D0(A). On Kauai, near to above normal June rains and scattered light July showers (0.5-2 inches) erased abnormal dryness. Elsewhere, conditions were maintained as most windward locations observed scattered light showers, while little or no rain fell on leeward stations.</p>
   <p>Surplus rains (0.5 to 2 inches) covered much of the western and central Alaska (including 0.85" at Aniak, 1.01" at McGrath, 1.54" at Iliamna, and 2.02" at Talkeetna), erasing abnormal dryness in southwestern sections.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes, Upper Midwest, and western Corn Belt">
   <p>Several clusters of severe thunderstorms rolled across parts of the Midwest, dumping copious amounts of rain on parts of the Corn Belt. Greatest weekly totals (2 to 4 inches, locally up to a foot) were reported in northeastern Nebraska, central Minnesota, most of Iowa, southern Wisconsin, northern Illinois, and much of Indiana and Ohio. Accordingly, dryness and moderate drought was eased or alleviated in southern Michigan, northern Indiana, northwestern Illinois, and northern Minnesota. In contrast, however, little or no rain occurred across northeastern Wisconsin, most of Missouri and Kansas, and southeastern Nebraska, creating 30-day deficits of 2 to 4 inches. Combined with temperature departures of +5 to +8F, highs between 95-105F, and crops beginning to enter the critical reproductive stage (in the latter three areas), abnormal dryness was expanded to reflect agricultural concerns.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Most of New England escaped the rains that fell on the mid-Atlantic and Ohio Valley, but not summer's warmth as temperatures averaged 3 to 6F above normal. Although the Northeast experienced surplus precipitation since late 2002, northwestern New England has not fared as well, with long-term moderate drought persisting in Maine. Even the 1-2 inches of rain that fell across northern Maine did little to dent the hydrological drought, with July 1-7 averaged USGS streamflow levels in the lower 25th percentile in 73% and 68% of monitored Maine and New Hampshire rivers, respectively. Farther west, a lack of significant rain since mid-June expanded D0 into northern parts of New York and Vermont.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Although temperatures moderated somewhat, with slightly cooler than normal weather in the Pacific Northwest and along the Pacific Coast, the rest of the West recorded near or above normal readings. Highs climbed into the 90's in the Intermountain region, and into triple digits in the Southwest. With the exception of scattered light showers (0.1 to 0.3 inches) from northeastern Oregon into western Montana, the rest of the region observed no appreciable rainfall, maintaining or worsening drought. According to NASS/USDA, pasture and rangeland conditions declined, with NM (69%), AZ (50%), CA (30%), CO (25%), UT (24%), MT (22%), and OR (21%) rated poor to very poor, and some dryland spring crops were starting to show stress in Washington and Idaho. Very high to extreme fire indices were reported in all Western States except Washington, and numerous large fires were reported on July 8, including 82,000 acres (Aspen) near Tucson, AZ, and 62,000 acres (Dry Lake Complex) near Silver City, NM. Farther north, a rapid snowmelt in early June, combined with current windy, warm, and dry weather, has most likely dropped streamflows to their base summer levels earlier than normalnot good news for low reservoirs in southwestern Montana (Lima and Clark Canyon Reservoirs at 7.5% and 25% of normal capacity, respectively). As a result, D1-D3 coverage increased across western Montana. Similarly, deteriorating conditions in southeastern Oregon slightly expanded drought in Owyhee, Harney, and Malheur basins.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains">
   <p>A persistent fetch of Gulf moisture triggered scattered daily showers and thunderstorms across the southern half of Texas, easing drought or eliminating abnormal dryness across most of the area. Many southern and eastern Texas stations measured over 2 inches of rain, and the frequent cloud cover kept weekly temperatures 2 to 4F below normal. Most short and medium-term deficits were eliminated, except north of Victoria, TX, where 90-day deficiencies of 4 to 7 inches remained.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
