<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020606</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) rains likely to exceed 1 inch across the Mid-Atlantic and Southeast states during June 5-9, with near normal temperatures; 2) above normal rainfall during June 11-15 across the East Coast; 3) abundant rains over the northern Plains during June 5-9, including Minnesota, the Dakotas, and Montana; 4) above-normal temperatures and little rainfall over the central Rockies and Southwest during the next 2 weeks.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Rains in southeast Alaska resulted in the removal of D1 drought in the Panhandle, but lack of rain has contributed to high fire danger in central Alaska. D0 expanded northward into central Alaska. D0 dryness continued in western Molokai, Hawaii. Rainfall was abundant over Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>The strong thunderstorms that hit the Northeast on May 31 caused D1 drought to retreat in Maine, Connecticut, southern New York and northwestern New Jersey, but D2 (severe drought) persisted from western Long Island through southern New Jersey into Maryland. The storms missed most of this region, where rainfall deficits since last September still exceed 10 inches. Monitoring wells in central Maryland are near record lows for this time of year. One to 2-inch rainfall totals in parts of Georgia and North Carolina had little impact on drought (D1 to D3), as high temperatures offset some of the benefits of the moisture. June 2 and 3 temperatures neared triple digit levels in South Carolina and Georgia. D2 drought expanded slightly westward and northward in South Carolina due to the heat and low rainfall.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>Heavy rains along the Gulf Coast eased drought, with thunderstorms causing a slight pullback of D2/D3 drought in South Texas and the removal of drought from the Houston area. As much as 4 inches of rain caused D1 drought to retreat from much of southern Mississippi and parts of eastern Louisiana, but lesser amounts allowed D1 to D2 drought to persist across most of southern and central Alabama. Widespread showers eased dryness across Florida, with D0 retreating from the southern peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>One to 2-inch rainfall amounts in northwestern North Dakota erased D0 dryness from the northwest corner of the state, but D0 dryness continued across most of the rest of the state and northwestern Minnesota as well. Persistent below-normal rainfall resulted in D0 expanding into northeastern Minnesota. Lack of significant rain allowed D1 drought to develop in southwestern North Dakota and northwest South Dakota. Spotty showers left little impact on the moderate to extreme drought covering western Kansas and southern Nebraska. Torrid temperatures did not help the drought situation. Goodland, Kansas saw the mercury hit 104F on May 31, setting a record for the month of May. D0 dryness expanded southward and eastward across western Texas, and severe to extreme drought continued over southwestern Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Hot, dry weather maintained severe to exceptional drought across the Southwest. Arizona, Colorado, California, New Mexico, and Utah reported very high to extreme fire indices as of June 4. Temperatures soaring into the 90s and 100s broke numerous records during the last two days of May. The reading at Douglas, Arizona, for example, of 105 F on May 31 set a new mark for the month. Park City, Utah tied their monthly record with a reading of 87F on May 30. Showers did bring some relief to northern Utah and eastern Colorado, with up to 2 inches falling on northeastern Colorado during June 3-4. The moisture resulted in a slight pullback of extreme drought (D3) from northeastern CO, but the heat and lack of rain also caused a minor expansion of D1 drought northward in western Nevada and western Utah. In Arizona, Flagstaff recorded their driest May and September-May periods on record, with Flagstaff measuring no rain at all during the month of May. Farther north, rainfalls exceeding 1 inch hit eastern Idaho and southwestern and northeastern Montana. D2/D3 drought receded slightly from southwestern Montana and adjacent Idaho, while D0/D1 retreated in northeastern Montana. The area of D4 persisted in north-central Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
