<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060622</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Through July 4, moderate rain associated with a broad flow of moisture from the Gulf and Atlantic is expected along the eastern seaboard.  The drought-stricken western Central and Southern Plains, and south Texas, may experience above normal precipitation.  Isolated or scattered showers may provide some local, but not wide-scale, relief to other drought areas.  Dry weather is expected from the Northwest to the Great Lakes region.  Temperatures are expected to be above normal in the west, and below normal in the Southeast.  In Alaska, the southern half is expected to be dry, and the eastern half is expected to be warm.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Gulf Coast">
   <p>Despite a few scattered thunderstorms, D0 to D3 conditions persisted in concert with increasing moisture deficits. An exception was the Houston area, over which torrential rains of up to 10 inches fell.  Most of the current D1 areas recorded 8 to 16 inches less rain than normal for the last 90 days, with 16- to 24-inch deficits reported in southern Mississippi and southeastern Louisiana. Since the middle of last June, precipitation totals were more than 20 inches below normal in southeastern Louisiana, southern Mississippi, and coastal sections of Alabama and the Florida Panhandle.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Outlying Areas">
   <p>Abnormally dry conditions persisted in southeastern Alaska and parts of northwestern Hawaii.  In Puerto Rico, rainfall was scattered with light to moderate intensity.  Alaska experienced two large wildfires.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Tropical Storm Alberto dropped widespread moderate to heavy rains on most areas of dryness and drought in the Southeast and mid-Atlantic coastal and piedmont regions. As a result, dryness ended in the eastern parts of Georgia, northward to the Chesapeake Bay, and D1 conditions improved to D0 slightly farther to the north and west. Conditions were essentially unchanged in drier parts of the region north of Florida.   Beneficial rains in South Florida improved conditions from D1 to D0.</p>
   <p>Drought intensified in the western Carolinas, with precipitation for the year being about two-thirds of normal or less.  Consequently, this area has been downgraded to D2.  Note that because of topographical influences on weather patterns, drought was occurring east of the Appalachian ridge line (North Carolina-Tennessee border), but normal conditions were experienced west of the ridge line.  The situation of improvement on the west side of the ridge and drought intensification on the east side resulted in a sharp discontinuity of conditions at the ridge line.  Elsewhere outside of the track of Alberto, only scattered light to moderate rains were observed, allowing dryness and drought to persist.  The driest areas were in a narrow band just east of the Appalachian ridge.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Beneficial heavy rainfall alleviated some of the dryness in parts of Nebraska, Iowa and South Dakota.  Weekly totals of 2 to 4 inches were common in these regions.  In western Oklahoma, rainfall totals of 1 to 3 inches led to a shrinking of the D3 area. Although conditions improved, the long-term drought conditions persisted.  According to the Lincoln Journal Star, in Nebraska, Gov. Heineman added 28 counties to a request for federal drought disaster relief, bringing the total to 36. The counties have suffered at least a 30 percent loss in one or more crop or livestock areas.  More than half of Nebraskas wheat crop was rated as poor or very poor, almost half of the pastures were rated poor or very poor, and cattle producers have been forced to cull herds in many areas.</p>
   <p>Relatively dry conditions elsewhere led to broad areas of dryness expansion and drought deterioration.  The D1 region of Iowa expanded northward, and the D0 and D1 areas of Illinois expanded eastward.  The lower peninsula of Michigan was becoming drier, and the D0 area of Kansas was also becoming drier, but the depiction for these areas was not changed from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West">
   <p>Similar to areas farther east, isolated heavy rains led to small areas of drought improvement, but dryness persisted in a vast majority of the Rockies and Southwest.  Numerous wildfires have been reported in Arizona and New Mexico</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Ned Guttman</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
