<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20081016</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (October 16 - 20, 2008), between 1.5 and 2.5 inches of precipitation are expected in the dry areas of the central Texas Coast while lesser amounts (0.5 to 1.5 inches) are forecast for adjacent central Texas and the dry areas of northwesternmost Pennsylvania and adjacent New York, east-central North Carolina, northeastern Indiana, and part of Michigan's Upper Peninsula. Meanwhile, light precipitation (less than 0.5 inch) can be expected along the northern tier of the country and in most areas from the Great Plains eastward to the Atlantic Coast while little or no precipitation is forecast for central and southern sections of the Rockies, High Plains, and Far West, as well as west-central Florida. During this 5-day period, temperatures should average above normal from the northern Great Plains and southern High Plains westward into the West Coast states, and near normal elsewhere.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (October 21 - 25, 2008), the odds favor above-normal precipitation across the Appalachians, the middle and upper Ohio Valley, the Great Lakes region, the central and northeastern Great Plains, the south-central High Plains, and from central Montana westward through the dry areas of Washington and all but southernmost Oregon. Meanwhile, below-normal precipitation is favored from the north-central High Plains southwestward through most of the central and southern Rockies, much of Nevada, and the southern two-thirds of California. Below-normal precipitation is also favored from central and southern Texas eastward through Alabama and southwestern Georgia, and across northwestern Alaska. During this period, above-normal temperatures are expected in the Southwest, the northern Rockies, the Plains from central Texas northward, and most of the Great Lakes region. In contrast, the odds favor cooler than normal conditions in northwestern Alaska and from central and eastern Georgia northeastward through the Appalachians, the upper half of the Ohio Valley, the easternmost Great Lakes region, the Carolinas, the Virginia Piedmont, Delaware, and New Jersey.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Only 2 isolated locations reported over 1 inch of rain in Hawaii, where D0 to D3 conditions cover the entire island chain. A few other scattered sites received 0.5 to 1.0 inch, but most locations in Hawaii measured only a few tenths of an inch. Farther north, the abnormally dry area in northwestern Alaska recorded 0.3 inch or less. This left dryness and drought in Hawaii and Alaska unchanged from the previous week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes and Upper Midwest">
   <p>A couple of wet weeks in areas west of the Great Lakes led to a substantial reduction in the extent of D0 to D1 across northern and western Minnesota, adjacent areas of eastern South Dakota, northeastern Nebraska, and western and northern Iowa, where 3-month rainfall totals range from slightly below normal to considerably above normal. In contrast, only light precipitation fell on the dry areas farther east as D0 to D2 conditions expanded northeastward across the Upper Peninsula of Michigan and northeastern Wisconsin, and persisted across the remainder of Wisconsin.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Moderate precipitation fell on most of eastern Montana and the northwestern Dakotas, including snowfall totals locally approaching 1 foot. In conjunction with a wet first week of October, this led to the elimination of D3 conditions and a substantial reduction in the extent of D0 to D2 designations throughout the area. Farther south, moderate to heavy precipitation also fell on parts of northern and eastern New Mexico, the Texas Panhandle, southwestern Oklahoma and adjacent Texas, much of eastern Colorado, western Kansas, the eastern Nebraska Panhandle, and adjacent South Dakota. As a result, D2 conditions near the Oklahoma/Kansas/Colorado triple point were eliminated, and D0 to D1 designations across the central High Plains contracted.</p>
   <p>Farther south and east, little or no precipitation fell on the dry areas of central and western Texas, the central Red River Valley, and central Oklahoma, where drought classifications remained constant or deteriorated. More specifically, D0 expanded to cover south-central Oklahoma, and D2 to D3 designations pushed southeastward across interior southeastern Texas.  Some improvements were introduced in central Texas (a slight reduction in the northward extent of D1 and D2) and west-central Texas (the elimination of D1 conditions), but these were based on a reassessment of conditions, and not as a result of any significant precipitation this past week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and East Coast">
   <p>Moderate to heavy rains were reported in most areas from the southern Atlantic states westward through Alabama and northwestward to the Mississippi and lower Ohio rivers. Almost all of these areas recorded over 1 inch of rain, with isolated totals exceeding 5 inches in northeastern, upper coastal, and south-central Georgia. Only southwestern Alabama, parts of southwestern Georgia, and the west-central Florida Peninsula received less than 1 inch. These rains substantially improved surface moisture conditions; however, because of the large precipitation shortfalls that have accumulated during the past 2 to 3 years (more than 1.5 feet over the interior Southeast, even after last week's rainfall), hydrologic drought improvement was much more limited, and the Drought Monitor reflects primarily this long-term drought situation. D0 to D2 conditions improved in western sections of Tennessee and Kentucky, and across central and northern Alabama. Farther east, exceptional drought (D4) receded from part of upstate South Carolina. From north-central Georgia northeastward through western South Carolina, and across central Tennessee, most locations recorded at least 2 inches of rain, but because of the large long-term precipitation deficits still existent throughout these areas, the only change made to the Drought Monitor was to replace former D1AH to D4AH conditions with D1H to D4H designations.</p>
   <p>Farther north, conditions were considerably drier last week. From south-central Kentucky, eastern Tennessee, and central North Carolina northward to at least the Canadian Border, only a few areas measured over 0.5 inch of rain as dryness and drought persisted or intensified. D1 to D2 conditions expanded northward near the middle Ohio Valley and the southwestern Virginias while D3 designations expanded to cover eastern Tennessee and south-central Kentucky, where precipitation totals for the past 6 months are generally 8 to 12 inches below normal. Farther north, increasing short-term moisture deficits prompted D0 expansion into eastern Ohio, northern West Virginia, central and western Pennsylvania, and westernmost New York. Over the last 3 months, only 25 to 70 percent of normal precipitation fell on these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Heavy snow blanketed much of central and western Wyoming and the southern tier of Montana, with the largest amounts (10 to 33 inches) piling up on the north-central Wyoming highlands, a few sites in central Wyoming, and the eastward-facing slopes of the western Wyoming mountains. Note, however, that snowfall totals were highly variable, as is typical in mountainous terrain, and a number of locations in central and western Wyoming recorded only a few inches of snow, if any. In terms of liquid-equivalent precipitation, the eastward-facing slopes of the west-central Wyoming mountains measured 2 to 3 inches, with amounts over an inch common across southern Montana and most of central and western Wyoming. This led to the elimination of abnormal dryness and a decline in the northern extent of D1 conditions through most of southwestern Montana and part of central Wyoming.</p>
   <p>In contrast, precipitation was neither as heavy nor as widespread across the remainder of the dry areas in the West. Isolated precipitation totals of 1 to 3 inches were reported in southeastern Idaho and northeastern Nevada, but most of the region received only a few tenths of an inch, if any. As a result, drought designations remained unchanged outside of Montana and Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
