<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20051026</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next five days (October 27  31), the upper level flow will continue to have a ridge in the west and trough in the east over the contiguous US. Dry conditions will prevail throughout most of the country, although the Pacific Northwest, parts of the Southeast and areas around the Great Lakes may experience wetter than normal conditions. A frontal system passing through the country during this time may also bring an increased chance of precipitation to the drought areas in Texas.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing five days (November 1 - 5) there are favorable conditions for below normal temperatures along the East Coast, while the western two-thirds of the US should have above normal temperatures. Dry conditions will continue in most areas, while the Northwest will continue to have above normal precipitation. An upper level trough will dominate over Alaska, increasing the possibility of precipitation along the panhandle and coastal areas and bringing colder than normal temperatures statewide.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Several areas of Alaska received rainfall this drought monitoring period. Juneau, reported 3.12 inches, Kodiak 3.71 inches, Bethel with 1.4 inches and Cordova with 1.12 inches, leaving Alaska drought free this period.</p>
   <p>For Hawaii, Honolulu reported 1.27 inches of rainfall and Hilo reported 2.27 inches, other areas had moderate amounts of rainfall leaving the abnormally dry conditions status quo for this drought monitoring period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Widespread showers affected the eastern regions of the nation during this drought monitoring period; however, some of the abnormally dry areas were missed. In the Southeast, the D0AH in western North Carolina was expanded eastward due to local feedback of dry soils and stressed vegetation. In the central part of the state, the previous D0H and D1H drought areas were changed from H only impacts to both AH impacts due to local reports of stressed vegetation and dry soils in that area of the state as well. In southwestern Virginia, the severe drought area was removed due to 0.5-1.0 inch precipitation amounts that fell this period. The region has also been experiencing cooler temperatures which have kept evapotranspiration low. Local fire officials reported fine fuels are wet and that fire hazards have been reduced. In West Virginia, 1-2 inch rainfall amounts this period alleviated drought in the central part of the state where a donut hole of D-nothing was cut over climate division 2. USGS streamflow maps, 7-, 14- and 30-day percent of normal precipitation maps also show this area improving.</p>
   <p>Abnormally dry conditions were introduced into northwestern Georgia and northeastern Alabama. This area received minimal amounts of precipitation during the drought monitoring period. The Climate Prediction Centers (CPC) short term blends, soil moisture percentiles and precipitation anomaly maps all support this introduction, as well as all time frames of the ACIS percent of normal precipitation maps out to 90 days. In Florida, the southern portion of D0 was retracted due to rainfall totals of 4-8 inches deposited by Hurricane Wilma. However, Wilmas rainfall did not make it far enough north to support total removal of the abnormally dry conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Several drought areas in this region received rainfall this period; however, amounts were not substantial enough to warrant improvements. In Lower Michigan, D1AH and D2AH were expanded eastward to cover climate divisions 9 and 8, respectively. USGS stream flow, Midwest Regional Climate Centers (MRCC) 12 and 72 inch depth soil moisture maps, and ACIS 7-, 14-, 30-, 60- and 90-day percent of normal precipitation maps are all showing this area dry. Conditions remained status quo in Illinois, with information from the Illinois NASS report indicating dry, hard soils are making fall tillage activities difficult. Even though the growing season is ending, agricultural impacts were still being experienced.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The High Plains, Rockies, and Far West">
   <p>This region of the nation received minimal amounts of precipitation during this drought monitoring period. The only change made was in northern Montana along the Canadian border. A slight southward retraction of abnormally dry conditions was made based on recent precipitation amounts up to 0.5 inch as well as wetness being indicated on many time frames out to 12 months of the ACIS percent of normal maps. No change was made to Wyoming this drought monitoring period; however, the sugarbeet harvest is currently about one week behind due to unseasonable warm temperatures, with only 49% being harvested compared to 61% last year and 73% for the 5 year average. While rainfall amounts of up to one inch fell in the abnormally dry area of Arizonas D0H, no change was made this period. Long-term hydrological impacts are still being felt in this area. The Native American Hualapai Tribe reported earlier in the month that they have had to postpone their tribe-sponsored Colorado River running trips because the boat ramp is still closed due to low water levels. The Tribe has also indicated slow recovery to rangelands, wetlands, wildlife and water supplies and has cut back the number of hunting licenses allowed to tourists in hopes to help bring relief for wildlife.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Very few areas in the Plains and Mississippi Valley received relief this drought monitoring period. In Iowa, the southern portion of the severe drought in climate divisions 7 and 8 was retracted slightly northward due to 2-3 inches of precipitation. In northern Missouri, D1 and D0 areas were also slightly retracted. All of the above changes are supported by the ACIS 7- and 14-day percent of normal precipitation maps and local input. Elsewhere in the Plains, D0A was introduced into the Texas and Oklahoma panhandles, westward into parts of eastern New Mexico. This introduction is due to minimal amounts of precipitation this period as well as the ACIS 30- and 60-day percent of normal maps. Also in Oklahoma, the D2AH area was expanded northward to cover the southeastern corner of the state and the D1AH and D0 areas expanded westward.  Parts of southeast Oklahoma were the driest on record since 1921 with only 12.69 inches year-to-date precipitation totals as of the end of the period, which is 13.51 inches below normal. Media reports the dry weather is withering fishing grounds, farms and the fall foliage in the area and a red flag fire alert was issued for 19 counties October 21. In other parts of Texas, the abnormally dry area in the central part of the state was expanded westward to cover all of climate division 3. Also in this region, D3AH was introduced into the Dallas- Fort Worth metropolis. Minimal rainfall affected this eastern portion of the state during this drought monitoring period. The CPC blends, soil moisture, ACIS 30- and 60-day percent of normal precipitation maps all support worsening conditions. Further south, the two D1AH areas were connected and extended eastward to the Galveston Bay area. Waco has received only 0.99 inch of rainfall since September 1, a negative 4.91 departure from normal. Austin International Airport reported only 19.37 inches for their year-to-date totals, which is 9.04 below normal. Statewide Texas wheat condition was rated 57% of normal, compared with 90% last year.</p>
   <p>In Arkansas, moderate drought (D1) and abnormally dry (D0) conditions were expanded eastward and southward to account for short-term dryness since the end of September. Changes were based on local feedback of below normal precipitation for the past three weeks, USGS streamflow reports, and the ACIS 30-day percent of normal precipitation map. The past three weeks of little to no rainfall in this area have begun to show impacts, with USDA reporting the wheat crop rated 29% very poor to poor with pastures rating 58% very poor to poor.</p>
   <p>Although Hurricanes Katrina and Rita both affected Louisiana in August and September, respectively, D0 was introduced as far east as Monroe southward to Lafayette. Most of this area is experiencing only 30-60 percent of normal year-to-date precipitation. Many areas have deficits as large as 20 inches below normal. Alexandrias year-to-date precipitation total is only 26.66 inches, which is 21.61 below normal. Lafayettes year-to-date precipitation total is only 31.01 inches, which is 20.23 below normal. This may be an area to watch for worsening conditions in coming weeks if precipitation amounts remain minimal.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Liz Love-Brotak</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
