<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20021121</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through November 30 which may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: Over the next 5 days (November 21-25): 1) The ridge upper air pattern in the West and the trough in the East will continue to bring warmer than average temperatures across the western U.S. while the eastern half of the country should remain cooler than average into early next week; 2) a low pressure system and an associated cold front should develop over the Great Lakes states and scattered showers are anticipated across the area; 3) rainfall is expected to develop along and ahead of the frontal boundary in the Great Lakes and is projected to move northeast, initiating precipitation from the central Gulf Coast through the Mid Atlantic states and into New England. Precipitation totals could be up to 1 inch along the Appalachian Range to the Gulf Coast and potentially over 2 inches in New England; 4) rain and snow are forecast across parts of central and southeastern Alaska throughout much of this period while Hawaii is expected to remain dry.</p>
   <p>For the 6-10 day period (November 26-30), expect the ridge in the West and trough in the East to remain intact. This will continue to bring warmer than average conditions across much of the West with little to no precipitation anticipated across the region over this period. Cooler than average temperatures are expected across much of the eastern U.S. throughout the period. Precipitation should return across Hawaii as tropical moisture south of the islands moves northward.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>The situation in Hawaii remained unchanged from last week, with moderate hydrological drought (D1 W) being confined to the western parts of Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>It was another wet week over the drought areas in the eastern United States, with a major winter storm over the Northeast. Two inches, or more, of rain (or liquid equivalent snow/ice) fell over a huge swath from northeast Georgia all the way to central Maine. Streams were high, topsoil saturated, reservoirs continued to fill, and many drought indicators, especially the short-term indicators, signaled wet conditions. The New York City Delaware River Basin reservoirs continued their march above the long-term median. In New Jersey, the only remaining concern was the south Jersey unconfined aquifers.</p>
   <p>D1 (moderate drought) was eliminated from New Jersey to southern Virginia, D2 (severe drought) removed from the Carolinas, and D1 reduced in the Carolinas. The southern boundaries of D0 and D1 areas were shaved back in Maine. The D0 in southern Florida was wiped out by widespread 2 inch rains with locally heavier amounts.</p>
   <p>This month marks the third consecutive wet month across much of the eastern drought areas, indicating that the short-term drought is over. Well observations show ground water levels increasing, however levels are still significantly below 1998 levels, up to 10 feet or more behind in some locations. According to USGS reports, the real-time well in Baltimore County, Maryland, is a deep well and has finally responded to the recent rains, after 15 months of declining water levels. But it is still below the record low levels set in the 1960s. Some Georgia users depend on ground water for up to 90 percent of their water supplies. Wells were still going dry this week around Maryland and Virginia. Water use restrictions continued in many eastern U.S. towns dependent on ground water. Some estimates call for several more months of above normal precipitation before the ground water levels fully recover. Substantial 12-month to 24-month precipitation deficits remain, especially in the Maine and Southeast to Mid-Atlantic areas. Consequently, D0 was left in place from New Jersey to southern Virginia, and D0 to D1 across the Carolinas and Georgia, to indicate the presence of these long-term hydrological drought conditions.</p>
   <p>Locally heavy rains fell over parts of western Puerto Rico this week. However, long-term conditions (out to 8 weeks) continued to be drier than normal, so no change was made to the D0 on the island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley, Great Lakes, and Plains">
   <p>A dry week for this region. Where precipitation fell it was generally below-normal amounts. D0 expanded into central Iowa in line with the drought indicators, westward across northern Illinois reflecting drying soil conditions, and into north central Arkansas to reflect recent and 90-day dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The week had wet bookends in the Pacific Northwest with precipitation amounts of 2 inches or more in the upslope areas of the Coastal and Cascade mountains of Washington and northwest Oregon (roughly near normal for the week), but only a few tenths to the lee of the Cascades. The depiction was improved in this area last week due to a major Pacific storm. The objective indicators suggest at least D0 should be kept in place across the region, with D1 to D3 in the interior, to reflect the long-term deficits. The only change in the Pacific Northwest was to shift the A boundary to the east of the Cascades.</p>
   <p>Half an inch of precipitation fell, with a few heavier reports, in northern Idaho and northwest Montana. This resulted in some improvement to the snowpack, but it was short-lived as this is early in the snow season and normals continue to increase thus making Water-Year-to-date percentages decrease. Many months of above-normal precipitation are needed to make up the long-term deficits, so no change was made here.</p>
   <p>Mountain precipitation for the water year to date was near or above average for this early season in Alaska. Snow water content in the mountain snowpack was below average for this time of year due to recent warmer than average conditions, but temperatures were cooling back to normal winter levels this week.</p>
   <p>The rest of the West was generally dry with little or no precipitation. No change was made to the drought categories to reflect continuing long-term moisture deficits.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Karin Gleason</name>
   <affiliation>National Centers for Environmental Information</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
