<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020124</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) generally above-normal rainfall across the East, especially in the southern Appalachians, with abundant rains on Thursday-Saturday, January 24-26 and again on Tuesday-Friday, January 29-February 1; 2) abundant rain and snow across the Pacific Northwest through Monday, January 28 followed by drier weather; and 3) little precipitation from southern California to the southern and central Plains states, although above-normal rainfall is expected across southern Texas, including the Big Bend area, during January 31-February 6.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Little rain fell over southern Puerto Rico this week, resulting in no change in the dryness depiction. Heavy rainfall hit windward areas of Hawaii, with much lower amounts in leeward areas. Moisture in the D0 and D1 areas on Oahu and elsewhere was not enough to result in changed categories.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Thanks largely to a storm system tracking northeastward across the South on Saturday, January 19, weekly precipitation amounts exceeded 2 inches across northern Georgia, eastern Tennessee, and parts of North Carolina and western South Carolina, while 1-inch totals covered large parts of the South and southern mid-Atlantic region. As a result, drought categories improved by one category over northern Georgia and eastern Tennessee and severe drought (D2) diminished slightly in North Carolina and southeastern Virginia. The first general snowfall of the season across the mid-Atlantic I-95 corridor had little impact on long-term moisture deficits. Severe drought (D2) remained from central and eastern Georgia to southeastern Virginia and north to New England.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>ight precipitation totals this week resulted in little change to the drought extending from southern Kansas through west Texas and into New Mexico. As the dryness is having an impact on agriculture and fire danger, the W designation was removed from South and West Texas. Abnormal dryness (D0) continued in parts of Iowa, Nebraska, and the Dakotas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Storm activity picked up across the Pacific Northwest over the weekend, allowing snow pack to increase. D1 drought continued to retreat in northern Idaho and eastern Washington and Oregon. Little to no precipitation caused some further expansion of abnormal dryness in Arizona and a slight westward migration of D0 and D1 dryness in southern New Mexico. An area of D0 (abnormal dryness) has developed in southern California. Cumulative rainfall this season has been near or under 50% of normal in Los Angeles and San Diego.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
