<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061012</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>By the end of October 16,  heavy rains (1.5 to locally 9.0 inches) should have fallen on south-central and southeastern Texas, with moderate totals (0.5 to 1.5 inches) forecast for the rest of central and eastern Texas and from the central Gulf Coast northward through Arkansas and Tennessee. In addition, moderate amounts are forecast for the Pacific Northwest, parts of western Montana, the northern and eastern Great Lakes region, and central through southeastern Arizona. Other areas currently experiencing abnormal dryness or drought are expected to receive light precipitation at best, with little or none anticipated in northeastern Florida, southeastern Georgia, the central and northern Great Plains, the High Plains, and the central Rockies. For the ensuing 5 days (October 17  21), the odds favor above-normal precipitation in the northern Plains and Rockies, across the southern Rockies, and in a large swath extending from the central and western Gulf Coast northward through the Great Lakes region. In contrast, below-normal precipitation appears most likely along the Pacific Northwest coastline, and in Florida and adjacent sections of the southern Atlantic Seaboard.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>A few inches of rain dampened some of the climatologically wet parts of the state, but most locations received light rainfall at best. As a result, D0 to D1 conditions persisted across the Islands.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Moderate rains of 2 to 4 inches fell on parts of eastern Puerto Rico while most other areas received 1 inch or less. These amounts did not significantly affect the moisture deficits that have been established during the past few months, thus D0 conditions remained intact.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Moderate to heavy precipitation fell on most of the central and south-central Great Plains, the southern High Plains, and parts of the upper Mississippi Valley and Great Lakes region, with isolated amounts of up to 4 inches reported in the northern Texas Panhandle. In contrast, little or no precipitation fell on South Dakota, central and eastern Wyoming, adjacent parts of Colorado and Nebraska, the east-central and southeastern Great Plains, and the middle and lower Mississippi Valley.</p>
   <p>The precipitation induced drought improvement in a few areas across northern New Mexico, the Texas and Oklahoma Panhandles, and central Nebraska. In contrast, the dry week led to the expansion of D4AH conditions into south-central Oklahoma, the introduction of D3AH conditions in part of north-central Oklahoma, and significant D2AH expansion in portions of central and western Oklahoma, southeastern Kansas, adjacent Missouri, and a small part of the ArkLaTex region. In addition, some D0AH and D1AH expansion took place in Illinois, extreme southeastern Iowa, and part of northwestern Arkansas. During the last 60 days, most of the east-central and southeastern Plains and the middle Mississippi Valley received less than 70 percent of normal precipitation, with less than half of normal reported in most of the D2AH to D4AH areas.</p>
   <p>Farther southeast, D1AH and D2AH conditions spread southward along the Sabine River that separates Texas from Louisiana, with D2AH reaching as far south as the Toledo Bend Reservoir, which is at its lowest level since it was built almost 40 years ago. In much of a broad area from western Missouri and southeastern Kansas southward through much of Oklahoma, Arkansas, Louisiana, and the central and eastern sections of Texas, precipitation totals for the past year have been at least a foot below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Cool and wet weather covered much of the regions areas of dryness and drought last week, abetting improved conditions for many locations. Widespread precipitation totals of 1 to 3 inches, with isolated amounts exceeding 5 inches, brought an end to abnormal dryness in central Idaho, most of eastern Utah, and much of western Colorado. Meanwhile, similar totals engendered 1-category improvements from last weeks conditions in west-central Montana, much of northeastern Arizona, and part of south-central Colorado. Over the course of the past year, less than half of normal precipitation was reported in most of north-central and southwestern Wyoming, and from the lingering D3AH in Arizona southwestward toward California.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Gulf Coast">
   <p>Isolated light to moderate rain fell on several small areas, but a vast majority of the region received little or no rain for the week, allowing dryness and drought to persist or intensify. D0AH expanded to include portions of north-central and western Tennessee, more of northern South Carolina, a little more of the Florida Peninsula, and southeastern Texas. D1AH conditions also expanded, now newly covering the north-central and northeastern Florida Peninsula, southeastern and part of northeastern Georgia, northwestern South Carolina, west-central Mississippi, and the northern half of Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
