<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001012</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect some of the areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) moisture associated with the remnants of Tropical Storm Olivia is expected to bring potentially heavy rains into southern areas of Arizona and New Mexico October 11-12; 2) unsettled weather in the western U.S. October 11-12 will move eastward into the Plains and could provide generous rains October 13-15 in a corridor from Minnesota and Michigan southward into western Texas; and 3) the latest 6-10 day forecast from the Climate Prediction Center (valid October 17-21) shows much of the nation with above-normal temperatures along with above-normal precipitation along the Gulf Coast, which may help ease long-term drought conditions in this region.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Long-term dryness and drought continues to affect leeward parts of all the islands in Hawaii. Severe drought (D2), with agricultural and wildfire-related impacts, occurs on the leeward sides of the islands of Maui and Hawaii. Abnormally dry conditions also continue along the northeastern coast of Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Rains during the previous week, and some snow October 9-10, helped improve the abnormally dry conditions (D0) across eastern and northern Maine. Precipitation totals were lowest in the far northern part of the state, around Caribou, and this area remains in the D0 classification.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The major story for the week in this region was the cold outbreak and the associated rains across southern Texas. Lake-effect snows and rains in the Upper Peninsula of Michigan brought 12.3 inches of snow to Marquette, but generally missed the areas with abnormally dry conditions (D0). Heavy rains did improve dryness and drought conditions in south-central South Dakota and around the Kansas City, MO, area. Meanwhile, another dry week expanded D1 (first stage drought) conditions into west-central and southwest Minnesota.</p>
   <p>Hurricane Keith made landfall in northeastern Mexico October 6. The remnants of Keith, combined with a cold front pushing through southern Texas, provided a wet four days (October 7-10) for the D3, D2, and D1 drought areas along the Rio Grande River. Brownsville, for example, has received 1.91 inches of precipitation since October 1, although its year-to-date departure is still greater than 8.0 inches. In addition, the maximum temperatures associated with the cold front were up to 30 degrees below the normal highs for these dates. Snow, sleet, and freezing rain was reported in and around Alpine, TX, in Brewster County. As a result, extreme drought (D3) conditions along part of the Rio Grande River have improved to a D2 classification, and severe drought (D2) in far southern Texas has improved to a D1 classification.</p>
   <p>Much of western Texas north of Interstate 10 did not receive any precipitation during the week. Drought conditions deteriorated, and Abilene, San Angelo, and Lubbock were included into an extreme drought (D3) classification. Year-to-date departures in Abilene and San Angelo are -8.91 inches and -9.16 inches, respectively. Lubbock has had only 0.04 inches of precipitation since September 1.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>Beneficial rains fell across large portions of the South and Southeast during the past week. The heaviest rains associated with a disturbance that later became Tropical Storm Leslie fell in southern Florida, but were generally south of the drought areas in the state. Exceptional (D4) and extreme (D3) drought conditions were upgraded one category in Mississippi, Louisiana, and Arkansas thanks to good rains. A second consecutive week with abundant precipitation in western Arkansas, northwestern Louisiana, and eastern Texas improved much of this area to the D1 (first stage) category. Severe drought (D2) remains in areas along the Louisiana-Texas border and between Houston and Beaumont that have missed the recent rains.</p>
   <p>Rains during the week also missed the greater Tampa and Orlando metropolitan areas. Long-term rainfall deficits remain, with year-to-date departures of -12.55 inches and -14.63 inches, respectively. An area of D2 (severe) drought conditions was added to the west-central coast of the Florida Peninsula. The past week was also dry in the southern Appalachian Mountains along the Tennessee-North Carolina border into southwestern Virginia. Daily streamflows continue to run at record lows in this region, according to USGS, and the area was included into the D1(W) and D0(W) classifications. Asheville, NC, has a year-to-date departure of -7.92 inches, and a departure since January 1, 1999, of -15.66 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation in the central part of New Mexico helped relieve drought conditions there, while no precipitation in the northern part of the state led to an expansion of D2 (severe drought) conditions. The extreme drought (D3) conditions in western Texas did expand into eastern New Mexico as well. In Arizona, another mostly dry week with above-normal temperatures supported a slight expansion of D2 (severe drought) conditions in the northern part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
