<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070125</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (January 25-29), after a brief warm-up, several cold fronts will push southward out of Canada, dropping temperatures across the eastern two-thirds of the nation and producing lake-effect snows in the Great Lakes region.  Meanwhile, two systems, including a stalled front over the Gulf of Mexico and a developing low pressure center, will trigger showers and thunderstorms along the Gulf Coast, including Florida and southern Texas, early and then later in the period.  Elsewhere, seasonable readings are forecast for the western third of the U.S., with mostly dry weather prevailing across the remainder of the lower 48 states.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6-10 day outlook (January 30-February 3) calls for subnormal precipitation in much of the West, in the middle Mississippi and Ohio Valleys, and southeastern Alaska.  An El Nio-like pattern of wetter-than-normal conditions is expected across the southern tier of states, from eastern Arizona to South Carolina and Florida, and in the western half of Alaska.  Unseasonably cold weather is forecast for the eastern two-thirds of the nation, with above-normal readings limited to California, Nevada, and especially Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Puerto Rico, and Alaska">
   <p>Tranquil weather was observed across Hawaii, with only a few light showers reported on the windward side of Kauai, Maui, and the Big Island early in the period, then not much at all from the weekend on.  As a result, abnormal dryness developed across eastern parts of Oahu and Maui and now covers all of Hawaii.</p>
   <p>In Puerto Rico, shower activity was confined to the northern half of the island, with little or no rain falling on southern sections. For the past 30-, 60-, 90-, and 180-days, generally less than 60% of normal precipitation has been observed across southern and southeastern portions, with 90- and 180-day deficits reaching more than 8 and 12 inches, respectively, in the southeast.  Accordingly, D0 was expanded to cover the &lt;60% area, and D1 added where 3- and 6-month deficits were greatest.</p>
   <p>Temperatures continued to moderate in Alaska, with early Januarys Arctic blast a thing of the past. With weekly readings 5 to 10F above normal, significant precipitation (more than an inch) was limited to along the southern and southeastern coastal areas.  With normal precipitation generally low in the winter in central interior Alaska, abnormal dryness was maintained.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>In the lower Midwest, additional precipitation, mainly in the form of light snow (2-6 inches), blanketed much of the Corn Belt, with slightly greater totals (4-10 inches) farther west in the central Great Plains. Since mid-December, frequent precipitation (&gt;150% of normal precipitation) has produced short-term surpluses in the western Corn Belt and lower Missouri Valley, improving conditions.  D0(H), however, remained in a few areas (southwest and northeast Missouri, southeast Iowa) where long-term deficits remained and recent precipitation was not as great.  In addition, drought conditions persisted in the upper Midwest and northern Plains, with little or no precipitation, moderating temperatures (weekly departures +4 to +8F), and an increasing shallow snow pack.</p>
   <p>Farther south, another round of beneficial precipitation fell on the central and southern Plains, making this the fourth (of five) wet week since mid-December.  Liquid equivalents of 0.5 to 1.5 inches were common in Kansas, Oklahoma, and northern Texas, with 1.5 to 2.5 inches in southwestern Texas.  Accordingly, short- to medium-term surpluses have developed across much of these three states, with topsoil moisture now mostly adequate to abundant, and a general one-category improvement was made.  Long-term deficits, subsoil moisture deficiencies, and low reservoir levels, however, still existed in parts of northern Oklahoma, southern Kansas, and south-central Texas, maintaining hydrological impacts (H).  For example, the Oklahoma Water Resources Board announced plans for the release of 15,000 acre-feet of water from Canton Lake to supplement supply in Oklahoma Citys central Oklahoma lakes.  Canton Lake, currently at about 60% capacity, should normally be at full capacity.  In addition, some parts of Texas, namely from Del Rio and north of Laredo northward to San Angelo and Brownwood, missed out on the recent heavy precipitation as compared to the surrounding area, and their water year (since October 1) percent of normal precipitation stood at only 50-75% of normal.  With reports of low lake levels (e.g., Lake Lometa only at 20% capacity), subnormal stream flows, and low or dry stock tanks, D2-D4 remained.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Appalachians">
   <p>With a more west to east upper-air flow, this weeks storm system, in conjunction with ample subtropical moisture, dropped widespread light to moderate precipitation (1-2 inches) on the Southeast, and slightly less (0.5-1 inches) on the Appalachians. January precipitation has been enough to alleviate abnormal dryness in most of the Appalachians and Southeast, although parts of the Appalachians and eastern Tennessee Valley still had lingering 30-, 60-, and 90-day deficits between 2 and 4 inches, and D0 remained there.  In northern Georgia, Lake Lanier, the primary water source for Atlanta, was still 3 feet below the winter guidance, creating low flows (and D0(H)) in the Chattahoochee River Valley.  In contrast, Florida (except the Panhandle) missed out on the widespread rainfall.  Temperatures averaged more than 4F above normal with highs in the 80s, and only 0.2 to 0.5 inches of rain was reported.  USGS 7-, 14-, and 28-day stream flows remained in the lower 10th percentile in north-central areas, and the KBDI (fire danger) remained high in southern Florida.  Although January normally has the least impact toward drought in Florida (rainfall, evaporation, temperatures, and water demand is usually low), it is also an ideal time for surplus rainfall to occur and diminish any lingering dryness.  Unfortunately, as more time passes and the expected El Nio-induced heavy rains fail to occur, drought concerns and impacts will increase.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southwest and Rocky Mountains">
   <p>Although temperatures slowly moderated from last weeks long-lasting, devastating freeze in California, they still averaged 4 to 8F below normal. Once again, precipitation was nearly absent throughout the Southwest and Great Basin, continuing the disappointing wet season (since October 1) in this region, and realistically leaving only 2 more months when decent precipitation could occur.  Water year-to-date Sierra Nevada basin average precipitation was only 51-62% of normal, and Jan. 23 basin average snow water content (SWC) stood at 37-50%, according to the NRCS.  This season follows a poor and spotty 2006 summer monsoon, and a dry 2005-06 wet season. If it wasnt for the near- to record wet 2004-05 winter season in the Southwest, conditions would be even worse.  Fortunately in California, major state averaged reservoirs stood at 70% of capacity, or 119% of normal, as of Dec. 31.  Rain-fed pastures, ranges, and wildlife, however, are in poor to dismal shape, with wildfire danger remaining high, especially in southern California. With 12-month precipitation less than 70% of normal in the southern half of California, western Nevada, and western Arizona, and under 50% in the desert Southwest, D0-D2(A) was expanded northward to reflect the growing precipitation deficits.  Meanwhile in southwestern Montana, another week with little or no precipitation dropped SWC to record low levels, expanding severe and developing extreme drought into the Shields river basin that includes the Bridger and Crazy Mountains.</p>
   <p>In contrast, eastern portions of the Southwest benefited from mid- and late-week systems that dropped badly needed precipitation (liquid equivalents of 0.5 to 1.7 inches) on eastern Arizona and southern New Mexico.  With plenty of cold air, much of the precipitation fell as welcome snow in the higher elevations, greatly increasing the water year-to-date basin average SWC.  For example, Jan. 16 basin average SWC stood at 42-54% of normal in central Arizona, and 42-69% of normal in western New Mexico. One week later, those numbers increased to 63-78% and 81-124%, respectively. With conditions better in New Mexico thanks to its record wet summer monsoon, D0 was erased in southwestern and southeastern sections. In Arizona, extreme southeastern sections showed improvement (D0 removed) as it was the only area of the state to receive ample 2006 summer monsoon rainfall, while D3 was removed in northeastern Arizona.  In the latter area, although it has the longest continuing run of deficits (going back 3 years), the last two snow storms have, at the very least, brought moderate improvement.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
