<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060928</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The next five days (September 28-October 2) show the potential for above-average precipitation in the Great Lakes region and the Northeast.  Near- to below-average precipitation is expected in the remainder of the country.  Below-average temperatures in the East are expected to gradually move eastward into the Atlantic and be followed by above-average temperatures.  In the West, above-average temperatures are expected throughout the period.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (October 3-7) above-average precipitation is expected from the Great Lakes to the Northeast, and below-average precipitation from Texas eastward to the Atlantic.  We can expect to see colder-than-average temperatures across the northern tier of states from the Rockies to the Great Lakes as well as in California.  Above-average temperatures are expected throughout the central Plains, south central part of the country, and southern Florida.  Temperatures in the remainder of the country are expected to be near average.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Dryness continued across the Islands.  There was some degradation in western Molokai.  The State Department of Agriculture has restricted users of irrigation water in the western part of the island.  Alaska remained free from drought.  In Puerto Rico, the southern coast has been becoming drier, and D0 has been added this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>A storm system traveled eastward across the northern tier of states during the week.  Weekly rainfall totals of more than 2 inches fell in the northern Plains and Midwest from Nebraska northeastward into Michigan.  Locally heavy amounts of 5 inches or more fell mainly in western South Dakota.  Associated with this storm system was an exceptional amount of precipitation (more than 10 inches) in a band from southeastern Missouri into Kentucky.  Drought lessened in the Dakotas, southern Minnesota, Iowa, and eastern Nebraska.  Although the rainfall was welcome, it will be a year or two before rangeland pastures in the Plains recover from the drought.  Beneficial rainfall north of the Red River led to removal of the D4 area in Oklahoma.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, West, and Southwest">
   <p>The Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies continue to be dry.  Fires are abundant from California to Washington and Idaho.  Conditions in Wyoming and Montana mostly remained the same as last week, but did improve in Colorado.  Recent precipitation in Colorado led to improving D1 conditions to D0 in many parts of the state.  The Southwest was mostly dry, and conditions remained the same as last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Gulf Coast, and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Precipitation was scattered and mostly light throughout most of these regions.  An exception was in northern Mississippi and Alabama, where an east-west line of intense storms produced in excess of 5 inches of rain in some places.  Rainfall across northern Arkansas-Mississippi-Alabama has been plentiful for the last couple of months.  Drought intensities in this area were reduced while the rest of the regions remained similar to last week.  The main impact in the Southeast was hydrologic.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Ned Guttman</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Liz Love-Brotak</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
