<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20131024</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next five days (October 24-28) temperatures are expected to be below normal over the eastern half of the United States and above normal over the West.  With a trough setting up over the East, temperatures will be 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit below normal over the Ohio River Valley and 3-6 degrees above normal over the Southwest.  Precipitation over the next 5 days is projected to be greatest over the Great Lakes and east Texas as most of the country will remain dry.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (October 29-November 3) has the continued chance of below-normal temperatures centered over the central Plains and extending over much of the central United States.  Temperatures are expected to be above normal over Alaska and in the Southeast.  The best chances for above-normal precipitation are over the Ohio River Valley and covering much of the eastern two-thirds of the country as well as Alaska.  Precipitation chances are trending below normal in the Pacific Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>There were no changes in Alaska and Puerto Rico this week.  In Hawaii, some changes were made on Maui and the Big Island.  On Maui, the leeward slopes have been dry and the recommendation was made to push the D3 farther north into the central Valley.  On the Big Island, most changes were improvements due to the impact of afternoon showers over the western slopes.  The county of Hawaii Department of Water has asked for a voluntary 10% reduction in water use.  The lower Kona slopes improved a category while the northeast side of the Big Island saw some D0 go to D1 this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Another week of widespread precipitation in Minnesota and Wisconsin helped to ease concerns over dryness.  In Minnesota, improvements were made to the D0 in the northeast portion of the state and to D1 in the central portion of the state.  Wisconsin was left unchanged this week as local conditions are improving but not quite to the point of warranting changes to the drought status.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South">
   <p>Short-term dryness over portions of northern Alabama has brought with it the introduction of abnormally dry conditions this week.  Deficits are approaching 4-6 inches below normal over the last few months.  With some widespread rains throughout central and east Texas, improvements were made in many areas this week.  In and along the reservoir system associated with the Colorado River in Texas, an area of D2 was introduced this week in response to the impact of the historically low reservoirs along the system, water restrictions, and even some communities having to ship water in for consumption.  There has been very little, if any, improvement from recent rains with regard to runoff into the reservoirs.  This can be attributed to the 3+ years of drought in the state.  Recent rains allowed for a full category improvement in southeast Oklahoma as well as some improvement to the D0 in Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Dryness over the last 60-90 days has allowed the introduction of some new areas of D0 in North Carolina, South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida.  Impacts are minimal at this time, with reports of soils drying out being conveyed.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Dryness over the last few months has brought with it more abnormally dry and even moderate drought conditions.  In New Jersey, New York, and Connecticut, the abnormally dry conditions were expanded this week.  Included with that was an introduction of moderate drought on Long Island and approaching New York City.  Central Park in New York City is 7.39 inches below normal since July, Islip Airport is 6.49 inches below normal since July, and Bridgeport, Connecticut, is 6.76 inches below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Precipitation in northwest Kansas allowed for improvements to the D3 conditions.  In South Dakota, D1 was pushed out of eastern portions of the state as well as along the southern border with Nebraska.  D0 conditions were also improved along the border with Nebraska.  In Nebraska, the D0 and D1 conditions were pushed to the south along the entire northern border.  A full category improvement was made in the panhandle of Nebraska as a further of assessment of recent precipitation events has the area recovering on multiple time scales.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The wet pattern continued with upper elevation snows and lower elevation rains in both Colorado and Wyoming.   In Colorado, D1 was improved in the northwest and southern portions of the state and into northern New Mexico.  Wyoming had widespread improvements as a reassessment of the last few months of precipitation prompted improvements to the D1 and D2 in the southwest portion of the state and a full category improvement in the northeast.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
