<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20031023</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The forecast calls for continued dryness across most of the drought areas for much of the next two weeks. During October 22-26, heavy rain should fall along coastal Washington and Oregon, and scattered showers may bring less than 0.25 inch to parts of Montana, the Idaho panhandle, and northern Wyoming, but little or no precipitation is expected across the rest of the West. A trace to 0.25 inch is forecast for the central and northern Plains, and up to an inch of rain may fall over Michigan and over the southern Mississippi Valley extending westward into eastern Texas, but the heaviest rain will occur well east of the drought areas. Warmer than normal temperatures are expected to accompany the dryness across the western half of the nation.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing period (October 27-November 4), odds favor above-normal precipitation over the northern to central Rockies and adjacent High Plains, but below-normal precipitation is favored in the rest of the drought areas. Colder than normal temperatures will likely sweep across much of the country east of the Rockies, with warmer than normal temperatures limited mainly to the Far West.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>The week was dry across most of the primary stations in Alaska, with month-to-date precipitation percentages also very low in the southeast part of the state. The D0H area centered near Northway was changed to D0AH and expanded slightly to reflect the continued dry conditions. Trade wind showers brought rain to many locations across Hawaii, especially early in the period. The rainfall amounts were enough to keep conditions from deteriorating, but not enough to improve the drought depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region, Mississippi Valley, and Plains">
   <p>Rainfall amounts of 0.3 to 1.0 inch over parts of Lower Michigan shaved the southern edge of the D0 area there. A third of an inch or less of rain along the drought boundary from northern Illinois to northeast Kansas and southeast Nebraska kept conditions there from deteriorating further, but little if any precipitation fell across the rest of the Midwest and Great Plains drought area. A large part of Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Iowa had 90-day rainfall departures of 4 to 8 inches below normal, which translates to about 25 to 50 percent of normal. October 19 USDA reports rated 52 to 75 percent of the topsoil moisture in these three states in the short to very short (dry to very dry) categories, which is about twice the 5-year average. October 20 USDA reports classified more than half of the statewide pasture and range land in poor to very poor condition in a triangular area bounded by Kansas, North Dakota, and Wisconsin. D1 was extended further into north central Minnesota, and D3 extended into northeast Iowa and southwest Wisconsin, to bring the drought depiction in line with objective indicators. D0 and D1 were expanded slightly northeastward in Wisconsin to conform to modeled soil moisture depictions. Otherwise, the changes made last week adequately reflect the current short term and long term dryness.</p>
   <p>Continued dryness in the southern Plains and Lower Mississippi Valley prompted the expansion of D0 from southern Oklahoma into southern Arkansas and northern Louisiana. Much of this area has had 25-50 percent of normal rainfall for the last 30 days, and soil moisture stress was reported in some parishes in central Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>This week saw a continuation of heavy precipitation along the western sections of Washington and Oregon. Seattle had the wettest day on record when Sea-Tac Airport recorded 5.02 inches on October 20, breaking the previous all-time wettest day of 3.41 inches. But the heaviest amounts (1.5 to over 10.0 inches) fell in areas that were already improved to drought-free status last week. D1 and D2 were nudged back slightly in north central Washington and the Idaho panhandle to reflect precipitation amounts of up to an inch. Scattered showers brought a few tenths to under an inch of moisture to parts of the northern and central Rockies, but this had little effect on the long-term deficits, so the drought depiction remained unchanged from last week.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere in the West, little if any rain fell during the period, resulting in drought persistence. October 19 USDA reports rated 91 percent of the topsoil moisture in Montana in the short to very short (dry to very dry) categories, with just over 80 percent in these categories in Colorado, Wyoming, and Oregon, and 70 percent or more in Idaho, New Mexico, and Utah. October 20 USDA reports classified a significant portion of the statewide pasture and range land in poor to very poor condition across the West. Some state figures include: 90% for California, 79% New Mexico, 76% Montana, about 60% for Oregon and Idaho, and 35-47% for the remaining western states. According to the U.S. Forest Service, the fire danger risk remained high to very high from southern California, across the Great Basin and Rocky Mountains, all the way to the Upper Mississippi Valley.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
