<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000727</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Factors which could affect some of the countrys dry or drought areas include: 1) Cool and possibly wet weather through this weekend from the Great Lakes region southward into the Ohio and upper Tennessee Valleys; 2) possible widespread showers and thunderstorms across Florida and the eastern Gulf Coast through the weekend; 3) through this weekend, high pressure should persist across the Southwest and southern Plains, keeping much of Texas and an area from Idaho southward to western Arizona mostly dry and warm, but monsoonal showers possible in New Mexico and Colorado; 4) chance of thunderstorms next few days impacting the western Corn Belt; and 5) increasing chance of showers in the Southwest, south-central Plains, Delta, and Southeast as next week progresses.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Continued cooler and damp weather further reduced the D0 area in Alaska to extreme southern sections of the state, where deficits of 2 to 4 inches since April 1 remained, as weekly temperatures averaged 2 to 6F below normal, highs were in the sixties, lows in the forties, and rainfall amounts ranged between 0.5 to 1.5 inches.</p>
   <p>For the second consecutive week, several windward Hawaiian locations in Kauai, Oahu, Maui, and the Big Island measured 1 to 4 inches of rain. However, little or no rain fell on most drought impacted leeward areas, although a few stations received significant showers (i.e. 2-3 inches along the western coast of the Big Island, 0.2-0.5 inches in southwestern Oahu). As a result, Hawaiian leeward drought conditions persisted.</p>
   <p>Drought conditions were revised across Puerto Rico upon investigation of the summarized daily data and supplemental sources. According to the San Juan Weather Forecast Office, only the North Coast (61% of normal, 10.94 inch deficit) and North Slope (75% of normal, 7.15 inch deficit) climate divisions reported any significant rainfall deficits since January 1. In addition, using corrected summarized daily data since April 1, deficits between 3 and 6 inches were found in east-central and northeastern areas, and deficiencies of 7 to 15 inches along the north coast. Accordingly, abnormal dryness (D0) was located in the northern and southeastern portion of the island, with first stage drought (D1) along the northern coastline. No significant relief occurred the past week as mostly dry weather was observed across northern and east-central areas, except for isolated moderate showers in the northeast that dropped 0.5 to 1.5 inches of rain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Heavy rains (locally 4 to 8 inches in central Kansas) fell on former D0-D1 areas of the central Great Plains as a series of thunderstorm complexes formed over the central Rockies/High Plains and moved southeast during the evenings of July 16-21. The rains and much cooler weather eliminated the D0 area in central and west-central Kansas, and diminished the D1 and D2 areas in northwestern Kansas, northeastern Colorado, and southeastern Nebraska. In the severe to extreme (D2-D3) drought sections, 1 to 1.5 inches of rain brought some slight relief to southwestern Nebraska. Unfortunately, only 0.1 to 0.5 inches of rain fell on northwestern Nebraska, keeping the drought intact. Spotty, mostly light showers occurred in western Iowa and northeastern Nebraska, but low evaporative demands (weekly temperature departures of -9F to -13F, and highs in the eighties) prevented further moisture degradation. According to the National Agricultural Statistics Service (NASS), crop reporting districts in western Iowa, northwestern Kansas, eastern Colorado, and much of Nebraska continued to report mostly short to very short topsoil and subsoil moisture, even after the cool and wet weather.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southern Plains">
   <p>After mostly dry and hot (highs around 100F) weather Wednesday-Saturday (the exception being Florida), cooler air filtered into the Southeast, and moderate to heavy thunderstorms (2 to 4 inches) fell along the central Gulf Coast, and from Florida northeastward into Virginia, with locally 5 to 9 inches along the South Carolina coast. Farther west, light showers (0.1 to 0.5 inches) dampened southeastern Texas Sunday night, the areas first widespread rains in a month. Unfortunately, significant rains bypassed the lower Mississippi Valley, most of Alabama and Tennessee, and the remainder of Texas. Even with the recent cool down and showers, temperatures still averaged above normal for the week, especially in southern and western sections. Accordingly, the recent rainfall was beneficial to portions of the southern Atlantic states, where the rain has put a dent in the drought; namely, improving conditions in the Carolinas, eastern Georgia, and parts of Florida. Streamflows have also shown some improvement in South Carolina, Florida, and Georgia from a week ago, according to the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), although 72% (GA), 55% (FL), and 38% (SC) of measuring sites were still among the lowest 10% on record for July 26. In contrast, another week of heat and subnormal rainfall increased dryness (D1 and D2) in southern Texas, and shifted the Southeast drought area (D1-D3) further west and north. The USGS noted that 85% and 76% of streamflow measuring sites in Alabama and Mississippi were among the lowest 10% on record for July 26. Extreme drought (D3) now encompassed southeastern Mississippi, and exception drought (D4) remained across southeastern Louisiana, southern Alabama and the Florida panhandle, and north-central Georgia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Warmer and drier weather returned to most of the West as a ridge of high pressure settled over the Four Corners. Significant rainfall (more than 2 inches) in D0 or D1 areas were limited to eastern Colorado (as mentioned above), with lesser amounts (0.1-0.5 inches) scattered across central Arizona, northern New Mexico, central Wyoming, east-central Idaho, and central Montana. With highs rising near or surpassing the century mark northward into Idaho and eastern Washington, numerous, large wildfires blackened parts the Great Basin, Rockies, California, and the Southwest. The Weather Forecast Office in Las Vegas, NV noted that the city has recorded two long dry spells during the past year (current spell of 138 consecutive days without measurable rain), and that the seasonal monsoon is late across the southern Great Basin. As a result, the D0(A,F) is expanded westward into southern Nevada, extreme eastern California, and northwestern Arizona, with first stage drought (D1(A,F)) now encompassing northern Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
