<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020307</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) another powerful storm crossing the nation on Friday-Sunday March 8-10 bringing 0.5 to over 1 inch of additional rain to the Eastern Seaboard and up to around 0.5 inches of equivalent liquid precipitation to the northern Plains, with variable snowfall amounts in Colorado; 2) above-normal rain and snow over the Northwest; and 3) generally below-normal precipitation over the southern Plains and Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>D1 drought continued in western Molokai and D0 dryness remained in southern Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>A storm brought 1 to 2 inches of rain to drought areas along the Eastern Seaboard on March 2-3, offering some respite from the persistent dry weather that has dominated the region since autumn. Although the rain was beneficial, it was not sufficient to significantly alter the overall drought picture, allowing extreme (D3) drought to continue over Maine, the mid-Atlantic from New Jersey to northern Virginia, and the Southeast from South Carolina to eastern Georgia. The biggest improvement took place in southern Georgia and northern Florida, where amounts of 4 inches or more eliminated dryness in most of northern Florida and caused D1 and D2 drought to recede in southern Georgia. The heavy rains in southern Georgia and southern Alabama resulted in these areas being placed in the W category, indicating that the dominant impact at this time is to water supplies, the recent moisture having eased agriculture and fire concerns for the time being. The drought in the mid-Atlantic and Northeast remains mostly a hydrological drought, with impacts on ponds, lakes, rivers, wells, and reservoirs. However, there are a variety of other effects from the drought, including long-term impacts on vegetation and trees. According to preliminary data, the Northeast experienced the second driest September-February in 107 years of record. The 12 months ending in February were the driest on record in Maine. New Jersey, Delaware, and Maryland reported the driest February on record.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The early-March storm had little impact on dryness in this region, as the heaviest snow and rain mostly fell in areas not experiencing abnormal dryness. D0 dryness continued in the northern Plains, with severe to extreme drought persisting in southwest Texas. D1 drought intensified to D2 drought in extreme southern Texas. Drought also intensified to D2 levels in western Oklahoma and southwest Kansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Little rain or snow fell this week across most of the region, resulting in little change to the drought depiction. Heavy snow in parts of Colorado failed to alter the D0 to D1 conditions there. Updated snowpack measurements prompted an improvement to D1 drought in southwestern Idaho. Severe to extreme drought continued from Montana into Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
