<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070118</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (January 18-22), subnormal temperatures will persist over the much of the nation as cold air continues to pour out of Canada.  This will be especially true over the southern High Plains where temperatures will average 20-25F below normal through the weekend.  Another weekend snow and icing event is possible over the southern Rockies and south-central Plains as a weak storm system tracks out of the Southwest and heads east-northeast.  This should bring more rain to the Delta, with parts of the Southeast receiving light to moderate rain. Unfortunately, Florida is expected to remain dry.  Farther north, light snow may fall on southern sections of the Midwest and mid-Atlantic. Rather tranquil conditions will continue in the Northwest.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6-10 day outlook (January 23-27) calls for below-normal temperatures over the eastern third of the U.S. and southern Texas.  The rest of the nation will begin to moderate as a ridge builds from the West Coast eastward into the northern and central Plains.  A drier weather pattern will envelop much of the nation, with only the extreme southern U.S., Great Lakes region, and New England expecting near-normal precipitation for the period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Another stormy week along the south-central Alaskan Coast dropped 3-6 inches of precipitation on the Kenai Peninsula, and around Cordoba, Valdez, and Yakutat, eliminating abnormal dryness in this area.  Farther west, although outside the D0 area, a historic snow storm unfolded in parts of western Alaska, where Nome (10.5 inches on January 9) had its snowiest January day on record (previously, 10.1 inches on 1/22/99).  The following day was Nomes third-snowiest January day with a 9.7-inch total.  Nearby Kotzebue received 21.4 inches of snow on January 10-11.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, after a very dry December (an expected El Nio impact), leeward showers increased early in the week, then somewhat tapered off.  Some of the heaviest rain fell on January 8-9, when 24-hour Big Island totals reached 5.15 inches at Kapapala Ranch and 3.67 inches in Glenwood.  Hilo also received 5.58 inches January 7-9. On Kauai, 10.43 inches fell at Mt. Waialeale during January 10-12, but other Kauai sites generally measured under an inch.  Overall, the showers were enough to prevent further deterioration, but not enough for improvement.  In Puerto Rico, heavier showers (more than 2 inches) occurred in west-central and eastern parts while southern sections were drier (0.1-0.4 inches), maintaining D0.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>While Arctic air (readings below 0F, including -30F in North Dakota) replaced unseasonably mild conditions in the northern Plains and upper Midwest, little or no precipitation accompanied the plunging thermometer. This maintained a thin to spotty or non-existent snow cover in parts of the Dakotas, Minnesota, and northwestern Wisconsin, and drought conditions remained status-quo.  Farther south, however, several waves of low pressure formed along the slow-moving cold front, dropping a widespread swath of 2-6 inches of rain (locally up to 8.6 inches) from eastern Texas northeastward into western Pennsylvania, with much of Arkansas receiving over 4 inches. In the colder air, although the moisture was needed in eastern Oklahoma, falling in the form of freezing rain was not (ice accumulations of 1 to 3 inches, locally up to 5), causing numerous large trees and power lines to topple that cut power to over 122,000 customers on Sunday.  As a result, conditions improved by one category in the eastern portion of last weeks drought area, namely eastern Texas, eastern Oklahoma, southeastern Kansas, and southwestern Missouri.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Appalachians">
   <p>As the cold front finally gained pace and advanced eastward toward the end of the period, it finally dropped temperatures to more winter-like levels in the eastern third of the nation, but brought little or no precipitation to the mid-Atlantic and Southeast.  Before the front dried out, however, it dropped 2-3 inches of rain on the northern part of the D0 area, alleviating abnormal dryness in northern Kentucky and western West Virginia.  Farther south, totals of 0.1 to 0.5 inches maintained deficiencies more pronounced at 60- and 90-day periods.  In Georgia, a reassessment of blends and products called for removal of most D0(H), except in the northwestern and southeastern sections of the state.  Meanwhile, Florida was still waiting for increasing winter rainfall once (and if) an enhanced subtropical jet stream (courtesy of El Nio) becomes established. Instead, another dry and warm week increased short-term deficits in the south, while lingering long-term departures in north-central Florida dropped several USGS river flow gauge readings into the lower 10th percentile for the 7-day, 14-day, and 28-day periods ending January 16.  Accordingly, northern Florida was labeled H for hydrological impacts (low rivers), while southern Florida was labeled A for short-term dryness and increased fire danger (KBDI over 600) as hydrological impacts were negligible around Lake Okeechobee.  January is normally the month with the least hydrologic impact due to lower temperatures, lower demand, and lower evaporation, but continued dryness into February could become a concern for Lake Okeechobee.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Rocky Mountains">
   <p>For a change, much quieter (and drier) weather enveloped the Northwest as Arctic air spilled into the western half of the U.S.  A stormy season since November has provided ample precipitation to the Northwest, with water year-to-date basin average precipitation and snow water content (SWC) at or above normal in the Cascades and northern Rockies.  In general, basin values decrease farther to the south and east, except where two major December snow storms blanketed the Colorado Rockies and northern New Mexico. With Water Y-T-D basin precipitation between 117% and 150%, and Jan. 16 basin SWC between 102% and 191%, D0 was erased in these two areas.</p>
   <p>In the Southwest, anticipated precipitation from the system that eventually hit the nations midsection was disappointing, with only 0.1-0.4 inches falling on east-central Arizona and northern New Mexico, and little or no precipitation elsewhere.  Since October 1, basin precipitation has averaged only half to two-thirds of normal, and Jan. 16 SWC was around half of normal, including the Sierra Nevada and major ranges in Nevada, Arizona, and southwestern New Mexico.  Hydrologic concerns are currently negligible in California due to above-normal major reservoir capacity (at 119% of normal capacity on 12/31/06, or at 75% average capacity), thanks in part to a near-record wet 2004-05 rainy season.  However, with a very dry 2005-06 rainy season, a poor 2006 summer monsoon, and this years rainy season that has yet to get established, rain-fed pastures, ranges, streams, and wildlife have all suffered, along with an increased fire danger potential.  As a result, where non-hydrological impacts prevailed (most of California), A was designated. Farther east, where both short- and long-term impacts remained (most of Arizona), both A and H were used.  In western New Mexico, where lingering long-term impacts remained but short-term moisture was adequate, only H remained.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
