<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060420</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During April 19  23, 2006, heavy precipitation is anticipated along much of the Eastern Seaboard, the upper Southeast, and parts of the lower Mississippi Valley and south-central Plains. The forecast calls for at least an inch of rain from New York and central New England southward through the Carolinas and central Georgia, across all but the northern and southern tiers of Arkansas, in central and southern Oklahoma, and over northern Texas, with 2 to 4 inches expected from the lower Northeast southward to southern Virginia, in the western Carolinas, across eastern Kentucky and most of Tennessee, through east-central Arkansas, and across southern Oklahoma. In addition, between 1 and 2 inches are forecast for western South Dakota and parts of northwestern and southeastern Montana. Meanwhile, light to moderate rain is expected from central Texas eastward through northern Florida, in the northwestern Great Lakes region, over northeastern Illinois, and across the northern Plains. Little or no precipitation is anticipated in southern Florida, the central Plains, the central and southern Rockies, and the Southwest. Temperatures are again expected to average above normal (though cooler than last week) through all current areas of dryness and drought except for parts of the Northeast, the Gulf Coast states, and southern Texas.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (April 24  28, 2006), the odds favor wetter than normal conditions from eastern Wyoming and Nebraska southward through the southern High Plains and the middle Red River Valley, and throughout the D0 area in Alaska. In contrast, below-normal precipitation is favored in the Great Lakes region, the middle and upper Mississippi Valley, the upper Southeast, and the northern Rockies. Warmer than normal conditions are likely in most areas from the upper and middle Mississippi River westward to the Pacific Coast, and across the Alaskan Panhandle. Meanwhile, the odds favor below-normal temperatures in southern Florida, the mid-Atlantic, and the Northeast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Central and southern portions of the Alaskan Panhandle generally received 1 to 3 inches of precipitation last week, but this was not enough to significantly reduce the dryness affecting this climatologically-wet region. For the 90-day period ending April 18, 2006, Juneau, AK received 6.7 inches of precipitation, more than 4 inches below normal. Farther south, Sitka, AK reported 2.3 inches of precipitation during March 9  April 18, 2006, which is only one-third of normal. Meanwhile, a few tenths of an inch of precipitation fell on interior east-central Alaska, and scattered light amounts were reported across non-coastal southern Alaska. Thus, D0 conditions remained unchanged from the previous week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Gulf Coast">
   <p>A week of above-normal temperatures and little if any measurable rainfall abetted expanding and intensifying dryness. Large precipitation deficits and increasingly serious impacts led to the introduction of D3AH in a band from extreme southeastern Texas eastward into southeastern Louisiana while D0AH to D2AH conditions all expanded northward, with abnormally dry or drought conditions now covering the southern halves of Alabama and Mississippi and most of Louisiana.</p>
   <p>For the past few months, precipitation deficits are largest in areas along and near the Gulf of Mexico. At most locations from the Florida Panhandle westward to central Louisiana, 30-day rainfall totals through April 18, 2006 were at least 4 inches below normal, 60-day totals were at least 8 inches below normal, and in a few areas 90-day totals were more than a foot below normal. Six-month totals 12 to 20 inches below normal were widespread along the central Gulf Coast inland as far as the southern tiers of Mississippi and western Alabama, including the areas most severely affected by Hurricane Katrina in late August 2005. The ongoing drought has increased the incidence and risk of wildfires, caused planting delays for some crops, impacted some sectors of the fishing industry, induced widespread below-normal streamflow levels, and raised some environmental concerns, but there have also been positive aspects. Construction and re-construction efforts in the areas affected by Hurricane Katrina have benefited from the reduced frequency of delays typically resulting from rainy weather.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Moderate rains of 0.5 to locally 3.0 inches fell on a swath from eastern West Virginia southeastward through northern and central Virginia, the lower Potomac Valley, the southern Delmarva Peninsula, and the Virginia Tidewater. Similar amounts were more scattered across central and western Pennsylvania and adjacent New York, and in a few small areas in south-central and southeastern North Carolina. Amounts of one-quarter to locally over one-half inch were reported across the rest of the central and southeastern Carolinas, the West Virginia and Maryland Panhandles, a few areas in northeastern Maryland and Delaware, all but the southeastern quarter of Pennsylvania, the southern tier of New York, and much of Connecticut. Little precipitation fell elsewhere, with barely measurable totals at best recorded in most of southern New Jersey and from the western Carolinas southward through Georgia and Florida.</p>
   <p>As a result, abnormal dryness ended in most of eastern West Virginia and parts of adjacent Virginia, and conditions improved to D0 in the lower Potomac Valley and the southern Delmarva Peninsula. Dryness and drought persisted or intensified along the rest of the Eastern Seaboard. Conditions deteriorated to D1A in an area from southern New Jersey southward and westward through southeastern Pennsylvania, the northeastern half of Maryland, and Delaware while D1AH expanded into far western North Carolina and adjacent Tennessee, central South Carolina, and northeastern North Carolina. Meanwhile, D2AH was introduced in part of northern South Carolina, and the broad D0A area expanded slightly in southeastern Tennessee, part of southwestern Georgia and adjacent Alabama, eastern South Carolina, and portions of north-central and east-central Florida. Abnormal dryness also expanded westward in northeastern Ohio.</p>
   <p>For the 60-day period ending April 18, 2006, precipitation totaled 4 to 8 inches below normal in most areas from Massachusetts southwestward through the central and western Carolinas, across the southern Appalachians and adjacent parts of Georgia and Tennessee, and from eastern and southern Georgia southward into southern Florida. Going back to mid-April 2005, totals were near or slightly more than one foot below normal in most of the D2AH areas in the Carolinas and adjacent Virginia.</p>
   <p>After some recovery earlier this month, streamflows are again dropping across the region. On April 18, 2006, new daily record low flows were reported at 17 percent of reporting sites in the New England water resources region, 16 percent of sites in the South Atlantic region, and 7 percent of sites in the mid-Atlantic region. The median streamflow of sites in the New England, mid-Atlantic, and South Atlantic regions was approximately the 5th percentile, the 9th percentile, and the 11th percentile, respectively.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Another week of moderate to heavy precipitation abetted continued improvement for regions of the upper Midwest experiencing hydrologic dryness and drought. The dry areas from eastern Iowa and southwestern Wisconsin southeastward through western Indiana received at least an inch of rain last week, with 2 to 5 inches reported in southwestern Wisconsin and adjacent Illinois, parts of eastern Iowa, and much of northeastern Illinois south of Chicago. As a result, the southwestern half of the former D2H area in north-central Illinois improved to D0H, and the northeastern half improved to D1H. In addition, D0H conditions were eliminated in southwestern Wisconsin, east-central Iowa, eastern Illinois, northwestern Indiana, and southwestern Michigan. Unfortunately, northeasternmost Illinois, including much of the Chicago area, received only 0.5 to 1.0 inch of rain for the week, keeping D1H conditions intact.</p>
   <p>Farther west, generally light precipitation, highlighted by scattered areas of moderate rain (0.5 to about 1.5 inches), kept dryness and drought essentially unchanged in the central and western Dakotas, northeastern Colorado, southern Nebraska, eastern Kansas, southern Iowa, northern and south-central Missouri, and west-central Illinois.</p>
   <p>The remainder of the Plains experienced unseasonably warm and dry weather, with significant rainfall limited to small, isolated areas in north-central Arkansas and western Oklahoma. Abnormal dryness and drought persisted or intensified as a result. D4AH conditions expanded slightly northward in south-central Texas while the adjacent areas of D2AH and D3AH pushed northward in central Texas and along the Rio Grande Valley. Farther north, D3AH stretched northward and eastward in southwestern Missouri, and southward into east-central Oklahoma. Significant expansions of D2AH occurred in southeastern Colorado, central and southwestern Missouri, central and interior northeastern Arkansas, and southeastern Texas while moderate drought stretched to cover new areas in northeastern Wyoming, far northeastern Arkansas and adjacent Missouri, south-central Arkansas, and northwestern Louisiana.</p>
   <p>Farther north, increasing short-term moisture deficits and declining streamflows led to the introduction of abnormally dry conditions across the western half of Michigans Upper Peninsula and adjacent sections of Minnesota and Wisconsin. For roughly the last month, precipitation totaled 1.5 to 3.0 inches below normal across the western Upper Peninsula and northeastern Wisconsin, and 60-day totals were under half of normal in northeastern Wisconsin and the adjacent south-central Upper Peninsula.</p>
   <p>Across the Plains and Midwest, short-term precipitation totals through April 18, 2006 were most anomalous in southwestern Missouri and northwestern Arkansas, where 60-day totals were more than 4 inches below normal, but longer-term shortfalls were generally more dramatic farther to the south and west. The last 6 months brought 8 to 12 inches less precipitation than normal to many areas from southwestern Missouri and southeastern Kansas southward through much of Oklahoma, Arkansas, and parts of eastern Texas while roughly the southwestern half of Texas, the Texas Panhandle, southern Colorado, and southwestern Kansas received less than half of normal. Just over half an inch fell on Del Rio, TX during this period, which was only about 10 percent of normal. Since mid-April 2005, much of upper southern Texas and southeastern Oklahoma have recorded less than 50 percent of their typical precipitation amounts.</p>
   <p>The extended period of below-normal precipitation has led to a drop in streamflows in the Arkansas-White-Red Rivers hydrologic region. On April 18, 2006, 14 percent of measurement sites in this region were at record low levels for the date, and only half of these sites were above their 13th percentile threshold. In other parts of the Plains, streamflow levels have been boosted somewhat by runoff from upstream precipitation and snowmelt in the Rockies.</p>
   <p>The warm, dry week led to more wildfires in the region, though their extent and severity remained below the levels reached earlier this spring. From January through mid-April 2006, wildfires scorched nearly 2.2 million acres across the country, which is almost 4 times the average for the same periods during 2001 - 2005. Of this acreage, about 72 percent (over 1.5 million acres) were in Texas. Thus, fires in Texas alone during the first 3.5 months of 2006 charred more than 2.5 times the NATIONAL average acreage consumed for the previous 5 such periods. High to extreme fire danger persisted for most of the dry areas in the High Plains and western Great Plains through at least April 18, 2006.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Southwest">
   <p>New Mexico and most of Arizona experienced a very dry and warm week, and the moderate to heavy precipitation that fell on some areas farther north generally missed the areas currently experiencing dryness and drought. Precipitation totals of 0.5 to near 2.0 inches fell on part of south-central Montana and isolated locations in the Wyoming and Colorado Rockies, but most of the dry areas from south-central Colorado and east-central Utah northward through Montana recorded only a few tenths of an inch. Farther south, light precipitation fell on northwestern Arizona and a few areas near the High Plains in New Mexico, but most of these states received no measurable rain. This is a relatively dry time of year across Arizona, New Mexico, and adjacent areas of Colorado and Utah, so precipitation totals for the past several weeks were not far from normal. However, 6-month totals were below half of normal through almost the entire Southwest, and 12-month totals were under half of normal in portions of central and southern Arizona. The only drought classification change this week was the expansion of D3AH into central New Mexico, where the preponderance of drought indicators suggested conditions similar to those immediately north and south of the region.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
