<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010628</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a warming and drying trend will begin in the Pacific Northwest during the weekend (June 29-30) as high pressure builds over the area, ending the current cool and relatively moist pattern in this area; 2) scattered thunderstorms associated with an upper-level low that will slowly move from Tennessee to Texas (June 28-30) will provide some beneficial rains to the drought areas in the mid-Mississippi Valley; 3) easterly flow over Florida will continue to provide moisture for abundant thunderstorms across most of the state; and 4) above-normal temperatures July 2-6 are forecasted to cover most of the nation from the Pacific Northwest to the Southeast, with excessive temperatures and above-normal heat indices possible in the southeast quarter of the country.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>A generally dry week occurred across the Hawaiian Islands, with various stages of drought still occurring. Pasture conditions have been improving on Molokai, so the west side of the island improved from extreme (D3) to severe (D2) drought, while the east side of the island improved from severe (D2) to moderate (D1) drought. Continued dryness during May and June in northeast Puerto Rico has prompted the establishment of a D0 designation in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeastern States">
   <p>Abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D1) continue in parts of Maine. Long-term dryness is also still a problem in a small part of New York and Pennsylvania, although generous rains during the week removed the moderate hydrological drought in this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Areas of D0 (abnormal dryness) increased in southwestern Nebraska and adjacent states, and across northern and central Texas into southwestern and south-central Oklahoma. While Houston has had a record 17.87 inches of rain for June thus far, Dallas has received less than one inch and Midland, currently experiencing severe drought (D2), has not received any rain for the month. Parts of El Paso, TX, received more than 4.50 inches of rain June 25-26. The heavy rain was isolated, however, with the official total for the city for the same period only amounting to 0.16 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Mid-South">
   <p>Much of this region was dry during the past week. The exceptions to this occurred across the Florida Peninsula, where reports around Tampa Bay ranged from 4 to 8 inches for the week, and in upstate South Carolina and western North Carolina, which experienced isolated heavy rains. The Drought Monitor map shows a little improvement from extreme to severe drought in the Tampa area, but the water supply situation remains critical for many areas of the Peninsula. Agriculturally, the situation across Florida has vastly improved during the month of June, but the Florida Agricultural Statistics Service reports that dryland crops and hay fields are showing drought signs and that waterholes are still very low. A wildfire threat still exists across most of the state according to the Florida Division of Forestry, but the recent rains have significantly reduced this threat. The rains in the Carolinas helped improve some extreme (D3) drought to severe (D2) drought there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Most of the West remained dry during the week. Some moisture from off the Pacific did move into the central part of the region June 25-26 from northern California into Idaho. However, because of deteriorating hydrological conditions, especially with streamflows and reservoir levels, the extreme drought (D3) area in southwestern Oregon expanded to include the Rogue and Umpqua River Basins. Within these basins, the Illinois and Applegate Rivers were at record low flows. Drought conditions also continued to deteriorate toward the south, with the D2, D1, and D0 designations spreading farther southward across Nevada, Utah, and Wyoming. Impressive wildfires were located west and northwest of Reno, NV, during the week, and conditions favorable for wildfires are increasing across the West. Reno is now on pace to set the second-lowest precipitation total ever for the October-through-September water year.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
