<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041230</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Many of the nations areas of dryness and drought could see storminess and substantial precipitation through the next 10 days. For December 29  January 3, 2004, the only areas expected to receive less than 0.5 inch are southern Florida, the deserts near the California-Arizona border, parts of eastern Arizona, most of New Mexico, central Colorado, central and eastern Wyoming, the western Great Plains from South Dakota southward, north-central Montana, and portions of eastern Washington, eastern Oregon, and adjacent Idaho. Meanwhile, more than an inch of precipitation is expected in eastern Minnesota, central Iowa, most areas from central Arizona northward through southeastern Idaho and from western Colorado westward through eastern Nevada, and most of California to the west and northwest of the southern desert region. Totals may locally exceed 2 inches near the Idaho/Utah/Wyoming triple point and in southwestern Utah, and 2 to locally 7 inches may pummel the Sierra Nevada. The odds favor continued above-normal precipitation for the ensuing 5 days (January 4  8, 2004) in most areas of dryness and drought, with near normal conditions restricted to northern portions of the Rockies and Intermountain West, and drier-than-normal weather limited to most of Washington and southern Florida.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>It was a snowy week for much of last weeks D0H region. Data are sparse, but both water-year-to-date precipitation and snowpack water content ranged from near normal to well above normal on December 28, 2004, and of the four first-order weather reporting sites in and near the region, none were below normal for the last 30 or 90 days, and only Fairbanks had a bit of a deficit for the previous 12 months, with the other locations near or slightly above normal. Therefore, D0H conditions have been removed, at least for the time being.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="From the Rockies to the Pacific Coast">
   <p>Stormy conditions encroached on this region from the west during December 21  28, 2004, but substantial precipitation for the period proper was restricted to coastal California. D0H was removed along this coastline from the Los Angeles area northwestward approximately through San Luis Obispo, where 2 to locally 6 inches of precipitation fell. Farther east and north, a few inches of precipitation eliminated D0AH in a small part of interior southwestern Washington, and scattered reports of 0.5 to 1.5 inches of precipitation had little impact on dryness and drought in parts of interior northwestern Oregon, western Montana, northern and central Wyoming, and the north-central and southwestern sections of Colorado. All other sites in areas of dryness or drought reported less than 0.5 inch. As a result, conditions generally persisted as they were last week, but some changes were warranted. Declining season-to-date precipitation totals led to a deterioration to D3 in part of north-central Wyoming where late-December snowpack water contents are only about 80 to 85 percent of normal. Meanwhile, late-December snowpack water contents 60 to 75 percent of normal led to the reduction of D1 and D2 conditions in northwestern Wyoming and adjacent Montana to D2 or D3. In contrast, part of northeastern Utah improved from D2 to D1 because several sites reported snowpack water content among the greatest 5 percent of all late December observations despite the dry week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>The D0AH area in northern parts of the Island of Hawaii persisted with little or no rainfall reported in the area. One streamflow measuring site near Kamuela reported flows of less than 0.5 cubic feet per second compared to a late-December median of about 1.7 cubic feet per second.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Scattered showers in most of the small remaining D0 region eliminated residual dryness, or at least confined it to an area too small to accurately depict on our national assessment. There is some concern about developing moisture deficits on eastern parts of the Island, but conditions do not seem to warrant D0 classification at this point.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Florida">
   <p>Substantial rains fell on the northwestern portion of last weeks D0 region, ending abnormal dryness from approximately the Tampa/St. Petersburg area southward to near Naples. Farther east and south, however, only a few tenths of an inch were observed at best, thus D0A conditions persisted. Most locations to the south and/or east of Lake Okeechobee received 3 to 6 inches less than normal rainfall for the 60-day period ending December 28, 2004.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>It was a dry week through the central and eastern Great Plains and the upper Midwest while scattered precipitation totals of 0.1 to 0.5 inch were recorded across the central and northern High Plains. As a result, most areas experiencing dryness or drought remained essentially unchanged from last week, with deteriorating conditions (to D2) restricted to portions of western South Dakota. However, a new area of D0 was assessed across a large part of Minnesota and adjacent portions of the Dakotas and far northwestern Iowa. 60-day precipitation totals through December 28 were below two inches throughout this region, with only 0.1 to 0.5 inch measured across lower northern Minnesota. For most of the new D0 region, these totals were less than 25 percent of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
