<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041118</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (November 18-22), the temperature pattern will be dominated by an upper-level trough in the west and ridge in the east, resulting in below-normal temperatures in the west and above-normal temperatures in the eastern U.S. An upper level low pressure system is expected to bring precipitation to the drought areas in Iowa, Wisconsin and Michigan.  Another storm system likely will move into the Pacific Northwest and track east-southeastward dropping heavier amounts of rain and snow into Colorado and Nebraska. Alaska is expected to receive heavy precipitation in the coastal regions with lighter amounts inland.</p>
   <p>The 6- to 10-day outlook (November 23-27) has above-normal precipitation over the following drought areas: the central Great Plains and the central and southern Rocky Mountains and High Plains. Below-normal precipitation is expected over much of the Great Basin, Pacific Northwest and the northern Rockies. Alaska can expect to see above-normal precipitation in the coastal regions with below-normal amounts over the drought areas. Temperatures are expect to be below-normal throughout much of the contiguous U.S. with the exception in the west coast, Pacific Northwest, and Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Persistent trade winds brought rainfall to the Hawaiian Islands this period, over 10 inches in a few locations. The rain was not enough to erase accumulated 60-day deficits, maintaining the D0A on Maui and the Big Island. Precipitation was spotty over the Alaska drought areas. Some Alaskan stations received 2 or more inches, while others had less than a tenth of an inch. No change was made to the D0H in Alaska, reflecting the long-term dryness associated with the warm seasons drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Dry weather affected a large part of northern New England this week and during much of the last 60 days. D0A was introduced across Maine, northern New Hampshire and Vermont, and into northeastern New York to the St. Lawrence River. This area of D0A reflects worsening modeled soil moisture deficits, low streamflow, and below-normal precipitation for the last week, month-to-date, and back to 60 days, as well as spotty reports of below-normal groundwater.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Great Plains">
   <p>A cold front early in the period brought precipitation to the D0 areas from eastern Nebraska to northern Illinois. The northern edge of the D0 was shaved back in eastern Nebraska and western Iowa, where a half inch to an inch of precipitation fell, and the bulge of D0 over north central Illinois was eliminated. The small area of D1 in Wisconsin along the central Lake Michigan coast was expanded southward to reflect dry soil moisture conditions as monitored by the Midwest Regional Climate Center. Other non-drought areas of the Midwest and Great Plains received precipitation this Drought Monitor period, especially the southern Plains where heavy rain fell. Some stations in the Texas High Plains recorded over 4 inches of rain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A couple winter weather systems moved across the central and southern thirds of the western drought areas during this Drought Monitor period, dropping a few tenths of an inch of precipitation in many areas and an inch or more in some areas. These amounts are far short of what is needed to make up the deficits during the last 3 to 5 years, which amount to 15 inches or more in some locations. Well above-normal precipitation fell across much of the Southwest during late October, replenishing soil moisture and laying down a heavy snow cover for this time of year. These changes were reflected in improving conditions on the Drought Monitor map during the last 3 weeks. But at mid-November reservoirs remained depleted across much of the West, and it is early in the snow season. Many more heavy winter storms are needed in the weeks and months ahead to bring the region out of drought. So changes made to the Drought Monitor this week amounted to just snipping at the edges.</p>
   <p>Improvements made during this weeks Drought Monitor include shaving back D0 in northern California and D2 in southwest Colorado and north central Nevada where over an inch of rain fell. In southern New Mexico, the D0, D1, D2, and D3 boundaries shrank westward. D2 was pulled back in south central Utah to reflect half an inch of precipitation during this Drought Monitor period and also new information assessing the heavy precipitation of late October. Many mountain locations in southern Utah already have 50-75% of the average seasonal peak snowpack, this early in the snow season.</p>
   <p>In southern Arizona, the area around Tucson has missed the beneficial rains of the last several weeks. Precipitation for the last 60 days has been below normal across the area, and Tucson has received only 60% of normal precipitation for the year-to-date. The D1 and D2 boundaries were shifted westward across south central Arizona, with an adjustment of the A,H impacts boundary into the area.</p>
   <p>Little or no precipitation fell this period over the southern California, northern Rockies, and Pacific Northwest drought areas. Much of the Pacific Northwest has experienced below-normal precipitation back to 60 days. No change to the Drought Monitor depiction was made in the non-drought Pacific Northwest due to wet conditions experienced during the preceding months.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
