<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20091210</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: http://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>The majority of the country will start the December 10 – December 14, 2009 period well below normal.  The will slowly give way to some normal to above normal temperatures along the Gulf of Mexico coast and up the Eastern Seaboard. Precipitation is expected along the East Coast and in the Southwest, with higher totals there in California.   Areas in the Northern Rockies, the upper Midwest, and New England may see snow accumulations as well.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (December 15 – 19, 2009), the odds favor cooler-than-normal conditions over most of the eastern US and across the states around the eastern portion of the Gulf of Mexico.  The majority of the US, from the High Plains to the west coast, is likely to see normal to above normal temperatures.  Normal to below normal precipitation is in the central US while above normal precipitation is expected in the Northwest, the Gulf of Mexico Region, and along the East Coast.  Odds favor cool conditions for Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought conditions remained unchanged across the Hawaiian Islands.  Recent rains in windward locations elevated streamflow but were not significant enough to change the drought depiction.  Conditions remain unchanged in Alaska and Puerto Rico.  If precipitation remains absent in eastern Puerto Rico, conditions will soon be abnormally dry.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Two storms affected the East Coast this week.  They reduced the areas of moderate drought and abnormal dryness from Florida up to Pennsylvania and eradicated the abnormal dryness in the Carolinas.  Remaining abnormal dryness and moderate drought is a reflection of longer-term hydrological impacts.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Most of the drought-affected areas of the region saw little to no precipitation this week.  Continued long-term deficits resulted in unchanged drought classification in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Mississippi River Delta">
   <p>In Texas, another week of beneficial precipitation continued to improve extreme (D3), severe (D2), and moderate drought conditions (D1), as well as abnormal dryness (D0)  in the southern part of the state.  Areas of 3 plus inches of precipitation fell while Dallas-Fort Worth experienced some snowfall.  Long-term impacts are still being felt and a few smaller streams are just now beginning to see flowing water.  This same storm dumped rainfall estimated at five plus inches in southwestern Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation fell from coastal California into Nevada, mostly covering the central part of the state.  Nine plus inches of snow fell near Reno, NV and 10-30 inches in the Sierras was reported.  The snow varied in water content with reports from 10:1 to 30:1.  This precipitation missed the areas of severe drought (D2) in northern California.  There was no change in drought status there this week.</p>
   <p>Areas of abnormal dryness (D0) were extended in northern Wyoming and western Montana and eastern Idaho.  Longer-term deficits and generally low snowpack for this time of year contributed to the conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
