<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20021003</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Hurricane Lili is expected to make landfall somewhere along the south-central Louisiana coast on Thursday, then transition into an extratropical cyclone as it gets caught in the mid-latitude westerlies and accelerates northeastward. As of Wednesday evening, the 5-day outlook (October 2 - 7, 2002) called for 1 to 3 inches of rain (from a substantial mid-latitude frontal and storm system and/or Lili's remnants) over much of the east-central Great Plains and adjacent Mississippi Valley from northern Oklahoma and northern Missouri northward into eastern South Dakota and central Minnesota, across the middle and lower Ohio Valley, over much of the Great Lakes region, and in the central and western Appalachians. In addition, 1 to 2 inches of rain are forecast in parts of far western and southern Texas, and light but fairly widespread precipitation, some of which may fall as snow, is expected in the Pacific Northwest, northern Intermountain West, eastern Great Basin, and central and northern Rockies, with up to an inch anticipated in some spots.</p>
   <p>In contrast, unseasonable warmth and below-normal precipitation are forecast for October 2 - 7, 2002 across the middle and southern Atlantic states, the eastern Appalachians, and southern New England. Farther west, little or no precipitation should be accompanied by near- or below-normal temperatures in northern Texas, the central High Plains, the southern Rockies, the desert Southwest, and most of California.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (October 8 - 12, 2002), warmer and drier than normal conditions are favored along the Eastern Seaboard from North Carolina and West Virginia northward, and in central sections of the Far West. Dryness is also anticipated along the rest of the West Coast, and in the Great Basin, northern Intermountain West, and west-central Rockies, accompanied by near- or below-normal temperatures. Favored areas for above-normal precipitation which are currently experiencing some degree of dryness or drought include central and east Montana, the central and southwestern Great Lakes region, Oklahoma, northern and central Texas, and part of the lower Mississippi Valley away from the immediate Gulf Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="East of the Mississippi River">
   <p>Moderate to heavy rainfall, associated with or enhanced by Tropical Storm Isidore or its remnants, fell on many of the region's dry areas. This reduced drought and dryness in areas from the Appalachian, central Gulf Coast, and mid-Atlantic northward and westward through most of the Ohio Valley and Northeast. Weekly rainfall totals ranged from 4 to locally 12 inches at most locations from the central Gulf Coast northward through Mississippi, western Alabama, northern and western Tennessee, and parts of central Kentucky and the middle Ohio Valley, eliminating dryness and drought that had existed in many of these regions. Farther east, a broad area from eastern Alabama northeastward through eastern Tennessee and Kentucky, the Appalachians, the upper Ohio Valley, the lower Northeast, and western New England recorded 1 to locally 6 inches of rain, with slightly more falling on scattered sites near the Appalachians. As a result, dryness and drought was eliminated, at least for the time being, across Vermont, upstate New York, and northern Pennsylvania, and conditions generally improved by one category in other parts of these areas.</p>
   <p>Even in those areas that did not receive the heaviest rains, enough has fallen recently to at least temporarily eliminate surface moisture shortages and any fire danger in areas south and east of western Ohio  essentially those areas that received at least scattered moderate rains associated with Isidore  so the D0 to D4 conditions in this entire region have been qualified as primarily hydrologic, with conditions now ranging from D0(W) to D4(W).</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the most severely drought-affected regions in the lower mid-Atlantic, the interior south Atlantic states, and Maine received less precipitation than those mentioned above. Scattered totals of 2 to 4 inches fell on areas near New York City, parts of eastern South Carolina, and coastal Georgia while 0.5 to 2.0 inches fell on most other sites. Many locations in southern Virginia and the central and southeast sections of North Carolina reported less than one-quarter of an inch. Since drought in Maine and in the middle and southern Atlantic states dates back a few years, and because groundwater and well water levels remain much below normal in most places, little drought relief was indicated in these areas. D4(W) continued in central North Carolina, where long-term precipitation deficits, groundwater levels, and reservoir stores remain exceptionally low, with D3(W) remaining in northeast Maryland and adjacent Pennsylvania, and in a swath from central Virginia southwestward to northern South Carolina.</p>
   <p>In contrast, Michigan, the adjacent Midwest, and areas near the Ohio and Mississippi Rivers' confluence missed most of the rains from Isidore, thus D0 to D1 coverage increased. Specifically, northern Indiana and the northeastern and southern sections of lower Michigan were increased to D1 as soil moisture continued to decline, with D0 expanding into northeast Illinois, western lower Michigan, and west-central Indiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>September dryness led to some expansion of abnormally dry conditions in scattered parts of the island chain. Maui's central valley received no rainfall during the month, making September 2002 the driest September on record at Kahului. As a result, D0(A,F) conditions have been expanded to include the windward portion of eastern Maui and the central valley. Farther west, continued below-normal rainfall across the western half of Molokai led to the removal of the hydrologic qualifier from the former D0(W) conditions, which are now categorically D0.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West of the Mississippi River">
   <p>In contrast to conditions farther east, only scattered light and isolated moderate precipitation was reported in the D0 to D4 areas from the Mississippi River westward, keeping drought conditions generally unchanged. Scattered amounts of 1 to 2 inches were reported in central and northwest Montana, central and southwest Colorado, and interior western Oregon while most other areas recorded 0.1 to locally 0.9 inch. Little or no precipitation fell on most of the central and southern Plains, necessitating the expansion of D0 into a broad area covering most of southern Kansas, Oklahoma, northern Texas, and adjacent Missouri.</p>
   <p>Also, little or no precipitation fell on the far southern Rockies, the desert Southwest, the Great Basin, California, southern Idaho, southern Oregon, and interior southeast Washington, but many of these regions are frequently dry at this time or year, so no increases in drought severity were introduced.</p>
   <p>In the rest of the western half of the nation, few changes in drought intensity were introduced. Among the exceptions were the limited expansion of D0 and D1 in northern Missouri and southern Iowa, the deterioration to D2 in northeast Kansas and adjacent Missouri and Nebraska, and slight increases in D3 and D4 coverage in south-central Nebraska. Only a few locations in these regions reported any measurable rainfall during the week. Farther west, D0(A) was brought into the Idaho Panhandle and adjacent Washington, where precipitation has lagged behind normal since mid-summer, and the extent of D1 to D3 conditions was slightly reduced in central Montana, northern New Mexico, and southwest Utah, where precipitation has been a bit heavier and more widespread in the last several weeks.</p>
   <p>Though changes in drought intensity levels were few, there was a significant reduction in areas identified as experiencing drought-induced increases in wildfire danger, which now seems restricted to the Great Basin, southern sections of Oregon and Idaho, California, and the desert Southwest. Cooler and damper weather has slowly increased in other areas, which has not significantly affected long-term drought, nor even topsoil moisture shortages for the most part, but which has brought an end to the severe 2002 wildfire season in the Pacific Northwest and most of the Rockies.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
