<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010614</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Significant weather features likely to have an impact on drought/dryness in the following 2 weeks include: 1) the remnants from Tropical Storm Allison, bringing 1 to 4 inches of rain to the Carolinas (heavy amounts struck northern Georgia and South Carolina on June 12-13 after the mapss valid time); 2) light to moderate rainfall in the Pacific Northwest, mainly in Montana (snow fell in higher elevations of the northern Rockies on June 12-13); 3) little or no rain in the Great Basin and southern Texas, but lower temperatures; 4) up to 1 inch rain in southwest Texas.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Locally heavy rains improved drought conditions on Maui and the Big Island, but amounts were not enough to end dryness on Oahu. Honolulu measured 0.99 inches in 24 hours on June 5-6, accounting for more than one-third of its year-to-date total of 2.91 inches (27 percent of normal through June 10).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeastern States">
   <p>Additional rains of .5 to 1 inch further eased D0 dryness in Maine and western New York, as well as western Pennsylvania. A small area of D1 drought persisted in north-central Pennsylvania and adjacent New York.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South and Ohio and Tennessee River Valleys">
   <p>The remains of Tropical Storm Allison inundated the Gulf Coast region, ending drought from Louisiana to the Florida Panhandle. Weekly totals ranged from 8 to 16 inches or more from east Texas to southwestern Mississippi, with 4 to 12 inches from southeastern Mississippi to northern Florida and southern Georgia. Local amounts exceeded 20 inches in the Baton Rouge area of Louisiana and the Houston area of Texas. The heavy rains improved conditions in western and southern Georgia, but severe drought (D2) lingered from the western Carolinas south through eastern Georgia to the Florida Peninsula. Thunderstorms continued to boost soil moisture and ease fire danger on the Florida Peninsula, but many wells and streams remained near record low levels. Extreme drought (D3) persisted over central Florida, with D1 or D2 drought to the south. Rainfall in Tampa since October 1998 is 31.65 inches below normal. Rains further eased dryness in the Kentucky/Tennessee area, with severe drought mainly limited to extreme southeastern Missouri and northeastern Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Plains">
   <p>Record heat offset the benefits of scattered thunderstorms in south Texas, allowing D1 and D2 drought to persist in the lower Rio Grande Valley. In west Texas, hot, dry weather caused D0 dryness to expand northeastward into central Texas, while D1 drought stretched southward to the Big Bend area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West">
   <p>Light to moderate rainfall had no significant impact on the D1 to D2 drought extending across the Pacific Northwest, but warm, dry weather resulted in a further expansion southward of D1 drought into central Nevada, with some expansion of D1 and D2 drought southward in northern California. D1 drought also extended southward into northern Utah, while D0 dryness expanded southward in western Utah and entered western Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
