<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080327</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (through March 31), the forecast again calls for the heaviest rains to fall just where they aren't needed in the middle Mississippi and Ohio River valleys. Parts of the southeast (along the northern fringe from Mississippi, Tennessee, Alabama, and Georgia) could also see some more welcome rains. A system coming out of the northern Rockies could also lead to some additional good moisture across most of South Dakota. Temperatures should remain cooler than normal across the northern Plains and southern California. Warmer temperatures are expected across the Desert Southwest, southern Plains, and western Gulf Coast states.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6 to 10 day outlook for April 1-5 shows that a strong zonal (west to east) flow pattern should build in, bringing with it warmer temperatures for most of the country everywhere east of the Rockies except for Florida, which is expecting more seasonal  readings. The abnormally dry region in Alaska can also expect to see above-normal temperatures. Precipitation for this period is more of a mixed bag, with below-normal amounts expected in southwestern Alaska, the southern Rockies, and western Texas. Those areas that should see above-normal precipitation are again centered on the Midwest and Great Lake states. The northern states in the Southeast may benefit from being on the southern edge of this wet pattern as well.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The lack of rains over the past 90 days or so has left most of Puerto Rico at or below 50% of normal (6- to 12-inch deficits), leading to below-normal streamflows.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, little rain means no changes to the D0 areas on all of the islands this week, and high pressure north of the islands should generally result in limited shower activity on the windward sides through the middle of next week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Good moisture from heavy snows (a nice 1-inch water equivalent) last week in northeastern South Dakota and southeastern North Dakota has brought about some improvement to the D1 there. The precipitation missed the western Dakotas and eastern Montana, leading to some expansion of drought conditions there. In Montana, D0 now covers all of the eastern counties and D1 and D2 have pushed slightly to the south and east. The lack of snow cover and/or rains coupled with high winds this spring, have already resulted in several pre-season fires.</p>
   <p>In the southern Plains, fire risk is still critically high in western and southern Texas along with parts of western Oklahoma. After another dry and warm week, both D0 and D1 have advanced slightly to the east in northwestern Oklahoma. In west-central Texas, the wet pattern continued for some this past week. Good rains (1.5 to 3 inches or more in places) have eaten away at some of the western and northern edges of the D1/D2 in the area, pushing the severe and extreme drought core (D2/D3) to the south, where D2 has actually pushed farther south this week along the Rio Grande toward Brownsville. This core region of D2 and D3 has only seen 50% or less of normal precipitation since October of last year.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeastern and Mid-Atlantic States">
   <p>On the heels of recent rains, slow and steady improvement continues for many parts of these regions. Heavy rains like those seen in the Mississippi and Ohio River valleys have missed the core drought region thus far. Worth highlighting this week is that with the removal of the D4 in Tennessee and Alabama, the United States is D4-free for the first time since May 2007. Impressive long-term deficits still remain and hydrologic recovery typically lags the immediate short-term benefits seen with the greening up of spring. Other changes in the region include the trimming (improvement) of D0-D3 on the western and northern edges in Mississippi and Tennessee and extreme western North Carolina. To the south in Florida, some heavier rains in the southern peninsula (Everglades region) totaled anywhere from 2 to 4 inches, leading to the removal of the D3 core that was centered off the western shore counties of Lake Okeechobee. Other improvements here include a trimming of D0-D2 on the eastern and northern shores of the lake as well. Long-term dryness is still reflected by low groundwater levels as far south and east as Dade County.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The month of March has only been holding serve as far as late season precipitation is concerned, and the generally cooler and beneficial weather of late gave way to warmer readings this past week. According to USDA-NRCS, the latest snow water equivalent readings within most of the basins east of the Sierras are only at, or just below, 100% of normal, so the situation is tenuous as the snow season winds down. Some late-season storm system boosts would be very much welcomed. One area that has made out pretty well this winter (water year) has been the Mohave and Yuma Desert regions in southeastern California and western Arizona, respectively. With much of this area seeing above-normal precipitation since October 2007, the D2 has been removed but D1 remains. There has also been a one-category improvement with the removal of D1 southward within the South Lahontan basin in eastern California along the Nevada border and across into west-central Nevada where D1 has been pushed slightly eastward.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
