<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010830</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Predicted weather features during the next 10 days (August 29-September 7) that may impact regions with dryness or drought include: Early in the period (August 29-September 2), 1) A ridge of high pressure over the West should keep most of the interior warm and dry, except west of the Cascades where cooler and showery weather may occur; 2) unsettled weather in the western Gulf, generating a large area of showers and thunderstorms, should move northward and eventually northeastward across eastern Texas, the Delta, and the Southeast; 3) a cold front moving southeastward out of central Canada should trigger scattered thunderstorms in the north-central Plains, upper Midwest, and Great Lakes region, eventually interacting with the western Gulf disturbance over the southern Appalachians and Carolinas during the weekend.</p>
   <p>The 6 to 10-day outlook (September 3-7) forecasts: 4) above-normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation for the northern Rockies, northern Plains, and upper Midwest, and 5) below-normal temperatures and above-normal rainfall for the Southeast, except for near-normal probabilities in southern Florida.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Occasional showers, mostly light to moderate (0.25-0.5 inches), fell on windward sites in Oahu, Maui, and Kona (Big Island), while little to no rain occurred at leeward locations, providing no improvement to abnormal dryness and drought. The islands of Kauai and Oahu will be closely monitored for possible future deterioration and negative impacts as showers became infrequent during the latter half of the period.</p>
   <p>On Puerto Rico, a rapidly-intensifying Tropical Storm Dean dumped copious, widespread rains on much of the island. Weekly totals ranged from an inch on the north coast to 13.25 inches on the southeastern coast, with a general 4 to 8 inches across the central and eastern interior. Amounts were somewhat lower (1.5 to 3 inches) in extreme western Puerto Rico, but Deans rains effectively erased short-term dryness across the island. The island will be closely monitored, however, as some longer-term (3-month) deficits still existed.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Several slow-moving frontal systems generated widespread showers and thunderstorms across most of the lower and central Corn Belt. Between 2 to 6 inches of rain fell on south-central Nebraska, eastern Kansas, north-central Missouri, south-central Iowa, southern Wisconsin, and most of Illinois and Indiana, erasing moderate drought and diminishing dryness in Illinois, and alleviating D0 in Wisconsin and south-central Iowa. Light to moderate rains in southwestern Nebraska during 6 of the past 7 weeks eliminated short-term dryness, but hydrological drought remained. In contrast, the generous Corn Belt rains once again missed southeastern Nebraska and southwestern Iowa (0.1-0.5 inches) as dryness lingered. Farther north, abnormal dryness developed across eastern South Dakota and south-central Minnesota as the last decent rainfall (1-2 inches) occurred in late July.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>The week was characterized by seasonable temperatures and widely-scattered light showers (between 0.3-0.8 inches). Exceptions to this included heavy (2-3 inches) thunderstorms in northern lower Michigan and northwestern Pennsylvania (where drought improved one category), and little or no rainfall across southern and eastern New England, eastern New York, southeastern Pennsylvania, and eastern Ohio, resulting in an expansion of abnormal dryness and drought across central Pennsylvania, eastern New York, and New England. Pennsylvania recently put 45 counties under a drought watch. Since June 1, deficits (% of normal) have accumulated to 6.35 inches (39%) at Buffalo, NY; 5.52 inches (48%) at Burlington, VT; 4.55 inches (58%) at Youngstown, OH; and 3.45 inches (64%) at Bangor, ME. 7-day averaged stream flows were in the lower 10th percentile at 47%, 52%, and 52% of the measured USGS river sites in Maine, Vermont, and New Hampshire, respectively. August shortages were more impressive at Caribou, ME (2.79 inches) and Concord, NH (2.25 inches) where only 0.77 and 0.67 inches of rain have been measured, respectively. Pasture conditions continued to deteriorate in Maine, Pennsylvania, and New Hampshire, where 84%, 75%, and 51%, respectively, were rated poor to very poor, according to the USDA/NASS.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>High pressure enveloped much of the Southeast, keeping thundershower development minimal and temperatures seasonable. Accordingly, little or no rain occurred across the northern half of Florida, southeastern Tennessee, and across most of Alabama, Georgia, and South Carolina. Fortunately, most Southeastern locations had recorded ample rainfall in late July and early August, with a few exceptions. These included the Georgia and South Carolina Piedmont, where 30-day deficits of 2 to 4 inches have accumulated, and USDA/NASS statewide topsoil moisture was rated 55% (Georgia) and 64% (South Carolina) short to very short. Longer-term drought (D1-D2) also persisted in northern South Carolina and south-central North Carolina, with several USGS sites in this area setting daily record low stream flows on August 28. In Florida, most rivers, lakes, and aquifers continued to stagnate or decline with another relatively quiet week. The level of Lake Okeechobee has stalled at 11.90 feet for 5 straight days, ending several weeks of large daily rises due to rains from Barry. A 14-day dry spell at Tampa that ended on Saturday was the longest such dry stretch during August on record, and north-central Florida rivers have responded by dropping their flows into the lower 10th percentile.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Delta">
   <p>A third consecutive week of scattered, moderate to heavy thundershowers in the south-central Great Plains has greatly diminished the flash drought which peaked in early August. Between 2 and 5 inches of rain was reported across south-central Texas, along parts of the Red River Valley, in central and southeastern Oklahoma, and eastern Kansas. A broad area of thunderstorms in the western Gulf dropped moderate rains along the Texas coast at the end of the period, dropping 24-hour (ending 12 GMT Tuesday) totals of 1.18 inches on Brownsville, 1.15 inches on McAllen, and 0.94 inches on Alice. Weekly amounts, however, were generally much lower (less than 0.2 inches) in southern, southwestern, and northeastern Texas, and northern Oklahoma, maintaining or slightly increasing drought. In the northern Delta, little or no rain plus hot weather (highs mid-90's to lower 100's, departures +4 to +7F) broadened abnormal dryness into southeastern Missouri, and drought into northeastern Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A potent Pacific storm system brought unseasonably heavy rains to coastal Oregon and Washington, and even portions of interior Washington and northern Idaho. Storm totals included over 3 inches at Astoria, OR, more than 2 inches at Seattle, WA, and about one-third of an inch at Wenatchee and Spokane, WA. The subnormal weekly temperatures (-2 to -4F) and higher humidities in the Pacific Northwest greatly aided firefighters, tempering the suddenly-active wildfire season during August in Washington and Oregon. Accordingly, the hydrological line (W) was shifted slightly southward where the heaviest rains (more than 1.5 inches) fell, indicating an improvement to agricultural and wildfire concerns. Unfortunately, the storm system was not as beneficial to the rest of the West, and occasionally aggravated wildfire conditions with gusty winds. From Californias Sierra Nevada northeastwards into Montana, little or no rain fell, temperatures averaged 2 to 6F above normal, and highs soared into the nineties, occasionally topping 100F, especially late in the period. With continued hot and dry weather, near-record low streamflows, and extreme fire danger, the D3 was expanded across the Musselshell and lower Yellowstone River drainage basins (in south-central Montana) and in northwestern Wyoming. In California, drought conditions edged southward into the central Sierra Nevada with increasing fire danger and unfavorable weather. As of August 28, there were 26 active large fires (10 in Montana), affecting over 200,000 acres.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
