<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020613</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) showers and thunderstorms dropping 1 to 2 inches of rain over the mid-Atlantic region June 12-16; 2) from 0.5 to 1.0 inches falling over the central High Plains during June 12-16; 3) normal rainfall over the central Rockies, including Colorado, during June 18-26; and 4) above-normal rainfall across the Southeast and mid-Atlantic region during June 18-22.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Scattered thundershowers brought locally heavy rains and isolated flash flooding to much of central and east-central Alaska; however, coverage was limited, and most locations did not receive enough rain to substantially reduce moisture deficits, though the active wildfire season was at least temporarily impeded. Following record spring dryness, June has been wetter than normal in south-central and southeastern parts of the state, including the Panhandle, but large precipitation deficits persist in many areas. Yakutat recorded about one-third of normal precipitation from mid-March through early June, and is 2 feet short of normal since the beginning of the year. D0 dryness continued in western Molokai, Hawaii. Rainfall was abundant over Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Widespread thunderstorms occurring mainly on June 6 dropped more than 2 inches of rain on the drought areas of New Jersey, southern Connecticut, and New York City-Long Island. The moisture ended D1 drought in Connecticut and Long Island, and improved the severe (D2) drought to D1 in central and southern New Jersey. D0 dryness continued across much of the Northeast due to remaining precipitation deficits dating back to at least last autumn. Rainfall was more spotty to the south, and D1 and D2 drought expanded slightly westward in Maryland and Virginia. In Georgia, a 5-inch deluge along the coast caused the D3 drought to retreat slightly inland, but overall improvement in the state was minor. Extreme drought persisted from central Virginia to central Georgia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>Scattered thunderstorms did little to reduce the drought along the Gulf Coast, and dryness even expanded northward slightly in Alabama.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The storm that brought the wintry mix to Montana also dumped heavy showers on northern North Dakota and northern Minnesota, eliminating abnormal dryness. D0 dryness did persist west of Lake Superior in Minnesota and across much of southern North Dakota. Continued lack of rain resulted in D1 drought expanding eastward across northwestern South Dakota and continuing in south-central North Dakota. Despite some thunderstorms, there was little change to the severe drought area affecting southwestern Nebraska, western Kansas, and northern, southwestern and southern Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A major winter-like storm dropped heavy rain and snow across western and northern Montana, leaving 2 to 6 inches of precipitation on drought-affected areas during June 7-11. Cut Banks record total of 2.30 inches on the 8th was its highest daily total in nearly 11 years. During June 1-9, several locations recorded 20 to 30 percent of their normal annual accumulations and several times their normal monthly totals. The moisture boosted topsoil moisture and streamflows, resulting in an improvement from D4 to D3 drought in north-central Montana and lessening drought elsewhere in western and northern Montana. In contrast, little or no rain fell over most of the remainder of the West, an exception being some welcomed showers over eastern Colorado. Severe to extreme drought persisted from Wyoming southward to the Mexican border and westward to southern California. The dryness caused drought to expand from D1 to D2 in parts of southern Idaho and extreme D3 drought to expand slightly southward in Wyoming to the Colorado border. D3 drought diminished in northeastern Colorado, but expanded northward along the Utah-Colorado border. D2 drought edged eastward in eastern New Mexico while D3 drought dipped southward toward El Paso.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
