<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070405</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecast weather that could have an impact on dry conditions during the next 2 weeks include: 1) abnormally cold weather in the central and eastern states, contrasting with warmth over the interior West during April 4-9; 2) 1.5 to 2 inches of rain forecast over southern Texas for the 5-day period; 3) storm systems crossing the Plains and the East during April 10-14 bringing moisture to dry areas in the Tennessee Valley and Southeast, as well as the northern Plains and northern Rockies; 4) the April 10-14 and April 12-18 forecasts showing above-normal precipitation for the northern Plains and the Southeast, with the exception of southern Florida, and above-normal warmth and below-normal rainfall for the Southwest into Texas.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Precipitation was light in Alaska, allowing D0 dryness to persist. Hawaii rainfall totals were variable, but mostly less than 1 inch, resulting in continued D0 dryness in many areas. Heavy rains hit Puerto Rico, although the greatest totals, which exceeded 5 inches, fell mostly in the north, outside of the dry areas. The south saw 0.5 to 2 inches. As a result, the D0/D1 area diminished.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>The storm system dropped smaller amounts of rainfall as it tracked across the Southeast, leaving the drought depiction nearly unchanged or even somewhat worse. D1 expanded into west-central Mississippi from the core drought area extending across Tennessee and Alabama. D2 edged westward into eastern Mississippi. D1 drought extended northward from Florida into southeastern Georgia. D2 expanded westward and southward in southern Florida. Jackson, Mississippi, set a March record with only 0.90 inches of rain. Huntsville, Alabama, notched a January-March record with 6.46 inches, over 10 inches below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>The storm that tracked onto the Plains during March 28-30 brought severe weather and heavy rains to the Plains states, as well as heavy snow to North Dakota. By Friday, the 30th, flood watches and warnings stretched from Texas to North Dakota and Minnesota. The heavy rains eliminated the lingering dryness in Kansas and north-central Oklahoma, which saw up to 5 inches of rain from Wednesday to Saturday. This was the first time since April 2005 that Oklahoma was drought-free, according to the Drought Monitor. Oklahoma City experienced their wettest March day on record, when 3.50 inches of rain fell on March 30. Heavy rains and flooding removed most of the drought in Texas, which saw widespread 2-5 inches of rain on top of the heavy rains measured during the previous week. San Antonio shattered its March rainfall record with 7.24 inches (383 percent of normal) for the month. D0H and a small area of D1H remained over south-central Texas to account for continued low reservoirs and still substantial 2-year rainfall deficits. Much of the northern Plains saw a 1-category improvement thanks to 1-3 inches liquid-equivalent across the Dakotas, Nebraska, and Minnesota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>An expansive storm system exited the Rockies on March 28th to the Plains, bringing widespread heavy precipitation and severe weather from the Mexican to the Canadian border. The storm dumped heavy snow across the northern Rockies during March 28-30, with the heaviest amounts over Wyoming, where storm totals ranged from 12 inches in Casper to 70 inches at Hobbs Park in the Wind River Range. Snow also fell on Colorado, Utah, and Montana. Temperatures plummeted by as much as 30 degrees from Wednesday afternoon to Thursday afternoon in the wake of the associated cold front. Drought levels generally improved by one category in Wyoming. The D2 retreated in southern Montana. Rain and snow amounts were not high enough to change the drought depiction over California and the Great Basin, so severe to extreme drought persisted across southern California and western Arizona, with D0 expanding farther northward in northern California. Los Angeles measured just 0.05 inches of rain in March, and is still on track to record the driest season (July to June) in more than 120 years. California statewide snow water content was at 40 percent of normal. Utah snowpack for early April was at the lowest levels since 1977.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Heddinghaus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
