<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100225</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (February 25 – March 1), an active weather pattern will prevail across the West, South, and East.  In particular, precipitation could total as much as 2 to 4 inches in the Pacific Coast States, while some additional snow may fall across parts of the southern Plains.  In the Northeast, rainfall could reach 3 to 5 inches near the New England coast, while snowfall could reach 2 to 3 feet across the interior.  A prolonged period of high winds will accompany the Northeastern precipitation.  Cold weather will persist into next week across much of the nation, with light freezes (temperatures near or slightly below 32 degrees F) possible as far south as interior southern Florida on February 26.  The Climate Prediction Center 6- to 10-day forecast for March 2-6 calls for a continuation of near- to below-normal temperatures across the majority of the U.S.  Warmer-than-normal weather will be confined to the nation’s northern tier.  Meanwhile, below-normal precipitation across the Intermountain West, Rockies, Plains, and Midwest will contrast with wetter-than-normal conditions in parts of California and from the Gulf Coast region into the southern Atlantic States.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Puerto Rico remained free of dryness and drought, while no changes were made in Alaska.  However, Alaska’s season-long “snow drought” has left more than one-third of the state abnormally dry (in D0).  Through February 23, Alaskan season-to-date snowfall totals included 21.6 inches (36 percent of normal) in Fairbanks and 33.2 inches (42 percent) in McGrath.  In Hawaii, agricultural impacts on Kauai led to further drought degradation.  Severe drought (D2) was introduced in northeastern Kauai, while moderate drought (D1) was expanded to cover much of the eastern two-thirds of the island.  Elsewhere in Hawaii, the drought depiction remained unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Texas">
   <p>Rain continued to chip away at the lingering dryness (D0) in southern Texas, where totals in excess of an inch resulted in a small reduction in the D0 area along the Gulf Coast.  In Corpus Christi, Texas, where the 2009 rainfall of 20.61 inches was 11.65 inches below normal, precipitation from December 1, 2009, to February 23, 2010, totaled 11.14 inches (6.24 inches above normal).  Elsewhere in Texas, San Antonio received 8.66 inches of precipitation during the first 54 days of the year (January 1 – February 23), compared with 8.43 inches during the first 8 months of 2009.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>An El Ni&#241;o-driven regime continued to influence Western weather patterns, resulting in drier-than-normal conditions in the Northwest and frequent storms in the Southwest.  Widespread precipitation fell in California, the Great Basin, and the Southwest, while only very light showers were noted across the interior Northwest.  In northwestern New Mexico, southeastern Utah, and southwestern Colorado, recent precipitation and generally near- to above-average mountain snow packs resulted in a broad reduction in the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0).  Some moderate drought (D1) was eliminated in southeastern Utah.  From February 18-22, unofficial snowfall totals in western Colorado included 56 inches at Gothic and 36 inches at Coal Bank Pass.  Meanwhile, rain and snow returned to California, easing concerns about the general lack of significant storminess in early to mid-February.  According to the California Department of Water Resources, the average water content of the high-elevation Sierra Nevada snow pack stood at 23 inches (99 percent of normal for the date) on February 22, compared to a 20-inch value (113 percent of normal) at the end of January.  Farther east, parts of the western Great Basin received heavy snow on February 20-21, resulting in a slight reduction of drought coverage.  Officially, 23.3 inches of snow fell at the National Weather Service office in Reno, Nevada.  Elsewhere, a few degradations were introduced from eastern Washington to northwestern Colorado.  For example, some moderate drought (D1) was introduced in eastern Washington, southwestern Wyoming, and extreme northwestern Colorado, while a ribbon of severe drought (D2) was placed along the Idaho-Montana border.  On February 23, the water content of the mountain snow pack averaged less than 60 percent of normal in numerous river basins across the northern Rockies and northern Intermountain West, according to USDA’s Natural Resources Conservation Service.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Upper Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Little or no precipitation fell across drought areas of the upper Great Lakes region, resulting in no change to the depiction.  North-central Minnesota was also dry, although a small reduction in the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) was introduced based on further analysis of precipitation and snow cover data.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
