<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20031113</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During November 12 - 17, heavy precipitation is forecast for the ArkLaTex region and most of the remainder of Arkansas (1 to 3 inches) while parts of the southern Rockies, Bear Basin, and Idaho Panhandle are expected to get 1 to 2 inches. At least moderate amounts (more than 0.5 inch) are anticipated elsewhere across the Texas Panhandle and Red River Valley, in the southern High Plains, and from the Rockies westward to the West Coast states. Meanwhile, light precipitation is forecast for the central and northern Mississippi Valley, but little or none is expected from Kansas and eastern Colorado northward through the central and northern Plains. The next 5 days (November 18 - 22) are expected to be cool and dry in southeastern Alaska, but the odds favor above-normal precipitation farther south across California, the Great Basin, the northern Intermountain West, the northern Rockies, and the northern Cascades. In contrast, warm and dry conditions appear more likely over most current areas of dryness and drought in the Plains, the central and northern Mississippi Valley, The Great Lakes region, and the central and northern Rockies' front range.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Light precipitation in part of southeastern Alaska was not enough to eliminate D0AH conditions, and in fact unusually quiet weather for the past several weeks led to the expansion of D0AH conditions to the south-central and southeastern coastline. Yakutat, which typically receives abundant autumnal precipitation, has recorded about 2 feet less than normal since mid-September.</p>
   <p>Light precipitation was also common across Hawaii, resulting in no changes to the dryness and drought conditions there, which range from D0 to D2 over all but the northernmost islands. At Hilo, rainfall has been falling regularly, though not very heavily, since the beginning of November. Accumulated totals are still about 6 inches below normal for the last 30 days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Northern Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Moderate to heavy precipitation improved dryness and drought conditions in a few areas. Generally 1.0 to locally 3.0 inches of precipitation ended D0H conditions in northeastern and central Illinois, lower Michigan, and a small part of northeastern Missouri. In addition, light precipitation and a re-evaluation of the effects of earlier rainfall led to the elimination of D0H in west-central Illinois and extreme southeastern Iowa, and a reduction to D0H across interior southeastern Iowa. Farther south, moderate precipitation (1.0 to 2.0 inches) fell on part of the D0H area in southwestern Missouri, but this did not warrant any classification changes because of the long-standing nature of the moisture deficits there.</p>
   <p>Most other areas recorded scattered totals of 0.5 to 0.9 inch at best, generally keeping D0 to D3 conditions intact, with deteriorated conditions noted in a few spots. D2AH and D3AH expanded westward into south-central Minnesota, where 3-month precipitation totals 4 to 6 inches below normal were similar to the deficits observed in areas to the east already classified as D2AH or D3AH last week. Farther south, little or no precipitation fell on northwestern Missouri and adjacent parts of Kansas and extreme southeastern Nebraska, where a re-evaluation of longer-term conditions led to the expansion of D1H and D2H, and the introduction of some D3H. Parts of northeastern Kansas have received 8 to 12 inches less than normal precipitation since April 1, and 2-year departures from normal are below -16 inches in part of the D3H region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Another damp week brought moderate to locally heavy precipitation to portions of the northern and central Rockies, the far northern Intermountain West, California, and southwest Oregon. Light to moderate precipitation (less than 1.0 inch) fell on most other areas, with negligible amounts at best reported across much of eastern Washington, central and southeastern Oregon, south-central Idaho, the southern Great Basin, and the southern tier of the region from southern California eastward through New Mexico.</p>
   <p>The largest totals (4.0 to locally 7.0 inches) were observed in the Cascades of California, and at isolated sites in the Sierra Nevada and northwestern California. As a result D0A and D0AH conditions were eliminated in these areas. Meanwhile, lesser totals (1.0 to locally 4.0 inches) were still sufficient to end D0A conditions in central and west-central California, and along the Oregon coastline.</p>
   <p>Farther inland, much of the ongoing dryness and drought date back multiple years. As a result, changes are occuring much more slowly, since precipitation surpluses or deficits resulting from even several weeks of abnormally wet or dry conditions pale in comparison to the magnitude of the long-standing, multi-year dryness (and resultant depletions in reservoir contents and soil moisture) that has gripped much of the interior West. Still, another week of moderate to heavy precipitation (1.0 to locally 4.0 inches) appeared sufficient improve conditions to D1H in part of southeastern Wyoming, and to D2H through parts of interior western Wyoming. In contrast, D1AH to D4AH conditions advanced slightly northwestward in Oregon, and seriously low long-term precipitation totals, along with resultant soil moisture shortages and reservoir storage depletions, led to a fairly broad expansion of D4AH condtions into southern Idaho and the Bear River Valley. Less than half of normal precipitation has fallen over the course of the past year in parts of the D4AH region, with 3-year running totals below 70% of normal common throughout southeastern Idaho and adjacent areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Lower Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Copious rains of 2.0 to locally 6.0 inches fell on parts of southeastern Oklahoma and adjacent Arkansas while moderate amounts (1.0 to 2.0 inches) fell on central Arkansas, east-central and south-central Oklahoma, and north-central Texas. This led to the elimination of D0AH conditions in parts of central and west-central Arkansas and adjacent Oklahoma; however, given the long-term moisture deficits in southeastern Oklahoma and adjacent Texas near the Red River, which exceed 16 inches for the past year in some spots, these areas kept D0AH and D1AH designations as they had the previous week.</p>
   <p>Other parts of the region recorded little or no precipitation, allowing short- and long-term rainfall deficits to increase, which in turn led to the expansion of D0AH and D1AH conditions in central and western Oklahoma, much of the Texas Panhandle, part of northeastern Texas, central and southeastern Louisiana, and the western tier of Mississippi. Furthermore, short-lived but acutely dry conditions led to the expansion of D2AH conditions into southwestern Oklahoma and adjacent Texas. In these areas, vegetation (including winter wheat) has been substantially impacted by dryness, as evidenced in satellite-derived assessments and local ground reports. Some areas have received 4 to 8 inches less rainfall than normal in the last 3 months.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
