<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000511</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Most of the Midwest should continue to see warmer-than-normal temperatures in the coming weeks, with normal precipitation expected in the western half of the Corn Belt. Above- normal rainfall may occur in the eastern half of the Corn Belt and up into Minnesota and the Great Lakes states.</p>
   <p>With forecasts showing a good chance of abnormally warmer and drier weather during the next two weeks in the Gulf Coast region, we can expect conditions to further worsen in eastern Alabama, Georgia, South Carolina, and northern Florida. Extreme drought (D3) is expected unless there is a major shift in the region's weather pattern in the coming weeks. Most of Texas can expect above or much above normal temperatures in the next two weeks, which will lead to a quick depletion of soil moisture levels that were recently boosted by rainfall. In addition, although Texas is expected to receive an inch or two in the next few days, little precipitation is expected across Texas and along the Gulf Coast up into the Carolinas for the 6-10 day period ending May 20.</p>
   <p>The Four Corners region can expect no precipitation and above-normal temperatures through the third week of May. Relatively normal temperatures and precipitation are expected across the rest of the West. Montana is expecting normal temperatures and precipitation in the coming weeks as dryness in this area bears watching.</p>
   <p>The apparent demise of La Nia in the coming weeks may play a role in changing the weather patterns that affect Puerto Rico and the Hawaiian Islands. In the interim, there isn't a lot of evidence yet that major changes will occur in the near future. This means that the first stage drought (D1) will continue across parts of the Hawaiian Islands.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>As has been the norm, little precipitation fell during the week across Hawaii. Long-term D1 (first stage drought) conditions continue to cause agricultural impacts and create the potential for wildfires in parts of the state. In the 365 days ending May 6, Hilo has run up an amazing rainfall deficit of 50 inches. Honolulu is already around 8 inches below normal for the year while other parts of the islands have accumulated deficits of 10 to 20 inches.</p>
   <p>There are no changes in the abnormally dry (D0) conditions that persist along the northern side of Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>In terms of precipitation, the first week of May was a story of feast or famine as a lot of the Corn Belt received normal or below-normal rainfall and saw well above normal temperatures. Most of the region should be seeing an inch or more a week now, but that hasn't been happening. The exception was the locally intense and slow-moving system that pounded eastern Missouri and southwestern Illinois, dropping more than a foot of rain in and around the St. Louis area. As a result, both the D2 (severe drought) and D1 regions (first stage drought) receded in this area.</p>
   <p>Over the weekend, a fast-moving system brought severe weather but relatively little moisture across most of Nebraska and western Iowa. On the heels of a dry April, much more precipitation is needed now that most of the crops are in the ground. This will soon lead to an increase in the demand on already low soil moisture levels across the entire Corn Belt. As feared, most of the sub-soil moisture levels never really came close to fully recovering from the dry and warm fall/winter period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>Again, much of the precipitation that fell during the last week avoided the extreme drought (D3) region in southeast Louisiana and the severe drought (D2) region in the Gulf Coast states.</p>
   <p>Conditions continue to deteriorate across parts of Alabama, Georgia, South Carolina, and Florida, where cooler temperatures last week were only a brief reprieve from a bone-dry spring. Very little rain fell across these states and hotter temperatures are around the corner as a Bermuda High builds in. Extreme drought (D3) regions now appear imminent in parts of the Southeast.</p>
   <p>Good rains fell over most of Arkansas and western Tennessee, reducing the areal extent of first stage (D1) drought there. The small area of severe drought (D2) that was in Arkansas has retreated back into southern Missouri for now.</p>
   <p>Plentiful rains in the last week have led to some improvement in drought conditions in eastern Texas. First stage drought (D1) has now been pushed back west of a line found roughly from Houston north to Dallas-Fort Worth and then to points westward. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions still remain across most of east Texas in what could be a see-sawing of drought conditions all summer long across what is becoming the skirmish line between drought in the South and across all of the Gulf Coast states.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Western States">
   <p>No improvement was seen across western Texas in the last week as precipitation stayed well to the east. Record heat has already made an appearance in areas already affected by extreme drought (D3) in western Texas. The end of April signaled a record six straight months of record low water storage across Texas. Nearly 90 public water supply systems located in central, northeast, and north-central Texas are currently limiting water use to avoid shortages. Most of the reservoirs in these areas are running at or below 50% of capacity, with several falling below 33%. In addition, extreme fire danger potential exists in several Trans-Pecos counties, according to the Texas Forest Service. Drought is still firmly entrenched in the western half of the state, which has never really recovered from the drought of 1996.</p>
   <p>Conditions remained dry and abnormally warm across southern New Mexico and Arizona. This pattern is also being seen in parts of the Northern Rockies. Officials in New Mexico expect disaster declarations to follow shortly in several counties. The wildfire threat remains very high across Arizona and New Mexico. High winds and heat have already led to an uncontrollable large-scale fire getting out of hand around Los Alamos, New Mexico. It bears repeating, however, that water supplies remain in good condition across most of the region as a result of brimming reservoirs due to good snows farther north the past few winters. As a result, we are not seeing widespread hydrological impacts at this time and most users expect to see their full water allotments this water year.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
