<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060601</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (June 1-5):  Over the next 5-day period, models are in fair agreement about a large-scale ridge dominating the central portion of the United States.  A trough over the West Coast and another over the East Coast will dominate the weather patterns over those areas.  Smaller-scale features look to ride along the top of the ridge, and will be responsible for widely scattered precipitation events out in front of the ridge as it moves to the east.  Temperatures during this time should be well above normal through the Rocky Mountains and into the northern Great Plains, while cooler temperatures will prevail along the East Coast.  The greatest precipitation amounts will be in the Pacific Northwest as the trough moves ashore, and along the East Coast.  Portions of southern Texas are also likely to see precipitation.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlook (June 6-10):  The ridge in the southwest part of the United States will be slow to move in the extended periods.  Models are quite confident that as the ridge slowly moves onto the Plains, a trough will continue to dig deeper into the Pacific Northwest.  Temperatures will continue to be well above normal through much of the western half of the country as this ridge dominates, with the warmest regions over the northern Rocky Mountains.  The warmest areas are also expected to be the driest over the forecast period, with the best chances for above-normal precipitation expected to be in New England and Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Gulf Coast">
   <p>Warm temperatures dominated the Gulf Coast region.  Temperatures for the week were 3-9F above normal.  For much of the Gulf Coast, dry conditions prevailed, with areas of Florida, Alabama, Mississippi and Louisiana deteriorating in their drought depiction.  Mobile, Alabama, is currently 6 inches below its previous lowest water year total.  Since October 1, 2005, Mobile has recorded just 18 inches of precipitation, compared to the next lowest, 24.52 inches recorded in 1940.  With these conditions prevalent through much of the Gulf Coast from Louisiana to the Florida panhandle, D0 was expanded into Florida and D1 and D2 conditions migrated to the east to include Mobile Bay.</p>
   <p>The western Gulf Coast experienced localized, heavy rain at the end of the Drought Monitor period.  More than 7 inches of rain fell in the area around and including Victoria County, Texas.  This helped to reduce the D3 and D4 conditions that were persisting in this region.  The Beaumont, Texas, region experienced more than 9 inches of rain.  The localized flooding rains were observed over a relatively small area, just off the coast, that helped to diminish any lingering effects of the D2 conditions from just north of Galveston Bay to the Louisiana state line.  In Texas Climate Division 9, the D4 conditions were expanded slightly to include the region around Corpus Christi.  With the continued impact on the cattle industry as well as year-to-date precipitation departures approaching 7 inches, this area continues to battle the ongoing drought in south Texas.</p>
   <p>D0 was expanded from Arkansas to include much of eastern Mississippi and northeast Louisiana.  After some recovery earlier in the spring, this area is again dry.  Rivers and stream flows are again reduced and soil moisture conditions are also declining.</p>
   <p>In Puerto Rico, D0 was added to the southeast part of the island because of dryness in the short-term.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Cool and dry conditions dominated much of New England and the East Coast.  Temperatures were 3-6F below normal for the week, with very little precipitation.  Some precipitation was more widespread across the coast of the Carolinas and the southern tip of Florida.  The widespread dry conditions continued to deteriorate the drought conditions.  Expansion of the D0 conditions into extreme eastern Virginia and Maryland along with expansion of D0 into central Georgia and southern South Carolina were the biggest changes for the region in this weeks depiction.  Seasonal rains in south Florida helped to thwart any expansion of drought in the Florida peninsula this week, and conditions there will continue to be monitored.  The Piedmont region of North Carolina into south central Virginia is developing as an area of concern.  Roanoke, Virginia, reported only 1.13 inches of precipitation in May (2nd driest since 1948) and Danville, Virginia, reported 1.66 inches of rain in May, its 4th driest.  Since January 1, Danville is just 38% of normal precipitation, with a deficit of 11.95 inches.  This area is currently D1, but if more impacts are experienced and this dry pattern continues, a further intensification of the drought in this region is expected.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Hot and dry conditions dominated much of the Plains and Midwest this week.  Temperatures were 9-12 degrees above normal for much of the region, while precipitation was localized to a few areas.   With several rain events in southeast Nebraska and into southwest Iowa, the D0 area in this region was reduced in the areas that received the most rain.  Elsewhere in Nebraska, dryness was the catalyst of expansion of the drought categories.  The D2 conditions in western Nebraska and Kansas were expanded further to the east, while D1 conditions also migrated to the east in Nebraska.  Much of northeast Nebraska was also included in D0, as abnormally dry conditions were starting to affect soil moisture conditions.</p>
   <p>In South Dakota, the D2 region was expanded to the east, as several counties in this region were showing total losses for the wheat crop this year.  Reports are still coming in, but from Pierre northward, losses are being experienced to both spring and winter wheat crops.</p>
   <p>The last lingering areas of D0 in Wisconsin were taken away this week, as conditions along the Great Lakes have improved over the last several weeks.</p>
   <p>Abnormally dry (D0) conditions were introduced in all of west Texas that previously was not showing any dryness.  A categorical deterioration of drought conditions in the Big Bend region of Climate Division 5 and into Climate Division 6 was made in response to the dryness in this region as well as continuing agricultural impacts in much of the southern half of Texas.  Dry conditions, along with temperatures well above normal, have continued to affect much of north-central and northeast Texas into Oklahoma.  Dallas, Texas, so far this year has experienced record warm temperatures that rank 1.8F above the previous warmest year, back in 2000.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West">
   <p>Cool temperatures and precipitation in the northern Rocky Mountains allowed much of the region to maintain current drought conditions.  The last bit of D0 in Montana was taken away as conditions were improving in this region.  D0 conditions were expanded in Wyoming into north-central Colorado as short-term dryness has started to affect both water and agricultural interests.  Colorado also had an expansion of drought conditions for much of the eastern half of the state.  D1 and D2 conditions were expanded westward as short-term dryness has started to affect the region.  Denver has received 1.73 inches of precipitation the last 3 months, which is about 30% of normal for what is typically one of the wettest parts of the year.  D3 conditions were also expanded in southeastern Colorado as conditions continue to decline.  In Arizona, the United States Department of Agriculture designated 14 of 15 counties as drought disaster areas, allowing producers to apply for assistance.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
