<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001116</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect some of the areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) arctic outbreaks sweeping across the Great Lakes November 17-18 and November 21-23 could bring locally heavy lake-effect snows to Michigans Upper Peninsula; 2) several rounds of showers and thunderstorms could bring additional drought relief to the Gulf Coast region November 15-19; 3) the latest 6-10 day forecast from the Climate Prediction Center (valid November 21-25) shows above-normal precipitation centered on the area in western Texas experiencing longer-term hydrological drought impacts; and 4) the same CPC forecast has most of the rest of the nation experiencing normal precipitation for the period, except for below-normal precipitation in the drought areas of Montana.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>The drought classification remained unchanged for Hawaii this week. Honolulu, on Oahu, did receive some additional rainfall and has now received 6.73 inches for the year, which is 41 percent of normal. The D1 category still exists on leeward sides of Molokai, Maui, and the island of Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Precipitation during the week, including a snowstorm in the central Plains, helped improve abnormally dry conditions in South Dakota, Minnesota, Iowa, Wisconsin, Michigan, and Missouri. Long-term deficits since April 1 persist for a small area in central Minnesota, while D1 (first stage drought) and D0 conditions cover the entire Upper Peninsula of Michigan. Improvements also occurred in the D1 and D2 areas in Kansas, Nebraska, and Iowa, but long-term hydrological concerns still exist in western Nebraska and northwestern Missouri. Similar long-term hydrological concerns are also true for a large area of western Texas and southeastern New Mexico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>Generous precipitation (greater than 2 inches) fell across large areas of the South and Southeast during the past week. This rainfall helped relieve short-term and some long-term drought impacts, but severe to extreme hydrological impacts are still widespread across the region. Coweta County, southwest of Atlanta, is the latest county in Georgia to impose a new round of water restrictions as a result of declining water supplies. Much of northeastern Mississippi, northern Alabama, and central Tennessee saw drought conditions improve from the extreme category (D3) to the severe category (D2). The area of exceptional drought (D4) along the North Carolina-Tennessee border improved to the D3 category. Rains during the week also eliminated the abnormally dry (D0) conditions across parts of southern New England and the mid-Atlantic states.</p>
   <p>In contrast, the drought situation in central Florida continues to deteriorate. Both the extreme and severe drought categories expanded to include more counties, especially north of the Tampa-St. Petersburg metropolitan area. These cities are at the center of the worst conditions. For Tampa, the year-to-date precipitation total is 26.54 inches (65 percent of normal), which ranks as the second driest behind 1977. Meanwhile, the October1998 through October 2000 period ranked as the driest such period since records began in 1890.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>In the West, improvements eliminated the need for the D0 classification in central Nevada, southern Colorado and southeastern Utah, and southwestern Montana. There was also improvement to the areas experiencing D1 drought in southwestern and southeastern Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
