<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010201</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Anticipated occurrences which may affect current areas of dryness and drought over the next 10 days include: (1) a series of Pacific storms bringing needed rain and snow to the West, with forecast precipitation amounts of 1 to 3 inches across western parts of Oregon and Washington during January 31 to February 5; (2) showers across Florida and southern Georgia from January 31 to February 3, amounts ranging up to 2 inches in northern Florida; (3) above normal precipitation forecast during February 6-10 in the Midwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Showers were fairly widespread across Hawaii last week, but amounts were not enough to significantly alter the D1 (Moderate Drought) remaining over the Big Island and D0 to D1 dryness/drought over the other islands. Honolulus month-to-date rainfall has totaled 0.11 inches versus a normal of 3.35 inches. Scattered light to moderate rains left the D0 areas of Puerto Rico intact.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>With precipitation amounts generally light to occasionally moderate, there was little change this week in the D0 (Abnormally Dry) area from western New York to West Virginia. D1 drought remained over southwest Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>The same storm system that affected the South dumped rain and snow on the Midwest, easing dryness. One to 3-inch rainfalls led to removal of D0 dryness across central Missouri and western Illinois while rain or snow removed lingering D2 drought in western Iowa and reduced the area of D1 in western Iowa and eastern Nebraska. The wintry mix also reduced the extent of D2 drought in northeast Kansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>A large storm system dumped heavy rain from Mississippi to Alabama and northward to Missouri and Tennessee on Sunday-Tuesday, January 28-30. The rains reduced the area of D1 and D2 drought in western Tennessee and northeast Arkansas, and reduced D0 and D1 conditions in western Alabama. Severe hydrological drought (D2) persisted from eastern Alabama northeastward to the western Carolinas. Abnormal dryness expanded eastward to the North Carolina coast. Severe (D2) to Exceptional (D4) drought remained over much of the Florida peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A Pacific storm brought rain and snow to the region during January 24-26. One to 4 inches of rain reduced D0 (Abnormal Dryness) over northwest California, but the Northwest states continued to report a declining percent of average snowpack, falling further behind conditions expected for this time of year. D1 drought expanded westward from northwestern Montana to northeast Washington, while D0 dryness continued over much of the remainder of the Northwest and southward to Californias Sierra. River basin season-to-date precipitation in northeast Washington, northern Idaho, and northwest Montana ranged from 37 to 43% of normal. Snowpack in the Columbia Basin above Portland is the second lowest in the past half century for this point in the season, and the snowpack (50% of average) for the Columbia River above the Grand Coulee Dam in Washington is below the February 1, 1977 value of 53%, formerly the lowest early February reading for this period.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
