<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001221</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features through December 29 that may impact the Nations drought areas are: 1) A storm system in the upper Midwest on Wednesday is forecast to bring light snow to the central Corn Belt and Great Lakes region, then produce light precipitation in the Southeast on Thursday, and affect the East Coast by Friday. South Texas may receive scattered showers Friday-Monday while lake-effect snow showers should be common in orographically-favored Great Lakes locations throughout the 10-day period. 2) Cold conditions are expected to persist across much of the country east of the Rockies during the next 10 days. 3) Precipitation should return to the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies through this weekend before drier weather is predicted for most of next week. 4) By early next week, a storm should develop in the central Plains and gradually move across the South, bringing an above-normal chance for precipitation during December 26-30 from Colorado and New Mexico eastward to the Carolinas and Florida. 5) Through Monday, no immediate relief from dryness is expected as high pressure north of both Hawaii and Puerto Rico should keep conditions generally fair.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Light, scattered showers (0.5 to 2 inches) were limited to windward areas of the Big Island, with lower totals (less than 0.5 inches) on Kauai and the windward sections of Oahu and Maui. Little or no rainfall was observed across Molokai, Lanai, western Maui, and northwestern Big Island, maintaining the abnormal dryness. In Puerto Rico, with November statistics now available, the abnormally dry (D0) area was redrawn to reflect 3-month deficits between 5 and 15 inches (especially after a relatively dry November). Additionally, the island has entered its normally driest time of the year (December-March).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Ohio Valley and Mid-Atlantic Region">
   <p>A mixed bag of precipitation, with weekly totals exceeding 2 inches, fell on eastern Ohio and extreme western Pennsylvania, and from southeastern Virginia northward into Maine, removing abnormal dryness (D0) from much of this region. Similarly, substantial precipitation (2 to 4") was reported in western North Carolina and eastern Kentucky, improving drought by one category. In the central Appalachians, however, relief was minimal as a band of lesser precipitation (0.5-2") was recorded.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Bitterly cold Arctic air (sub-zero lows, weekly temperatures averaged 12 to 18F below normal), plus a series of winter storms (liquid equivalent of 0.2 to 0.8 inches), increased the blanket of snow across portions of the central Great Plains, western Corn Belt, and Great Lakes region. On Tuesday morning, one-half to two feet of snow covered most drought areas of eastern Nebraska, Iowa, and the Upper Peninsula of Michigan, with nearly three feet in parts of the latter area. With the ground frozen and snow covered, drought relief would not be expected until a prolonged period of thawing (spring) occurs; however, the 2-3 feet of snow on Michigans Keweenaw Peninsula insured enough future moisture to remove D1(W) drought there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>After two relatively tranquil weeks, a very active weather pattern produced not only widespread moderate to heavy rainfall (2 to 6 inches), but also numerous reports of severe weather, including devastating twisters in Alabama. The greatest totals (more than 4 inches) fell from northern Mississippi northeastward into eastern Kentucky, generally reducing long-term (hydrological) drought by one category, and eliminating any short-term (topsoil) dryness except in extreme northwestern areas where lower amounts (&lt; 2 inches) occurred. This was also reflected by the USGS streamflow information as most Southern sites rose from near-record low levels a week ago to near-record high values on Sunday. However, a sustained period of surplus precipitation is needed to alleviate long-term drought in the South as large year-to-date deficits still remain (i.e. New Orleans, LA 21.22"; Meridian, MS 18.61"; Montgomery, AL 17.99"; Atlanta, GA 14.23"; Memphis, TN 12.87"), major reservoir and lake levels are still below average, and most streamflows have already begun to drop below normal levels even after this weeks significant precipitation. In sharp contrast, drought remained or slightly intensified across Florida with another week of very warm weather and light showers (rainfall of 0.1-0.6", highs in the mid-80's, and temperatures departures of +8 to +12F). Accumulated deficits since January 1 have reached 12 to 18 inches in central Florida, and 18 to 24 inches in the Panhandle.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>With high pressure entrenched over the Far West, the bulk of the Pacific storm systems trekked northeastward into British Columbia, and then dove southeastward into the northern Rockies. This storm track brought additional light to moderate snowfall (liquid equivalent 1-2") to the northern and central Rockies as October 1-December 19 SNOTEL basin precipitation stayed or slightly increased to near normal, alleviating abnormal dryness in parts of Idaho, Colorado, and Wyoming. Light to moderate precipitation from a cold core system around mid-week, plus a weekend cold front, slightly increased season-to-date SNOTEL basin average precipitation and snow water content in the Sierra Nevada and Cascades to between 50 and 75% of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
