<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20131205</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>A powerful storm moved into the eastern U.S. early in this US Drought Monitor week just ahead of Thanksgiving.  Snow accumulated from the southern Appalachians up through Maine while areas to the south and east experienced rain.  Lake effect snows in western Pennsylvania and New York led to snowfalls in excess of 13 inches.  This, combined with windy conditions following the cold front, caused delays in most modes of transportation.  All this moisture helped to alleviate dryness in the East while cool temperatures kept drought conditions from intensifying over most of the CONUS.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the December 5-9, 2013 time period, precipitation is forecast along much of the eastern U.S., from the Southern Plains extending into New England.  An above normal chance of precipitation is also present across areas of the West, particularly in the Southwest.   Temperatures are expected to be below-normal across the country, with the exception of the East Coast during this time.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (December 10-14, 2013), the odds favor above-normal temperatures in the Southeast and in northern Alaska.  Normal to below-normal temperatures are favored across the rest of the CONUS and in southern and central Alaska. Above normal-precipitation is likely across most of the eastern third of the country, in northern Alaska, and from the Pacific coast, through the Rockies and into the northern Plains. The eastern Southwest and the Central and Southern Plains, as well as the southwestern Midwest and southern Alaska are likely to see below-normal precipitation.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>A heavy rain event over Kauai and Oahu, in combination with several other similar events in the past month, led to improvements on those islands.  Moderate Drought (D1) was eliminated and areas of Abnormal Dryness (D0) were reduced.  On the Big Island of Hawaii, dry conditions continue in the central part of the island.  Coincidently, Severe (D2) and Moderate Drought (D1) expanded in the area.  Elsewhere in the Big Island, recent rainfall led to improvements to Severe Drought (D2) in the south and Moderate Drought (D1) was abated in the east.  On Puerto Rico, heavy rainfall was experienced this week including a record rainfall report for San Juan on December 1.  Abnormal Dryness (D0) was scaled back as a result.  In Alaska, areas of Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormal Dryness (D0) were reduced in the interior of the state, consistent with above normal precipitation for the last few weeks abating drought impacts there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Northern Plains and Midwest">
   <p>This area remained status quo for the week.  Moderate to cool temperatures and areas of frozen soil led to no change in the drought depiction in the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>The intense storm that moved through the East just before Thanksgiving provided some needed relief for dryness in the region.  Areas of abnormal dryness (D0) in Alabama, Georgia, North and South Carolina, Virginia, Pennsylvania, New York, New Hampshire, Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Maine were reduced as was Moderate Drought (D1) in Maine.  Conversely, Moderate Drought (D1) in southern Alabama expanded slightly in the area that missed most of the precipitation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southern Plains">
   <p>Beneficial rains fell from eastern Texas, through southern Louisiana, and into Mississippi.  Areas of Abnormal Dryness (D0) were alleviated in those areas.  The lack of precipitation in other parts of Texas led to an expansion of Extreme (D3) and Severe Drought (D2) in the Panhandle and Severe (D2) and moderate Drought (D1) in the southern part of the state.  Despite other parts of the region receiving little precipitation, drought status did not change.  Cool temperatures helped mitigate impacts from the lack of precipitation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Abnormal Dryness (D0) expanded in the northern Cascade Mountains in Oregon and Washington as well as on the Oregon Coast.  These areas have missed most of the recent precipitation that has fallen around the Northwest and have significant deficits for the year.  The rest of the West remains unchanged this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
