<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070308</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch over the next 2 weeks that could affect current dry or drought areas include: 1) a much milder and drier pattern for much of the country outside of the northern tier states, with unseasonable warmth and dryness pronounced from the Great Basin to the central Plains; 2) an exception to the dry pattern will be showers over the southern Plains and the lower Mississippi Valley during March 9-12, with locally as much as 2 inches possible in Texas; 3) above-normal precipitation in the Pacific Northwest the next 2 weeks, and Great Lakes region days 6 through 14.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The second week of heavy rains eliminated the D0 over windward areas of the Hawaiian Islands. Precipitation amounts were not high enough to affect the D0 and D1 area in Puerto Rico. The D0 area in Alaska expanded slightly northward, westward, and eastward based on updated snow pack information and continued dry weather.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Central States">
   <p>An intense storm system centered near southeastern Colorado on February 28 tracked northeastward to the southern Iowa area on March 1 and Wisconsin on the 2nd. The storm dumped at least 14 inches of snow on eastern South Dakota, southern and eastern Minnesota, northern Wisconsin, and northern Michigan, with totals reaching 20 inches in Duluth, Minnesota, and 25 inches in northern Wisconsin. The moisture caused a further pullback of the D0/D1/D2 drought complex in northern Minnesota and removed most of the D2 drought in Wisconsin and northern Michigan. In the core drought area of northern interior Minnesota, D3 persisted, as snowfall amounts totaled less than 10 inches, and 12-month precipitation totals remained as little as 50 percent of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>The thunderstorms associated with the severe weather outbreak late in the week dropped over 2 inches of rain on parts of Kentucky, Tennessee, Georgia, and the Carolinas, reducing the D1 drought to a small area of eastern Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky, and removing D0 dryness from central Kentucky and most of West Virginia. The heavy rains ended D0 across central Georgia, but lingering low lake levels resulted in D0 remaining over northwestern and northern Georgia. Rainfall amounts were variable over Mississippi and Louisiana. With 60-day rainfall under 60 percent of normal, D0 dryness expanded into southwestern Mississippi and parts of Louisiana. This area has seen numerous wildfires develop, and streamflows have been unseasonably low.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains">
   <p>With the dry February pattern continuing into early March, D0 dryness expanded eastward in Texas and northwestward toward the Panhandle. The area of D3 and D4 remained over south-central Texas. Both Austin and San Antonio recorded their sixth driest February on record.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The drought area from southern interior California through Arizona saw little precipitation this week, resulting in no improvement to the D1 to D2 drought. Los Angeles has seen their driest season to date on record, with cumulative rainfall of 2.42 inches (21 percent of normal) since July 1. The Sierra did see additional snowfall early in the week, but snow water content remained less than 60 percent of normal at many locations, so there was no change in the D1 area across southern California and western Nevada. Low snowpack resulted in a slight northward advance of the D1 into southern Utah and also in eastern Oregon. A re-assessment of overall conditions, including updated surface water supply conditions, resulted in some pullback of the D3 and D2 in northern Wyoming and retreat southward of the drought areas in Montana. For similar reasons, D1 expanded slightly westward in eastern Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
