<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020711</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through July 12 that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) over the next 5 days, (7/10-15) cooler temperatures are on tap for virtually the entire eastern half of the country while the western half can expect well above-normal temperatures; 2) over the same time period, the West looks to be headed for very dry weather as well. Parts of the Midwest and Mid-Atlantic states could see anywhere from 1 to 2 inches to go along with the cooler weather. The Southeast may stand to benefit the most, as they could see 3 to 5 inches, especially in Tennessee, northeastern Alabama, northern Georgia and the Carolinas; 3) looking out at the 6-10 day period (7/16-20) we can expect to see above-normal temperatures from the Interior West over to the Great Lakes region as high pressure dominates the weather picture and pushes the jet stream well north. The Southeast is also likely to see above-normal temperatures while Texas should see below-normal temperatures. Heat index readings could be very intense from the central Plains down to Texas and over into the Southeast, with readings well into triple figures; 4) precipitation over the 6-10 day period shows signs that the monsoon could be on its way in the Southwest as totals should be above normal there as well as in southern Texas and the Mississippi Delta region. Below-normal precipitation is expected in the central Plains and front range region of Colorado; 5) Most of Alaska is expected to be cooler and wetter in the 6-10 day period while Hawaii isn't expecting to see enough in the way of rainfall to change the situation there.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Abnormally dry (D0) conditions continue across central and southeastern Alaska. In addition to Molokai, abnormally dry (D0) conditions have been introduced to the leeward side of Oahu as concern grows about recent brush fires and agricultural interests in the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>Most of the Gulf Coast saw normal temperatures and spotty rainfall. Severe drought (D2) has slowly begun to creep further into northwestern Louisiana and abnormally dry (D0) conditions have now moved north into eastern Arkansas and even into southwestern Tennessee. The relatively quick onset of dryness here has largely been due to rainfall totals only falling around 50% of normal since June 1.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Southeast">
   <p>The Northeast as a whole was relatively warm and dry, with the exception of Maine. Conditions in Maine continue to slowly improve. The recent heat and dryness have led to the movement northward of the W (hydro) line in the Mid-Atlantic. Abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) have again started to push northward in Virginia toward the Washington D.C. area. Farther north, abnormally dry (D0) conditions have also spread back into western Massachusetts, eastern New York and further west into south-central Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>Most of the Southeast experienced a pretty normal week in the way of temperatures and rainfall. The heavier rains fell on parts western Virginia and North Carolina and extreme northeastern Tennessee. Things remain quite dry in the eastern Carolinas as severe drought (D2) has now pushed its way to the coast and into the Wilmington, North Carolina area. Conditions have also worsened in parts of southeastern Tennessee. Chattanooga has seen only 43% of its expected rainfall since June 1, and is also seeing a deficit of -7.44 for the year. As a result, abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) have now begun pushing toward central Tennessee as virtually the entire state is well below normal since June 1. Abnormally dry conditions have also migrated back into east-central and northeastern Tennessee.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The northern Plains and Midwest remained hot and dry (for the most part) over the last seven days as the heat wave of June carried over into the first week of July. The exception, of course, was found in the southern Plains, where Oklahoma, Texas and eastern New Mexico saw cooler than normal temperatures prevail. Naturally, all the clouds and rain plaguing the region contributed to this cool-down.</p>
   <p>Rainfall totals were again well above normal in the southern Plains as flooding continued over parts of Texas while parts of southern Oklahoma and eastern welcomed the rains. The heavy rains simply shifted to north-central Texas. Consequently, drought conditions that were reaching a peak in south-central Texas as recently as late June have now been eradicated by widespread rainfall amounts in central Texas, which ranged from just under 8 inches in Abilene to over 15 inches in San Antonio, with many locations in the outlying areas seeing well over 20 inches of rain. On the flip side, extreme southern, western and coastal areas of Texas remain in drought. Not all of the stations within this area saw a total removal of the deficits they had accrued to this point, so some areas will still bear watching over the next two traditionally hottest months. For example, Austin, Texas is still nearly 5.5 inches below normal (70%) for the year even though they benefitted greatly from the recent rains.</p>
   <p>Further north, moisture from the stalled system in Texas worked its way up into the northern Plains and brought the fuel needed to dump heavy rains on parts of the eastern Dakotas and southwestern Nebraska. Over 10 inches in just 6 hours led to the washing out of I-80 near Ogallala, Nebraska. While long-term drought conditions remain in the region, improvements were made in these areas because of the locally heavy rains. As a result of the long-term drought in the Missouri River basin and its headwaters, barge traffic from Sioux City, Nebraska to Kansas City, Missouri, could stop entirely this summer, as the river is already at its minimum navigational flow level.</p>
   <p>Abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) also expanded in the region last week as the combined heat and lack of rainfall has led to a continued march eastward into southeastern South Dakota, southwestern Minnesota and northern Iowa. Moderate (D1) and severe (D2) drought continue to press into southwestern North Dakota as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Rains were a welcome sight up and down the Rocky Mountain spine last week (from Montana to New Mexico). In the drought affected areas, mostly normal to slightly warmer than normal temperatures were seen, except in parts of northwestern Montana, eastern New Mexico and southern California, which benefitted from cooler than normal temperatures during the past week.</p>
   <p>Recent outbreaks of large fires in the Intermountain West/Great Basin region (ID, UT, and NV) and eastern Oregon in the past few days have led to the addition of the fire impact label (F) here. In addition, exceptional drought (D4) has expanded to include all of the Rio Grande basin in southern Colorado and northern New Mexico. According to the USDA-NRCS, at the forecast point of Del Norte, Colorado, the April-September runoff forecast of 90,000 acre-feet is nearly twice as low as the previous record low runoff of 155,700 acre-feet seen in 1977. Other changes in the West included an expansion of abnormally dry (D0) conditions into southwestern Oregon.</p>
   <p>Recent rains in northern and eastern Montana and eastern New Mexico continue to slowly help alleviate the situation there.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
