<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040923</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>For the next 5 days (September 23-27) scattered showers will gradually diminish along a weakening frontal boundary draped across the Plains and upper Midwest. Nevertheless, some additional rainfall, locally heavy, may fall on the central Plains very early in the forecast period. Thereafter, the focus for significant rainfall will briefly shift to the Dakotas (due to a departing low-pressure system) and the southern Rockies (in part due to upslope flow). Meanwhile, remnant tropical moisture from former Hurricane Ivan will spread westward across the Gulf of Mexico and may produce showers in Louisiana and eastern Texas. Mostly dry weather will prevail into early next week along and west of a line from Arizona to Montana. The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for September 28 - October 2 calls for above-normal temperatures nearly nationwide. Mostly dry weather is expected across the northern half of the U.S., but wetter-than-normal conditions are likely across the southern Plains and parts of the Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Cool, showery weather settled across much of Alaska, virtually ending the threat of additional wildfire activity. Nearly 6.4 million acres of vegetation burned in Alaska during the summer of 2004, easily surpassing the 1957 state record of 5.1 million acres. Despite the end of the wildfire season, abnormal dryness persisted across much of eastern Alaska. Following Fairbanks third-driest June-August period (1.81 inches, or 37% of normal) in the last half-century, 0.80 inch (94% of normal) fell during the first 21 days of September. Fairbanks year-to-date precipitation through September 21 was 5.55 inches (72% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Abnormal dryness (D0) persisted across northern and eastern portions of the Big Island and developed in parts of southern Maui.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Weekly rainfall topped 2 inches in north-central Wisconsin, reducing the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>More than 2 inches of rain fell in parts of the middle Missouri Valley, resulting in a slight reduction in the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0). Lighter amounts of rain fell across the remainder of the northern half of the Plains, helping to offset the effects of late-season warmth. Temperatures on the central Plains averaged as much as 10 degrees F above normal from September 14-20. Poor range/pasture conditions remained a concern in several states, including Nebraska (50% very poor to poor), Montana (47%), North Dakota (37%), South Dakota (35%), Kansas (28%), and Colorado (25%). In recent weeks, dry weather has reduced topsoil moisture reserves across the southern half of the Plains. Although effects of the short-term dryness are not yet significant, winter wheat will soon need rain during the autumn establishment season. As of September 19, winter wheat was 29% planted nationally (compared to the 5-year average of 23%), with state values on the Plains ranging from 21% planted in Kansas to 62% in Colorado. Reservoir storage remains a long-term concern across the northern half of the High Plains. For example, western Nebraskas Lake McConaughy fell to an historic low level on September 8, falling to 3,198.2 feet above sea level and matching the record set in 1956. McConaughy contains only about 20 percent of the water it can hold at capacity and the lakes level is 67 feet lower than its 1999 peak.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Abnormal dryness (D0) continued to expand from the lower Mississippi Valley westward. D0 was introduced in parts of Arkansas and adjacent areas across Missouris Ozark Plateau and the Arklatex region. In Little Rock, Arkansas, rainfall totaled just 0.11 inch from August 21 - September 20, breaking the record for that 31-day period (previously, 0.18 inch in 1936). Dry weather continued to take a toll on pastures and late-maturing summer crops. According to the U.S. Department of Agriculture, 26% of Louisianas cotton and soybeans were rated in very poor to poor condition on September 19. The percentage of ranges and pastures rated very poor to poor included 37% in Louisiana and 25% in Arkansas. Those numbers represented sharp declines in range/pasture conditions from September 5, when 15 and 8% of the pastureland was rated very poor to poor in Louisiana and Arkansas, respectively.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The remnants of former eastern Pacific Hurricane Javier were absorbed into a cold front, providing central Arizona with a significant rainfall event. Javiers low-level circulation moved within about 200 miles of El Paso, Texas, on the night of September 19-20 before dissipating. A few central and northern Arizona locations reported 4 to 6 inches of rain, with many more netting at least 2 inches. In a 48-hour period on September 18-20, the Grand Canyon Airport netted 3.30 inches of rain, exactly 20% of its normal annual total. Despite large, multi-year precipitation deficits and water-supply shortages, the magnitude of central Arizonas recent rainfall event warranted a general reduction from extreme to severe drought (D3 to D2). On September 18, the Salt River reservoir system held 802 thousand acre-feet of water, while the Verde River system held 124 thousand acre-feet. Four days later, the storage figures stood at 809 and 132 thousand acre-feet, respectively. In the 72-hour period following the Arizona rainfall, inflow at three key river locationsthe Salt River at Roosevelt, Tonto Creek at Roosevelt, and the Verde River at Tanglewas 16,130 cubic feet per second, compared to the September 19-21 normal of 1,386 c.f.s. However, the single rainfall event put only a slight dent in central and northern Arizonas multi-year precipitation deficits. For example, Prescott, Arizona, noted a 33.89-inch deficit from January 1999 - August 2004, representing 1.77 years worth of precipitation shortfall in a 5.67-year period. Prescotts normal annual precipitation is 19.19 inches.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere in the West, heavy precipitation continued in northwestern Montana, mainly west of the Continental Divide. As a result, lines depicting abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) were nudged farther to the east. There were also some minor reductions in dryness and drought in the central Rockies and adjacent areas due to widespread showers, including early-season snowfall. Despite recent precipitation in parts of the West, the condition of ranges and pastures remained a concern. As of September 19, USDA reported 100% of ranges/pastures rated very poor to poor in California. Other Western states with more than half of their ranges/pastures rated very poor to poor were Wyoming (69%), Arizona (56%), and Nevada (54%).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
