<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100506</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Heavy rain and flooding impacted areas of the country this week.  Two-day rainfall in Nashville, TN totaled 13.57 inches, breaking the old record for two-day rainfall of 6.68 inches.  Measured precipitation in Franklin, Camden, and Brownsville, TN exceeded 17 inches.  Estimates in Benton County , TN are nearly 20 inches for the two-day event while it is estimated that over 15 inches fell in areas in and around Hickman, Davidson, and Wilson Counties.  As of Tuesday, flood waters were still present and at least 28 persons (in three states) have been killed in the event.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Precipitation is expected to move across the northern and central Plains and into the Great Lakes and Northeast regions in the May 6-10, 2010 time period.  Additional areas of precipitation are expected around the Gulf of Mexico.  Western precipitation is expected to fall mainly in coastal Washington and into the northern Rockies in Idaho and.  Above normal temperatures are expected throughout the South while below normal temperatures are expected across the Northwest, the Plains, and into the East.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (May 11 – 15, 2010), the odds favor cooler-than-normal conditions across most of the West, through the northern Plains, and into the mid-Atlantic and Northeast.  Warmer-than-normal conditions are expected in the extreme South and around the Gulf of Mexico.  The odds of above-normal precipitation extend from the interior of the country, roughly from the Great Salt Lake, all the way through the Northeast.  Odds favor below-normal precipitation along the Gulf of Mexico and through the northern Plains and western Great Lakes.  Odds favor dry and cool conditions throughout most of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought conditions remained unchanged across Alaska and Puerto Rico this week.  The lingering effects of the El Nino are still being felt in Hawaii.  Lower than normal rainfall over the last few months have led to water restrictions on Oahu, leading to an increase in abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1).  Conversely, Kauai saw reductions in areas of severe (D2) and moderate (D1) drought, as well as abnormal dryness (D0).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Heavy rains and extensive flooding brought an end to abnormal dryness and drought that had been impacting Alabama, Tennessee, and most of Kentucky.  Other areas in the mid-Atlantic and Northeast saw rain from West Virginia, through southern Pennsylvania and into the New York City area, as well as a secondary area of precipitation from upstate New York through northern Vermont and New Hampshire and into northern Maine.  These rains missed the drought-impacted areas along the eastern Great Lakes, from Ohio to New York.  Coastal areas of the Carolinas also missed recent rains.  Abnormal dryness (D0) expanded in eastern North Carolina and into southern Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Most of the drought-affected areas of the region missed the beneficial precipitation this week.  Precipitation fell just west and south of the northern Great Lakes drought areas.  Continued long-term deficits resulted in unchanged drought classifications in this region.  Rains in the East fell to the south and northeast of the drought areas along the eastern Great Lakes, leaving the drought-impacted areas from Ohio to New York unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>For the most part, the northern Plains experienced areas of normal to above normal precipitation while most of the central and southern Plains received below normal precipitation this week.  Areas of central and western Louisiana and eastern Texas saw increases in the extent of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderated drought (D1), as this area is beginning to see deficits at the 60-day and beyond timescales.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Storms dropped precipitation across much of the Northwest Coast, from northern California to western Washington, as well as along the US – Canadian border from eastern Washington all the way across Montana. Smaller areas of Wyoming, Utah, Colorado and New Mexico saw above normal precipitation.  Across the areas, this precipitation fell largely as rain and did had little to no impact on the below average snowpack present throughout most of the region.  The storm was followed by strong winds, increasing surface evaporation.  Areas of dryness and drought were left unchanged this week, awaiting the spring runoff. The exception was north-eastern Montana where abnormal dryness (D0) was relieved.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
