<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030807</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may have an impact on dryness or drought areas during the next 2 weeks: 1) mostly dry weather will persist over the Plains states through Sunday, August 10, but temperatures in the southern Plains should gradually return to more normal levels during the next 5 days; 2) after August 10, temperatures are forecast to be below normal from Oklahoma south through Texas, with near to above-normal rainfall; 3) most of the western drought area should see near to below normal temperatures in the next 2 weeks, but rainfall should be below normal in the Southwest; 4) above-normal rainfall is forecast over the dry areas in Montana, northern and central Idaho, Wyoming, and the western Dakotas during August 12-16.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Showers eliminated D0 dryness over eastern sections of the Big Island in Hawaii, but D2 drought continued in leeward areas. A small area of D0 remained in southeastern Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region and Middle Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Heavy rains of 2 to 3 inches eliminated D0 dryness across eastern Wisconsin and southwestern Michigan, but a small area of D0 persisted in southeastern Michigan. Rains reduced dryness in southern Illinois but failed to end long-term dryness in parts of northern Minnesota. D0 dryness spread across southern Minnesota into southwestern Wisconsin, as this area has seen under 50 percent of normal rainfall in the past 30 days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Another week of moderate to heavy rain (1 to 3 inches), with 1-2 inches in eastern Maine reducing the extent of long-term dryness in that state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Lower Missouri Valley">
   <p>Heavy rains of 2 to 4 inches improved drought by one category in east-central Oklahoma, while 1-2 inches in parts of southern and central Kansas led to local relief. Severe drought, D2, remained across much of Kansas into northwestern Missouri, as well as western and southern Nebraska. Dodge City, Kansas, recorded the driest July since 1978, with a total of 0.48 inches. Kansas City International Airport's July total of 0.12 inches was the lowest ever for July. Twelve-month rainfall was 14.68 inches below normal. D0 to D1 dryness expanded eastward across northern Missouri. Lack of rain resulted in D2 drought growing southward in western South Dakota. Hot, dry weather in northern and eastern Texas caused expansion of D1 and D0 southward and eastward. Severe drought, D2, developed across northern Texas from the Panhandle to the Red River border with Oklahoma. Virtually no rain has fallen over much of northern Texas since the start of July, and triple digit heat has rapidly dried soils. Wichita Falls, Texas, went without a drop of rain during July, resulting in the driest July on record. No measurable rain has fallen in Lubbock since June 26.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Monsoon rains and lower temperatures brought scattered relief across the West, especially in Arizona. Amounts of 0.5 to 1.0 inch, with locally higher totals, caused some retreat of D2 and D3 drought in southern and eastern Arizona, but totals were generally not enough to significantly change the drought situation elsewhere. Lack of rain even caused some eastward expansion of D3 in northwestern Colorado and expansion of D0/D1/D2 in eastern Montana. Extreme drought persisted over much of the interior West. Preliminary data indicate the Southwest region experienced both the hottest and driest July in 109 years of record-keeping.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
