<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020502</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the period May 2-6, a storm system tracking through the eastern Great Lakes and Northeast will bring beneficial rains from New Jersey to Maine, where widespread totals greater than one-half inch will be common during the 2nd-3rd. Another concentrated area of showers and thunderstorms early this weekend will occur along a stalled frontal boundary across the Southeast, from Virginia and the Carolinas southward into northern Georgia and Alabama. A frontal system crossing the Pacific Northwest is forecast to bring rain and mountain snow to portions of Washington and Oregon eastward into areas of Montana and northern Idaho during the 5th-6th. Elsewhere across other drought affected areas, precipitation amounts are expected to be scattered and light during the period. The NWS 6-10 day outlook for May 7-11 calls for near normal rainfall along the Eastern Seaboard, while above average precipitation is expected from the Pacific Northwest eastward along the US/Canadian border. Below normal rainfall is forecast from Colorado southeastward through Texas and eastward along the Gulf Coast including Florida. Above normal temperatures will encompass much of the eastern half of the United States during the upcoming 6-10 day period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Abundant rains fell across Puerto Rico during the period. In Hawaii, portions of eastern and southeastern Big Island received 2 to 5 or more inches of rain, and isolated pockets on Oahu and Maui received 1 to 2 or more inches. An inch or less rainfall was reported over Kauai and Molokai. No changes were made to the existing D0 designation across western Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Good 1 to 3 inch rains occurred in eastern West Virginia to Washington DC, across southern Delaware and southern New Jersey, and centered around northeast Pennsylvania, with some improvement in soil moisture conditions. Daily rainfall records were broken April 28 with 1.68 inches falling at Dulles IAP and 1.43 inches falling at Baltimore's BWI airport. However, 6-month and 12-month precipitation were still well below average and New York City reservoirs were rising only at the rate of climatology and were still in the drought warning category. Consequently, the D3 area was pinched in two over northern Virginia. Some contraction was made to the drought boundaries from West Virginia to New York City, but no dramatic improvements were made.</p>
   <p>It was a very dry period along the Gulf Coast to the Tennessee border and also in the Carolinas, but locally 1 to 2 inch frontal rains occurred late in the period in parts of west central Georgia, with severe weather in the area. These heavier rains were barely normal for the week. The D0 boundary was expanded across Alabama into southeastern Mississippi and westward across Florida. The D1, D2, and D3 boundaries grew in Georgia, and the D3 waistline was widened in central North Carolina. Low 6-month precipitation totals and worsening KBDI indices prompted an expansion of D0 across much of south Florida.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>One to three inch rains fell in some areas from west central Iowa into eastern Nebraska during the period, improving soil moisture, but the week was dry in western and parts of north central Nebraska. The Iowa-Nebraska D0 and D1 areas were adjusted to reflect these changes. D2 was expanded slightly in the drier western Nebraska. Two inch rains bordering the D0 area from southeast Kansas to northwest Texas resulted in a D0 contraction in those areas. Rains reduced D0 in north central Minnesota. The period continued hot and dry in southern Texas. Brownsville set a new record consecutive number of days with high temperature of 90F or above ... 10 consecutive days from April 21-30.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Conditions deteriorated over the Southwest as dry weather continued over much of the area. Drought emergencies were declared during the period by the governors of Arizona, New Mexico and Utah, joining those declared earlier by the governor of Colorado and the Navajo Nation. Mountain snowpack continued decreasing well ahead of the climatological norm from a Wyoming to Utah line southward, with the Brianhead snow course in southern Utah reaching zero before May 1 for the first time ever. Worsening soil moisture conditions, dropping reservoir levels, and increasing threat of fire danger characterized the Southwest, while daily and 7-day streamflow ranked at record or near record low levels from Montana to New Mexico and Arizona. As a result ... the D3 area in the Southwest was expanded further north in Colorado, across northern Arizona, and into south central New Mexico. Moderate drought (D2) in Arizona and New Mexico pushed to the Mexican border. The D2 line in Utah was adjusted northward slightly. The A,F impacts region in the Southwest shrank to reflect expanding impacts in all three categories.</p>
   <p>Very dry conditions in north central Montana were reflected in several indicators, including the Standardized Precipitation Index, Palmer Drought Index, and long-term precipitation. Local impacts included reports of severe blowing dust with visibility in some areas one tenth of a mile or less for several hours during March and April, and dust drifting to several feet deep along fence lines in Liberty County. A wedge of D4 was consequently introduced in this Montana hi-line dust bowl from roughly Cut Bank to Havre to east of Great Falls.</p>
   <p>Precipitation in the Northwest ranged from near average in Washington to somewhat drier than average over Idaho and Oregon. D0 was expanded and a spot of D1 introduced in north central Oregon due to increasing stress on crops combined with lingering impacts from the 2001 drought year. Slight adjustments were made to the hydro impacts line in western and southeastern Idaho.</p>
   <p>Abundant rains in San Diego County resulted in a slight shift eastward in the D2 line in southern California. Significant precipitation, for the April time period, occurred over parts of Alaska this week. Increasing snowpack and snow water equivalent improving to over 100 percent of normal in the Koyukuk and Chena basins contracted the northern edge of the D0 in Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
