<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070712</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather that could have an impact on dry areas in the next 2 weeks: 1)a cold front will bring cool Canadian air to the Midwest and East and needed rain to eastern and southern drought areas during the first days of the period, with 1-inch or greater amounts of rain expected over much of the Eastern Seaboard and South during July 11-16; 2) the interior West will continue hot the first 5 days, but below-normal temperatures are indicated in the Pacific states on the 6-10 and 8-14 day forecasts; 3) the onset of the summer thunderstorm season will lead to above-normal rainfall from days 6 to 14, July 17-25, over much of the West; 4) above-normal temperatures will return to the Midwest and East for days 6-14, and below-normal rainfall is forecast for the Ohio Valley and the mid-Atlantic states.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Some beneficial rains reduced the D0 area in the southwest and parts of the southeast interior basin, but D0 dryness persisted elsewhere. Numerous wildfires have broken out across the interior basin.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Many locations on the Big Island recorded over 0.5 inches of rain this period, but rainfall amounts were light over the other islands. There was no change to the overall drought picture this week. Honolulu has measured just 2.68 inches of rain this year, 29 percent of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>The heaviest rains missed the area of D0 dryness in the southeast, resulting in no change in the island's depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Moderate to heavy showers dropped 0.5 to 2.0 inches of rain on much of Wisconsin, with lower amounts across the rest of the region. Below-normal totals led to D1 drought expansion from southwestern Michigan into northern Indiana and northern Ohio. Topsoil moisture ratings dropped considerably in Michigan, where topsoil ratings rose from 71 percent short to 83 percent short. D2 drought also developed near the shores of Lake Superior in Minnesota, Wisconsin, and Michigan. D1 drought also expanded into southwestern Minnesota and northwestern Iowa.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Heavy showers led to improved moisture conditions across New England, but significant short-term rainfall deficits continued in Maine, where D0 dryness has developed. Short-term deficits led to D1 development from western Pennsylvania into central parts of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>The remnants of the upper air disturbance that had brought flooding rains to the southern Plains edged eastward and contributed to heavy rains from Texas into Mississippi. Weekly rainfall totals to July 10 ranged from 2 to 5 inches from west-central Alabama into northern and central Mississippi and southern Arkansas and northern Louisiana. Even the core of the D4 exceptional drought area in northern Alabama picked up 0.5 to 2.0 inches this week, although lesser amounts fell in northeast Alabama into southeast Tennessee. The rains had a major impact on the drought in Mississippi, D1 to D3 drought levels improving to D0 to D1, with parts of northwestern Mississippi seeing a removal of D0 dryness as streamflows continued high and soil moisture ratings improved markedly. USDA-reported topsoil moisture ratings improved from 85 percent short to very short statewide in Mississippi last week to 34 percent this week, close to the 10-year mean. To the east, the improvement was spotty in Alabama, where topsoil ratings went from 96 percent to 87 percent short, and 87 percent of the corn crop rated poor to very poor. D4 drought continued across much of northern Alabama and expanded into southeastern Tennessee. Despite picking up 2.65 inches of rain this month, Tuscaloosa, Alabama, has measured just 12.20 inches of rain so far this year, 20.56 inches below normal. Heavy rains continued to shrink the drought area in southern Florida, but D2 drought persisted near and north of Lake Okeechobee, where water levels remained near historical lows due to minimal stream inflows. To the north, lack of rain led to expansion of D1 drought across northern North Carolina into southeastern Virginia. Continued below-normal rainfall and soaring temperatures early this week led to D1 development across the Tidewater area of Virginia, southern Maryland, and into the Delmarva Peninsula. The drought also expanded into northern Virginia. The corn crop in parts of eastern Virginia began showing severe stress as soil moisture conditions deteriorated tremendously in the past week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and High Plains">
   <p>Heat was the big story this period, as a severe heat wave brought triple-digit temperatures from the arid Southwest northward to the Canadian border. The heat peaked in the Southwest around July 5, when the maximum temperature at Las Vegas, Nevada, reached 116 degrees F and Reno tied its all-time maximum with 108 degrees F. Temperatures averaged over 8 degrees F above normal over large portions of the interior West for the 7-day period. The sizzling high temperatures combined with little rainfall led to decreased soil moisture and some expansion of dryness and drought across the West, including D0 to D1 in western Montana west of the Divide, D1 over nearly all of Idaho, and expanded D0 across Washington and Oregon. D2 also expanded across northern Nevada into western Utah. One impact of the dryness was the sudden outbreak of wildfires across the region. By July 11, all 11 western states reported large wildfires, with approximately 46 such fires in the West plus a large fire in southwestern South Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
