<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20081009</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the early part of the next Drought Monitor period, a moderately strong winter-like trough system is forecast to move into the western US, bringing below average temperatures and hard freezes in the Great Basin and Rocky Mountain states.  With this trough in the West, a ridge will be in place in the East with warmer than average temperatures.  Hurricane Norbert in the eastern Pacific could enhance the chance of precipitation in the southwest US.  In the central US, wetter conditions are projected in the next six to ten day period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Dry conditions persisted in northwestern Alaska this week, leading to the retention of D0 in this region.  In northeastern Kauai, Hawaii, pasture conditions in the area are very poor and cattle stocking rates have been reduced by over 50% in some areas.  A new area of D2A was added to reflect these impacts.  Continued lack of rainfall on the Big Island has led to deteriorating conditions there, and D3 was expanded along the western slopes.  Moisture from the extreme precipitation events in September continues to stave off any drought development in Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes and Upper Midwest">
   <p>Modest improvements were made this week in the Upper Peninsula of Michigan where lake-effect rains fell.  D0 was removed in areas north of Houghton, on the lee side of Lake Superior, and eastward to Marquette and Manistique.  In northern Ohio, many areas received one to two inches of rain this week, particularly around the Cleveland area, resulting in the removal of D0 north of US-30, with the exception of Ottawa County on Lake Erie.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Plains">
   <p>A beneficial amount of precipitation fell in eastern South Dakota and southwestern Minnesota, warranting an improvement from D1 to D0.  As much as four inches fell in parts of this region over October 5-7, reducing the amount of precipitation deficit.  Unfortunately for North Dakota, most of the heavier rain fell in the eastern portion of the state, so drought conditions remained status quo this week.  In Oklahoma, adjustments were made following rainfall on October 6, taking into account soil moisture status.  The three areas of D0 were fine tuned to reflect recent moisture.  The gradient from D2 to D0 in the Panhandle was tightened.</p>
   <p>Many recent drought impacts have been reported in west central Texas, and this led to degradation in Mason and McCulloch Counties, which now stand in D2.  In Eden, September rainfall amounted to only .10 inches, compared to a normal of 3.34 inches.  Since June 1, this location has recorded just 5.53 inches, 4.02 inches below normal for that period.  Precipitation deficits in the San Antonio area and westward, as well as low streamflow and vegetation greenness indices, contributed to an extension of D2 in Uvalde, Medina and most of Bexar Counties.  Rainfall in other areas prevented further worsening of conditions this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and East Coast">
   <p>Moderate amounts of precipitation fell in some drought stricken areas, but not enough to substantially improve drought.  Extreme to exceptional drought conditions continue in Georgia, eastern Tennessee and the Carolinas.  The result was no change anywhere in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The first strong cold front of the season passed through the western U.S. this week, bringing welcome rain and snow at some higher elevations.  Overall, precipitation in the area did not bring significant relief, but instead prevented deterioration of drought conditions.  Areas that experienced heavy rainfall include the coastal Washington, Oregon and northern California regions west of the Cascades.  A one-category improvement in drought conditions was made in coastal Oregon to the California border.  In the northern Sierra Nevada of California, significant precipitation of two to four inches fell, which helped to restore soil moisture and alleviate the precipitation deficit in the previous D3 region.  The removal of D3 in the northern Sierra Nevada is a reflection of short-term improvement.  D2 drought conditions hold strong with residual long-term deep soil moisture shortages across much of northern California, carryover impacts from the record dry spring and climatologically dry summer, two years of below normal precipitation, and very low reservoir storage.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere in the West, D1 was improved to D0 in southern Nevada in northeastern Clark County and southern Lincoln County due to recent beneficial rains.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Laura Edwards</name>
   <affiliation>Western Regional Climate Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
