<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080605</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (through June 9) a ridge should continue to set up and strengthen across the southern Plains in more of a summer-type pattern. This should bring the best chances of rain to the north of that line, and an active storm pattern should continue across the Pacific Northwest, northern Plains, Great Lakes region and the Northeast. That ridge should result in much warmer temperatures from the Southwest, central Great Plains, Midwest and East as well. Temperatures are expected to be below normal across northern California, parts of the Intermountain West, and the Pacific Northwest and then eastward into the western Great Lakes region as well.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (June 10-14) is calling for a greater likelihood of warmer temperatures across the Southwest, the southern Plains and the entire eastern United States except for Florida, where they are expecting more seasonable readings. Below-normal temperatures are expected in Alaska and the Pacific Northwest and over into the Dakotas. As for precipitation, the best chances for precipitation appear to be in the central Plains, lower Mississippi Valley, western Great Lakes region and southern Florida. Below-normal totals are more likely in Alaska, the coastal regions of Oregon and Washington and also in the Mid-Atlantic region up into southern New England.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Hawaii experienced another dry week across most all of the islands, resulting in no changes this week. Streamflow levels remain low and impacts are becoming notable in the agricultural sector.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, a dry week leads to the status quo this week as well.</p>
   <p>Puerto Rico did experience some scattered rains across most of the northern half of the island but more will be needed to erase the abnormally dry (D0) conditions that persist in the southern locales.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Mid-Atlantic and Southeast">
   <p>Warmer, seasonal temperatures returned to most of the region last week. However, precipitation was a bit spotty, leading to some improvements and some areas that took a turn for the worse. The relatively good news is that rains continued to fall in some of the areas that need it the most. Parts of eastern Tennessee, northern Alabama and northwestern Georgia saw rains on the order of 2 to 4 inches. A one-category improvement is the result along the western and northern areas of drought in Alabama, Tennessee and Georgia. Worth noting this week is that D3 was removed from northern Alabama. Before this week, they hadn't been D3-free statewide since March 2007. Severe drought (D2) still persists in these areas, though. In Georgia, some improvement on the heels of rains last week is evident in the west-central counties along the Alabama border, but for the most part, dryness and drought pushed south and east this week toward the coast. To the south, notable dryness (25-50% of normal) over the past 30-60 days has once again led to some expansion of D0-D1 into north-central Florida. Indicative of persistent drought, stream flow levels remain quite low for many parts of this region. Conditions remain unchanged this week in the Carolinas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>An active storm track across parts of the Pacific Northwest and northern Great Plains brought rain and cooler temperature readings last week. On the heels of last week's stormy weather, parts of the Dakotas and western Minnesota shared the rains. This has brought some improvement to some parts, but long-term deficits and dry soils have tempered the effects of these rains, and more precipitation is needed. This has led to the trimming of the D0 in northern South Dakota and removal of D0 in extreme southeastern North Dakota. The rains were not as plentiful in the western and northern reaches of North Dakota along the international border, leading to a slight expansion of D2 and D3 to the east. A slight reduction of D1 and D2 occurred in extreme eastern Montana along the border with North Dakota.</p>
   <p>In the southern Plains, D0 has expanded south and east into southwestern Oklahoma along the Red River border region with Texas. Texas saw a dry week over most of the drought areas, leading to a push north of both D1 and D2 in southern Texas as well as a complete push of D2 south to much of the Gulf Coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The dryness continued this past week for the entire Southwest and most of California. This was somewhat tempered by cooler-than-normal temperatures that occurred across the Great Basin, Arizona, and California as well. New Mexico saw an expansion of D2 to the west across the extreme southern counties of the state. Precipitation has been pretty dismal for most time frames out to the Water Year (October 1), with only 25-50% of normal being reported in that period.</p>
   <p>In California, many locations recorded a record or near-record dry spring. In fact, on June 4, Governor Schwarzenegger declared a statewide drought. On the heels of last winter's low totals, the water strain has been increased after a disappointing finish to this winter. Final snow water content levels statewide were only around 67% of average and thus streamflow runoff forecasts are only calling for a little more than 50% of normal. As a result of the past 90 days, D0 and D1 have pushed north up the valley and along the coast north of Santa Barbara up to Eureka.</p>
   <p>To the north, this same dryness has started to have an effect on parts of eastern Washington and southern Idaho as well. D0 has now advanced into eastern Washington. According to the USDA-NRCS, the February-May precipitation in the Big Lost basin was the second lowest since 1982, while the Little Wood basin experienced their third lowest total. This came after both basins recorded 180% of normal precipitation in January. This has led to the expansion of D0-D1 in southern Idaho this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
