<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010607</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Significant weather features likely to have an impact on drought/dryness in the following 2 weeks include: 1) the rains from Tropical Storm Allison, which delivered significant totals to the drought area in Louisiana on June 5-6, are forecast to total 5 to 8 inches or more during June 6-11; 2) the moisture from Allison will spread across the Gulf states, bringing 2-3 inches to the region on June 6-11; 3) hot, dry weather will cover much of the Great Basin during June 7-10.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Showers fell across the Hawaiian Islands, but drought persisted, especially in leeward areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeastern States">
   <p>Widespread rain further relieved dryness, with 2 inches or more ending (D0) dryness in New Jersey and most of New England. Lingering D0 dryness remained in Maine. D1 drought has been removed from Maine, although near-drought conditions remain in some areas. The rains diminished D1 drought in Pennsylvania and New York, leaving a small area in north-central Pennsylvania and adjacent New York. The dryness mainly affects groundwater levels.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Ohio and Tennessee River Valleys and the South">
   <p>Another week of ample rains spelled additional relief for much of the region. The moisture relieved dryness across the eastern half of North Carolina and Virginia, although extreme drought remained over western North Carolina and adjacent South Carolina. Widespread rains exceeding 2 inches in much of the Ohio and Tennessee Valleys continued to reduce drought, with D1 drought mainly positioned over central and western Kentucky and southeastern Missouri, and lingering D2 drought from extreme western Kentucky to extreme southeastern Missouri. Heavy showers removed dryness over most of Mississippi and Alabama and removed D1 drought across far western Georgia. Seasonal rains continued to improve moisture conditions across Florida, but it will take longer to see significant impacts on water supplies. Wells in interior south Florida remain near record low levels. Groundwater levels are near normal along the southeast coast, and drought has been removed from the coastal strip. Rains from Tropical Storm Allison mostly occurred after the valid time of the map, so there was little change in the drought shown for Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="West">
   <p>Warm and dry conditions gave way to abnormally cool weather, with record snows in Montana on June 3-4. The moisture improved short-term dryness in Montana and northern Idaho, but additional precipitation is needed to end the drought, so D2 to D3 drought remained over central and western Montana and Idaho. Hot, dry weather caused D0 dryness to spread southward to central California and D1 drought to edge southward over the northern part of the state. D0 dryness expanded southward to include central Nevada, while D1 drought covered the northern part of the state. D2 (severe) drought expanded southward along the Nevada-California border to the Reno area. There was little change in the moderate to severe drought over the Pacific Northwest, although the dryness is now affecting all drought categorieswater, fire danger, and agriculturefrom south-central Washington southward.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
