<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050324</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a promising scenario is shaping up over the Pacific NW, where much-needed precipitation could exceed 4 to 6 inches of liquid equivalent over the next 5 days (3/23-3/28) along the coastal ranges from northern California to northern Washington. Central and northern Idaho can expect to see up to 2 inches of precipitation; 2) in the Southeast, heavy rains (3 inches or more) are predicted across eastern Alabama, northern Florida, most of Georgia and South Carolina and southern coastal North Carolina for the 5-day period; 3) the unsettled weather patterns will also bring cooler temperatures across all of the West, and normal readings are expected in the Southeast over the same time frame; 4) the 6-10 day period (3/29-4/2) continues to show better odds of above-normal precipitation in the Pacific NW and Great Basin regions. Below-normal amounts are expected across the entire mid-section of the country; 5) as for temperatures, below-normal temperatures are forecast for western Oregon and western Washington while the rest of the country should expect above-normal temperatures, except for the Southeast, where normal temperatures are called for.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>On the heels of expanded moderate drought (D1) conditions last week, another dry week in southern Puerto Rico keeps conditions unchanged across the island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>The major snowstorm that tracked across the High Plains and into the Upper Midwest tracked south of the D0 areas in Minnesota and South Dakota for the most part, leaving these abnormally dry (D0) areas mostly intact. Some beneficial rains also fell across parts of northern Kansas and southern Nebraska last week, but they are not enough to offset the short-term or long-term dryness/drought that has a grip on this region. Most of the Plains and Midwest were dry during the last seven days, leading to no changes in this weeks depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and West">
   <p>Last week finally brought some beneficial moisture to the coastal ranges of western Oregon and Washington (1 to 3 inches), but it isnt nearly enough to reverse the fortunes in the region given the persistent warmth and dryness this winter. Following the trend of late, most of the Pacific NW was again warm and dry. As a result, the region remains unchanged this week as the odds grow long for a last-minute change of heart by Mother Nature. Snow water equivalent readings for most basins in Washington and Oregon along the Cascades are still at or near record lows, and streamflows echo the same story as the peak snowpack date rapidly approaches. In anticipation of the coming impacts, USDA suspended spring grass seeding and tree and shrub planting in eastern Washington for the first time in the Conservation Reserve Programs 20-year history.</p>
   <p>The situation is not any better in Idaho and Montana, where some basins would need three to five times their normal amount of precipitation in the next month just to get some basins merely back to average. Although not impossible, this isnt likely to happen.</p>
   <p>Re-assessment of the situation in southwestern Arizona shows most of the western half of the state in a surplus mode out to 36 months in many cases, leading to a slight pushing of the D0 eastward in southern Arizona toward Tucson. Precipitation amounts in most of the Southwest and southern California are running 200-300% of normal for the both the year-to-date and water year (since October 1, 2004) time frames.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>Most of the rain last week found a way to miss the pockets of abnormally dry (D0) areas found in the region. Rains avoided the D0 areas in both Alabama and Florida but found their mark in extreme southeastern Mississippi, leading to the removal of the recently introduced D0 conditions there for now. Good rains (1 to 2 inches or more) in parts of extreme southeastern Georgia and South Carolina (in and around Savannah, GA, and Charleston, SC) and across northeastern coastal North Carolina have led to a recession of D0 in these areas. Overall, though, a very dry start to 2005 (50-70% of normal readings are common) across virtually all of the Southeast (except for southern Florida) bears watching as crop and human demands rise along with the temperatures. Recent rains have not been enough to keep pace with the year-to-date deficits that are accumulating across extreme northeast Texas, northern Louisiana and southwestern Arkansas, where D0 conditions continue to slowly expand.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
