<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20131226</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Two low-pressure systems transited the contiguous 48 states during the past week. The first brought light rain and snow to the Mid-Atlantic and northeast.  The second system moved from the Pacific Northwest, across the Great Plains to the Ohio Valley, where heavy precipitation fell.  As a result of those two storm systems, heavy precipitation fell across the Pacific Northwest (1.0 – 4.7 inches) and along the Ohio and Tennessee Valleys to the east coast (0.5 – 7.7 inches).  Continued dry conditions were observed east of the Cascades to the central Great Plains, with only small amounts of frozen precipitation falling across the northern Rockies.  Light rains (0.5 – 1.5 inches) were observed across southeastern Puerto Rico.  Heavier rains were recorded across Maui (2 stations reported more than 2 inches of precipitation), while the rest of the Island chain remained mostly dry.  Significant precipitation also fell across the Alaskan Panhandle (1.0 -4.7 inches).</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During December 25-30, moderate precipitation is forecast across extreme southeastern Texas and Florida, with totals exceeding 1.5 inches. Moderate amounts of 0.5 to 1.5 inches are anticipated across the Great Lakes and New England.  Outside of those regions, generally dry conditions are likely during the next week, with colder than average conditions east of the Rockies.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (December 30 – Jan 3), the odds favor above-normal precipitation from the northern Great Plains to the southern half of Texas eastward to the Carolinas Coast, and from northern New England and the Pennsylvania Appalachians westward through most of the northern half of the Plains and the northeastern Rockies. Wet weather is also favored throughout Alaska. In contrast, enhanced chances for dryness exist in the central Plains, a swath across the upper southern High Plains and Rockies, most of the Intermountain West, and the West Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation fell across the Alaskan Panhandle, leading to the removal of D0.  Elsewhere, dry conditions persisted.  Maui was the only island to report significant rains (2.0 – 3.8 inches at the 2 reporting stations for which data was available.  The short-term rains had little impact on the overall drought conditions, so no changes were made elsewhere.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Lower Mississippi Valley and Southern Plains">
   <p>The axis of heaviest rains extended into Arkansas, so some D0 was removed from central Arkansas and along the Mississippi River.  The heaviest of rains (0.5 – 2.5 inches) extended southward to eastern Texas, leading to a slight trimming of the D0 across northeastern Texas and southeastern Oklahoma.  Many of the remaining sections of Texas saw drought intensify slightly due to continued dry conditions.  SPI values remain well below 0 across the Texas Panhandle and southern Texas.  Recent deficits out to the 90 day time period (10 - 25 percent of normal) are especially strong across northeastern New Mexico and Texas, so some adjustments to the drought depiction were made in those regions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Mid-Atlantic and Southeast">
   <p>The cold front associated with the second low-pressure system stalled across the southeast during Sunday and Monday, so significant rains fells from Tennessee to the Carolinas and the Florida panhandle.  Abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D1) were trimmed from Alabama while the region of abnormally dry conditions from Alabama to Georgia was significantly reduced in size.  D0 was also removed from central VA due to locally light to moderate (0.5 – 1.5 inches) of rain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Heavy precipitation fell across the Great Lakes region and into the Adirondacks, and the Green and White Mountains in New England.  Unfortunately the heaviest rains missed the driest areas, so minimal improvements were made to western New York and central Pennsylvania where the areas of abnormal dryness (D0) were removed, while the drought conditions across rest of the region remained unchanged.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northern and Central Plains and The Midwest">
   <p>Pockets of abnormal dryness were removed from Indiana, Michigan, Illinois, and Missouri due to recent rainfall.  The streamflows have not responded as much as necessary to remove the D1 (moderate drought) designation for most of this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies Westward to The Pacific Coast">
   <p>Some light to moderate precipitation fell across the northern and central Rockies, although it was frozen so had little impact on the drought conditions and water supply.  Surface Water Supply Index values across much of Idaho are in the lowest 30 percentile with many in the lowest 25%.  Combined with longer-term rainfall deficits (2.0 – 8.0 inches below normal) during the past 180 days and 10-20 percent of normal during the past 90 days, the drought depiction including extreme drought was not modified.  Dry conditions continued east of the cascades in Washington, so D0 was expanded there.  Despite some significant rains during the past 7 days, 30 day totals are near normal across much of Washington and Oregon, so no change was made to the depiction there.  Severe drought was expanded slightly across northern California as SPI values out through 24 months indicated more intensely dry conditions than what was indicated on prior Drought Monitor maps.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Matthew Rosencrans</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
