<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030206</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The 5-day outlook (Feb.5-10) shows a strong ridge building into the West, which should bring much drier weather to most of the West. In fact, very little in the way of precipitation is expected in drought affected regions except in southern Georgia and the coastal regions of the Carolinas. These areas could see and inch or more of precipitation. Very cold temperatures are expected across all but extreme northern Montana for this same time period.</p>
   <p>Looking out further, the 6-10-day forecast (Feb. 11-15) shows the ridge persisting in the Pacific NW, however a cutoff low is expected to develop off the coast of southern California, which could be a promising kick-start for some storms to bring much needed moisture across the southern United States. Precipitation is expected to be above-normal from southern California all the way over to southern Atlantic coast. Unfortunately, the entire northern half of the country is expected to see below-normal precipitation and below-normal temperatures through the middle of February.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>El Nino continues its persistent dry grip on the islands, leading to some changes in the abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) affecting the state. On the big island, Hilo recorded its 7th driest January (1.24", or 13% of normal) since 1950. Moderate drought (D1) has now pushed across most of the northern half of the island of Hawaii. Dry conditions here are beginning to have an affect on crops on the windward side of the island as soil moisture levels continue to fall.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>On the heels of modest rains two weeks ago, last week's generous rains were on the order of 3-6 inches across the northern reaches of the island. This boosted the 8-week precipitation totals and streamflow levels to near-normal or above-normal readings for the period ending January 31. As a result, abnormally dry (D0) conditions have been removed from northern Puerto Rico. Several locations in the south remain abnormally dry (D0) because of longer-term precipitation deficits.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Most of the Northeast experienced a cold and dry week. Late weekend snow in the Northeast and rains in the Southeast continued on into the work week. Florida recorded their driest January on record while Tennessee and Georgia saw their third driest January. Up the coast a bit, the Carolinas saw their 6th driest January since 1895.</p>
   <p>After good fall and early winter rains, it has turned dry again for areas trying to pull out of this stubborn multi-year drought. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions have expanded slightly in southern Georgia and toward the coast in the Carolinas. The agricultural (A) designation has been added to southern Georgia (D0 A,W) where irrigation has been needed to boost winter grain crops along. In addition, streamflow levels have continued to remain low from the Florida panhandle up into Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>Warm weather (5-15 degrees above normal) was felt across the Plains for much of last week before Arctic air pushed in over the weekend, bringing needed snow through Nebraska and over into the Ohio Valley. While the storms were a needed break from a dry winter pattern, the drought situation remains unchanged in the central United States. As was the case two weeks ago, liquid totals were generally less than half an inch and colder weather dominated the Great Lakes. In general, January was quite dry for many states in the region as all but Iowa and Indiana recorded top ten dryness rankings, with Minnesota experiencing their driest January on record.</p>
   <p>Heavy snows over the last two weeks have brought the northern Upper Peninsula up to more seasonal values, leading to a removal of moderate drought (D1). Abnormally dry (D0) conditions remain across all of the U.P., however.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Even though parts of the Northwest experienced their second consecutive wet week (bringing increases to upper elevation snowpacks), the real story has been the warmth of this winter. This warmth has led to very high snowpack temperatures and low snow water content in many basins in the Pacific Northwest leading to some early melting. This has led to an expansion of moderate drought conditions D1 (W) into central Oregon and D0 (W) into central Washington as well. Early runoff does not bode well for sustaining water storage levels into summer and in effect the relatively high streamflow readings may serve as a precursor for hydrological drought later this summer. Recent wetness in western Washington has led to the removal of the agricultural (A) impact designation.</p>
   <p>Heavy precipitation in parts of northern Utah, Idaho, western Wyoming and southwestern Montana has led to only slight changes in the drought situation, with most of the improvement being seen in central Idaho and extreme northwestern Wyoming where extreme drought (D3) has receded back into extreme northwestern Wyoming. Unfortunately, these recent storms have not yet brought enough relief to break the region out of drought.</p>
   <p>Following the national trend (2nd driest January in the U.S. since 1895), Nevada and Utah recorded their warmest January on record, while Oregon, California, and Arizona experienced their second warmest January. Farther north, it was the third warmest January on record for Idaho and Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
