<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061221</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>A strong winter storm spinning across the Great Plains December 20-21 will move into the Great Lakes December 22 with a cold front trailing across the Southeast, bringing much-needed moisture to the drought areas of the central and eastern U.S.  Another system is expected to form in the Gulf of Mexico over the weekend and bring precipitation to the abnormally dry/drought areas of the Southeast and central Appalachians December 24-25.</p>
   <p>A series of Pacific storms is forecast to continue their march into the Pacific Northwest and British Columbia coast during the next 2 weeks, leaving most of Alaska and southern California basically dry.  Pieces of these storms will break off and weaken, possibly surviving to reach the northern and central Rockies.  Generally, the predicted pattern for December 25-January 2 is wet in the Pacific Northwest and along the East Coast, dry in Alaska and from the Southwest and southern Plains to the Great Lakes.  Temperatures are expected to be below normal for Alaska and the south central states, and above normal for the northern half of the contiguous U.S.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Continued dryness across much of Alaska prompted the introduction of D0 from the interior regions to parts of the south central coast.  Many stations in this area have received less than 50% of normal precipitation for the last 60 days, with below-normal snowfall, and some stations have been dry over the last 6 months.  Fairbanks reported only 0.76 inch of precipitation since October 1, or a third of normal, and only 7.9 inches of snowfall, which is a fourth of normal, or 26.6 inches below normal.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, D0 was introduced across the islands of NiIhau and Kauai based on below to much below normal precipitation at many stations for the last 6 months.  Other islands showed deficits, but not as severe.  Early December rains improved pasture conditions on Maui, so the D0 there was removed.</p>
   <p>The rainfall pattern across Puerto Rico was mixed.  Some stations received an inch or two, but many stations received considerably less, especially over the D0 areas, so no change was made to the depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Precipitation fell across central Iowa early in this Drought Monitor period, but conditions remained dry in other parts of the state.  The northwest and southeast D0 areas expanded to reflect low farm ponds and deficits out to 90 days, and a spot of D1 was added to southeastern Iowa.</p>
   <p>A few tenths of an inch of precipitation fell across the Upper Peninsula of Michigan with around an inch in the eastern reaches, but this was not enough to erase longer-term deficits.  D1 and D2 were expanded eastward across the Upper Peninsula to reflect moisture deficits at the 60-day to 12-month timescales and subnormal snowpack.  D0 was added to the northwestern shore of the Lower Peninsula.</p>
   <p>In spite of recent rains across Arkansas and Tennessee, long-term deficits remain.  D0 was expanded across eastern Oklahoma, the southeastern half of Arkansas, and into western Tennessee to reflect moisture deficits at the 30-day to 2-year timescales, and D1 was expanded into southwestern Arkansas.  Half-inch to 2-inch rains in central Tennessee this week limited the expansion of the western Tennessee D0.  An H impact boundary was added to the Arkansas-Tennessee D0 to emphasize the contrast between long-term dryness and recent wetness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Appalachians">
   <p>Several days of scattered showers over southern Florida brought a couple of inches or more of rain to stations along the Atlantic coast, with less than an inch to the west.  This was enough to bring month-to-date amounts near to above normal at some stations, but generally not enough to erase deficits accumulated over the last 60 to 90 days.  The exception was West Palm Beach, which was deluged with 9.85 inches of rain December 12-16, most of it falling on the 14th.  D0 and D1 were pulled back near and north of West Palm Beach.  In northern Florida, D1 was expanded into the panhandle and the northeastern D2 was expanded to the west, and AH impacts were designated.  This area has seen worsening 90-day to 6-month moisture deficits with agricultural impacts being reported.  According to the December 17 USDA Florida weather crop report, topsoil and subsoil moisture was rated mostly very short to adequate in the Panhandle and northern Peninsula areas.  Pasture conditions remained poor and hay production was down with drought conditions negatively impacting yields.</p>
   <p>December has been persistently dry from the Ohio and Lower Mississippi rivers to the East Coast.  Moisture deficits extending back to 90 days were affecting streamflow and groundwater levels across West Virginia and southwestern Pennsylvania, where D0 was added.  Moisture deficits were severe across parts of Georgia, Alabama, Tennessee, and Kentucky for the last 60 days to 6 months, with Tennessee abnormally dry even at the 12-month timescale.  The D0 in Georgia was expanded into central and northeastern Alabama and northward into south central Kentucky to reflect these conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West, Great Basin, and Rockies">
   <p>Precipitation amounts of an inch or more eased long-term moisture deficits in western Wyoming, where D3-D2-D1 boundaries were pulled back.  The nose of D2 in Wyoming-Montana near Yellowstone National Park was shaved back.  In north central Montana, moisture this week improved long-term conditions, resulting in the elimination of D2 and contraction of D0.  D1 in the area was split and contracted.  But the precipitation missed southwest Montana.  Moisture deficits were severe for the last 7 days out to 6 months, especially in Beaverhead County, so D0 and D1 were expanded in southwest Montana and adjoining Idaho.</p>
   <p>High elevation SNOTEL station data indicated that Sierra Nevada snowpack was significantly below normal and water year-to-date precipitation lagged normals.  While the area is not in drought, this abnormal dryness marks a slow start for the snow season.  D0 was expanded into the California Sierra Nevada, and D0 spread into adjacent west central Nevada where significant precipitation deficits were evident at the 7-day to 6-month timescales.  D1 was expanded into the deserts of southern California.  Recent rainfall helped the southern California coastal metropolitan areas, but large precipitation deficits at the 60-day to 12-month timescales remained over the inland areas.</p>
   <p>A strong low pressure system developed over the Southwest at the end of this weeks Drought Monitor period.  The winter storm brought rain and snow to the mountains of western and northern New Mexico and parts of the Texas panhandle on the last day.  However, the precipitation missed southeastern New Mexico and adjoining parts of Texas as the storm moved out of the area.  D0 was expanded across much of the Trans-Pecos and southeastern New Mexico to cover the areas with the greatest moisture deficits at the 60-90 day and 12-month timescales.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Liz Love-Brotak</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
