<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080306</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (through March 10), the period begins with a mean trough pattern working through the Great Lakes.  As this system moves through and out of New England, the general pattern becomes zonal for the United States. Precipitation associated with the trough will allow significant precipitation over New England and south along the East Coast.  Secondary precipitation maxima are forecasted for east Texas and the Florida Panhandle. Temperatures are forecasted to be below normal for all areas from the Rocky Mountains east.  Temperature departures will range from 15 degrees Fahrenheit below average near the Great Lakes and 6 to 9 degrees Fahrenheit below average over much of the Plains and Southeast.  Warm conditions dominate the Pacific Coast during this time, with temperatures 3 to 9 degrees Fahrenheit above average.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6 to 10 day outlook for March 11-15 is setting up to be a transitional period for the United States with zonal flow changing to more meridional flow over the western and central United States.  Below-normal precipitation is expected over much of the southern tier of the country and up the east coast and Alaska.  The Pacific Northwest, northern Plains, and upper Midwest are looking at above-normal precipitation.  Temperatures over the eastern half of the United States look to be below normal with areas west of the Missouri River near normal. Southern California, southern Nevada and Arizona are forecasted to have above-normal temperatures.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>D0 was introduced into several of the Hawaiian Islands this week.  Most of Maui did not see much of the heavy rains that occurred during early February, which included 40 inches in 5 days on the east side of the Big Island.  East Oahu and all of Molokai and Lanai were put into D0 as well because of low rainfall totals.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Dry conditions continued to plague the northern Plains over the last several months.  Several stations in South Dakota have recorded top 10 driest periods from November to February, with two locations having the driest on record.  Madison, South Dakota, has recorded just 0.92 inches of precipitation since November, with the previous low amount of 2.24 inches in 1999.  The Waubay National Wildlife Refuge in South Dakota also has recorded the lowest recorded precipitation from November to February with just 0.73 inches. This breaks the previous record of 1.43 set in 1967.  In North Dakota, D3 conditions were pushed farther to the west and a new area of D1 was introduced in southeast North Dakota and northeast South Dakota.  D1 conditions were also expanded in northwest South Dakota, bringing the D1 all the way east to the Missouri River.  D0 conditions were pushed south in eastern South Dakota.  The winter has been dry but cold for much of the northern Plains, limiting any drought impacts for now.</p>
   <p>Dryness continues across central and west Texas.  After an eight-month period of wet weather in 2007, the end of 2007 and start of 2008 has been very dry over much of the western half of Texas.  D2 was expanded north and west this week and D1 conditions were pushed to the west as well.  D0 was introduced into the Big Bend region as well this week.  D0 was improved slightly in south central Oklahoma as it was on the western fringe of heavy rain and snow this week.  Places east of the D0 area received more than 4 inches of rain, with 4 to 6 inches of snow reported on top of that.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeastern and Mid-Atlantic States">
   <p>Several precipitation events impacted the region, helping to improve some of the drought status.  At the end of the current Drought Monitor period, several inches of rain were reported in the Mid-Atlantic region, which will be analyzed next week for improvements to the drought status there.  For this week, D1 conditions were pushed north in Maryland and eastern Virginia in response to low streamflows associated with the recent dryness.  In Alabama and Tennessee, the western stretches of the D3 and D4 regions were improved as up to 4 inches of rain fell.  In Tennessee, there were also improvements to the western extent of the D0, D1 and D2 categories.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>It was a dry week for most of the West, as the main precipitation was recorded along the Oregon and Washington coasts.  Some improvements have been made, generally in response to the snowpack conditions and snow water equivalent amounts that have recently been surveyed.  In Utah, a categorical improvement to drought intensities was made for the entire state except for the northern drainage basins.  Wyoming had improvements as well, with the far northwest corner improved as well as the south central portions of the state.  D0 and D1 conditions were improved for both regions as continued snowfall has pushed seasonal values above normal.  Improvements in both Idaho and Montana were also made with the improvements in Wyoming.  For the West in general, if the above-normal snowpack continues, the opportunity for further improvements will be available as we reach the later portions of the snow season.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
