<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20071025</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (October 25-29), above-normal temperatures should settle in across the entire West, northern Plains, and extreme northern reaches in the Northeast while unseasonably cooler weather is expected in the southern Plains and lower Mississippi Valley. Not much in the way of precipitation is expected anywhere west of the Missouri River. The best bet for heavy rains and drought relief in the near term is likely to be found along the Atlantic Seaboard and up into the Northeast.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlook (October 30-November 3) is calling for above-normal temperatures in Alaska, across California, the Intermountain West and Great Basin, and southern Rockies. Cooler-than-normal temperatures are expected from Montana eastward into North Dakota, Minnesota, Wisconsin, and the Upper Peninsula. The same is likely across most of Florida. As for precipitation, above-normal areas are likely to mirror the cooler regions in the north and across most of southern Florida as well. Below-normal precipitation is a good bet in the Pacific Northwest, Intermountain West, southern Rockies, southern Plains, middle Mississippi Valley, and up into the Ohio Valley and northern Mid-Atlantic.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>There was very little in the way of rains across the dry/drought-affected areas over the past week, leaving the map unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>A rather spotty pattern emerged last week, bringing relief to some areas in upstate New York while leaving the status quo in New England and the Northeast. There was a slight reduction of D0/D1 in northern New York State east of Lake Ontario. Temperatures remain the big story in the region as most locales were running 10-15 F above normal on the week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Seasonal weather was prevalent across most of the Plains last week. Heavier rains (2-5 inches or more) were found in northern Oklahoma and eastern Kansas, but these rains fell outside of the region's dry areas.  Thus, there are no changes in this week's map.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, Ohio and lower Missouri Valleys">
   <p>Finally, some major relief in the form of a strong system that worked its way across the Southeast, tapping into good Gulf moisture and bringing a much-needed injection of ample rains to the rain-starved region. As opposed to last week when only expansion was noted, this week brings about some major improvements for parts of the region where the rains were heaviest. Along the upper Gulf Coast, rains were heaviest, with 6 to 12 inches falling from extreme southeast Louisiana across coastal Mississippi, Alabama, and the Florida Panhandle. They weren't the only ones seeing heavy rains, though, as the system brought 3 to 6 inches, or more, in places up the Mississippi Valley and into the Midwest and Ohio Valley. In general, a one- to two-category improvement was noted in western Mississippi, eastern Arkansas, western Tennessee, western and northern Kentucky, southeastern Illinois, southern Indiana, and southern Ohio. Two- and even three-category improvement is noted this week in the Florida Panhandle and extreme southern Alabama because of the heavy rains. However, the gradient here is steep between those areas that saw copious amounts of rain versus those who only saw an inch or two at best. The core area of the drought (D3/D4) remains intact across most of Alabama, Tennessee, southeastern Kentucky, northern Georgia, the Carolinas, and Virginia. In addition, the impact lines have changed this week to reflect those areas within the core (AH) and those on the perimeter who saw the heaviest rains this week (H).</p>
   <p>In the Mid-Atlantic, persistent unseasonably warm temperatures (6-12 F above normal) and lack of rains (10-16 inch deficits/50% of norm on the year) has led to an expansion of D3 up out of southern Virginia into northern Virginia, and southern Maryland. In Delaware, the governor has issued a drought watch asking residents there to voluntarily conserve water. This follows a September request to the Secretary of Agriculture for a drought disaster declaration.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Upper Mississippi Valley and western Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Temperatures were unseasonably warm last week, running some 5 to 15 degrees above normal. Precipitation was more of a mixed bag, with some areas seeing good rains and others seeing at least something in the way of the wet stuff. This recent trend of wetness over the past 60 days (150-200%+ of normal) across northern Minnesota, northern Wisconsin, and the Upper Peninsula of Michigan has led to several improvements worth noting this week. On the heels of removal of D2 last week in northern Minnesota, the D2 has been removed in central Minnesota and in northern Wisconsin and Michigan's western Upper Peninsula. In addition, D1 has been removed from northern Minnesota and D0 has receded westward off of the shores of Lake Superior. The D1 has also been removed from all but the western Upper Peninsula. In addition, the AH impact area has now been changed to H in these areas as we head into winter. Longer-term deficits still remain but are on the mend.</p>
   <p>To the south, good rains fell across northwestern and southeastern Missouri, with little to none found in between. Improvements continue in the mid section of the state, with slight reductions in the D0/D1 found there. A slight expansion of D0 is noted in central Missouri as streamflows still lag below average. The Bootheel regions saw the heaviest rains as part of the strong storm system that worked its way across the Southeast, tapping into Gulf Moisture. Totals ranged from 3 to 5 inches, leading to a two-category reduction of drought here and leaving D0 and D1 in the storm's wake.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The big story, of course, is the catastrophic fires burning in southern California this past week. Extreme drought conditions over the past 1 to 2 years have played a large role in setting the stage for what we are seeing there now. To the north, good rains again fell across the coastal ranges from northwest California all the way up to the Olympic Peninsula. This continues the trend of slow recovery, with D0/D1 being pushed south and east. The rains and snows weren't limited to just the coastal areas, though, as precipitation (2-4+ inches) was a welcomed sight on the leeside of the Cascade Range, leading to some improvement of D0, D1, and D2 conditions there. In Idaho and northeast Oregon, the good start to the water year has also led to some removal of the D3 in the central basins of the state, but longer-term water issues still leave virtually all of Idaho in severe drought (D2) at this time and D3 remains in eastern basins within the state. In Montana, rains during the past two months have provided some relief with a reduction of D2 along and east of the northern Rocky Mountains in the west and with a removal of most of the D1 in the eastern part of the state. The AH impact line in the Pacific Northwest has also been removed leaving an H designation behind as winter approaches.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
