<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000106</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Unseasonably mild weather should cover the region during January 5 - 10, especially in the northern and central Plains. Only light precipitation is anticipated in most areas, with substantial totals (over 0.25 inch) restricted to the far northeastern Plains and southern Texas. The ensuing 5 days (January 11 - 15) should again be mild in central and southern parts of the region, but near- or below-normal temperatures are expected to return to the northern Plains. Most sites should again record little or no rainfall, with near- to above-normal amounts restricted to the northern Plains.</p>
   <p>Little or no precipitation and near-normal temperatures are expected during January 5 -10 in the D0 regions west of the Rockies, though some substantial precipitation may brush areas near the California/Oregon border. For the following 5 days (January 11 - 15) above-normal precipitation and subnormal temperatures may abet some relief in most of central, northern, and southwestern California. Farther southeast, however, generally warm and dry conditions should continue across most of Arizona and New Mexico.</p>
   <p>Hawaii should experience gradual improvement over the next few months as seasonal rains continue.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Light to moderate rains fell on central and western Hawaii during the past 7 days while below-normal precipitation fell farther to the east. As a result, D1 (first stage drought) conditions persisted in parts of central and eastern Hawaii. In Hawaii County, areas of north and south Kona, where some agricultural impacts have been noted, would particularly benefit from increased short-term rainfall.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Eastern States">
   <p>Mild weather and little precipitation covered most of the region's dry areas through the first day of the new year, then a strong storm system brought locally heavy precipitation (1 to 5 inches) to parts of east Oklahoma, north Arkansas, south Missouri, and parts of the Ohio Valley as this week got underway. As a result, D1 (first stage) to D2 (severe) drought in these areas generally improved by one category, leaving D2 (severe) drought restricted to northern Indiana. D0 (abnormally dry) to D2 (severe) drought conditions were essentially unchanged or expanded slightly in other parts of the Plains, Midwest, South, and Southeast, where less precipitation was observed. D2 (severe) drought conditions pushed into north Florida, north sections of Georgia and Alabama, and areas near the Arkansas/Louisiana/Mississippi triple point. 90-day precipitation deficits through January 2 exceeded 7 inches in parts of the latter region. In addition, average streamflow indices in the South Atlantic-Gulf, Texas-Gulf, and Tennessee hydrologic regions dropped to levels near or below those observed during last summer's drought. Farther north, persistently sub-normal precipitation for the last several months prompted the re-introduction of D0 (abnormally dry) conditions across much of the northern Plains, primarily due to the increasing possibility of insufficient soil moisture for the start of the 2000 growing season.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>Light to locally moderate precipitation (generally under an inch) fell on parts of the Four Corners states and southern California through early this week, benefitting but not eliminating dryness in the latter region. Central and southern sections of New Mexico and Arizona have received only 5% to 20% of normal precipitation since the start of the water year (October 1), leading to dry rangelands and low stock water supplies. Farther north, below-normal seasonal precipitation has similarly impacted ranges and stock water supplies in the valleys and foothills of central and northern California, and in areas just east of the northern Sierra Nevada and southern Cascades, prompting the introduction of D0 (abnormally dry). Some of these areas are now reporting below-normal precipitation totals for the past 12 months.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
