<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030501</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) the storm system that brought heavy rain to Nebraska and Iowa April 29 will continue to provide heavy rains and some severe weather across the Mid-Mississippi Valley and Ohio Valley April 30 and May 1; 2) another system will provide rain and snow to the Black Hills region of South Dakota and northeastern Wyoming April 30 and May 1; 3) the disturbance south of Louisiana April 30 will move across southern Florida May 1-2 and potentially develop into a system that could bring beneficial rains to northern New England over the weekend (May 3-4); and 4) the unsettled weather pattern is expected to continue in the West next week (May 6-10), with generally seasonal temperatures and scattered snow and rain showers.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>A large part of Alaska experienced record or near-record high temperatures during the past week. Adjustments were made to the abnormally dry (D0) area in the southwest part of the state because of positive 90-day and 365-day precipitation anomalies at King Salmon, Bethel, McGrath, and Talkeetna.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>No changes have been made for the week across the state. Hilo received an approximately normal weekly rainfall total of 4.5 inches, yet precipitation deficits approach 20.0 inches for the recent 90-day period there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Long-term hydrological concerns continue across northern New England, and no changes were made to the D0 and D1 areas in Vermont, New Hampshire, and Maine.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes">
   <p>Wildfires making the news in the northern parts of Lower Michigan and in northern Ohio near Cleveland highlighted another relatively dry week across the Great Lakes region. As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) increased in western New York, western Pennsylvania, and southern Ohio. Moderate drought (D1) spread into both northern Ohio and northern Lower Michigan, while severe drought (D2) expanded across northern Indiana, southern Wisconsin, eastern Iowa, and northeastern Minnesota. Fifty-four streamflow monitoring sites from central Michigan to central Illinois set daily record lows April 29th.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Heavier rains in excess of 1.0 inch fell during the week across portions of central Nebraska, eastern Kansas, and much of Missouri, improving extreme drought (D3) conditions in central Nebraska to D2. Minor improvements were also made in Missouri, Kansas, and South Dakota. However, the week was relatively dry across large parts of the southern Plains. This recent trend toward dryness since the beginning of the year has created a large area of abnormally dry (D0) conditions across central and eastern Texas, northwest Louisiana, and southern Arkansas. Moderate drought (D1) conditions are also increasing in western Arkansas and eastern Oklahoma. Large percentages of pastures remain rated "very poor" and "poor" across North Dakota, South Dakota, Nebraska, and Kansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The northern Rocky Mountain states had a relatively wet week, and as a result some improvements were made in the drought categories in central Montana and southeastern Wyoming. Long-term hydrological drought concerns are still severe (D2) and extreme (D3) in these states, with Montana officials particularly concerned about the Red Rock Lakes area and the Clark Canyon Reservoir in Beaverhead County in the southwest part of the state. The recent precipitation has reduced concerns about some agricultural issues but, as with their neighbors to the east, pasture conditions remain poor in large parts of Montana, Wyoming, and Colorado.</p>
   <p>The week also continued a two-month trend of relative wetness across Oregon and Nevada. Drought conditions improved one drought category in eastern Oregon and adjacent parts of Nevada and Idaho. Consistent precipitation in recent weeks also improved drought conditions to D2 in northeastern Nevada.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, the past week was relatively dry across Utah, southwest Colorado, Arizona, and New Mexico. As a result, severe drought (D2) expanded southward in north-central New Mexico, and concerns about agricultural issues, including pasture conditions, are increasing in the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
