<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000914</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect some of dry or drought areas across the nation include: 1) remnants of Hurricane Lane in the eastern Pacific may bring only light precipitation across the northwestern United States during the next couple of days; 2) Hurricane Florence is expected to remain off the Southeast Coast and not provide any precipitation to the region; 3) dry and warm conditions are expected for the next 10 days over much of the West; and 4) welcome precipitation is continuing in parts of Texas, Louisiana, Arkansas, and Mississippi September 12-13 and, for some areas, is the first rain in several months.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>The past week was generally dry in the drought regions in Hawaii and Puerto Rico. Long-term drought continues in parts of Hawaii. Extreme drought (D3) concerns involving agriculture and wildfire potential exist for a small part of the Island of Hawaii. Abnormally dry (D0) and first stage drought (D1) conditions continue along the northern coast of Puerto Rico as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Another hot, dry week took place across the drought areas in the Plains, although the extent of the extreme heat was somewhat reduced from the previous week. Temperature departures for the week were greater than +5F from North Dakota to Texas, with extreme high temperatures during the week above 110F in central Texas.</p>
   <p>The heat and dryness contributed to the increasing drought severity across the Plains. Severe drought (D2) conditions pushed north across most of Texas and into southern Oklahoma. Dallas continued to add to their record streak of consecutive days without measurable precipitation, reaching 73 days on September 11th. First stage drought (D1) conditions expanded into northern Oklahoma, most of southern and central Kansas, and southwest Missouri. In northern Kansas, deteriorating conditions led to the expansion of D2 and D3 drought levels southward from Nebraska. The abnormally dry (D0) conditions expanded across western and southern South Dakota.</p>
   <p>In the northern Great Lakes, rains removed the remaining abnormally dry areas (D0) in northern Lower Michigan. But continuing record dryness for the summer in parts of the Upper Peninsula of Michigan has maintained the D1 and D0 areas in the eastern third of the peninsula, and the abnormally dry (D0) category now exists for the northwestern portion of the peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Generous rains fell across the Gulf Coast region during the week, bringing drought relief to these areas. Exceptional drought (D4) was downgraded to D3 across southern Louisiana, Mississippi, Alabama, the Florida Panhandle, and western Georgia. Meanwhile, conditions deteriorated to severe drought (D2) levels in eastern Texas, northern Louisiana, Arkansas, and western Tennessee. The severe drought (D2) category also shifted southward in Florida to include the Tampa Bay metropolitan areas.</p>
   <p>Drought concerns in some parts of the South are shifting from agricultural and wildfire impacts to hydrological impacts, especially as the fall season approaches. An area including western South Carolina, most of Georgia, and northern Florida has had near-normal to above-normal precipitation since July 1, but extreme, severe, and first stage hydrological drought remain for this area. Approximate long-term precipitation deficits since September 1999 (a 12-month period) include: Columbia, SC (-16 inches); Atlanta, GA (-8 inches); Tampa, FL (-12 inches); Tallahassee, FL (-30 inches); Memphis, TN (-17 inches); Mobile, AL (-19 inches); and New Orleans, LA (-34 inches).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A generally dry, but cool, week occurred across most of the western United States. Beneficial moisture and the cool temperatures relieved the areas of D0 across eastern Oregon and south-central Washington.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
