<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020117</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) widespread rain across the South in the next 5 days, mainly this Saturday and Sunday, measuring 1 to 2 inches over the southern Appalachians and southern Piedmont; 2) a series of storm systems bringing rain and snow to the Northwest starting this weekend and continuing for the next 2 weeks; and 3) little precipitation for the dry areas of the Southwest and the southern and central Plains states.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Little rain fell over most of the leeward areas of the Hawaiian Islands or over southern Puerto Rico this week, resulting in no change in the dryness depiction for both areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>An intense coastal storm on January 13 dumped heavy rain and snow from Long Island to Maine, with up to 20 inches of snow falling in northern Maine. Over 2 inches of precipitation fell on Cape Cod. As a result, the area of D3 (extreme) drought diminished in Maine and the area of severe drought (D2) retreated slightly westward in southern New England. D1 drought gave way to D0 dryness on the Cape. In contrast, D1 drought extended toward Vermonts Lake Champlain, where water levels are the lowest for this time of year in the past 30 years. Liquid-equivalent precipitation of .5 to .7 inches in West Virginia resulted in the area of abnormal dryness receding from northwestern parts of the state. In the Southeast, weekly rainfall exceeded 1 inch over southern parts of South Carolina and Georgia, but the moisture had little impact on the drought in both states due to the severity of the long-term precipitation deficits. Heavy rains swept across central and northern Florida on the 14th, with amounts exceeding 2 inches over the northern peninsula. The rains reduced the area of abnormal dryness in the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Mostly dry weather with unseasonably high temperatures prevailed across the central states. Continued below-normal rain and snow led to expansion of D0 dryness from Iowa westward into central Nebraska. There was little change in the drought covering west Texas and extreme south Texas, as well as southern Kansas and central and western Oklahoma.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Little rain or snow fell across the Southwest, and D0 (abnormal dryness) expanded into northern and central Arizona, where most locations have recorded under 50% of normal precipitation since September. In the Northwest, the heaviest precipitation, with over 1-inch liquid-equivalent moisture, fell in western Washington, northwest Oregon, and parts of northern Idaho and adjacent Montana. D2 drought gave way to D1 drought in northern Idaho and D1 improved to D0 dryness in the northern panhandle of Idaho. D2 drought was scaled back in southern Oregon, southern Idaho, and northeastern Nevada based on updated snowpack and streamflow information.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
