<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040422</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas  experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) as mentioned above, heavy rains moved across parts of the Midwest April 20-21, especially eastern South Dakota, Minnesota, and Illinois; 2) heavy rains are expected to continue April 21-24 across the Ohio Valley and across areas of southern Missouri and central Arkansas; 3) a spring snowstorm may help parts of Wyoming and Colorado April 22-23, with beneficial moisture also spreading across the High Plains of eastern Colorado, western Nebraska, and western Kansas; 4) a ridge is expected to build across the entire eastern half of the nation April 27-May 1, bringing above-normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation to the drought and dryness areas of the West, similar to what the region experienced during March.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Long-term abnormally dry (D0) conditions continue to exist in the interior parts of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Abnormal dryness (D0) continues to occur in a swath from Michigan to Texas and, as a result, D0 has been added this week to areas of southern Indiana and Illinois, southeast Missouri, extreme western Kentucky, northern Arkansas, and eastern and central Oklahoma. According to the USGS, streamflows are very low across this region. Abnormal dryness (D0) has also developed across an area of central Illinois, although heavier rains hit this region on April 20.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, beneficial rains clipped parts of the drought area in the Upper Midwest. As a result, conditions in the D0 and D1 areas of northwest Wisconsin and east-central Minnesota improved slightly. These rains did miss the western part of Minnesota and eastern South Dakota, allowing an expansion of severe drought (D2) conditions in these areas. For Minneapolis, the recently completed 9-month July 15-April 15 period was the driest on record for that period.</p>
   <p>Drought conditions did not improve across the Plains during the week. In fact, continued dryness in the Black Hills region of South Dakota forced the designation there to be switched to D1 from D0. Blowing dust closed I-70 in extreme eastern Colorado, and blowing dust was an issue across the central Plains over the weekend. In addition, officials across the Plains are concerned about the 2004 wildfire season.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Another dry week occurred across the Southeast, and conditions continued to deteriorate for most of the region. Moderate drought (D1) conditions have developed for an area of central Georgia to southern Alabama, or basically from Augusta, Georgia, to Mobile, Alabama. Following its record dry March, Mobile has only had 0.35 inches of rain so far during April (11% of normal). Macon, Georgia, has had 1.23 inches of rain since March 1 (18%). Abnormally dry (D0) conditions also spread farther west into east-central Louisiana. In North Carolina, however, heavier rains from the previous week and early into this week allowed D0 to be removed from the north-central and eastern parts of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The ramifications of a warm and dry March continue to be felt in some parts of the West. Two counties (Clark and Butte) have been declared as Drought Emergencies by Idahos Governor Kempthorne. Exceptional drought (D4) has been extended into Clark County this week. Conditions are also deteriorating in central and western Idaho, causing an expansion of the D1 and D2 areas in this part of the state. Extreme drought (D3) has also been expanded to cover more of the Snake River Basin in western Idaho. In Montana, some rains did fall in the northwestern part of the state. However, these rains were not sufficient or widespread enough to keep moderate drought (D1) conditions from spreading into the region. Meanwhile, dryness over the winter has exacerbated drought conditions in the north-central part of Montana. Great Falls had their driest October-March period in 112 years of record, and are currently at their third driest water year ever through April 20. Cut Bank and Havre had their second and third driest October-March periods on record, respectively. As a result of this continuing dryness, the severe drought (D2) and extreme drought (D3) classifications were extended northward in this area. In Wyoming, extreme drought (D3) expanded across northern portions of the state. All states in the West are gearing up for a potentially early and long fire season as a result of the drought and early snowmelt combination.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
