<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080807</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (August 7-11), seasonal conditions should dominate the United States.  Temperatures should be near normal over the Plains and 3 to 6 degrees Fahrenheit below normal over the east.  Above-normal temperatures over the northern Rocky Mountains are also expected.  An active precipitation pattern is setting up, with maxima projected over the southern Plains, New England and the Southeast. The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for August 12-16 has the models in strong agreement of a trough off the Pacific coast and another over the eastern United States.  Temperatures should be below normal for the Alaskan coast and throughout the Plains and Midwest.  Temperatures look to be above normal from Florida to south Texas, along the Gulf Coast.  Precipitation is projected to be above normal over the Plains and southern United States as well as in New England and along the southern coast of Alaska.  Below-normal amounts of precipitation should be anticipated over the Great Lakes region as well as over the Great Basin and northern Rocky Mountains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes were made this week to either location.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>The area was left unchanged this week as seasonal to above-normal precipitation was recorded over most of the region.  The lingering D0 region in New Jersey is the one area that has missed out on enough of the recent rainfall.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Above-normal rainfall over North Dakota and northeast South Dakota allowed for some improvements this week.  D3 was pushed back to the west in North Dakota and D0 and D1 were improved in northeast South Dakota and eastern North Dakota.  The extreme drought in North Dakota was not changed much by these rains, as most of the agricultural damage is done and the recent rains will not reverse these impacts this late in the summer.  Dryness continues to plague portions of Minnesota, so a new area of D1 was added this week, showing the driest portions of the state over the last several months.  D0 was expanded in northern Minnesota this week as well, as the abnormally dry region expanded and was refined for accuracy.  A new area of D0 was added in northeast Nebraska and into South Dakota.  This area has started to show signs of a flash drought developing as the lack of rain and hot temperatures have begun to stress crops in the region.</p>
   <p>A continuing dry pattern over east Texas, southwest Arkansas, and Louisiana resulted in the expansion of D0 and D1 as well as a new D2 region centered over Louisiana.  Several burn bans are already in place as well as voluntary water restrictions.   Improvements were made over west Texas and southeastern New Mexico, where D0 and D1 conditions were improved upon.  These changes were made as the full response to tropical storm Dolly was realized.  Portions of coastal Texas and Louisiana as well as east Texas have been impacted by the most recent tropical storm, Edouard, with 5.00 or more inches of rain recorded in the Houston metroplex.  With the impact of the storm coming at the end of the current Drought Monitor period, a full assessment of the precipitation associated with this storm on the drought regions will be done next week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Near-normal rainfall over the region helped offset the above-normal temperatures and keep much of the drought intensity in check.  Heavy rains over portions of North Carolina allowed for some improvement to the eastern fringes of the D2 and D3 designation.  D1 was also improved along the coast, where 5.34 inches of rain was recorded at Elizabethtown, NC, and several other locations along the southern coastal plains recorded over 2.00 inches as well.  In North Carolina, D1 was expanded over the Tar River Basin as recent rains have not been able to offset problems in this area.  In Alabama, two new areas of D3 were added where the long-term hydrological problems are holding course, with many streamflows still measuring in the lowest 1 to 5 percentiles.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Outside of Arizona, New Mexico and northwest Washington, the dry pattern continued over the western half of the United States. D0 was added to northeast Oregon and northwest Colorado. D0 and D1 were expanded in southern Wyoming as well.  In Colorado, D0 and D1 were shifted westward to the continental divide while the D2 in southeast Colorado was pushed to the northwest.  The story in the West has been that reservoir levels and surface water supplies are doing well.  The areas being impacted the most are those natural landscapes that are not influenced by stored water.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
