<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20140313</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The next 5 days (March 12-16) should bring moderate precipitation (0.5 to 2.0 inches) from the lower Mississippi Valley eastward across the Southeast. New England, far northwestern Washington, deep south Texas are expected to measure 0.5 to 1.0 inch. Light amounts of up to 0.5 inch at best are expected elsewhere.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (March 17-21), the odds favor above-normal precipitation along the immediate East Coast and in part of the Alaskan Panhandle. In contrast, there are enhanced chances for drier-than-normal conditions in a broad area covering much of the central and western states. Specifically, along a stripe from the Ohio and middle Mississippi Valleys westward through the central Rockies, California, and Oregon…and from there southward to the Mexican border and Gulf of Mexico coast. Neither wet nor dry conditions are particularly favored anywhere else.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Between 1 and locally 4 or more inches of rain fell on east Hawaii Island and much of Molokai, Maui, and Oahu. Only a few tenths of an inch dotted the rest of the Big Island and parts of the western periphery of the other islands. Dryness and drought remained unchanged.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, a few tenths of an inch of precipitation fell on the D0 to D1 areas in eastern Alaska, keeping conditions intact. Farther south, D0 has been introduced in the southern half of southeast Alaska. Precipitation has recently increased here, but conditions have also warmed up and snowpack is lower than usual. In spring, below-normal snowmelt into already-short reservoirs could affect water supplies. Already, power generation has been stopped on Ketchikan Lake, and while other lakes and reservoirs are at adequate levels, they’re dropping quickly..</p>
   <p>Dryness was expanded in Puerto Rico to cover the north-central and northwestern coastlines. Dryness here is of much shorter duration than along the southwest and particularly the south-central coast. For the South Coastal region as a whole, January and February brought 1.3 inches of rain, compared to the normal of 4.5 inches. In February on the north side coast, 1 to 2 inches fell on areas that typically get 2.5 to 4.0 inches; also, the Northern Slopes region, just south of the coastline, measured about 6.5 inches of precipitation during the month, considerably below the February normal of over 15 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and South-Central Plains">
   <p>Another week of below-normal precipitation affected the region, causing dryness and drought to generally persist and locally worsen. Between 0.25 and 1.0 inch of precipitation was measured from central Oklahoma northeastward into south Missouri, and in the central High Plains near the Rockies; otherwise, a few tenths of an inch fell, at best. Given the time of year, few changes were made in northern parts of this area, with more increasing areas of deterioration observed moving southward toward the Red River Valley. Severe drought expanded in central Nebraska, and D1 expanded considerably eastward from central Oklahoma to southeast Kansas. Over the past 60 days, precipitation totaled 3 to 6 inches less than normal across central and east Oklahoma, southeast Kansas, north and west Arkansas, and south Missouri. Both 60- and 90-day amounts are only half of normal at best across the south-central Plains approaching the Red River Valley and Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Southern Rockies">
   <p>Generally 0.5 to locally 2.5 inches of precipitation fell on the higher elevations in central and western Colorado, and central Utah. A few tenths of an inch fell on much of Wyoming, north New Mexico, and east-central Arizona, and little or none fell elsewhere. Improvement was introduced in parts of Colorado and Wyoming, where relatively wet patterns have been established for some time now. Conditions changed little elsewhere. Snowpack was considerably above normal in central Colorado, and near to a bit below normal in south Colorado, north-central New Mexico, and much of Utah. Very low snowpack – less than 25 percent of normal – was observed across higher elevations in Arizona and New Mexico. A lack oc water availability isn’t a widespread issue, but a few smaller systems are struggling to keep water flowing. In Utah, the water availability index in the Weber River, Provo, and San Pitch regions is below the 5th percentile level, but other regions are faring better.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Intermoutain West and Far West">
   <p>Heavy precipitation again pelted the northwestern and northeastern parts of this region, but dryness persisted farther south. Drought remained in the exceptional range in parts of California and northeast Nevada.</p>
   <p>Over 3 inches of precipitation fell from the northern Sierra Nevada and the Cascades westward to the Pacific Coast, with 5 to 10 inches reported in the higher elevations of the Cascades and in northeast California. As a result, D0 and D1 was reduced in western Washington, as was some D2 in southwest Oregon, but from Oregon southward, obvious relief was not as widespread and snowpack remained very low.</p>
   <p>In central and northern Idaho and some areas in nearby Washington and Oregon, 2 to 6 inches of precipitation was common. Conditions have improved in these regions significantly in the past few weeks, thus broad areas of improvement were introduced.</p>
   <p>In contrast, dryness and drought persisted farther south, where precipitation was lacking. Between 1 and 3 inches fell on the central and southern Sierra Nevada, but little or none was reported from western Utah, northern Nevada, and central California southward. Snowpack remained under 70 percent of normal roughly south and west of a line from northeast Oregon to north-central New Mexico, and was less than half of normal in southern Oregon, the Sierra Nevada and southern Cascades, northwestern Nevada, southwest Utah, and the higher elevations of Arizona and New Mexico.</p>
   <p>Water supplies are also being affected. Small-scale water supply systems serving at least 17 California communities are struggling to keep water flowing out of taps. The large Southern California Metro Water District is expected to draw about 20 percent more water than usual from Lake Meade (water it had banked in wetter years). As of March 6, the four large reservoirs on the periphery of the southern half of the San Joaquin Valley held 35 to 50 percent of their normal quantity for the date while reservoirs farther north along the central California Valley held 55 to 75 percent of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>It was a dry week across the region. A few tenths of an inch of precipitation fell on upstate New York and northern New England. Only scattered amounts below 0.2 inch were measured elsewhere. Impacts remained minimal, however, partly because of the time of year, so the scattered areas of D0 were left alone this week. The dry areas in northern New England are 2 to 4 inches below normal precipitation for the last 90 days, and almost all of the D0 areas remain at least 6 inches below normal for the last 6 months.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>It was a drier than normal week region-wide from Georgia and Florida westward into Mississippi. Moisture deficits increased enough in a few areas for the introduction of abnormal dryness. D0 persisted or expanded into northwest Alabama and adjacent locations, northeast Georgia, east-central Alabama and west-central Georgia, south-central Alabama and the extreme northwestern Florida Panhandle, and a stripe across southern Georgia. The past 60 days brought 3 to 5 inches less precipitation than normal to these regions, and 90-day totals are now 4 to 6 inches below normal in northeast Mississippi and northwest Alabama.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Lower Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Moderate to heavy rains of 1 to 3 inches fell on much of southern and southeastern Texas last week, but most of the region was drier than normal again. Precipitation totals topped a half inch across roughly the southeastern one-third of Texas and parts of Louisiana; Only isolated totals above 0.25 inch were reported elsewhere. To wit dryness and drought improved in portions of south and southeast Texas, but numerous areas elsewhere deteriorated. For the past 6 months, precipitation amounts ranged from 4 to locally almost a foot below normal in the Red River Valley, Oklahoma outside the Panhandle, Louisiana, and northwestern Arkansas. Since the start of the water year (October 2013), a mere 15 to 35 percent of normal precipitation has fallen on much of the Texas Panhandle and northeast New Mexico.</p>
   <p>Impacts resulting from this dryness are increasing. Low reservoir levels are common from the Texas Panhandle into central parts of the state, and short surface moisture is beginning to affect early-planted crops. Statewide across Oklahoma, 40 to 45 percent of oats, canola, and rangelands are in poor or very poor condition, as is roughly 30 percent of rye and wheat, according to the National Agricultural Statistics Service. In Texas, more than half of all rangelands are starting the season in poor to very poor condition.</p>
   <p>Some reservoirs have taken a beating. The elevations of Lakes Buchanan and Travis rival the record and near-record low levels of the mid-1960’s and early 1950’s, and Highlands Lake storage came perilously close to setting an all-time record low level in September 2013, but has since rebounded slightly. Both the Edwards Aquifer and the San Antonio water supply system soon will need to impose their strictest mandatory water conservations measures ever (stage 4 and 3, respectively) if precipitation doesn’t start to increase.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Upper and Middle Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Between 0.5 and 1.0 inch of precipitation fell on a swath from southwest Minnesota eastward into southern Wisconsin while other areas received only a few tenths of an inch, if any. For areas north of southern Iowa, the drought assessment has been static awaiting spring snowmelt progress. From southern Iowa into north Missouri and west Illinois, dryness did prompt some regions of D0 and D1 expansion.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
