<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100211</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (February 11-15), temperatures for most of the United States will be below normal.  Temperatures will range from 12 degrees Fahrenheit below normal in Texas to 3 degrees Fahrenheit below normal across the northern plains and Great Lakes regions.  The southern jet will continue to stay active, bringing widespread precipitation over much of the southern United States from Arizona to Florida.  The coastal regions of Oregon and Washington as well as portions of New England and the Ohio River valley will be impacted by heavy precipitation.  The Climate Prediction Center 6-10 day forecast (February 16-20) shows that the eastern half of the United States should experience below-normal temperatures, with the greatest departures in and around the southeast.  The best chances for above-normal temperatures are from Alaska through southern California.  The best chances for above-normal precipitation are over the plains states and into portions of the Gulf coast.  The coastal regions of Alaska and into the Pacific Northwest should also experience above-normal precipitation.  The best chances for drier-than-normal conditions are centered on the Great Basin and into the Great Lakes regions.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes were made this week in Alaska, Hawaii or Puerto Rico.  Dryness continues to plague Hawaii, as it is the only state currently showing D3 extreme drought.  For the start of 2010, most locations are below normal.  On the Big Island, Hilo is 11.43 inches below normal for the year, Volcano National Park is 12.61 inches below normal, and Paauilo and the Kapapala Ranch are 8.61 inches below normal this year.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Texas">
   <p>The wet pattern across Texas continued this week with most locations in the state receiving precipitation.  In the drought areas of south Texas, precipitation amounts were generally around 1.0 inches, but Carrizo Springs and Pleasanton recorded 3.17 and 2.71 inches, respectively.  With the ongoing moisture, a full category improvement was made for most drought areas in Texas except for the D0 in west Texas.  A small area of D1 is all that remains of the drought in Texas and with the weather pattern continuing to stay active, further improvements may be needed.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A less-than-stellar snowpack has warranted expansion of D0 and D1 in Idaho this week.  Below-normal snowfall along with warmer-than-normal temperatures has lowered the spring run-off forecast for Idaho.  With decent carryover in reservoirs, the full impact of the dryness will not be felt for a while, but the consensus was to introduce D0 to the entire state, including eastern Oregon, and expand the D1 in the panhandle and southeast portions of the state.  Portions of Wyoming and Colorado continue to be dry and are being watched closely for any further degradation.  Good precipitation in the Four Corners region has allowed for an improvement to the D1 in that area.  D0 was also improved slightly in eastern New Mexico as more precipitation was recorded last week, allowing for some improvements.  Improvements to the D0 in southwest New Mexico and southeast Arizona also were made.  Lingering long-term hydrological issues continue to plague the western portions of Arizona, with conditions staying the same as last week.  Lake Mary in north central Arizona is running at 31 percent of normal, which is unchanged so far this winter.  D1 was improved in southern California and into southern Nevada this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
