<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020815</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period (through August 24) that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) over the next 5 days ending August 19th, expect cooler temperatures to settle into the Plains states with well below-normal temperatures being felt in the northern Plains. Ridging (high pressure aloft) in the east and west will result in above-normal temperatures on both ends of the country. Expect the oppressive hot and humid weather to plague the Mid-Atlantic and lower Northeast states for a few more days; 2) precipitation over the same 5-day period should bring the potential for totals of 1-2 inches or more (in places) from the Missouri and Mississippi rivers all the way to the Atlantic. Unfortunately, very little is expected in the way of precipitation from the Missouri River westward toward the Pacific Ocean; 3) for the 6 to 10-day period (Aug. 20-24), below-normal precipitation is forecasted for the West, while the South and East are expected to be warmer than normal; 4) precipitation over this period continues to show a suppressed monsoon signal and drier-than-normal weather across the entire west. In the Southeast and Midwest, above-normal precipitation is expected and would bring welcome relief; 5) the forecast for all but southern Alaska calls for below-normal temperatures with above-normal precipitation predicted for southern and southeastern coastal Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>No change to the abnormally dry (D0) conditions found in western Oahu and Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Parts of eastern and western Puerto Rico saw good rains last week, with 2 to 3 inches falling on both sides of the island. Given the longer-term deficits that have accumulated over most of the island, only the southwestern corner of the island saw enough rain last week to bring them out of abnormally dry (D0) conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>After last weeks good rains, almost the entire eastern seaboard saw a very dry week. Consequently, drought is on the move again in the region and has begun to slowly expand with an increase of abnormally dry (D0) or moderate drought (D1) noted in Rhode Island, Massachusetts, Connecticut, West Virginia, Maryland, and Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast and Southeast">
   <p>Even though Tropical Storm Bertha brought much-needed relief to the Gulf Coast last week, other inland areas continue to suffer as year-to-date deficits accumulate. Where the rains missed, drought is again on the move as abnormally dry (D0) conditions have spread out of northern and western Louisiana into extreme northeastern Texas, southwestern Arkansas and extreme southeastern Oklahoma.</p>
   <p>On the right flank, conditions have slipped back farther, with abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) encroaching farther into central Alabama. Meanwhile, Georgia and South Carolina continue to be mired in a drought they cant shake as extreme (D3) and exceptional (D4) conditions once again expand within state lines. Exceptional drought (D4) can now be seen continuously linking Virginia in the north to Georgia in the south.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, Ohio Valley, Great Lakes">
   <p>Good rains fell again last week over parts of these regions, with anywhere from 2 to 4 inches or more being reported in parts of Nebraska, South Dakota, Iowa, Wisconsin, Kansas, Oklahoma, Missouri, and Illinois. This has led to an improvement (1 category) of drought conditions in extreme northeastern Nebraska and southeastern South Dakota. Beneficial rains have also served to chip away at the drought on the southern and western edges in Kansas and in the Oklahoma and Texas panhandles. For other parts of the region fortunate enough to see some rains, they were simply enough to stave off any further worsening of conditions, and in many locales could be a case of too little too late for this growing season.</p>
   <p>Not everyone shared in the rains, though, as the Corn and Bean belt remains in a vice, with some improvement being felt on the western fringe, while at the same time, conditions continue to worsen on the eastern front as the drought spreads in from Ohio and into Kentucky, Indiana and Illinois. Soil and crop conditions continue to deteriorate in these states and the region in general. In Ohio, this has led to an expansion westward of severe drought (D2), and moderate drought (D1) now covers most of the state. In addition, D0 and D1 conditions have spread into more of Kentucky, Indiana and Illinois.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Alaska">
   <p>The Southwest saw a pretty quiet week overall, with most of the monsoon rains limited to southern New Mexico and southeastern Arizona. Recent improvements (both in rain and in drought depiction) in the region have somewhat stabilized the drought situation there, but havent been enough to warrant further improvements in the drought classification here.</p>
   <p>Farther north, north-central Montana welcomed another bout of good rains. While the rains havent been enough to eradicate years of drought, they have been steady over the past few months and have led to a slow improvement in the drought depiction here as moderate (D1), severe (D2), and extreme (D3) drought have been pushed southward away from the Canadian border.</p>
   <p>As for the rest of the West, it was another typical dry summer week with not many changes to report. One area of expansion worth noting can be found in central Idaho, where extreme drought (D3) has spread out of Montana and into the Big Lost and Little Lost basins as low streamflow and reservoir levels continue to wreak havoc on agricultural activities and the natural environment. Although these levels are no worse than they were last summer at this time, it will be vital to the region to see a recharge of the water supply this winter in order to get through next summer. Dryness since the beginning of the year in the Palouse region of eastern Washington has led to the introduction of abnormally dry (D0) conditions there.</p>
   <p>Although conditions have improved somewhat over parts of southern coastal Alaska (leading to some reduction in the abnormally dry (D0) depiction there), high to extreme fire danger remains a worry for areas in the central part of the state. Dryness continues to feed the fires, which have burned nearly 900,000 acres this month alone.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
