<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010301</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: 1) a vigorous storm system is forecast to slowly cross the southern U.S. during the next several days, resulting in the likelihood of heavy rain in much of the Southeast. Lighter amounts of precipitation are expected in southern Florida, western Texas, and southeastern New Mexico; 2) the storm may turn northward along the East Coast early next week, bringing a chance of snow to the central Appalachians; 3) Storm systems will continue to approach the West Coast, providing additional moisture to the Sierra Nevada but only light precipitation from the Pacific Northwest to the northern Rockies; 4); only light precipitation is forecast across the northern half of the Plains; and 5) the National Weather Service 6- to 10-day outlook for March 6-10 calls for a continuation of wet weather in the southwestern and south-central United States, including the southern Sierra Nevada, southeastern New Mexico, and western Texas. Below-normal precipitation is forecast across the Pacific Northwest, while near-normal amounts are expected in most other drought areas. Cool conditions are forecast to return to the Southeast, following a month-long period of unusually warm weather.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Generally quiet weather returned to Hawaii, following significant, drought-easing rainfall during the first half of February. Recent storms produced enough rainfall on Kauai to warrant eliminating the area of abnormal dryness (D0 for agricultural and wildfire concerns). In contrast, most of the storms moisture bypassed western Molokai, necessitating an increase to extreme drought (D3) for agricultural interests and the threat of wildfires. Meanwhile, only light showers dampened Puerto Rico, leaving an area of abnormal dryness (D0) along the southwestern coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Appalachians">
   <p>An area of abnormal hydrological dryness (D0) continued to affect southern West Virginia, where only light snow fell during the week. Little precipitation fell from western and central Pennsylvania northeastward into New Yorks Finger Lakes region, leaving an area of abnormal dryness intact.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>In western Texas and southeastern New Mexico, a mostly dry week brought little change in the long-term hydrological drought situation. A pocket of severe drought (D2) continued to affect areas in and near Midland, Texas, where staggering precipitation deficits have accumulated over a 7-year period. Midlands precipitation from January 1, 1994, to February 26, 2001, totaled 70.92 inches (67 percent of normal), or 34.78 inches below normal. Farther south, early-season heat aggravated the effects of abnormal dryness (D0) in southernmost Texas, where February 24 high temperatures soared to 92F in McAllen and 91F in Cotulla. Meanwhile on the northern Plains, a cold, dry week produced few changes to a drought that remained severe (D2) in central Montana. Elsewhere, a major winter storm tracked northeastward across the east-central Plains, providing additional long-term drought relief. Although some hydrological drought concerns linger across southern and western Nebraska, the remainder of the state is drought-free. As much as 1 to 2 inches of rain left only a pocket of abnormal dryness in northeastern Kansas. A pocket of moderate drought (D1) persisted in west-central Iowa due to long-term precipitation deficits.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>During the week ending February 26, more than 2 inches of rain fell at many locations in an area centered on the southern Appalachians, temporarily boosting streamflows and providing slight relief from long-term drought. Central Tennessee was removed from abnormally dry (D0) status, while western Tennessee retained a pocket of abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1), despite year-to-date precipitation totals that increased to 10.05 inches (130 percent of normal) in Memphis and 9.25 inches (115 percent) in Jackson. Farther east, serious long-term precipitation deficits persisted in the southern Appalachians and adjacent piedmont areas, despite recent showers. For example, Greenville-Spartanburg, South Carolina, received 5.32 inches (65 percent of normal) during the first 57 days of 2001, leaving its May 1, 1998 - February 26, 2001, precipitation at 101.11 inches (70 percent of normal), a deficit of 43.11 inches in less than 34 months. An area of severe to extreme drought (D2 to D3) continued to affect areas from northern Georgia, northeastward through the western Carolinas, into southwestern Virginia.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, Floridas drought situation grew increasingly serious due to persistent dryness and record warmth, resulting in diminishing freshwater supplies, heavy citrus and vegetable irrigation requirements, and the threat of additional wildfires. Year-to-date rainfall through February 26 remained as low as 0.08 inch (2 percent of normal) in Ft. Myers, where a daily-record high temperature of 88F was reported on February 24, and 1.33 inches (25 percent) in West Palm Beach. In the South Florida Water Management District, which includes Lake Okeechobee, rainfall for the period from October 8, 2000, to February 27, 2001, totaled 2.35 inches (20 percent of normal). Okeechobee itself fell to record-low levels for this time of year. As of February 27, the average elevation of the lakes surface stood at 10.56 feet, down from 12.50 feet as recently as early October 2000. Wildfires continued to burn a large amount of Florida underbrush that was initially stressed by drought, then further browned by repeated freezes in late December and early January. During the 30 days ending February 26, more than 1000 Florida wildfires consumed nearly 100,000 acres, boosting the states year-to-date total to 104,191 acres.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>According to the California Department of Water Resources, the average water equivalent of the Sierra Nevada snow pack increased to 18 inches (75 percent of the late-February normal) on February 26, up from about 9 inches (approximately 50 percent of normal) at the beginning of the month and only 5 inches in early January. Despite six consecutive years (1994-95 to 1999-2000) with a near- to above-normal Sierra Nevada snow pack and near-normal cumulative holdings in Californias 156 major reservoirs, summer water-supply concerns remain sufficient to warrant an abnormally dry (D0) tag in key watershed areas. Farther north, more serious concerns exist with respect to spring runoff prospects and summer water supplies. Most river basins from the Cascades to the northern Rockies received October to late-February precipitation totaling just 45 to 70 percent of normal. As a result, much of the region retains a moderate drought (D1) label.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
