<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001109</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 10 days, several anticipated developments will affect the nations dry areas, including: (1) Heavy rain (1 to 3-inch totals) during November 8-13 over the Mississippi Valley, including some of the hardest-hit drought areas in Louisiana, Mississippi, Alabama, and Tennessee; (2) Light to moderate rain over the Appalachians and Piedmont in the next 10 days, breaking a dry spell that began in late September; and (3) above-normal precipitation and below-normal temperatures over central and southwestern areas of the country. On November 7-8, additional rain in the lower Mississippi Valley and rain and snow in Texas further eased dryness.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>A record-breaking deluge hit the windward portions of the Hawaiian islands, and significant rainfall helped improve drought conditions in leeward areas. Abnormal dryness (D0) ended on Oahu and Kauai, while dryness categories improved by one level to D0 to D1 on the Big Island, Maui, Molokai, and Lanai. On November 1-2, Hilo recorded 27.24 inches of rain, setting a record for their greatest 24-hour total of all time.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Four to 10 inches of rain caused widespread flooding in central and eastern Texas. These heavy rains, on top of earlier October rains, have virtually eliminated short-term drought across the state. The moisture removed all categories of dryness across most of eastern and central Texas, with D1 to D2 hydrological drought lingering in western Texas, where rainfall amounts totaled under 2 inches and reservoir and groundwater supplies remained below normal. Hydrological drought and dryness (D0 to D1) persisted in southwest and southern Texas along the Rio Grande, due to lingering reservoir concerns. Heavy rains also reduced dryness elsewhere across the U.S. Great Plains. D1 to D2 lingered in eastern Nebraska and western Iowa, but conditions ranged from normal to D0 over the rest of the Plains. D0 to D1 persisted in northern Michigan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>Continued dry weather led to expansion of D0 dryness from Virginia and western Maryland northward to Pennsylvania and southern New England. Light rain offered only minor relief for fire fighters in North Carolina, and D1 to D3 drought persisted from southwest Virginia into much of the Southeast. A small area of D4 drought developed on the border between Tennessee and North Carolina. Heavy showers left up to 4 inches on south-central Alabama, improving D4 drought to D3. Two to 5 inches of rain brought drought relief to Arkansas and Louisiana, eliminating drought in western Arkansas and northwestern Louisiana. D4 drought persisted from extreme east Louisiana into southwestern Alabama.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Still another relatively wet week brought continued drought improvement to the region. Drought is mostly limited to Montana, with recent rain and snow ending drought in Colorado</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
