<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010329</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Anticipated occurrences during March 28 - April 2 which could affect areas experiencing dryness and drought include: (1) Heavy precipitation (over an inch) and subnormal temperatures from central Alabama, eastern Tennessee, and the central Ohio Valley eastward, as far south as Lake Okeechobee. Between 3 and 5 inches are possible in the southeastern Carolinas, central and southern Georgia, and adjacent Alabama and Florida; (2) Substantial precipitation (0.5 to 2.0 inches) in the central Plains, northwest Colorado, southern and western Montana, the Idaho Panhandle, and all but central and southeastern Washington; and (3) Little or no precipitation in southern Texas, the southern High Plains, and areas south and west of central Nevada and southeastern Oregon. For the ensuing 10 days (April 3 - 7) the forecast is highly uncertain, but the odds appear to be leaning toward: (1) Subnormal precipitation in much of the West; (2) Below-normal temperatures for the northern halves of the Rockies and High Plains; (3) Surplus precipitation in the central Plains and adjacent Rockies; and (4) above-normal rainfall across peninsular Florida.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Another week of significant rains (1.5 to locally 8.2 inches) in most of eastern and southeastern Puerto Rico eliminated D0 conditions, but lesser totals allowed abnormal dryness to continue for a small part of southwestern Puerto Rico. Across Hawaii, light to moderate rains fell on many locations, but both year-to-date and longer-term precipitation totals remained well below normal in the D0 to D3 areas, thus dryness and drought categorizations are unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Appalachians and Ohio Valley">
   <p>Moderate precipitation (1 to 2 inches) in north-central Pennsylvania and adjacent New York eliminated D0 conditions. Farther south and west, about an inch of precipitation fell on the western slopes of the Appalachians and interior eastern Kentucky, 0.2 to 1.0 inch was measured in the central Appalachians and the rest of central and eastern Kentucky, and less than 0.2 inch was recorded elsewhere.</p>
   <p>As a result, 90-day precipitation deficits exceeding an inch prompted the expansion of D0 conditions into large portions of the central Appalachians and Ohio Valley, and the reclassification of D0(W) conditions near the Ohio/Mississippi Rivers confluence to D0. In scattered areas north of the central and lower Ohio River, 30-day deficits topped 2 inches, and 90-day deficits exceeded 4 inches. Furthermore, streamflows were among the lowest 10% of historical occurrences for this time of year in much of a broad area from northeastern Ohio southwestward across Indiana, southern Illinois, and southeastern Missouri on March 27.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>A rather nondescript week was observed in those areas affected by dryness and drought, with generally light precipitation (up to an inch) falling on south-central Nebraska, adjacent Kansas, and much of west-central Iowa. Farther west, little or none was observed in the west-central Plains. Given the relatively small totals, no changes were introduced to D0(W) areas in the central Plains.</p>
   <p>ther south, moderate precipitation around the middle of last week prompted a reduction to the eastern extent of the D0(W) area in western Texas. However, only scattered light precipitation was recorded in the remainder of southern and western Texas and adjacent New Mexico, keeping D0 to D1 and D0(W) to D2(W) conditions intact in those regions.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Significant precipitation (1 to locally 3 inches) fell on parts of central and northern Georgia, most of the Carolinas, and Virginia during the last 7 days. The rest of the region recorded less than an inch. These totals brought most locations outside central Florida, the southern Appalachians, and eastern Tennessee to near or above normal for the 30 days ending March 27.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, most areas remained below normal for the 90-day period ending March 27, and those areas demonstrating a 90-day surplus (much of Georgia and eastern Alabama) were also areas where dryness dates back the longest (to May 1998) and accrued long-term deficits were very large. Therefore, only limited reductions in dryness and drought categorizations were noted. Specifically, one-category reductions were introduced in former D0(W) to D1(W) areas of west-central Georgia and the western Florida Panhandle, former D3 to D4 areas in a small section of northern peninsular Florida, and former D1 areas of central North Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Near- or above-normal precipitation fell on interior eastern Washington, the central and southern Cascades, much of central and eastern Nevada, and a few sections of western Montana and central Idaho during the 7 days ending March 27, but subnormal totals allowed deficits to continue increasing in other areas affected by dryness and drought. In addition, warmer-than-normal weather contributed to unseasonably-early high mountain snowmelt in some areas, further increasing concerns about the chances for locally inadequate water supplies and hydroelectric power generation over the next several months. On March 27, snow water content was less than half of normal in much of Idaho, adjacent sections of northern Montana and Washington, much of southern and eastern Oregon, and the Sierra Nevada near Lake Tahoe. In addition, some locations in Idaho and adjacent Montana may hold near record low snow water equivalents for this time of year, with records dating back 40 to 55 years. However, the changes in conditions noted just during the last 7 days did not warrant any re-categorizations, for better or worse, of the regions dryness and drought.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
