<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041124</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The upper-air circulation pattern for the next 14 days will consist of a long-wave ridge over the eastern Pacific Ocean just off the North America coast and a long-wave trough extending from near Hudson Bay down across the southwestern U.S. This will allow winter storm systems to move into the West, track into the Southwest, then intensify as they move across the Gulf Coast states and up the Appalachians into the Northeast. Cold air from western Canada behind these systems will move into the Lower 48 States, resulting in below-normal temperatures from the inter-mountain basin in the West to the Appalachian Mountains in the eastern U.S. Above-normal temperatures will be limited primarily to the Pacific Northwest coast, the east coast, and Alaska.</p>
   <p>A half inch or more of precipitation is expected to fall over a large area from Washington state to western Colorado November 23-28, with some areas receiving more than an inch. Lesser amounts are forecast for the other western drought areas and for the central Plains to Great Lakes drought areas. The Northeast abnormally dry areas may receive an inch or more of precipitation. An upper-level system near Hawaii will bring a chance for heavy rain showers over the D0 areas early in the period, followed by scattered showers later (November 26-28).</p>
   <p>The 6 to 10 day outlook (November 28-December 2) calls for below-normal precipitation over the Pacific Northwest and above-normal precipitation over a wide swath from the Southwest to the Great Lakes, eastward to the Appalachians. Western Alaska is forecast to be wetter than normal during this period, with the eastern Alaska drought area drier than normal.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>In Alaska, the D0 in the panhandle was completely removed based on NWS airport station reports of well above normal precipitation totals. Yakutat was reporting 97% of normal since September 1, 2004. Also in Alaska, Pelican has already received 18.70 inches during the first 21 days of November. There was no change made to Hawaii during this Drought Monitoring period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Moderate amounts, 0.25 to 0.50 of an inch, of precipitation fell over the abnormally dry areas of New England this period but 7-day stream flow, the Climate Prediction Centers (CPC) soil moisture and the High Plains Regional Climate Centers (HPRCC) percent of normal maps for 7-day thru 60-day time frames are still showing this area of D0 drier than normal. Therefore, no changes were made to the area this drought monitoring period. Areas that have been drying out in the Southeast over the past several weeks became D0 during this monitoring period. One section of abnormally dry A, H conditions was introduced into coastal South Carolina based on all time frames of HPRCC percent of normal precipitation maps from 7- to 90-days. The NWS airport weather station at Charleston reported only 0.20 inch of precipitation for November. An area to watch in the coming weeks is south Florida. Naples has received only 0.16 inch of rain this month and Fort Lauderdale has 66% of normal for year-to-date. These are mainly areas that missed the hurricane activity of August and September and are showing up dry as far out as 90-days on the HPRCC percent of normal maps.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Great Plains">
   <p>Precipitation fell across many of the drought areas this period. In central Wisconsin, D0 was shaved eastward based upon recent precipitation totals of 1-2 inches, CPCs and the Midwest Regional Climate Centers (MRCC) soil moisture models, and HPRCCs 7-day to 60-day time frames of the precipitation anomaly. Also in the Midwest, the abnormally dry region in Iowa climate division 5 was completely removed and in divisions 3 and 4 trimmed back, based on recent precipitation amounts of 1-2 inches that fell this period and the MRCC soil moisture models. The hydrological impacts line was extended into eastern Nebraska to reflect recent rains of 1-2 inches along Interstate 80. The remaining D0 in Kansas, Iowa, Missouri and southeast Nebraska was designated as A, H impacts to denote both short- and long-term dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Only a few storm systems moved across the northwestern drought areas during this monitoring period generally bringing below-normal precipitation for the week. In Washington, abnormally dry conditions were extended westward into climate division 6 and southward to the Oregon state boundary. This expansion was based on HPRCC 30-day percent of normal precipitation maps, and SNOTEL reports that are also showing dryness east of the Cascades . An impacts line was also added to the Washington D0 area to delineate between short- and long-term dryness. Heavier precipitation fell over the southwestern drought areas. A doughnut hole of D0 was introduced into south-central Utah and the D2 and D3 areas just east of there were retracted as well as. This change was made to reflect rain and snow that fell in southern Utah near the end of this Drought Monitoring period, as well as longer-term improvements as indicated by SNOTEL reports (up to 200-300 percent of average snow water equivalent and water year precipitation). In Arizona, the D2 in climate division 3 was trimmed slightly to the east under the area of heaviest precipitation of 1-2 inch totals based upon RFC radar estimates. Also in Arizona, the D3 in climate division 2 was retracted due to 2-4 inch precipitation radar estimates, at the end of the Drought Monitoring period.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
