<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000928</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect some of the dry or drought areas across the nation include: 1) After the tropical bombardment of the past few weeks, much cooler and drier weather will dominate much of the Southeast into the first week of October; 2) A very quiet weather picture is shaping up for most of the country over the next few days (9/20-10/2) as high pressure systems dominate; and 3) The latest 6-10 day forecast (valid 10/3-10/7) indicates that the warming trend should continue with near-normal to above-normal temperatures expected from the Rocky Mountains all the way to the East Coast. No precipitation is expected in the Southwest and below normal precipitation is expected from Oklahoma up into the Ohio Valley. Above-normal precipitation is called for along the coastal areas of the Gulf Coast states from southeastern Texas to Florida, and up into South Carolina. In other drought affected areas, below-normal temperatures and normal to above-normal precipitation is expected across most of Montana for the 6-10 day period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Rains over the past month or so have gradually eased drought conditions in the Hawaiian Islands. Severe drought (D2 A,F) still remains over some leeward areas.</p>
   <p>Rainfall over the past few weeks has led to the removal of first stage drought (D1) from the northern coast of Puerto Rico, but abnormally dry (D0) conditions remain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Many areas of the northern Plains saw their first taste of winter as 6" of snow fell in parts of the Nebraska Panhandle over the weekend. Good rains earlier in the week in southwestern Nebraska, northeastern Colorado and northwestern Kansas were welcomed and will go along way toward helping with hard red winter wheat planting in the region. The extreme drought (D3) area here has been downgraded to severe drought (D2) as a result.</p>
   <p>In other areas of the Midwest, there was some improvement in parts of southeast Nebraska, northwest Missouri and southern Iowa, where some of the severe drought (D2) has receded but remains close by. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions continue to be seen in parts of southwestern Minnesota but have receded out of Illinois and back into south central Iowa. Better precipitation over the past two weeks has led to first stage drought (D1) being removed from the Upper Peninsula of Michigan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>A week after seeing Hurricane Gordon make landfall on the Florida peninsula, Tropical Storm Helene came inland in the Florida Panhandle bringing with it heavy rains. The combination of Helene and a stalled front in the Southeast led to more rainfall out of Helene than they saw out of Hurricane Gordon the previous week. Totals ranged from 8-10" in the Florida Panhandle, and this moisture also worked its way northeastward into Georgia and the Carolinas, where 4-6" was common. In Florida, recent heavy rains have led to a reduction of extreme drought (D3) and severe drought (D2) in the Panhandle. Hydrological concerns remain here, though, as significant year-to-date deficits remain in Pensacola (-19") and Tallahassee (-15").</p>
   <p>Similarly, extreme (D3) and severe (D2) drought has slowly receded to the north, out of southern Georgia. Concerns in Georgia have turned to the hydrological side; streamflows are still very low in the southwest corner. Year-to-date deficits are around, or exceed, 10" in Columbus, Savannah, Athens and Atlanta.</p>
   <p>The relief trend of the last few weeks continued for the Gulf Coast states last week. Severe drought (D2) along the southeast coast of Texas was downgraded to first stage drought (D1), as was the case across the coastal fringe areas of Louisiana, Mississippi and Alabama. Areas to the north, however, could use a lot more rain. Deficits for the year are above 23" in and around New Orleans (48% of normal) and Baton Rouge (51% of normal). Mobile, AL continues to see a 21"+ deficit for the year (59% of normal).</p>
   <p>Much-needed rains in southwest Texas have led to the removal of the exceptional drought (D4) area around Del Rio. We should keep in mind, though, that extreme drought (D3) conditions remain. The Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport recorded their first precipitation in 84 days last week.</p>
   <p>In Oklahoma, since July 1st, the entire state has seen about one-half of its normal precipitation. The western third of the state has seen less than one-third of their normal rainfall over the same period. A burning ban remains in effect for all of Oklahoma as fire danger remains very high to extreme.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Significant snow fell in parts of southwestern Wyoming and parts of northern Colorado on Sunday (9/24), with the front range even getting in on some of the action. Much colder temperatures invaded the area, serving as a stark contrast to the hot dry weather of the past few weeks. First stage (D1) drought has receded to the west in Wyoming. To the north, conditions remain quite dry as severe drought (D2) remains entrenched and extreme drought (D3) has slowly expanded in west central Montana.</p>
   <p>The situation remains serious in eastern New Mexico as they hope that the demise of La Nia will bring a much better snowfall season this year. The same holds true for Arizona, where abnormally dry (D0) and first stage drought (D1) have pushed a little farther to the south. Flagstaff has seen a precipitation deficit of almost 6" this year-to-date, which leaves them at 64% of normal. Streamflow levels remain low compared to normal in the central and east central parts of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
