<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20091112</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (November 11-15), an active weather pattern should impact much of the country.  As the remnants of Ida continue up the coast of North Carolina and into the Mid-Atlantic, precipitation amounts should be quite large, with 6 or more inches not out of the question.  The next system coming onshore in the Pacific Northwest will have a trough moving through much of the country, bringing a good chance of precipitation for the Rocky Mountains and Plains states.  Temperatures during this time will be above normal for the eastern half of the United States in front of this trough, and cooler than normal behind it.  Temperatures should average well above normal in the northern Plains, where departures of 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal are expected.  Behind the trough, temperatures are going to be 0-3 degrees Fahrenheit below normal. The Climate Prediction Center 6-10 day forecast (November 16-20) establishes a ridge over much of the United States, with temperatures expected to be well above normal for the northern Rocky Mountains, Plains, Great Lakes and New England regions and below normal over Alaska and portions of northern California.  Dry conditions look likely over the Plains and Rocky Mountains and northern portions of Alaska.  Along the Pacific Northwest and Ohio Valley, wetter than normal conditions are probable during this time.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes for Alaska or Hawaii this week.  In response to dryness over the last several months, D0 was added to the eastern half of Puerto Rico this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Florida">
   <p>As Ida impacted much of the Southeast, much of the Florida peninsula did not receive the heavy rains that other areas did.  No changes were made this week, but the lingering dryness in many areas will continue to be analyzed in the coming weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Considering the time of year and the associated impacts from the long-term dryness in Wisconsin, the D3 was improved to D2 this week.  Recent rains have helped conditions in the area, and the full impact on the hydrologic concerns is yet to be known.  If the region continues to receive precipitation, this will help improve the hydrological impacts further.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast and Mid-Atlantic, and Carolinas">
   <p>A dry week over the region has allowed the drought status to remain the same as last week.  At the end of the current Drought Monitor period, the remnants of Tropical Storm Ida were impacting the Carolinas with heavy rains.  This should bring some welcomed relief to the region where dryness was becoming a concern. With the rain falling after the period of consideration for this current Drought Monitor, changes reflecting Ida’s impacts will be made next week when a full assessment of the event can be done.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains">
   <p>D1 was added in the area around Lubbock in west Texas.  This area is experiencing dryness on short- and long-term scales that has caused some shortages of surface moisture.  The rest of Texas remained unchanged this week as the rainfall that was recorded did not allow for any additional changes.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>D0 in Washington and Oregon was improved again this week, pushing the D0 to the east, farther from the coast.  In New Mexico, D0 was expanded in the eastern portion of the state as well as along the border with Arizona.  D2 was expanded in northern Arizona while D0 and D1 was expanded out of northern Arizona and pushed further into Utah.  In Nevada, the area around Lake Tahoe reverted back to how it was depicted in early October.  Even after an early October storm, flows on most Lake Tahoe and Truckee River tributary streams are now at or below what they were in early to mid October.  This is the earliest that required flow rates have not been met on the Truckee River since 1994.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
