<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061214</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch over the next 2 weeks that could affect current dry or drought areas include: 1) up to an inch or more of rain in central and southern Florida through December 16; 2) Pacific storms bringing rain and snow to western Montana and Wyoming through December 16; 3) a developing storm system bringing rain and snow to the Southwest and Rockies December 17-19; 4) the same storm bringing widespread rain and snow to the Plains states on December 19-21.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Summary">
   <p>In contrast to the prior week, little rain or snow fell over most of the areas experiencing dryness or drought, with the bulk of the precipitation falling in areas that have been recently wet, such as the Pacific Northwest and the Mississippi Valley. As a result, changes to the Drought Monitor depiction were minor.</p>
   <p>West Coast storminess did swing far enough southward to bring some needed rain to southern California on December 9-10. Amounts of 0.10 to 0.50 inches were common outside of desert areas, and some mountain locations and coastal areas farther north picked up 1 to 2 inches. The moisture was welcome, but not enough to end the rainfall deficits that have characterized late summer and autumn this year. Since July 1, San Diego has recorded 1.10 inches of rain, and this is 49 percent of normal. Downtown Los Angeles has measured less than an inch (0.93 inches, 38 percent of normal). The continued deficits resulted in only a minor retreat of the D0 area in California despite the increased rainfall.</p>
   <p>With water year precipitation well above normal, D1 retreated eastward in western Montana, but there were no changes in the depiction for the rest of the northern Rockies and northern Plains.</p>
   <p>The season is off to a dry start across Arizona and New Mexico. In Arizona, Phoenix has seen no measurable rain since mid-October. Flagstaff has recorded merely an inch of snow this season, 20 inches below normal. Tucsons 0.27 inches of rain since October 1 is just 12 percent of normal, even lower than this time last year. The Drought Monitor expanded D0 dryness in southeast Arizona and filled in the slot of D0 with D1 in south-central Arizona. In New Mexico, where basin snow water content is under one-half of normal outside of the far north, and under 25 percent of normal in the southwest, D0 expanded across the west and into the northeast.</p>
   <p>Moderate to heavy rains of 0.5 to 2.0 inches benefited dry areas in South Texas, but areas farther north near the Rio Grande measured little rain. With rainfall this year totaling less than one-half of normal, D4 was introduced to an area extending from near San Antonio to the Rio Grande. To the north, drier weather this week along with a re-assessment of the water supply picture led to some changes in Oklahoma, including removal of D0 in the southeast and some expansion of D1/D2/D3/D4 southward and eastward. Normans water source, Lake Thunderbird, is reported to be at an all-time low. D1 also stretched farther north into central Kansas due to persistent dryness.</p>
   <p>In Florida, continued dry weather led to extension of D0 dryness over the rest of the southern Peninsula. Fort Myers has seen just 0.04 inches of rain since November 17. Low soil moisture and streamflows led to northward expansion of D0 into central Georgia, and some increase of D1 in southeast Georgia.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, D0 was introduced across the western portions of the Big Island in response to dry weather. D0 remained over western Maui.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Thomas Heddinghaus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
