<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010208</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Anticipated occurrences which may affect current areas of dryness and drought over the next 10 days include: (1) a large storm bringing rain and snow to the center of the country on Thursday-Friday, February 8-9, improving moisture supplies over Kansas, Nebraska, and Iowa; (2) 1 to 2 inches of rain over the Tennessee Valley and the western Carolinas from this storm and a second one on February 12-13; (3) 1 to 2 inches of rain in the lower elevations and heavy mountain snows in central and northern California on Friday-Sunday, February 9-11; (4) chance of heavy showers Friday-Sunday, February 9-11 over Hawaii; (5) below-normal rainfall and above-normal temperatures over the drought areas of Florida and southern Georgia.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Showers were mainly confined to windward areas of Hawaii, while dryness continued elsewhere. D1 increased to D2 (A,F) drought across the western two-thirds of the Big Island. In Puerto Rico, above-normal rains eased D0 dryness over all areas except the southern coast.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>The coastal storm diminished dryness in Pennsylvania, allowing a reduction of D0 in the eastern half of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Precipitation was generally light following the previous week's storm, so there was little change to the dryness depiction. In Nebraska, hydrological dryness (D0) continued across southern and western areas, reflecting low reservoir levels.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Frequent showers from a stalled cold front left over 2 inches of rain in parts of north-central Florida, easing fire danger and improving topsoil moisture. Subsoil moisture improvement was negligible, and measurements indicated that much of the topsoil improvement was temporary. Considerably more rain is needed to relieve long-term drought, and D4 (Exceptional) drought remained over the central peninsula. Farther south, continued dryness caused drought to expand slightly southward over the southern peninsula. There was no material change across the D2 drought areas of Alabama and Georgia, with continued below-normal precipitation leading to the introduction of D3 (Extreme Drought) in western North Carolina and a slight expansion eastward of D2 (Severe Drought) in South Carolina and North Carolina. The recent coastal storm allowed D0 dryness to recede from coastal North Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Pacific storms brought beneficial rain and snow to the Pacific Northwest, increasing mountain snow water content by around 3 to 7 percent. The modest improvements were not enough to change the abnormally dry (D0) situation across most of Oregon, Washington, and Idaho and the D1 drought over northeastern Washington, Idaho's Panhandle, and Montana. In southwest Oregon near Crater Lake, snow water content measurements showed February 1 readings to be the 6th driest in 71 years, so this area was increased to D1 drought. California missed most of the rain and snow, so dryness (D0) expanded slightly southward and westward from the Sierra Nevada as well as southward along the Pacific coast from Oregon to just north of San Francisco. Streamflow continued unusually low across northern California, with several locations reporting flows under 10th percentile levels. An area of D0 was introduced in the Los Angeles-San Diego area due to below-normal rainfall and low streamflows.Statewide snow water equivalents as of February 6 averaged 48% of normal, but water storage in reservoirs was near normal.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
