<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20051208</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 5-day period (December 8-13) that may affect areas of dryness or drought include: 1) a quieter precipitation pattern may be on tap for central and coastal California and up into the coastal ranges of Oregon and Washington as well. Cooler weather is forecast for the Pacific NW in general; 2) an unsettled weather pattern is expected to bring relief to southern and southeastern Alaska; 3) because of some cold Canadian air, a mixed bag of winter precipitation is expected in the central and southern Plains, with temperatures pegged to be well below normal; 4) in the Ohio River Valley and Mid-Atlantic, colder-than-normal temperatures are called for along with the potential for favorable precipitation in the drought areas on this weeks map; 5) farther south, heavy rains could lead to the removal of the dryness in northern Florida.</p>
   <p>The 6- to 10-day (December 13-17) outlook from the Climate Prediction Center calls for: 1) a good likelihood of above-normal temperatures coupled with above-normal precipitation across Alaska; 2) the West coast looks to be warm, while the Pacific NW is looking at a dry and cool weather pattern over the same time frame; 3) in the central and southern Plains, a continuation of colder temperatures and a slight chance of above-normal precipitation is predicted; 4) the probability of above-normal precipitation and below-normal temperatures is forecasted for the Great Lakes region; 5) in the South and Southeast, conditions will remain cool and wet along the Gulf Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Good frontal rains continued over parts of the Hawaiian Islands, leading to the removal of D0 on Molokai and Lanai. However, D0 continues to keep a foothold and has expanded on Kauai, Oahu, and the Big Island.</p>
   <p>After a dry week, no changes are reflected in the D0 area in Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>This region is seeing its drought depiction literally freeze dried into place as the air and soils have gone frigid thanks to a flurry of arctic air outbreaks over the past week or so. Snows in the region last week were only enough to hold the status quo and have only served to prevent further deterioration at this point. As the soils freeze up this moisture wont work its way into the profile until it thaws out. As a result, the depiction remains unchanged this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>The dryness continues, especially across the Southern Plains. In particular, Texas and Oklahoma continue to see a deterioration of drought. D1 now stretches across eastern Oklahoma to the west and into the Panhandle of Texas and now covers the entire southern half of the state, as well as east Texas into Louisiana. The month of November was both warm and dry, coming in as the 4 th driest and 11 th warmest on record. Soil moisture levels and winter wheat conditions continue to take a turn for the worse as we wind down 2005. Agricultural conditions continued to worsen across Texas, with 74% of range/pasture lands, 77% of oats, and 58% of winter wheat rated poor to very poor. The picture gets worse in the eastern half of Oklahoma, where D2 and D3 have expanded north and east and have also encroached into western Arkansas, where the year-to-date precipitation is 72% of normal (a 13.03 inch deficit for the year).</p>
   <p>In central and north-central Kansas, very low streamflow levels are being observed, which has led to an expansion of D0 across the region. Streams in this region (including the Republican River Valley in Nebraska) were commonly running below the 15 th percentile, with many at or near new lows (below the 5 th percentile) for the 7-day period ending December 6.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Last week brought some good rains to northern Alabama, northern Georgia, the Carolinas, and the Mid-Atlantic, with totals of 1-4 inches. This brings some refinement to the D0 line, which has been pushed north out of Georgia, Alabama, and South Carolina because of good rains over the past month (125-150% of normal). In addition, the recent wet pattern, cooler temperatures, less demand, and a modest recovery to the reservoirs in the region have led to the removal of D2 from North Carolina. Longer-term deficits and some lingering water supply concerns leave D1 intact, but also reduced, for now. D0 has been reduced in southern and southwestern Virginia and southern North Carolina as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Cool temperatures and a good bit of precipitation (1-4 along the coast and 3-6+ in the foothills and mountains) fell along much of the West coast last week from San Francisco up to Seattle. Heavy precipitation in central and east-central California has led to the reduction and confinement of D0 in the San Joaquin Valley and removal of the D0 altogether in the Sierra Nevada Range in and around Lake Tahoe and down into the Yosemite National Park region. The favorable precipitation has also led to continued improvement along the coastal ranges of Oregon and Washington. A general 1-category improvement is noted in western Oregon and Washington, where D0 has been pushed eastward and D2 was removed from the north-central part of Oregon. The D1 area has also been reduced and pushed to the north in Oregon. In Washington, D2 was reduced, leaving D1 conditions in its wake.</p>
   <p>In Idaho, D1 was removed from the Panhandle while the rest of the state remains unchanged at this time. In Montana, D0 was trimmed in the central part of the state and along the southern border with Wyoming. Just to the south in Wyoming, good snows this water year (since October 1) have led to the removal of D1 in northwestern Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
