<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000120</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecasts call for an increasingly active storm track across the central and southern Plains into the Southeast for next week. Much of the eastern half of the country is expected to receive some precipitation. Moderate amounts (greater than one inch) are possible from Oklahoma to Illinois and Georgia to the Carolinas. Temperatures will again be above normal, with much above normal temperatures across a large area of the northern Plains.</p>
   <p>A developing trough in the western U.S. should bring precipitation across many of the abnormally dry areas in the West. Snowfalls in the mountains will be especially welcomed by skiers and ski resorts.</p>
   <p>Hawaii should experience a gradual improvement to the D1 region during the next few months as seasonal rains continue.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Central and Eastern States">
   <p>Parts of the Northeast and New England saw very wintry conditions during the week, and some locations there finally had their first snowfalls of the season. Toward the end of the period, winter moved into the central Appalachians and the Carolinas in the form of colder temperatures and a mix of wintry precipitation. In most of the areas of the central and eastern U.S. experiencing dryness or drought conditions, very little precipitation fell during the week.</p>
   <p>Concern is mounting about the increasing dryness in the Winter Wheat Belt of the central and southern Plains (southern Nebraska to northern Texas). A combination of very warm temperatures, winds, and recent dryness across both Kansas and Oklahoma have caused soil moisture levels to rapidly decline, and pasture and winter wheat conditions to deteriorate. As a result, the area classified as abnormally dry (D0) covered all the central Plains except for eastern Colorado. The area in the first drought stage (D1) expanded southward to include more of northern Kansas and northwest Missouri.</p>
   <p>For the D2 (severe drought) region in southwestern Minnesota, northwestern Iowa, and eastern Nebraska, the September through December period was the driest on record. This period is critical for soil recharge, and spring precipitation will have to be significantly above normal for the soil moisture levels to rebound enough to support summer crops in the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Little precipitation fell during the week in the Hawaiian Islands, with the exception being parts of the Island of Hawaii. Long-term D1 (first stage drought) conditions continue to cause agricultural impacts and create the potential for wildfires in parts of the state. In Alaska, frigid temperatures accompanied generally light precipitation during the week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Western States">
   <p>systems continued to pound the Pacific Northwest during the week. Precipitation eventually pushed south into central and southern California over the weekend, as well as parts of Nevada, although totals were generally light.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, significant precipitation did not make it to the drier regions of Utah, southern Idaho, Wyoming, Colorado, Arizona, and New Mexico. Snowpack levels in these states are between 20-80% of average for this time of year. As a result, the area described as abnormally dry (D0) expanded into northern Nevada, southern Utah, and central Colorado to account for these low snowpack levels. For example, the statewide snow water equivalent for Colorado as of January 1, 2000 was 44% of average, which was the lowest in at least 19 years.</p>
   <p>The good news for Colorado, and all other states in the West, is that reservoir storage in most areas is running well above the average and ahead of last year's levels. Last year also started dry in the central Rockies, but finished with very plentiful snowfall totals during the spring months.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
