<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20031030</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During October 29 - November 2, little to no precipitation (less than 0.50 inch) is forecast for most areas currently experiencing dryness or drought. The upper air pattern is expected to shift over the contiguous United States setting up a deep trough in the West. Precipitation is forecast for southern portions of Montana, Wyoming and western Colorado. In addition, precipitation is expected across portions of the Midwest region in amounts ranging from 1-3 inches. Below normal temperatures are forecast for much of the drought areas, with above normal temperatures expected in the eastern half of the contiguous United States. For the ensuing 5 days (November 3 - 7), above normal precipitation is expected for the Southwest eastward into the Ohio Valley with below normal precipitation in Oregon, Washington and Idaho. Temperatures are expected to remain below normal across the majority of the drought areas.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Even though primary stations in Alaska did receive precipitation during this drought monitoring period, it was not enough to warrant an improvement in the D0 AH area. In Hawaii, significant rains fell over the island of Kauai and parts of Oahu, but the remaining islands were basically dry during this monitoring period. However, no change was made to the depiction. Puerto Rico received ample precipitation during this period, with reports of 2 - 4 inches in the western section of the island. Although the northeast portion was below normal according to 4 week percentages, there was no change to Puerto Rico's depiction during this drought monitoring period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region, Mississippi Valley, and Plains">
   <p>In the upper peninsula of Michigan, abnormally dry conditions (D0) were introduced to account for degradation in soil moisture. In South Dakota and Minnesota a bridge of D1 was added between the D1 in the two states, due to below normal precipitation and modeled soil moisture deficits. Also in Minnesota, D2 was extended into Wisconsin as according to short and long term blends and modeled soil moisture, and D1 was extended northward in Wisconsin. Extreme drought (D3) was also extended south/southwestward in Iowa, and northeastward in Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>In Arkansas and Louisiana, the D0 that was introduced last drought monitoring period was trimmed away due to 0.5  2.0 inch rains, and was completely erased from the southwestern corner of Mississippi. In Texas, all four drought intensity categories (D0, D1, D2, D3) were extended eastward in north central Texas as reflected in soil moisture and precipitation departures. In Oklahoma, abnormally dry (D0) conditions were extended into the southern half of the state. The D1 conditions were also extended northward into southwestern Oklahoma to account for precipitation departures and very dry KBDI values. There was an area of expansion of severe drought (D2) and extreme drought (D3) in northwestern Kansas and southwestern Nebraska; this is attributed to low amounts of precipitation and reports of low stream flow. Moderate drought (D1) was expanded eastward covering most of the Kansas and Nebraska border, per local reports of no water flowing into Harlan County reservoir. During this time of year, inflows normally exceed outflows in the reservoir. According to October 26 USDA reports of topsoil moisture short to very short (dry to very dry), conditions deteriorated significantly this Drought Monitoring period from Wisconsin and Minnesota, southward across the Plains, to New Mexico and Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Severe drought (D2) was extended southeastward in Wyoming to cover the entire state and is justified by the objective blends and the precipitation departures in that area. The hydrological impacts in Wyoming were also expanded into the southwestern and south central parts of the state due to low reservoir levels and stream flows in the area. New Mexico had continued dryness during the drought monitoring period resulting in the introduction of two new areas of exceptional drought (D4). The southwestern corner and parts of the north central region in New Mexico were the areas of focus due to several stations reporting the driest 33 month period ending in September 2003. The area of D3 in New Mexico was also expanded eastward to account for the May-September 2003 dryness. According to media reports and local expert feedback, the extended drought coupled with a bark beetle infestation was killing New Mexico's state tree, the pinon pine. Many areas around Sante Fe, Los Alamos, and the Sandia Mountains near Albuquerque were experiencing 90 percent pinon die-off. In Arizona, extreme drought (D3) was extended into the northeast part of the state, justified by long and short term precipitation deficits. In California, there were two areas of focus this monitoring period: the Central Valley and the southern portion of the state. Moderate drought (D1) was extended westward in Southern California due to low precipitation and justification from the KBDI and fire danger indicators. Currently 600,000 acres and over 1600 homes have been burned in the area. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions were introduced in the Central Valley in accordance with low precipitation, KBDI and fire danger indices.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
