<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100909</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>During the first 7 days of September, weak cold fronts traversing the northern tier of the contiguous U.S. and tropical activity contributed the most to drought improvement.  At the beginning of the week, low pressure organized in the Nation’s midsection along a stalled front that extended from the upper Great Lakes to the central Great Plains.  As the system developed, it moved northeastward and spread precipitation from eastern North Dakota to the lower Great Lakes, with some isolated showers along the associated trailing cold front.  Simultaneously, Hurricane Earl was located off the coast of the Carolinas.  As the front progressed eastward and Hurricane Earl moved northeastward and weakened, rains spread along the East Coast and into coastal New England.  A quiet weekend gave way to another storm system moving from western Canada into the northern Great Plains.  By September 6, moisture from Tropical Storm Hermine spread northward over the western Gulf Coast and southern Great Plains, and the storm system intensified across the central Great Plains.  Significant rains accompanied each of these systems.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Predictions from the Hydrometeorological Prediction Center indicated rain for a wide area that follows the remnants of Tropical Storm Hermine and stretches from the Southern Great Plains to the lower Ohio River Valley.  Additional rainfall is expected across the northern tier of the country from the Northern Rockies to the Upper Great Lakes.  The Climate Prediction Center 6-10 day outlooks indicate an end to the wet conditions across the Southern Great Plains but favor continued wet and cool conditions across the northern tier of the contiguous 48 states.  Continued dry conditions are expected across the drought areas in the southeast.  Western Alaska is expected to experience wet conditions with the opposite being the case further east</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Colorado, Northern Great Plains, and the Great Lakes">
   <p>Continued dryness prompted the expansion of D0 conditions across the Upper Colorado River and Rio Grande basins.  Across northern Colorado, Vegetation Health Index products, wildfires, and some USGS stream flows in the lower quartile indicated dryness near the surface, while slightly longer term indices have yet to reflect these conditions.  Dryness over the past month across southern Colorado prompted an expansion of D0 in the Rio Grande basin.</p>
   <p>In North Dakota, the abnormal dryness in Grand Forks County was removed based on decent rainfall (1.2 to 2 inches) late in the period.  Additional improvements were made in south-central North Dakota with precipitation amounts ranging from 0.5 to 3.1 inches.  The rainfall almost followed the North Dakota-South Dakota border, so only modest removals of D0 conditions in South Dakota were pursued.</p>
   <p>A small area of abnormal dryness was added to northwestern Nebraska to reflect the lack of rainfall plus warm and windy conditions over the past 60 days.  Farmers have reported trouble sowing wheat and are concerned about a shortened growing period for the winter wheat crop.</p>
   <p>Rainfall (0.5-2.8 inches) that spread across Wisconsin and the Upper Peninsula of Michigan prompted some improvements.  The severe drought in the UP of Michigan was removed and adjacent drought areas were trimmed back from the south.  Additional improvements were made across lower Michigan and Illinois to reflect rains that fell with the passage of weak cold fronts early in the week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>No changes were made to the drought depiction in Hawaii.  Reports from the field are reflective of conditions on the drought monitor.</p>
   <p>A slight expansion of the D0 conditions in north central Alaska was prompted by continued rainfall deficits.  Across the panhandle, surpluses have emerged in the last week as precipitation totals ranged from 1.0 to greater than 5.0 inches.  The abnormal dryness across the panhandle was removed as a result of these surpluses.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mid-Atlantic and Northeast">
   <p>Rainfall associated with Hurricane Earl (0.5 to 4.5 inches) prompted improvements in the drought conditions from Long Island to Maine.  Away from the path of the hurricane, little to no precipitation fell across this region.  Another dry week with above average temperatures (up to 5 degrees F above normal) from the lower Great Lakes to the Carolinas led to some expansions and intensifications of drought conditions.  The most dramatic changes were made in New Jersey and around the panhandle of West Virginia.  In New Jersey, severe drought was introduced to align the drought monitor depiction with North American Land Data Assimilation System (NLDAS) soil moisture values and 3-month standardized precipitation index (SPI) values.  Both of those variables indicated extreme drought, but the depiction was kept to severe drought due to the short duration of the drought as the most recent 30 days are much drier than the most recent 90 days (40% of normal precipitation for the most recent 30 days versus about 70% of normal on a statewide basis for the most recent 90 days).</p>
   <p>Across the panhandle of West Virginia, northwest Maryland and extreme southwest Pennsylvania, extreme drought (D3) conditions were added.  Precipitation for the most recent 30 and 90 days measure in at about 40% of normal, while the SPI, NLDAS soil moisture and stream flows are all below the 5% threshold for indicating extreme drought.  Across northern Virginia, abnormal dryness was expanded from the west toward the District of Columbia to reflect the field reports of deciduous trees dropping leaves and fruit earlier than normal due to lack of recent rainfall.</p>
   <p>Abnormal dryness and moderate drought were also expanded into eastern Pennsylvania and across Delaware, where the entire state is now experiencing abnormal dryness or moderate drought.   Dropping lake levels and scorched lawns are becoming more common across this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Across the Carolinas, temperatures above 90 degF and a continued lack of rainfall drove an expansion of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) across both the western and eastern portions of the state.  Rainfall from Hurricane Earl was restricted to eastern North Carolina’s Outer Banks (up to 4.5 inches reported) while the rest of the state reported less than an inch, which did little to alleviate drought.  SPI for the most recent 3 months indicates an expansion of the severe drought conditions already present across the eastern half of Virginia, while NLDAS soil moisture values indicate the most intense drought conditions extend into North Carolina.  SPI-6 and SPI-9 (SPI over the most recent 6- and 9-month periods, respectively) indicate widespread D2 conditions across the southern Appalachians but SPI3 indicates no worse than D0 across most of North Carolina, as the extreme drought conditions over the last 3 months were confined southward.</p>
   <p>Northeastern Florida continued to experience dry conditions.  Since May, the hardest hit areas remained Brevard and Indian River Counties with rainfall deficits at Titusville, Melbourne, and Vero Beach running around 10 to 12 inches below normal (45-60 percent of normal).  Water level reports released at the end of August show well levels across these counties running around 40-60 percent of normal, with isolated spots around 20-40% of normal.  Summer rainfall rankings showed this was the driest summer on record for Orlando and Titusville, while Vero Beach ranked 3rd driest and Melbourne 6th driest.  However, rainfall from May-August ranked Melbourne as the driest ever observed during this period.</p>
   <p>Slight expansions of D0 across portions of Alabama, Georgia and Mississippi were made to reflect the continued overall dry conditions marked by brief periods of rain.  Reassessments of the status in Alabama prompted the removal of some abnormal dryness and adjust the depicted moderate drought to more accurately reflect the SPI3, SPI6 and NLDAS soil moisture values.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Great Plains">
   <p>Tropical Storm Hermine brought copious amounts of rainfall to many portions of southern and central Texas.  Reports ranged from 1.0 to more than 6.0 inches.  Improvements were made along the path of greatest rainfall while degradations were made in northeastern Texas to reflect the areas where the rain missed the dry areas before the September 7 12 UTC cutoff.</p>
   <p>In southeastern Missouri, continued dryness cause an intensification of the drought status.  The blend of short-term objective drought indicators, SPI and NLDAS soil moisture all indicate this area should be downgraded to D2 status, with some locals drawing comparisons to the 1950s.  Additionally, agricultural impacts ranged from stunted crop growth, to lack of germination for crabgrass, to supplementation of feed for livestock due to poor pasture conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
