<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040506</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During May 6  10, most of the contiguous 48 states will be warmer to much warmer than normal, with daily highs forecast to average 15F to 20F above normal in the west-central Plains and the central Rockies. In addition, most areas of dryness and drought should receive little or no precipitation, with a few notable exceptions. Between 1 and 3 inches of rain are expected northern Minnesota, southwestern Wisconsin, southern Michigan, northern Indiana, and adjacent Ohio. Meanwhile, light to moderate totals (0.1 to 1.0 inch) should dampen central Oregon, eastern Washington, the Idaho Panhandle, northwestern Montana, the northern and eastern Dakotas, and the remaining dry areas in the middle Mississippi Valley and lower Midwest. Above-normal precipitation is expected to be more prevalent during the ensuing 5 days (May 11  15), with odds favoring wetter-than-normal weather across the northern tier of the country from the Intermountain West through the Great Lakes region, and from the eastern Plains eastward to the Appalachians. In contrast, below-normal precipitation appears likely in the dry areas in Alaska, and from the southern half of the High Plains westward through the southern half of California. Meanwhile, warmer-than-normal weather has a good chance of covering the areas of ongoing dryness in the southeastern Rockies, the southern High Plains, Oklahoma, the northern Ohio Valley, and the Southeast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Light precipitation was observed in southern sections of the D0 region, with little or none reported farther north. As a result, D0 conditions persisted.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Moderate precipitation (1 to locally 4 inches) fell on southern and northeastern Indiana, much of southern Michigan, northwestern Missouri and adjacent Kansas near Kansas City, and parts of central Illinois. Between 0.5 and 1.0 inch fell on a band just north and west of these areas, but lesser amounts (if any) were reported in areas from northern Illinois, southern Iowa, and western Kansas northward to the Canadian border and eastward through the northern half of the High Plains.</p>
   <p>The precipitation eliminated D0 conditions in southern Indiana, and reduced or eliminated former D0 to D1 conditions in lower northwestern Missouri. However, moisture was not enough to re-classify the D1 area across southern Michigan and northern Indiana, and in fact increasing dryness led to the introduction of D0 across broad sections of southern Iowa, central Illinois, and adjacent Indiana. Most of these areas have received 1 to 4 inches less than normal precipitation in the last 3 months, with 30-day anomalies of -2 inches or lower observed in parts of southern Iowa and northern Indiana.</p>
   <p>The dry week left last weeks conditions generally unchanged over most of the upper Mississippi Valley, northern Plains, and central High Plains, but some areas deteriorated. D2 expanded into parts of southwestern South Dakota as well as southeastern Minnesota. Precipitation totals for both Rochester, MN and Minneapolis, MN were more than 9 inches below normal since July 2003. Elsewhere, D3 conditions were introduced in southeastern Montana, east-central Wyoming, and a large area in central South Dakota. Less than 25% of normal precipitation in the last 30 days, and less than half of normal in the last 90 days, was reported at many locations in the new D3 regions.</p>
   <p>Broad sections of the northern and central Plains reported short or very short subsoil moisture, according to the National Agricultural Statistics Service, and topsoil moisture is similarly lacking in northern sections. In South Dakota and Montana, between 55% and 70% of topsoils are short or very short of moisture, as are 70% to 75% of subsoils. Farther south, the proportion of dry topsoils is lower (about 45% across Nebraska and Wyoming, and 28% across Colorado), but subsoil moisture shortages are prevalent (65% to 80% short or very short across the same 3 states). This dryness has been affecting the development of winter and spring wheat in the Plains states.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Copious rains benefited areas of dryness and drought, particularly in southern and eastern parts of the region. Between 2 and 6 inches of rain fell on many locations across southern Alabama, northwestern Florida, southwestern Georgia, and the immediate Atlantic coastline, generally improving the former D0 to D1 conditions by 1 category.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, moderate rainfall was the rule, and relief was much more spotty. D0 conditions were eliminated in most of Mississippi, and conditions improved to D0 over interior upstate South Carolina, but otherwise last weeks rains were not enough to improve drought classifications.</p>
   <p>Rainfall was sufficient to eliminate 30-day precipitation deficits in almost all areas, but longer-term moisture shortages (2 to 9 months) persisted, and remained quite marked in some areas. Many locations away from the Atlantic and Gulf of Mexico coastlines were still 3 to locally 9 inches below normal since early March, and 6-month totals 10 to 15 inches below normal were reported at several sites. Streamflows in all but southwestern Georgia and through much of upstate South Carolina had already dropped back below the 25 th percentile for this time of year by May 5, with several observations reported below the 10 th percentile. In short, the rainfall was helpful, but more is needed for significant relief to occur in the remaining D0 and D1 areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Scattered locations from western Montana southward through Colorado and part of eastern Utah reported 0.5 to 1.5 inches of precipitation, but unseasonable warmth with little or no precipitation was the rule elsewhere. The precipitation did prompt improvement to D2 conditions for a part of central Utah, but elsewhere conditions remained unchanged or deteriorated. D4 conditions expanded northeastward into part of central Montana, where Great Falls and Cut Bank appear on course for their 2 nd and 3 rd driest water years, respectively, in over 100 years of record. Farther south and west, D1 to D3 conditions expanded westward in the Salmon River Basin of Idaho, where high-elevation March-April precipitation was a record low for the 20+ years that such records have been collected. Elsewhere, D3 conditions expanded into parts of western Wyoming and northeast Utah, and conditions declined to D2 in areas just south of the Great Salt Lake. According to reports from the Natural Resources Conservation Service, the Bear River watershed is experiencing the lowest water levels since the 1930s.</p>
   <p>Farther south, recent heat and wind in Nevada and southern California, in addition to several years of persistently sub-par precipitation, have led to unseasonably early very high to extreme fire danger assessments, according to the National Interagency Coordination Center. Several fires have already singed parts of southwestern California, where the elevated fire danger is unprecedented for this time of year.</p>
   <p>In addition, the multi-year dry spell has left groundwater levels in southern California unfavorably low. According to the United States Geological Survey, a recent groundwater level of 174.1 feet was reported at one Los Angeles well, which was below the 8th percentile threshold based on periodic quasi-monthly data back to July 1932 (the record low was 188.45 feet in March 1991). HOWEVER, it should be emphasized that water supplies in California are near typical historic levels for this time of year, thus currently water shortages are not a concern.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
