<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000504</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Below-normal precipitation and normal to above-normal temperatures are expected during the next two weeks, which could increase drought conditions across parts of the Midwest, especially in the D2 regions of Missouri, Iowa, and Nebraska.</p>
   <p>Once the slow-moving storm system affecting the Gulf Coast (May 1-3) exits the region, below-normal precipitation is expected for all of the South Central and Southeastern states, except for normal amounts in southern Florida. No precipitation is expected along the eastern Texas, Louisiana, and Alabama coasts for the 6-10 day period May 9-13. No precipitation is also forecasted in the D3 region in western Texas for the same period.</p>
   <p>A continuation of warm and dry weather is expected in the next two weeks across most of the western United States. A region of "much above normal" temperatures covers southern Wyoming; all of Utah, Colorado, and Arizona; and the western half of New Mexico. The exception to this will be in the Pacific Northwest, where above-normal precipitation is expected, extending into the D0 regions of Montana and North Dakota.</p>
   <p>Little relief is expected in the D1 regions of Hawaii, and below-normal precipitation is expected for Puerto Rico during the next two weeks.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Little precipitation fell during the week across the Hawaiian Islands. Long-term D1 (first stage drought) conditions continue to cause agricultural impacts and create the potential for wildfires in parts of the state. In Puerto Rico, abnormally dry (D0) conditions continue along the northern side of the island. San Juan finished April with 1.20 inches of rain (33% of normal) and has had 5.36 inches since January (49% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>April saw drier than normal conditions across a large area of the Midwest. Parts of northeastern and southeastern Minnesota, central Iowa, and most of Missouri had less than 50% of normal precipitation for the month. A considerable portion of Missouri was below 25% of normal, with monthly departures between 2 and 4 inches. Kansas City (MO) received a record low 0.65 inches of rain for the month, and many counties in the state had monthly totals of less than 0.50 inches. As a result, both the D2 region (severe drought) and the D1 region (first stage drought) expanded to the west and south. The D0 region also expanded in northern Minnesota to the Lake Superior shoreline and in eastern Kansas because of the abnormally dry conditions for April.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, a third consecutive week of generous rainfall decreased the D2, D1, and D0 regions in western Nebraska. The rest of the Corn Belt experiencing drought conditions received only light amounts of rain during the past week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>No precipitation fell during the last week for the Extreme Drought (D3) region in southeast Louisiana. Preliminary data shows that the January through April period was the driest on record for the Southwest, South Central, and East Central Climate Divisions in the state, and second driest in the Southeast Climate Division. Dry conditions continued along the Gulf Coast, and the area of D2 expanded to include southern Alabama and the Florida Panhandle. In Arkansas, the D1 category extended farther south in response to increasingly dry conditions there. A small area in the northern part of the state fell into the severe drought (D2) category.</p>
   <p>A major storm system April 30 and May 1 produced significant rainfalls across Oklahoma and the eastern half of Texas. As a result of these rains and good year-to-date totals, areas in the North Central and South Central Climate Divisions in Texas had the D2 (severe drought) classification reduced to a first stage drought (D1) classification. This included the Austin and San Antonio areas. However, with long-term drought concerns continuing, D1 regions remained unchanged in eastern Texas. The D0 classification was removed from the Low Rolling Plains Division in north central Texas around Wichita Falls.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Western States">
   <p>Little or no precipitation fell across the existing drought and dry regions in the western states during the past week. Extreme drought (D3) remains in western Texas. In Arizona, the D0 classification was extended into central and northeastern parts of the state and D1 extended to the Phoenix area because of the abnormally low winter precipitation totals and little relief in April. The wildfire threat is high across Arizona and New Mexico, and the dryness is impacting ranching interests. The hydrological situation, including available water supplies, remains good in Arizona, however.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
