<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050630</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2-week period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a cold front moving through the Midwest was bringing cooler weather and scattered thunderstorms during June 28-30, but rainfall amounts for June 29-July 4 were forecast to total just 0.25 to 0.50 inches over the drought areas; 2) thunderstorms occurring on Tuesday and Wednesday, June 28-29, brought dryness relief to many areas from the mid-Atlantic into New England, and more rain was forecast with frontal passage later in the week; 3) near-normal temperatures were forecast to continue through week 2 from Missouri to Ohio, but rainfall was forecast to be normal to below-normal; 4) hot, dry weather was forecast for the 5-day period from June 29 to July 4 over Texas, southern Oklahoma, southern Arkansas, and western Louisiana, but above-normal rainfall was forecast for the 6-10 day period and the 8-14 day period for most of this region.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska ">
   <p>Warm, dry weather led to development of D0 dryness in the northern Interior Basin. As of June 28, there were five large fires burning in northern Alaska and one in southern Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii ">
   <p>Despite additional showers, D0 dryness persisted over the Big Island and western parts of Maui and Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East ">
   <p>D0 dryness developed in West Virginia and extended into Virginia and Maryland, linking with the dry area in Pennsylvania. On June 27, heavy rains alleviated dryness in New Jersey, but D0 remained in the lower Hudson Valley and adjacent parts of New England. Although abundant rains hit parts of North Carolina, most of the D0 area introduced last week picked up less than 1 inch, so dryness continued over interior eastern parts of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Abnormally hot weather accompanied by spotty rains resulted in persisting or worsening drought conditions for most of the region. Daily maximum temperatures hit the mid-90s F during June 23-27 from Illinois, Indiana, and Ohio southward. Heavy rains exceeding 2 inches reduced D1 drought in southern Wisconsin, but dry weather led to D1 development to the north in the Oshkosh area. Hot, dry weather led to D2 expansion across northern and central Illinois and D1 expansion into southeastern Illinois and southeastern Iowa. Month-to-date rainfall across central and northern Illinois was less than an inch, and this follows the states third driest March-May period in the past 111 years of record keeping. USDA reported that 93 percent of Illinois farmland was short topsoil moisture. To the east, D1 drought continued across northern Indiana, and D0 expanded across eastern Kentucky and southern Ohio.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Heavy rains in North Dakota reduced D1 drought and D0 dryness in western parts of the state. The moisture also improved surface moisture in western Nebraska and western Kansas, but high temperatures and only scattered showers led to D0 development in southeast Nebraska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Parts of Missouri reported over 1 inch of rain, but less rain fell over southeastern areas southward into Arkansas and Louisiana and east Texas. Extreme D3 drought developed in a small portion of southeastern Missouri and extended southward into northeastern Arkansas. Another area of extreme D3 drought developed in northeastern Texas and included adjacent parts of Oklahoma, Arkansas, and Louisiana. Longview, in northeast Texas, has experienced the second driest March-June since 1902. D0, D1 and D2 drought expanded in Texas, with D1 stretching into the Blacklands. Farther south, D3 developed across the Lower Valley. As of June 28, year-to-date rainfall in Brownsville totaled just 2.85 inches versus the normal amount of 10.68 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Another week of wet weather led to slight reduction of D1 drought in eastern Montana and D0 dryness in northern Montana. Monthly rainfall amounts of 4-6 inches and greater helped to end D0 dryness in east-central Montana. Widespread showers had little impact on lingering areas of long-term drought in the Southwest, but did reduce the fire danger in some areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
