<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000427</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Normal to above-normal temperatures and generally normal rainfall will result in little significant change to drought in the next 2 weeks.</p>
   <p>Below-normal rains are expected over the Southeast, with below-normal temperatures. No significant change in drought is expected in the next 2 weeks. Above-normal rains are anticipated from northern Texas into southern Nebraska, but current drought areas will largely be spared. With above-normal temperatures forecast from Texas to Missouri, some intensification of dryness is likely in this region.</p>
   <p>No significant change expected in the next 2 weeks.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name=" ">
   <p>Normal to above-normal temperatures and generally normal rainfall will result in little significant change to drought in the next 2 weeks.</p>
   <p>Below-normal rains are expected over the Southeast, with below-normal temperatures. No significant change in drought is expected in the next 2 weeks. Above-normal rains are anticipated from northern Texas into southern Nebraska, but current drought areas will largely be spared. With above-normal temperatures forecast from Texas to Missouri, some intensification of dryness is likely in this region.</p>
   <p>No significant change expected in the next 2 weeks.</p>
   <p>No significant changes expected in the next 2 weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought continued leeward areas of Hawaii. At Honolulu, year-to-date rainfall totaled 2.17 inches (23% of normal). Abnormal dryness persisted over the north coast of Puerto Rico and expanded southward into the interior reservoir areas. San Juan's year-to-date rainfall totaled 5.22 inches (53% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Heavy rains (2 to 4 inches) fell during April 19-21, significantly relieving dryness from eastern Iowa to Michigan's Lower Peninsula. The moisture ended drought in much of Wisconsin, northern Illinois, and parts of Michigan's Lower Peninsula. The rains also reduced drought from Iowa to northern Indiana, but left drought little changed in Nebraska and western Iowa, where rainfall totaled generally under 1 inch. A second storm brought additional moisture to the southern portions of the Corn Belt on April 23-25 , while another system delivered locally heavy rain to central Nebraska. As of April 25, severe drought persisted from eastern Nebraska through western Iowa and into central Illinois and parts of northern Indiana. Additionally, severe drought expanded southward into much of eastern Missouri. Cumulative rainfall since July has been 10 inches below normal over a large part of southern Missouri, with year-to-date rainfall as little as 57% of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South-Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>Heavy thunderstorms on April 23-24 brought over 1 inch of rain to much of the South from Arkansas and Louisiana eastward to Georgia and Tennessee. As a result, drought retreated slightly southward toward the Gulf of Mexico. Due to large accumulated rainfall deficits, severe drought persisted in southern Louisiana, western Georgia, southeastern Alabama, and northern and central Florida. Southwestern Louisiana has measured as little as 35% of normal rainfall so far this year. With rainfall deficits around 20 inches since last July, southeastern Louisiana was added to the D3 (extreme drought) category. Heavy thunderstorms left up to 7 inches of rain in southern Georgia on April 24, bringing local drought relief, but the area affected was relatively small, and drought persists over most of the state. In Texas, hot, dry weather caused drought to intensify to extreme levels (D3) in the southwest (Trans Pecos). The government of Mexico has recently declared drought emergencies for states bordering Texas. D1 to D2 drought continued elsewhere in central and southern Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Drought persisted over southern New Mexico and extreme southeastern Arizona, while abnormal dryness remained over large parts of Montana and parts of northern Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
