<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20051006</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During October 6  10, 2005, there is a good chance for widespread heavy rain in many of the dry areas in the East as Tropical Storm Tammy interacts with a strong frontal system pushing eastward from the Mississippi Valley. Most locations from the Appalachians eastward are expected to get at least an inch of rain, with totals of 2 to locally 7 inches expected in a broad area from the Carolinas northward through New England. Elsewhere, moderate totals of 0.5 to 1.5 inches are forecast for portions of the northern Great Plains, High Plains, central Rockies, northwestern Washington and central Idaho. In contrast, only a few tenths of an inch at most are anticipated from the central and eastern Plains eastward to the western Appalachians, in the Great Basin, across parts of the Southwest, and at scattered locations in the northern Rockies and Intermountain West. The ensuing 5 days (October 11  15) should feature above-normal precipitation again along the Eastern Seaboard from the Carolinas northward, in southern Florida, across most of the Great Lakes and upper Mississippi Valley, over the central and northern Great Plains, and in the central and southern High Plains. Meanwhile, the odds favor below-normal precipitation in the lower Ohio Valley, much of the middle and lower Mississippi Valley, the ArkLaTex region, the northern Rockies, the Intermountain West, and parts of the Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Recent subtle increases in precipitation, along with the continued seasonal decline in temperatures, brought an end to D0 conditions in northeastern parts of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Locally heavy rains eliminated D0 conditions in Oahu, but light to locally moderate precipitation elsewhere was not enough to change the D0 conditions observed in other parts of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>From the Carolinas northward through southern New England, another week of below-normal precipitation allowed dryness and drought to persist or intensify. Little or no precipitation fell from southern New Jersey and southeastern Pennsylvania southward through most of North Carolina and central South Carolina, and totals exceeding 0.5 inch were limited to parts of southern New England, western Pennsylvania, eastern Ohio and Kentucky, and a few isolated sites in the Carolinas. As a result, several locations reported new record low September rainfall totals, including Columbia, SC, which received no measurable precipitation for the month. In addition, new records below 0.1 inch were established in Florence, SC and Richmond, VA while Washington, DC, Martinsburg, WV and New York/La Guardia, NY all set records with less than 0.4 inch. The prior record low September totals had stood for more than a century in Richmond, VA and Washington, DC.</p>
   <p>The continuing dryness led to the expansion of D0A conditions into eastern Tennessee, central Kentucky, and western West Virginia, and D1A conditions pushed into south-central Pennsylvania, eastern Kentucky, and much of western Virginia. Meanwhile, D2AH conditions were introduced from south-central Virginia southward through the central Carolinas, where subnormal precipitation totals date back more than 2 years.</p>
   <p>Farther south, between 1 and 3 inches of rain were observed from the Tampa, FL vicinity southward and in part of north-central Florida, but other locations in and near the D0 area in Florida received only 0.5 inch or less. This led to a reduction in the northward extent of D0 conditions, but also to some westward expansion along the northwestern Gulf Coast. A new dryness record for the July-August-September period was established at Tampa, FL, where the 3-month rainfall total was more than a foot below normal, and 30 percent (3.65 inches) less than the previous record. In addition, Bradenton, FL set a new record low September precipitation total with just over an inch of rain (less than half their previous September record).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The High Plains, Rockies, and Far West">
   <p>Heavy precipitation, with many locations reporting 2 to 6 inches, brought some improvement to the drought and dryness affecting central and western Washington, northwestern Oregon, the northern Idaho Panhandle, and northwestern Montana. As a result, the Drought Monitor depiction improved by 1 classification through almost all of these areas. Elsewhere, precipitation totaled 1 to 3 inches in the remainder of the Pacific Northwest and northern Intermountain West, and at many locations in northwestern Wyoming, southeastern Idaho, northeastern Nevada, eastern Utah, and northern New Mexico. Significant and widespread improvement did not result from this precipitation due to the exceptionally long-term nature of the dryness affecting the region, but some localized changes seemed appropriate, including the elimination of D0H in part of southeastern Utah and central New Mexico, and improvement to D0H in north-central New Mexico.</p>
   <p>The end of September is also the end of the water year as tabulated across the West, and despite the weeks heavy precipitation, several locations indicated that 2004/05 was one of the 10 driest water years on record, including Portland, Salem, and Eugene, OR.</p>
   <p>Isolated moderate precipitation, at best, was observed last week across the rest of the United States from the High Plains westward to the Pacific Ocean, keeping areas of dryness and drought essentially intact. East-central Colorado and adjacent Kansas were the only exceptions as D0H conditions expanded into these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Rainfall totals of 1 to locally 4 inches fell on much of northern and eastern Missouri, central and parts of northeastern Illinois, northwestern Indiana, northern and western Michigan, and northern Wisconsin, leading to the erosion of D0AH to D2AH conditions in parts of these regions. In contrast, most locations across Nebraska, Iowa, northern Illinois, and southern Wisconsin received less than 0.5 inch, resulting in slight expansions of the D0AH to D3AH regions relative to last week. Most notably, D3AH pushed further into parts of northwestern Illinois and southeastern Iowa. Over the course of the last 3 years, accumulated precipitation totals are more than 20 inches below normal in sizeable portions of north-central Illinois, northwestern Illinois, and east-central Iowa.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Between 0.5 and 2.0 inches of rain provided limited relief for the dry areas near the middle Red River Valley, and similar totals were reported at isolated locations in southeastern Texas and northern Arkansas. Unfortunately, little or no precipitation fell on most other locations in the region. As a result, D0AH conditions expanded into southwestern Missouri and adjacent sections of Oklahoma and Arkansas, a large portion of central Texas, and portions of the Big Bend and adjacent New Mexico. Short-term moisture deficits increased significantly in the new dry areas in Texas, and year-to-date precipitation totals remained below 5 inches in much of the D0AH region in the western Big Bend and adjacent New Mexico. In addition, College Station, TX broke a 75-year-old record by reporting only 0.02 inch of rain for the month of September.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
