<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020926</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecasted weather that may affect dry and drought areas the next 5 days (September 26-30) include: 1) A weakened but large Tropical Storm Isidore will bring heavy rains to the central Gulf Coast early in the period, then race north and east ahead of a cold front and drop heavy rains on the Delta, Tennessee and eastern Ohio Valleys, and the Northeast. Lighter amounts should fall east of the Appalachians, namely the mid-Atlantic, Carolina, and Georgia coastal Plains. 2) A cold front that sweeps Isidore northeastward should generate some showers from the central Plains northeastward into the upper Midwest. 3) Once Isidore and the front exit during this weekend, high pressure should prevail, bringing dry and cool weather to much of the Nation. 4) Tropical systems Lili and Kyle may be a factor late in the period for Florida.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6-10 day (October 1-5) outlook calls for wetter-than-normal conditions from South Carolina northward into Maine and the northern half of the Plains, and subnormal precipitation in the remainder of the western three-quarters of the Nation. Below-normal temperatures are expected in the northern Rockies, the northern two-thirds of the Plains, the upper Midwest, and Great Lakes region, with warm weather predicted in the Southwest, Rio Grande Valley, and western half of the Gulf Coast.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>While typical light showers dampened orographically-favored windward locations, mostly dry weather, with isolated light showers (less than 0.10 inches), fell on parts of southwestern Oahu and western Maui, maintaining abnormal dryness, while mostly dry weather kept D0(W) across western Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>A series of strong cold fronts produced severe thunderstorms, including damaging tornadoes to Indiana and Ohio on the 20th, but also brought welcome rains to most of the Midwest. In the Missouri Bootheel, western Kentucky, southern Illinois and Indiana, and southeastern Michigan, over 2 inches of rain (locally 4-6 inches) eliminated abnormal dryness or diminished drought by one category, while lower amounts (1-2 inches) prevented further deterioration of conditions as weekly temperatures averaged 2 to 4F above normal. Some parts, however, received under an inch of rain, including eastern Ohio, northern Missouri, and north-central lower Michigan. In particular, the latter two areas have accumulated 30-day deficits of 2 to 4 inches, or about 25% of normal precipitation, and D0 and D1 were drawn for these areas. Even with the rains, topsoil moisture still remained short to very short (IN 64%; MI 64%; MO 66%; and OH 89%), according to the USDA/NASS.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Late in the period, a slow-moving cold front triggered showers and thunderstorms, mostly in central portions of New England and the mid-Atlantic, with the largest totals (2 to 4 inches) falling on the Appalachians and along coastal Massachusetts. As a result, abnormal dryness was alleviated in south-central New York, eastern Massachusetts, and northern Vermont, and moderate to severe drought was eased in across central Pennsylvania and southern West Virginia. Elsewhere, however, rainfall was much lighter west and east of the Appalachians (weekly amounts less than 0.5 inches), and with temperatures averaging 5 to 10F above normal, drought conditions were maintained, or slightly increased (southeastern Pennsylvania, southern New Jersey, northeastern Maryland, central Virginia). In the aforementioned areas, extreme hydrological drought remained as numerous USGS-monitored rivers hit record to near-record low (less than 10th percentile) flows for the 7-day period ending September 23, while several ground-water monitoring wells in central Maryland hit September record lows. According to USDA/NASS, September 22 mid-Atlantic pasture conditions remained very poor to poor in NJ (86%), PA (80%), VA (60%), and MD (51%), and farther north, Maine jumped from 70 to 86% in a week. Additionally, short-term dryness (1-2 inch deficits) along the eastern Great Lakes region and in Maine prompted an eastward shift in the Hydro(W) line.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>With intense Hurricane Isidore slowly churning in the lower Gulf of Mexico, abundant tropical moisture flowed northward and interacted with several slow-moving cold fronts, generating widespread, numerous showers and thunderstorms from eastern Kansas southward to eastern Texas and then eastward to the western Carolinas, and along the North Carolina coast. Most locations in the South received over 2 inches of rain, with over 4 inches in the southern Appalachians, northern Delta, southeastern Texas, and southwestern Louisiana. As a result, the Drought Monitor map registered a one category improvement as did most drought indices and blends. In contrast, much lower totals (&lt;1 inch) fell on the eastern Georgia and Carolinas Coastal Plains, and most of Florida, but these areas received very heavy rains in late August, so conditions were status quo. Even with the recent rains, the average weekly (September 17-23) USGS streamflows were still in the lower tenth percentile in most of the Carolina Piedmont, and 50% of the North Carolina pastures were rated very poor to poor.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Plains">
   <p>Cool and unsettled weather in the Northwest, along with scattered thundershowers in the Rockies, maintained drought conditions, but also kept large, active wild fires to a minimum, although the wild fire danger still remained moderate to high in many Western States. Unseasonably heavy rains (1 to 3 inches) fell on the Black Hills of South Dakota, northern New Mexico and southern Colorado, and southwestern Oregon, providing some slight reduction of drought/dryness in these 3 areas. Another week of near to above-normal precipitation (0.5 to 1 inch) across most of New Mexico (plus adequate July and August monsoon rains) also eased drought conditions somewhat. In the Plains, mostly dry weather was tempered by temperatures averaging 3 to 6F below normal.</p>
   <p>In contrast, the Southwest experienced seasonably dry weather with above-normal temperatures, with two large, active wild fires reported in California. Significant hydrological drought improvement (or deterioration) is not likely to occur in the West and Rockies until the 2002-2003 wet season (November-March) is well underway.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
