<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20101125</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Precipitation this week fell mainly in two swaths.  The first went from the Ohio River Valley up into portions of northern New England.  The second was from the southern Pacific Coast into the Pacific Northwest and extending into North Dakota, Wyoming, and Colorado.  Composite estimates show coastal Oregon and Washington received over two inches of precipitation, with some estimates over eight inches.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>There is an enhanced probability of precipitation throughout the eastern U.S. and in the Pacific Northwest early in the November 25-29, 2010 time period.  Later in the period, chances of precipitation are highest along the Pacific Coast. Temperatures are generally forecast to be normal to below normal throughout most of the western U.S. as well as from the extreme southern Plains up into the mid-Atlantic.  Above normal temperatures are generally limited to a swath from the southern Plains into the Midwest.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (November 30 – December 4, 2010), the odds favor cooler-than-normal conditions from the northern High Plains as well as in the Southeast and mid-Atlantic.  Warmer-than-normal conditions are expected in northern New England.  The odds of above-normal precipitation extend throughout the Pacific Northwest and into the Rockies.  A second area of above normal precipitation is forecast from the South, to the Ohio Valley and through New England.  Odds favor below-normal precipitation in the southern Plains, and in Florida south of the Panhandle. Odds favor normal to below normal temperatures and normal to below normal precipitation throughout Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought conditions remained unchanged across Alaska and Puerto Rico this week.  In Hawaii, conditions of Extreme Drought (D3) were alleviated on Kauai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>In the Southeast, Abnormal Dryness (D0) and Moderate (D1) and Severe (D2) drought expanded throughout much of Georgia and the entire state is now at least abnormally dry (D0).  Conversely, Severe (D2) and Extreme (D3) drought was alleviated by the recent rains in southwest Alabama.  Abnormal Dryness (D0) and Moderate (D1) drought expanded slightly in the Carolinas.  Recent rains alleviate some Abnormal Dryness (D0) near central Pennsylvania but areas in the northwest part of the state and in southwest New York began to experience Abnormal Dryness (D0) this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Abnormal Dryness (D0) and Moderate Drought (D1) continue to be experienced through the Central Plains, from southwest South Dakota down to southern Texas.  Dry conditions have intensified in throughout central Texas. Severe (D2) Drought was introduced this week into the east-central part of the state</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The effect of continued beneficial precipitation continued to be experienced in the West.  Lingering Severe (D2) Drought in Oregon and California was removed and Abnormal Dryness (D0) and Moderate Drought (D1) were reduced in the area and extending into northern Nevada.  Some low reservoir levels are still being experienced in the area.   Snow in Colorado and Wyoming has also alleviated Abnormal Dryness (D) and Moderate Drought (D1) in the western parts of both states.</p>
   <p>According to local observers, the Steamboat Ski Area in Colorado has opened all ski runs, from base to top, for the first time ever before Thanksgiving.  Ski areas around Lake Tahoe are also opening trails, at least for a few days this week, due to the abundance of snow.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
