<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000921</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect some of the dry or drought areas across the nation include: 1) The first shot of cold Canadian air is expected to push through the Rockies and Northern Plains and into the Southeast over the weekend, kicking off high winds, snow and locally heavy rains in some areas; and 2) Tropical Depression 12 and the strong cold front coming down from the north will bring much needed moisture to a large area of the Gulf Coast states and the Southeast over the next few days. Generous totals (2 to 5+) could be seen (and very much welcomed) in areas of southeast Texas, Louisiana, Mississippi, Alabama, Georgia, Florida and the Carolinas. This would seem to be just what the doctor ordered precipitation-wise in getting this region off to a good start this fall.</p>
   <p>The seasonal U.S. Drought Outlook (for the period ending in December 2000) issued by NOAA on September 15th calls for likely improvement over much of the drought affected areas in the Plains and the Gulf Coast states. Improvement may also be seen in the West in Utah, Wyoming, Idaho and Montana. Hawaii is also expected to slowly improve over the coming three months. Drought is likely to persist in west Texas and may redevelop in the Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Rains over the past month or so have gradually eased drought conditions in the Hawaiian Islands. Although extreme drought (D3) has retreated from this region, severe drought (D2 A,F) still remains over some leeward areas. Long-term deficits over the last year are still impressive around the state with Lihue, Kauai showing a 20 inch deficit while Hilo, Hawaii has a 33 inch deficit. Abnormally dry (D0) and first stage drought (D1) conditions continue along the northern coast of Puerto Rico as well, although there have been signs of improvement here lately due to increased tropical activity.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>The inauspicious start to fall continued in the Plains as hot and dry weather dominated the weather picture here while cooler and wetter weather settled into the Midwest and the Great Lakes states.</p>
   <p>While this is good for harvesting activities, it is a double edged sword in that the warm and dry start to fall following on the heels of a dry 12-month period and/or hot and dry previous two months have many concerned about moisture conditions for hard red winter wheat planting throughout the entire Plains region. If rains dont come by mid-October, this crop will have some major obstacles to overcome. Most areas of the Plains (through the middle of September) have seen less than 25% of normal precipitation going back to August 1st. In several areas, this in addition to the deficits they have accumulated since last fall.</p>
   <p>The need for soil moisture and water level recharge during this fall through spring period will be even more critical as most areas in the region are more vulnerable after already seeing drought hang on for the better part of a year (or more) now.</p>
   <p>The continued warm and dry pattern has led to an expansion of severe drought (D2) eastward out of Nebraska and into parts of western Iowa. This has also led to an expansion of the extreme drought (D3) region within Nebraska as well. Severe drought (D2) has pushed farther south and east in Kansas and has also reappeared in south central Missouri. The Black Hills region of South Dakota is now experiencing first stage (D1) drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>While beneficial rains fell earlier in the week along coastal areas of the Gulf Coast states, it was Hurricane Gordon who stole the headlines bringing heavy rains to Florida and parts of the Southeast. In Florida, the welcomed rains helped to push severe drought (D2 W) farther north. All-in-all, though, Gordons drought impact was relatively weak as rainfall totals did little to eradicate long-term deficits across much of the region. Ironically in fact, the rains have proven to be a nuisance for those trying to harvest peanuts, cotton and other crops in the areas where the rains didnt come when they were needed most.</p>
   <p>Extreme drought (D3) along the southeast coast of Texas was downgraded to severe drought (D2), as was also the case across the coastal areas of Louisiana, Mississippi, Alabama, the Florida Panhandle, and southwestern Georgia. Not all areas saw improvement, however, as severe drought (D2) has continued pressing northward out of Texas and Louisiana into parts of Oklahoma, Arkansas, and Tennessee. The threat of wildfires remains high across a great deal of this region as we head into windier weather associated with the change of seasons.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Much above normal temperatures returned to most of the drought affected areas of the western United States. Rains were welcomed in northern Idaho and to a lesser degree in extreme western Montana. In southeastern Montana, continued high temperatures and dry weather have led to an expansion of first stage (D1) and severe drought (D2) conditions. Streamflow levels up and down the Rocky Mountain Range remain very low for the most part. The summer heat and dryness have taken their toll on the Colorado landscape again as fires were a concern in the Boulder area.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
