<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020822</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the period August 22-26, a frontal system will trek slowly eastward across the Plains and into areas east of the Appalachians. Showers and thunderstorms are anticipated across parts of southeastern Nebraska and adjacent areas of Iowa, Missouri and Kansas, providing some relief from ongoing drought conditions. Rainfall is expected to ease dryness over parts of the Ohio Valley, and scattered showers and thunderstorms could provide limited relief to Piedmont areas of the Carolinas northward into the Mid-Atlantic by late in the period. Out West, most precipitation will be confined to areas of Montana and northern Idaho, where scattered showers could reduce dryness. During the period August 27-31, above average rainfall is expected from the Mid-Atlantic and into parts of the Southeast. Precipitation probabilities will also be greater than average across parts of the High Plains, from eastern Montana southward into north Texas. Across the West, mainly dry weather will team with above normal temperatures to maintain existing drought conditions.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Subnormal rainfall was observed across western portions of Oahu and Molokai where abnormally dry (D0) conditions persisted.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>An increase in tropical rains nudged abnormal dryness out of southwest and northeast parts of the island, as weekly precipitation totals were locally 2 to 4 inches. Longer term dryness persisted across the remainder of Puerto Rico where D0 was maintained.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>A week of virtually rainless conditions across Delmarva prompted the expansion of exceptional drought (D4) into the middle peninsula of Virginia, and into parts of eastern Maryland and Delaware. Extreme drought designation (D3) was pushed westward to include the greater Washington, D.C. area as rainfall during the period from September 1 through August 19 was nearly half of average. For Washington, this was the driest such period on record with only 21.09 inches of rainfall, or about half the average. Extreme drought also expanded north into southeast Pennsylvania and much of southern New Jersey as streamflows and soil moisture decreased dramatically under hot temperatures and a lack of rainfall. Despite an increase in daily shower and thunderstorm activity in the Southeast after the 15th, the scattered nature of the precipitation did little to ameliorate D3 to D4 drought conditions. In Charlotte, N.C., mandatory water conservation measures were implemented on the 21st, and this is only the second time in city history that mandatory measures have been implemented. Charlotte joins over 70 other North Carolina cities enforcing water conservation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast">
   <p>Tropical downpours relaxed dryness across coastal areas of Texas in the Corpus Christi area, with D0/D1 designated drought areas shifted farther to the south. Deep South Texas missed most of the rainfall, and the severe to extreme drought categorization was maintained in the greater Brownsville area. Locally heavy showers and thunderstorms significantly moistened topsoil conditions across Louisiana and adjacent areas of northeast Texas and Arkansas, with elimination of D1 along with significant shrinkage of D0.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, Ohio Valley, Great Lakes">
   <p>Clusters of heavy thunderstorms brought drought-easing rains to extreme southeastern Nebraska, southwestern Iowa, northwestern Missouri and parts of northeast Kansas where drought classification was reduced by about one category. Elsewhere in Nebraska, extreme to exceptional drought persisted, and the Platte River at Columbus ran dry for the first time in decades. A series of cold frontal passages, each accompanied by showers and thunderstorms, reduced dryness in Wisconsin and Michigan, where D0 was eliminated in much of the area. Farther to the south, D1 was reduced to D0 over northwest Indiana and the Chicagoland area and D2 was removed across northern Ohio as rainfall on the order of 1 to 2 inches brought some relief.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and Alaska">
   <p>Seasonably dry weather prevailed throughout much of the area west of the Front Range, with weekly precipitation totals generally less than a tenth of an inch. Monsoon rainfall across Arizona and New Mexico was scattered and light, and resulted in no net change in existing drought conditions. Numerous wildfires continued to burn in parts of the West, with over a half-million acres of vegetation charred from the current series of active fires across the state of Oregon. Locally wetter conditions over extreme northeast Oregon allowed for the erasure of D0 here. Meanwhile, D2 and D3 areas were expanded in central and southern Idaho, where streamflows dwindled throughout the Salmon River and Big Wood basins. Across Alaska, rainfall amounts of around an inch during the past week over central parts of the state allowed for a removal of D0 in the region around Fairbanks.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
