<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030327</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through April 5 which may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: Over the next 5 days (March 27-31): 1) A developing spring storm system in the central U.S. should bring some drought relief to portions of the Plains and Great Lakes regions; 2) rain and snow will be a factor across portions of the northern Intermountain West and northern Rockies early in the period and again a few days later as the next storm system approaches the Pacific Northwest coast.</p>
   <p>For the 6-10 day period (April 1-5): expect warmer than average temperatures across much of the southwestern U.S. and below average temperatures across the northern quarter of the contiguous states. Above average precipitation is possible from the Pacific coast through the northern Plains states and into the northern Great Lakes. An active weather pattern is expected across the Hawaiian Islands during this period. A front should pass through or stall over the islands in the next several days bringing widespread rainfall across Hawaii. Potential exists for additional rainfall early next week with the approach of another frontal system. Snowfall on the order of two to five inches is expected across parts of south central Alaska over the next couple of days.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>The Susitna and Kenai Basins, where snow water content was much below normal, received some light snow to cover dry grass and help reduce the fire hazard. However, most of the state had generally clear skies and little precipitation. No change was made to the drought depiction this week since the D0 area was expanded last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>A pattern of dryness continued, overall, for Hawaii, with unusually warm temperatures this week. Some stations on the Big Island received an inch or more of rain, but elsewhere stations received a few tenths of an inch or no rain. No change was made to the drought categories in the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Half an inch or more of rain fell at stations in the southern and southeastern coastal slopes this week, with generally a third of an inch or less being reported elsewhere. Little change in overall streamflow conditions was reported, so no change was made to the D0 depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and New England">
   <p>Over an inch of precipitation fell in the northern New York D0 area introduced last week, causing contraction of the moisture deficits in the modeled soil moisture. The D0 was pulled back some here to reflect this week's moisture plus melting of the snowpack.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>The Colorado winter storm pumped a broad swath of Gulf of Mexico moisture into its center, causing heavy thunderstorms across parts of the southern and central Plains. Two inches or more of rain fell in a band from southeastern Oklahoma to central Kansas, with some Kansas stations reporting up to 4 inches. The D0, D1, D2, and D3 boundaries were pulled back one category from central Kansas to the Nebraska border.</p>
   <p>Rain and snow from the winter storm reached as far north as the Montana-Dakotas border, where an inch or more of precipitation resulted in a contraction of the D1, D2, and D3 boundaries. D3 was pulled back across western South Dakota to the Nebraska and Wyoming state lines, reflecting both inch-plus precipitation this week and improving conditions over the longer term. The impacts line, which separates Hydrological impacts to the west and Agricultural and Hydrological impacts to the east, was moved to parallel the state line with Montana and Wyoming on the west and the Dakotas and Nebraska on the east. The impacts line was also opened up across Kansas.</p>
   <p>Precipitation totals dropped off sharply from southwestern Nebraska toward the northeast. While southwestern stations received an inch or two, stations from around Kearney to about Norfolk reported only a couple tenths of an inch. The spot of D4 in southwestern Nebraska was shifted northeastward, and the D2 boundary in northeastern Nebraska was bulged outward a bit, to reflect both this week's dryness and longer-term deficits.</p>
   <p>As it moved out of Colorado, the winter storm generally tracked south of the main drought areas from Missouri to the Great Lakes. Most stations in these drought areas reported a couple tenths to half an inch of precipitation or a little more. The area of D1 was pulled back across part of Upper Michigan where an inch or more of rain fell. D2 retreated into central Lower Michigan where about an inch of rain was reported. In west central Illinois, 2+ inches of rain occurred resulting in the dimpling of the D0, D1, and D2 boundaries.</p>
   <p>A spot of D2 was introduced in northeastern Minnesota to reflect very dry conditions on both the short-term and longer-term timescales. This area has had 25% or less of normal precipitation as far back as the last 3 months, a couple tenths or less this week, and is experiencing rural wildfires. D1 was expanded into northern Ohio and D0 pushed into eastern Ohio and adjoining areas of Pennsylvania and West Virginia to reflect dry conditions this week and back to 3 months. The D0 area has received less than 75% of normal precipitation over this period with drying soils.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>An enormous storm centered over southeastern Colorado dropped heavy snow and closed most of the Denver area for several days. Many stations along the Colorado Front Range were buried in up to 4 feet or more of snow, with one station reporting 87.5 inches. In terms of mountain snowpack, the USDA Natural Resources Conservation Service reported that the storm produced a whopping 30 percent of average increase in water equivalent in the South Platte basin and a corresponding 26 percent of average increase in basin cumulative precipitation. That amount of increase in cumulative precipitation is extremely rare at this point through the season. Other Colorado basins reported snowpack increases of 10 to 20 percent. Lesser increases occurred in Wyoming. But improvements were mostly in the upslope areas to the divide, with western Colorado and downslope areas in other states missing out on the bonanza, and, in spite of the enormous snowfall totals in the wet areas, season-to-date snowfall amounts were still just at or below seasonal norms.</p>
   <p>The greatest precipitation amounts occurred in the northeastern third of Colorado, with upwards of 7 inches of moisture in some foothills locations. The rain and snow (when it melts) was not enough to fill empty reservoirs, but was enough to meet landscape water needs and early irrigation needs for agriculture ... but just into April. For example, several days after the storm, Denver Water's reservoirs, overall, were at only 43% of capacity. Some estimates project that a near normal snowpack would bring these reservoirs up to only 70-75% of capacity after the spring runoff. The depiction of drought on this week's Drought Monitor was constructed to meet the needs of the large variety of users who are impacted by drought. Certainly the storm produced very wet conditions in the short-term, but a few weeks of heavy precipitation will not erase record and near-record deficits that have built up over a 3 to 4 year period. The heavy mountain snowpack will take several weeks to melt, soak into the ground, run down streams and eventually reach the depleted reservoirs. Consequently, a patch of D2 was pulled back over the wettest area of northeastern Colorado and the impacts line, which separates Hydrological impacts to the west and Agricultural and Hydrological impacts to the east, was moved eastward out of northeastern Colorado. The spot of D4 in southeastern Colorado was shrunk, the D3 in central Colorado and in northern New Mexico was contracted, and the D3 was pulled back in southern Wyoming and the southern Nebraska panhandle. D4 was pulled out of the Nebraska panhandle and eastern Wyoming. The D3 boundary in northwestern Wyoming was moved eastward to reflect well above-normal water content in the headwaters of the Powder-Tongue river basin.</p>
   <p>Another storm system brought rain and snow to the Pacific Northwest and northern Rockies this week. Heaviest precipitation (6+ inches) occurred along the coastal/Cascade range, with considerably less lee of the mountains. Inland, the heaviest precipitation fell in areas that were upgraded to drought-free last week. SNOTEL snow water content observations showed little significant improvement in the adjoining drought areas of Oregon, Idaho, and Montana, so no change was made here.</p>
   <p>Generally less than half an inch of precipitation fell across the rest of the western drought areas. Snowpack water content was generally well below seasonal norms and reservoirs remained depleted or empty, so no other changes were made to the drought depiction in the West.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>A wide area of 1 to 2 inch rains, with locally heavier amounts (4+ inches), fell across the Georgia and Carolinas D0H area during the week. Much of this area has had 2+ inches since March 11, and 6+ inches for the month so far (which equates to twice the month-to-date long-term mean). Groundwater levels in Georgia wells have been rising, although with some now just about halfway toward the levels they were at before the drought hit, and wells in South Carolina are almost fully recharged. A couple areas missed out on the very heavy rains during this week, and they have considerably below-normal precipitation across all timescales, from the last week to last month, and especially back to 2 to 5 years ago, in some cases 85% or less of normal. If the U.S. Drought Monitor product consisted of two separate maps for different timescales, a short-term map would show solid green wet conditions for the Southeast and a long-term map would indicate a large area with significant 24- to 60-month precipitation deficits. However, the Drought Monitor is one map which integrates conditions across all timescales. In the Southeast, the D0H area was all but eliminated, being reduced to a small spot over south central North Carolina.</p>
   <p>Unusually hot temperatures have occurred in southern Florida, with daily maximum temperature records being set or broken on at least 14 days since February 27. However, the heat has been accompanied by wet conditions, with frequent showers and thunderstorms helping to keep drought at bay.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
