<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20011115</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) beneficial precipitation (mainly in the form of rain) has been falling across much of Oregon, and Washington November 13-14, and should continue through the end of the week, with additional rains expected for northern California as well; 2) dry conditions and wildfires have continued in the eastern United States, with little relief expected through the 10-day period ending November 24; 3) the exception to the dryness in the East is the continued onshore flow of tropical moisture into northeastern Florida and extreme southern Georgia November 14-16; 4) beneficial rains fell November 14 in the drought areas of western Texas, with additional rains expected November 15-17 due to a slow moving upper-level system; 5) the above-normal temperatures for the past several weeks across the Plains will be replaced by more seasonal temperatures during Thanksgiving week; and 6) Hawaii will remain in a drier-than-normal pattern through November 22.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes were made for the week to the drought and abnormally dry conditions affecting Hawaii. For Puerto Rico, heavy rains fell during the 7-day period ending November 9 across the northern, central, and eastern parts of the island. Precipitation totals reached 17.30 inches for the week in Orocovis, and helped remove D0 (abnormally dry) conditions from these areas. Totals were considerably less along the southern coast of the island, and longer-term deficits still remain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic States">
   <p>Continuing a trend that has lasted throughout the fall, the past week was again dry across the Northeast and Mid-Atlantic states. Only a small area of western Maine saw precipitation totals greater than 1 inch, with many areas in the region receiving less than 0.25 inches. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions returned to areas in central Pennsylvania still experiencing some long-term effects from previous dry conditions during the summer months. As of November 13, New York City Delaware River Basin storage is in the Drought Warning stage, and is 54% of normal for this time of year and 36% of the storage at this time in November 2000.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Very little precipitation fell during the week in the abnormally dry or drought areas in the Plains or Midwest. As a result, much of western Iowa and northern Nebraska were included in the D0 (abnormally dry) category. Abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) conditions also expanded northward into western and central Kansas, while D2 (severe drought) and D3 (extreme drought) expanded slightly in western Texas. Moderate drought (D1) expanded to include more of eastern Montana as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>No precipitation fell across this entire region during the past week, except across portions of southern Florida not included within the D0 (abnormally dry) area. Wildfires continue to be the major impact from the recent dryness, although water supplies are also of concern (particularly in rural areas). Agriculture is also being affected by the extreme dryness during the fall months. Severe drought (D2) expanded in eastern North Carolina and central Georgia. Moderate drought (D1) pushed farther west into southern West Virginia, extreme eastern Kentucky, western Virginia, eastern Tennessee, and northwestern Georgia. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions now exist in central Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky. During the past week, large wildfires have been reported in Pennsylvania, West Virginia, Maryland, Kentucky, Virginia, Tennessee, North Carolina, Georgia, and South Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>One storm affected the region, mainly California, November 10-12, with additional storms expected later in the week. Downtown San Francisco recorded 0.66 inches November 10-11 and 2.09 inches November 11-12. It is still too early to gauge the improvement these storms might bring to the drought situation across the West, but one positive outcome was a reduction in wildfire potentialparticularly in northern California. The hydrological impact designation (W) was extended south along the Pacific Ocean to San Francisco, as well as to the Washington-Oregon border.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
