<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040429</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas  experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) record high temperatures in the western U.S. April 24-27 will be replaced by more seasonable temperatures April 28-May 1, before warming up again May 2-8; 2) another snowstorm will move through the central Rockies April 28-30, affecting more of Wyoming and Utah than the previous storm last week, but also bringing more snow to the southeastern mountains in Colorado; and 3) precipitation will break out along and ahead of a cold front as it moves across the country April 29-May 1, bringing the potentially heaviest rains to the Gulf Coast region.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Little or no rain has fallen during the past week in the abnormally dry area of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Very heavy rains occurred during the week across the Ozarks and the mid-Mississippi Valley. Parts of northern Arkansas received more than 8 inches of rain for the week, and serious flooding occurred in some of these areas. Areas northwest of the Dallas-Fort Worth metropolitan area also received heavy rains. As a result, the abnormally dry category (D0) was removed from parts of northern Texas, most of Arkansas, all of southeast Missouri and eastern Kentucky, and most of southern Illinois. Rains north of St. Louis also improved the abnormally dry (D0) conditions in west-central Illinois. Unfortunately, very little rain fell during the week across northern Indiana, northern Ohio, and southern Michigan. An area of moderate drought (D1) has developed in this region.</p>
   <p>Conditions have also deteriorated in western South Dakota, and the severe drought (D2) category was expanded westward. As farmers become more active with the arrival of spring, the dryness and drought conditions across the Dakotas and Minnesota have also begun to have agricultural impacts in addition to those related to the longer-term hydrological situation across the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>A storm system brought rain across the Southeast April 25-26. The rains were heaviest across southern Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama. New Orleans, for example, recorded 7.67 inches on April 25. Farther east, the rains diminished in intensity. As a result, moderate drought (D1) conditions expanded southward across central Georgia and upstate South Carolina. Columbia, South Carolina, has received only 0.78 inches of precipitation during April (29% of normal), 1.65 inches since March 1 (23% of normal), and 7.61 inches since January 1 (48% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A storm with significant snows and rains hit southeastern Colorado April 22-23, as well as adjacent areas of western Kansas and the panhandles of Oklahoma and Texas. The greatest snowfall totals occurred in the Sangre de Cristo Mountains west of Trinidad, Colorado, where 35 inches of snow fell. As a result of this storm, severe drought (D2) and extreme drought (D3) classifications were improved across the southeast part of Colorado. Moderate drought (D1) and abnormally dry conditions improved across northwestern Texas, western Oklahoma, and southwest Kansas. The heaviest snows and rains missed most of the northeast part of Colorado and the northern Front Range Mountains. The extreme drought (D3) classification was expanded southwestward toward the Fort Collins area.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, across the rest of the West, little precipitation fell and the region experienced much above normal temperatures April 24-27. Some cities in California have recorded all-time record highs for the month of April during this four-day stretch. Along the Sierra Nevada range, summer runoff forecasts continue to look poor for the drainage basins along the east side of the range, and the Lake Tahoe summer inflow forecast is estimated around 58% of normal. The deterioration of conditions has caused the D0, D1, and D2 boundaries to be moved westward along the California/Nevada border.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
