<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050818</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 5-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) scattered showers and thunderstorms should continue across the southeastern quarter of the Nation, possibly providing some relief to the Ohio and Tennessee Valleys and parts of the Delta; 2) the Southwest Monsoon should continue, bringing additional moisture to the Four Corners States, and northward into the Rockies; 3) an active storm track across the southern Canadian Prairies may bring rain to the northern Plains and upper Midwest; 4) only light showers may fall on the central and eastern Corn Belts into the Northeast; 5) the Pacific Northwest should remain dry.</p>
   <p>The 6- to 10-day (August 23-27) outlook from the Climate Prediction Center calls for above-normal precipitation in the southern Rockies and Southeast, with drier-than-normal weather across the northern half of the Nation. Temperatures should average above-normal in the Southwest, northern halves of the Rockies and Plains, upper Midwest, and New England, while cooler than usual weather should affect the southern Plains and Delta.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Hawaii remained status-quo, with only light showers dampening the orographically-favored windward (mauka) areas while leeward sides were generally dry. An exception to this was on the leeward (western) side of Kona (Big Island), where Honaunau, Kealakekua, Waiaha, and Puu Waawaa measured over a 5-day period 5.61, 4.56, 3.97, and 1.93 inches, respectively, from 8 am HST August 9 until 8 am HST August 14. On western Oahu, recent heat and short-term dryness sparked a large wildfire near Nanakuli, charring nearly 2,000 acres as of August 16.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, continuing short-term dryness and recent warmth (temperatures averaged 5 to 10F above normal) across central sections has aggravated the wildfire situation, justifying two new D0 areas. As of August 16, there were 3 large wildfires affecting over 266,000 acres, according to the Alaska ICC. In August alone, over 1.135 million acres have been charred, while over 2.631 million acres burned during the past 60 days. The Alaska wildfire year-to-date acreage stood at 3.152 million acres, or almost half of the national total acreage (6.379 million acres).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest and Delta">
   <p>A stationary front meandered from the western Corn Belt into the lower Missouri Valley during the week, producing widespread, moderate to heavy rains that drenched many drought-affected portions of the Midwest. Many locations in central Wisconsin, most of Nebraska, Iowa, Missouri, and Illinois, eastern Kansas, and northern Indiana measured over 2 inches of rain, with locally up to 6 inches in central Missouri. Accordingly, a one-category improvement was made to these areas, even though the short and long-term drought indices showed additional improvement. In general, one wet week will not eliminate drought accumulated from several consecutive dry and warm weeks. An exception to this was in northwestern Illinois where D3 remained as weekly totals were lower (0.75-2 inches), leaving 8-10 inch deficits since March 1. The rains were most likely too late to aid the corn in Missouri (68% dented) and Illinois (41% dented), but might assist the filling soy pods and rejuvenating the pastures. According to NASS/USDA, the percents of corn/soy/pastures rated very poor or poor were 45/43/83% in Missouri and 60/39/83% in Illinois, respectively. Elsewhere, lighter amounts kept conditions status-quo in most of the Great Lakes region.</p>
   <p>Farther south, however, showers were more scattered and lighter across the Delta, and conditions generally remained static. In central and eastern sections, however, no rain fell (eastern Arkansas, northern Mississippi, and western Tennessee), and drought expanded eastward. Greenville, MS, has accumulated a deficit of more than 15 inches since the start of the year, including only a trace of rain this month.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Tennessee and Ohio Valleys and the Northeast">
   <p>A slow-moving cold front triggered scattered showers and thunderstorms across the Northeast, but weekly totals were generally less than an inch. A few areas along the New York and Pennsylvania border, southern New Hampshire, and parts of Massachusetts received over 2 inches of rain, easing dryness there. However, abnormal warmth (temperatures averaged more than 6F above normal with highs in the 90s) and increasing short-term deficits (30-days, 1 to 4 inches; 90-days, 2 to 6 inches), expanded D0 and D1 into central New York (Mohawk Valley) and central Pennsylvania. As a result, 7-day average USGS stream levels have dropped into the lower 25 th percentile across most of central Pennsylvania, while 66% and 55% of the pastures in Pennsylvania and New York were rated poor or very poor, according to the NASS/USDA.</p>
   <p>Farther to the southwest, the third consecutive week of little or no precipitation and near- to above normal temperatures in the northwestern Tennessee and southwestern Ohio Valleys finally ended the drought-less gap between the Delta and eastern Ohio Valley as D0 spread across the region. Severe short-term drought (D2) developed along the Ohio and Kentucky border where 90-day shortages approached 7 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Similar to the Midwest, the same stationary front, with occasional waves of low pressure developing along it, also generated moderate to heavy rains in the central and southern Plains. In combination with ample moisture moving northeastward out of northwestern Mexico in association with the Southwest Monsoon, much of eastern New Mexico, northern and central Texas, Oklahoma, Kansas, eastern Colorado, Nebraska, southeastern Wyoming, and southwestern South Dakota received over 2 inches of rain. Localized flooding hit parts of north-central Texas and southern Oklahoma where 5 to 9 inches fell, much of it within 24-hours. As a result, dryness and drought was reduced by one-category in the southern third of the High Plains, the western Red River Valley, and parts of the central Plains. Where totals were lower (northern Kansas, central Dakotas), dryness remained. Additionally, temperatures were much cooler than normal (departures around -4F in the southern and central Plains, -6 to -10F in the northern Plains), greatly reducing evaporative and evapotranspiration demands.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West ">
   <p>In the Southwest, central and southern Rockies, the late-arriving but now active Southwest Monsoon expanded, dropping ample rainfall (1 to 3 inches, with localized flash flooding) on Arizona, New Mexico, southern Nevada, southeastern California, southern Utah, and Colorado while keeping temperatures down. Accordingly, some short-term drought relief was provided to the Four Corners States. Farther north, the same stationary front in the Nations midsection also snaked across the northern Rockies, triggering scattered showers (0.1 to 1.5 inches) in northern Idaho, Montana, and Wyoming. Continuing precipitation in southwestern Montana over the past several weeks warranted some improvement to the Gallatin and Madison Valleys.</p>
   <p>In contrast, seasonably dry weather persisted over the Far West, with temperatures generally close to normal. As of August 16, however, 21 large wildfires were concentrated in northeastern Oregon, southeastern Washington, north-central Idaho, and extreme western Montana, affecting over 187,000 acres, while the remainder of the West reported only 3 large wildfires.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
