<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100401</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>During the past 7 days, significant rains fell across much of the Pacific Northwest and from the middle Mississippi Valley to the Mid-Atlantic and New England.  Those rains were part of a low-pressure system that moved from the central Great Plains to the Mid-Atlantic coast late last week.  As that storm system moved eastward, another low-pressure system moved into and across the Northwest.  During the weekend, the second storm wrapped up in the center of the contiguous 48 states, then moved eastward.  This storm system tapped deep moisture from the Gulf of Mexico and brought it northward, creating flooding rains across many locations east of the Appalachians. The drier regions of the country during the past 7 days were across portions of Alaska, Hawaii, eastern Puerto Rico, the Gulf Coast, the central Appalachians, the Great Lakes, and the central and southern Rockies.  These areas missed out on the storm activity of the past week.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Moderate rainfall is expected across portions of the central Great Plains and the middle Mississippi Valley between March 31 and April 5, 2010.   Additional heavy rains are expected across the Pacific Northwest, with storm systems moving from the north Pacific into the northern Rockies.   Beyond April 5, wetter than normal conditions are expected across the Pacific Northwest, Great Lakes, lower Mississippi Valley, and into the Northeast.  Dry conditions are expected to continue across much of Alaska, with the exception of the Panhandle and Aleutians.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Great Lakes and Ohio River Valley">
   <p>Precipitation deficits continued to mount across the Great Lakes region as the storm track was firmly south of the region.  Precipitation totals for the previous 14- and 90-day periods were less than 50 percent of normal, with the most recent 14 days showing most of the Great Lakes region below 5 percent of normal.  Low vegetation demand for water and minimal evaporation during the colder months precluded the expansion of the more intense drought categories; however, the area of abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded to include most of Michigan.  The Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI) for the past 3 months (less than -2.0) painted a dire picture, while the 6- and 9-month SPI values across northern lower Michigan (0.0 to -0.8) were not as low.  With spring thaws upon us and more active vegetation not too far off, this area should be monitored closely.</p>
   <p>Precipitation over the past week bypassed most of Kentucky (precipitation totals less than 0.6 inch) while many reports out of southern Indiana indicated widespread rain totals of 1.5-2.5 inches.  Soil moisture models indicated that soil moisture values in the region were mostly between the twentieth and thirtieth percentiles across Kentucky, with isolated areas below the twentieth percentile.  Analyses of rainfall totals (percent of normal and SPI) for periods longer than 6 months indicated some wetness across this region, while for shorter time scale dryness is most pronounced at 30 days (totals between 5 and 25 percent of normal).  The area of abnormal dryness in this region was modified to reflect the heavier rains in Indiana and the continued dryness in Kentucky.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>No change was made to the drought indications across the Hawaiian Island chain.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, western and interior portions continued to see dry conditions. Unalakleet reported no precipitation over the past 90 days while McGrath reported less than an inch over the past 3 months (less than 30 percent of normal).  Bethel, near the west coast and just a bit south of Unalakleet has reported near normal precipitation for the past 90 days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast and Texas">
   <p>Dryness across the southern Mississippi Valley continued.  Climate divisions 2 and 3 in Louisiana reported rainfall deficits of 4.70 and 5.88 inches over the past 45 days.  Soil Moisture values from models run at the University of Washington (UW) and the National Centers for Environmental Prediction (NCEP) both indicated moisture deficits in this region, with the North American Land Data Assimilation System (N-LDAS) showing D0 conditions and the UW model more consistent with moderate drought (D1).  The mitigating factor in indicating D0 rather than D1 was that some light precipitation fell across the region during the past 7 days.</p>
   <p>The areas of abnormal dryness in southern and western Texas persisted, with little precipitation reported in these regions during the past 7 days.  As temperatures continue to rise and agricultural use of water increases, these areas will need to be closely monitored.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation fell across much of the eastern slopes of the Rockies from Montana to Colorado to northern New Mexico.  Unfortunately most of the areas affected by drought are west of the continental divide, so only minor improvements were made in the drought conditions. Across much of the northern and central Rockies, precipitation was ongoing at the data cutoff (8 am, EDT, Tuesday of each week), so most of the impact from that precipitation will be felt in the coming weeks.  Despite the recent precipitation, snowpack is still approximately 3 feet below normal near Franklin County, Idaho.</p>
   <p>In northern Colorado, most of the precipitation fell outside of the drought areas, with the exception of Jackson County, where many areas received between 1.0 and 1.5 inches, and a single report in Routt County of 1.5 inches.  That precipitation prompted the removal of Moderate Drought from southern Jackson County, and trimming of some abnormal dryness (D0) from northern Jackson, western Larimer, and eastern Grand Counties.  Rainfall of about 1.0 inch across Mesa County led to a small trimming of D0.</p>
   <p>Across northern Arizona, the impacts of an El Nino winter storm track continued to be felt.  Snowpack of approximately 48 inches on the north rim of the Grand Canyon and other areas of deep snowpack at higher terrain across Navajo and Apache Counties prompted a one-category improvement across much of northern Arizona.  Severe drought (D2) is now indicated only in the shadow of the Mogollon Rim.</p>
   <p>With the storm track shifting northward as the El Nino weakened, rainfall across much of California became scarce.  This recent lack of rains is highlighted by 14-day precipitation totals below 5 percent of normal from the central coast of California to central Nevada.  Given the prior wetness in this region, only a minor expansion of D0 was indicated across Mono and Inyo Counties.  This area will need to be closely monitored as the end of the rainy season is quickly approaching.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Matthew Rosencrans</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
