<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040916</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather conditions that could have an impact on areas of drought or dryness across the United States over the next 2 weeks include: 1) extremely heavy rains from Hurricane Ivan hitting eastern Louisiana, Mississippi, and much of the Southeast, with the bulk of the moisture missing the dry areas in central and western parts of Louisiana, as well as Arkansas; 2) generally normal to above-normal precipitation from Montana into the Dakotas during the next 2 weeks, with chilly temperatures across Idaho and most of Montana, and some high-elevations snows; 3) warm and dry weather from Nebraska southward to Texas through September 20, followed by normal to above-normal rainfall in Nebraska and Kansas, as well as lower temperatures.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Cool weather continued to ease the impacts from the dry, warm summer, with Fairbanks seeing snow on September 14. Heavy rains across the southern Panhandle resulted in removal of D0 there, while moderate rains eliminated D0 on the southern Kenai Peninsula. Although precipitation amounts were generally light in the interior basin, the lessening of wildfire threat from the long-term precipitation deficits led to removal of the D1 drought area in the eastern basin.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Lack of significant rain led to expansion of the D0 dryness to the northern part of the Big Island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Lower Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Short-term D0 dryness developed across south-central and southwestern Louisiana, as this area has seen 30-day rainfall only around one-half of normal or less, and declining soil moisture has become a concern for farmers. As of September 12, topsoil moisture was rated 58 percent short or very short in Louisiana. The area of below-normal rainfall extends northward into Arkansas, but the dryness severity has not yet reached D0 levels. Topsoil moisture is rated 71 percent short to very short in Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>A dry week through early Tuesday allowed slight expansion of the D0 dryness area southward in Wisconsin, although pre-frontal rains moved into the region during the day on Tuesday.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Hot, dry weather affected the region during the latter part of the week, with daily high temperatures soaring into the mid to upper 90s in Kansas, Nebraska, and South Dakota on September 10, 11, and 12. A cold front began bringing relief to the region, but not before readings hit 99 degrees F in Kansas and 97 degrees F in Nebraska on September 13. Heavy frontal showers mitigated the impact of the heat in the Dakotas and Nebraska, but Kansas and Oklahoma stayed mostly dry. As a result, topsoil moisture conditions deteriorated in Kansas, causing D0 dryness to expand into central areas of the state, as well as southward into southwestern Kansas and into the Panhandle of Oklahoma.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Several areas in Washington, Idaho, and Montana picked up over an inch of rain, but most of the moisture fell outside of the ongoing drought region. Nevertheless, the rains reduced the D0 area in Washington and contributed to some retreat of the drought areas in Montana and eastern Idaho. An updated drought analysis provided by the state of Montana also contributed to changes there. Heavy showers fell in the interior of southern California, leading to slight retreat of the D2 area there, but the impact on the long-term drought was minor. Some showers also fell in western Arizona and southeastern Wyoming, with little impact on the ongoing drought. The drought areas in southeastern Arizona expanded a small distance westward. Above-normal temperatures maintained high wildfire danger in California.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
