<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020919</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period through September 28 that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: Over the next 5 days (through September 23), a cold front will slowly cross the eastern two-thirds of the U.S., preceded and accompanied by widespread showers and thunderstorms. The NWS forecasts that as much as 1 to 3 inches of rain, with locally higher totals, are likely across the eastern Plains, Midwest, and South. Showers are also forecast across the Northeast. A wild card in the forecast is the eventual track of Tropical Storm Isidore. On September 18, Isidore soaked Jamaica with wind-driven downpours, and the storm is likely to track generally northwestward and reach hurricane intensity. According to the National Hurricane Center no portion of the Gulf of Mexico coastline can be ruled out as a potential...landfall [site]. In addition, Isidore may interact with the approaching cold front as early as the weekend. Meanwhile, cool, mostly dry weather will trail the cold front in areas from the Intermountain region eastward, but hot, dry weather will continue across California. During the 6- to 10-day period from September 24-28, the NWS indicates that very cool air will overspread most areas from the Rockies eastward. The coldest weather, relative to normal, will affect the northern Plains and upper Midwest. In contrast, very warm, mostly dry weather will prevail in the West Coast States. Most of the South is likely to receive above-normal rainfall as a cold front interacts with tropical moisture, but below-normal precipitation is expected in the Midwest. Meanwhile, above-normal precipitation may provide some drought relief on the central High Plains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Dry conditions persisted in leeward locations, maintaining agricultural dryness (D0) and a threat of wildfire activity on parts of Oahu and Maui. In addition, longer-term hydrological concerns (D0) continued across western Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Tropical Storm Hanna moved ashore near Mobile, Alabama, on September 14, sparking heavy rainfall across the Southeast. The heaviest rain (4 to 10 inches, with locally higher totals) fell from the central Panhandle of Florida northward to near the triple point between Georgia and the Carolinas. There was a general one- to locally two-category reduction in drought severity across the wettest areas, including much of Georgia, upstate South Carolina, and southwestern North Carolina. Farther north, tropical moisture interacted with an approaching front to produce a band of heavy rain (locally 2 inches or more) and provide as much as one category of drought reduction from central Ohio into the northern Mid-Atlantic region and parts of New England. In addition, recent soil moisture improvements eased stress on Eastern pastures and curbed the threat of wildfire activity, leaving many areas with primarily hydrological drought concerns.</p>
   <p>Between the areas of heavy rain, only scattered, light showers dampened the central Appalachians and the remainder of the Mid-Atlantic region, allowing drought to remain undiminished or even slightly intensify. The area of exceptional drought (D4) diminished markedly but remains entrenched across portions of southern Virginia and western North Carolina. Extreme drought (D3) now stretches from the northern half of Georgia into central Virginia, and also includes parts of northern Maryland and southern Pennsylvania.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Lower Midwest">
   <p>Scattered showers provided limited drought relief in the middle Ohio Valley, but only light rain fell in the lower Ohio Valley, where conditions range from abnormally dry to severe drought (D0 to D2). Dry weather prevailed in Lower Michigan, resulting in an expansion of abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Tropical moisture lingered across Deep South Texas in the wake of Tropical Storm Fays dissipation, further easing long- and short-term drought. Nevertheless, a small area of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) persists in southernmost Texas. Farther north and east, late-season heat and dryness were favorable for summer crop maturation and harvesting, but quickly dried topsoils in preparation for planting winter grains. The area of abnormal dryness (D0) expanded across the lower Mississippi Valley and adjacent areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West and the Plains">
   <p>Heavy rain was observed in much of the Four Corners region during the first half of September, aiding drought-stressed rangelands and boosting drought-reduced irrigation reserves. September 1-15 rainfall totaled 3.90 inches in Flagstaff, Arizona, accounting for 45 percent of its year-to-date total. Similarly, Vernal, Utah, netted 2.35 inches, more than 500 percent of its September 1-15 normal and 57 percent of its year-to-date precipitation. As a result, some reductions in drought severity were noted across the Southwest, although extreme to exceptional drought (D3 to D4) persists in parts of 12 states from southern California northeastward to portions of the central and northern High Plains. However, recent wetness allowed the wildfire (F) designation to be removed from much of the Plains and roughly the eastern half of the West. Meanwhile, very dry weather continued in the West Coast States, bringing increased concerns about a lack of moisture for dryland winter wheat.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
