<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041209</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather conditions potentially having an impact on the areas of dryness or drought over the next 2 weeks include: 1) continued rain and snow over the Northwest, northern California, and central Great Basin through around December 12; 2) with potentially above-normal precipitation during December 14-18 in the Great Basin; 3) normal to above-normal precipitation in the Southwest from around December 18-22; 3) periods of light snow over the Great Lakes and northern Plains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>In Alaska, the D0 persisted in the eastern interior basin as generally light precipitation prevailed. In contrast, more heavy rains hit the windward areas of Hawaiis Big Island, further trimming the D0 area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Great Plains">
   <p>Snow on December 1 and again on the 6th left around one-half inch of precipitation across Michigans Lower Peninsula, resulting in removal of the lingering D0 area. An expansive storm system brought moderate amounts of rain and snow to the Great Lakes region on December 6-7, eliminating the remaining D0 dryness in southern Wisconsin. The past 30 days have been quite dry in Minnesota and the Dakotas, with amounts less than 25 percent of normal in many locations, but light snows this past week prevented expansion of D0 dryness for the time being.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Drier weather took hold for most of this week, as a cold high pressure system dominated the region. Weekly temperatures averaging 5 to 15 degrees F below normal prevented significant snowmelt. A low pressure system did track eastward across southern California and southern Arizona and southern New Mexico during December 5-6, bringing low-elevation rains and high-elevation snows. Precipitation amounts exceeding one-half inch resulted in improvement from D2 to D1 in southern Californias Imperial Valley, although significant long-term rainfall deficits remained. Farther north, a broad flow of moist Pacific air brought widespread rain and snow to central and northern California, the Northwest and central Great Basin beginning December 6. Precipitation amounts ranging up to 2 inches reduced the D0 dryness in northern California. In contrast, below-normal rainfall during the past several weeks coupled with long-term rainfall deficits resulted in slight expansion of the southern California D0 area northward along the coast.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
