<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20071004</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>In the near term, zonal flow will give way to a deepening trough over the western U.S., while a ridge of high pressure continues to dominate the eastern U.S. Above-average rain and snowfall in the Pacific Northwest may provide some drought relief from Washington State to the northern Rockies. By the weekend, some models predict the development of a cutoff low over the central Rocky Mountains which slowly moves to the northeast bringing light to moderate precipitation to the Northern Plains and Great Lakes. With the ridge in place over the East there is little chance for widespread drought relief from the Deep South to the Ohio Valley and Mid-Atlantic. Additionally, the ridge over the eastern U.S. should direct any systems of tropical or subtropical origin across the Gulf of Mexico. According to the National Hurricane Center, there is the possibility that a broad area of low pressure over the southern Gulf of Mexico may develop into a tropical or subtropical depression within the next day or two. Conditions have also become favorable for the development of a tropical depression east of the Bahamas in the near term with a subsequent slow westward movement.</p>
   <p>The National Weather Service outlook for October 8-12 indicates the persistence of a ridge of high pressure over the central and eastern U.S. This will provide for above-normal temperatures from the central and southern Plains to the East Coast. Above-average precipitation is possible in the northern Mississippi Valley with the passing of a frontal system. A deep trough extending into the Northwest may bring below-normal temperatures and above-average precipitation from southern Alaska to the Pacific Northwest, northern Rocky Mountains, and northern California. Outlooks extended to 14 days indicate some retrogression of the ridge and above-average temperatures across the entire contiguous U.S.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, near- to above-normal rainfall in September led to the removal of D0 on windward areas of Kauai and Maui. No improvements were made over Upcountry Maui as water restrictions have not been lifted by the local water board. Water is sent from windward Maui to Upcountry Maui by a series of ditches that feed public demand and agriculture operations, and while the boost in windward Maui rainfall has helped improve conditions over Upcountry Maui, the totals have not been sufficient to allow the local board of water supply to remove the water restrictions.  September rainfall less than 1.0 inch in much of the drought-affected areas on the Big Island of Hawaii and Oahu was insufficient for improvement. D0 conditions remained unchanged in both Alaska and Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>In addition to an extension of D2(AH) conditions from extreme northeastern West Virginia to Baltimore County in Maryland and the Delmarva Peninsula, an unusually warm and dry September led to an expansion of D0(H) in southern New Jersey extending into east and central areas of Pennsylvania. For the month of September, less than 0.75 inch of rain fell in Philadelphia, PA, and Trenton, NJ, and temperatures were 3.2 degrees F and 2.2 degrees F warmer than average, respectively. D0(A) was also introduced in eastern New Hampshire and eastern Maine to reflect a drier-than-average September and low USGS streamflow conditions. Conversely, in western New York, a large area of 1.0 to 1.5 inches of rain led to a 1-category improvement in areas south of Lake Ontario. Conditions also improved in some parts of Upstate New York, but D2(A) to D0(A) conditions remain from the eastern shore of Lake Ontario to central Vermont.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Much of the Dakotas received little or no precipitation during the past week, and precipitation totals for the past two to three months remained below average from central North Dakota to northwest South Dakota. Although 7- to 30-day rainfall totals were above average from southeastern North Dakota through eastern South Dakota, September rainfall was less than 50% of average elsewhere. Deteriorating conditions were reflected by an extension of D0(A) conditions from northeastern North Dakota to northwest South Dakota. There was also an expansion of D1(A) in western and extreme northeastern North Dakota and an introduction of D2(A) along the Canadian border. Elsewhere from South Dakota to Kansas there was no change in drought conditions. Heavier precipitation fell in central Nebraska, but rainfall in the drought-affected areas of western Nebraska and eastern Wyoming was generally less than 0.25 inch, and no change was made to the drought designations in this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, Ohio and lower Missouri Valleys">
   <p>Unusually warm and dry conditions persisted across areas of the Southeast where drought conditions have worsened during the past several months. Although the warm and dry conditions were interrupted by the passage of a cold front during the middle of the period, it weakened as it moved east and only scattered showers fell in the areas in most need of rainfall. September precipitation was less than 50% of average throughout much of the region and several locations such as Greensboro, NC, and Norfolk, Virginia, which normally receive more than 3 inches of rain in September, reported totals less than 1 inch for the month. The continued lack of rain and warmer-than-average temperatures following a record- to near-record warm August led to continued deterioration of conditions across a large region from South Carolina to Virginia. Extremely low USGS stream flows from the Gulf Coast to the mid-Atlantic along with low CPC soil moisture percentiles reflected the extremely dry conditions. The outbreak of several wildfires in parts of the Southeast during the past week was indicative of the extremely dry conditions. The drought also created water supply problems in some areas. In the town of Monteagle, Tennessee, in Grundy County, the town's source of water was reported to be days away from being exhausted, forcing the town to find other sources of water including the possible use of mobile filtration and treatment units to produce potable water. The Tennessee Valley Authority's winter flow reduction for Normandy Dam was enacted two months early to conserve water, and approximately 750,000 Tennesseans began to experience voluntary or mandatory water conservation restrictions, including some areas with a first-ever reported instance of any mandatory water restrictions having to be applied. In Virginia, the governor requested that the Secretary of the United States Department of Agriculture declare Virginia a statewide disaster area due to reductions in farm production caused by drought and high temperatures in 2007.</p>
   <p>To reflect the worsening conditions, D4(AH) was introduced in northwestern South Carolina and the western Piedmont of North Carolina to the Tar River Basin in eastern North Carolina. D3(AH) expanded from North Carolina into southern Virginia and D2(AH) in Virginia expanded toward the West Virginia border, north into Maryland, and northeast to the Delmarva Peninsula. Year-to-date precipitation deficits in northern Virginia and Maryland have approached or exceeded 10 inches in many locations. A 1-category degradation of drought also occurred from eastern Kentucky into Virginia, as well as central parts of Tennessee.</p>
   <p>Conditions also worsened in southwest Alabama, southeastern Mississippi, and extreme southeastern Louisiana, where D0(AH) conditions were introduced. Extreme D4 drought remained across parts of Georgia. Most types of outdoor residential water use were prohibited in the northern third of the state by the declaration of a level four drought response by the director of the Georgia Environmental Protection Division. In Alabama, water demand dropped for some municipalities with the onset of fall, but about 50 percent of the population was under some type of water restriction, either voluntary or mandatory. Twenty percent of monitored streams in the state were at their all time lows, and the number continued to increase throughout the week.</p>
   <p>In contrast to the deteriorating conditions in much of the region, more than 1.5 inches of rain fell near and along the Ohio River from southeastern Missouri to Ohio. This led to scaling back of D3(AH) in southern Indiana, southern Ohio and adjoining areas of West Virginia. In Arkansas, more than 1 inch of rain contributed to a wetter-than-average month and removal of D0(H) conditions in southern Arkansas and northeast Louisiana, and adjacent areas of western Mississippi. Drought conditions were also scaled back in northeastern Arkansas. In southern Florida, a wetter-than-average September led to a 1-category improvement in the Gulf Coast counties of Lee and Charlotte, while continued drier-than-average conditions northwest of Lake Okeechobee led to an expansion of D2(H) in Highlands County.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Upper Mississippi Valley and western Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Wet weather during the past one to two weeks brought drought improvement from central Minnesota to northern Wisconsin and the Upper Peninsula of Michigan. Rainfall totals for the past two weeks exceeded 3 inches with several reports of greater than 5 inches of rain, prompting a 1-category improvement of drought in a large part of the region where conditions ranged from D3(H) to D0(H). However, continued drier-than-normal conditions led to the expansion of D1(A) in Canadian border counties in northwestern Minnesota and adjoining areas of northeastern North Dakota. In south-central Illinois, continued drier-than-average conditions led to a small extension of D2(AH) across Marion County. There have been reports of lower soybean yields in this county and fall planting of winter wheat is in jeopardy because soils are too dry for germination. Although several drought indicators suggest the D2 conditions also should be extended farther north in the state, agricultural production has been generally good, and the small number of reported impacts support retaining the D1(AH) designation in central Illinois.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Two fast-moving Pacific storms raced across the Northwest U.S. during the period. The heaviest rain and snow fell from the Cascades to the Pacific coast where drought or abnormally dry conditions have been absent. Precipitation amounts generally less than 1 inch fell in areas in need of drought relief, which was not sufficient for widespread improvements. But combined with precipitation that fell the previous week across the northern Rocky Mountains, precipitation totals of 1 to 3 inches supported a 1-category improvement, from D2(AH) to D1(H) over a small area of western Montana. Precipitation during the past month has improved short-term conditions to the point that the designation was changed from AH to H across much of Montana.</p>
   <p>In western and northern Colorado, precipitation that fell during the past two weeks (1 to 4 inches) allowed for the removal of D0(H) conditions from western Colorado along with a small retraction of D0(H) and D1(H) conditions in extreme eastern Utah. Conditions also improved in much of northern Colorado, allowing for D0(H) to be pushed farther north along the Wyoming border. With the retraction of D2(H) and D1(H) to extreme southwest Wyoming, D2 conditions are now absent from Colorado and only a small area of D1(H) remains in the northwest corner of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Jay Lawrimore</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
