<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010705</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) in the short term (July 5-9), above-normal temperatures (+4 to +8 degrees) are expected in the Pacific NW and Great Basin states. In addition, excessive heat is expected to build under a ridge in the central and southern Plains through the weekend with triple digit heat indices being common; 2) the subsequent ridging in the west and the troughing in the eastern third of the country should result in very little precipitation in the West, but should bring above-normal precipitation to the Southeast; 3) in the 6-10 day period (July 9-13), temperatures are expected to remain above normal across the Intermountain West and in southern Texas eastward along the Gulf Coast to the Florida panhandle; 4) for the 6-10 day precipitation outlook, below-normal rainfall is expected again over the Great Basin and southern Texas. Above-normal precipitation could bring some relief to drought affected parts of Nebraska, Missouri, the Tennessee Valley and the western Carolinas; 5) an early start to the monsoon season may bode well for parts of the Four Corners region, western Texas and points up along the Rocky front ranges and into the western Plains over the next month or so.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Hawaii continues to be in a drought holding pattern with long-term dryness firmly established over most of the islands. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions remain across northeastern Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeastern States">
   <p>The abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1) in Maine has now pressed westward into northern New Hampshire and Vermont.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>The area of abnormal dryness (D0) continues to increase in southwestern Nebraska and has now pushed into both Wyoming and north central Kansas. In addition, abnormally hot temperatures (+10 degrees or more the past week) coupled with below-normal precipitation over the past few weeks and months have led to the emergence of a small area of moderate drought (D1) in southwestern Nebraska. The potential for a flash drought is heightened during this time of year and bears watching as a rapid onset of hot and windy conditions accompanied by a few days, or weeks, of little precipitation can quickly impact agriculture, livestock and wildfire potential. Further south, abnormally dry (D0) and moderate (D1) drought have spread north and east out of Texas and into southwestern Oklahoma. The severe drought (D2) area has also pushed north and east towards the panhandle of Texas. Recent rains in central and eastern Texas have moved the abnormally dry (D0) line westward.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Mid-South">
   <p>Beneficial rains (2 to 4 inches or more was common in Louisiana eastward to the Carolinas and down into Florida) and cooler temperatures were a welcome sight throughout the region last week. The recent trend of cooler and wetter weather has allowed conditions to continue their slow improvement. While long-term (hydrological) drought remains entrenched, we are seeing an improvement in the fire and agricultural sectors. A good start to the rainy season in Florida has brought relief to these sectors in the short term while also buying time in helping to improve the long-term deficits and water supply issues that will remain until well after the rainy season is gone. Conditions continue to improve across the board in regards to pasture, livestock, soil moisture and crop conditions for most of the region, especially in Georgia and Florida. The above mentioned rains across the entire region have led to improvement in the Carolinas, Georgia and Florida where the agricultural (A) label has been removed for now to reflect on the recent favorable conditions. Extreme drought (D3) areas in both the western Carolinas and in Florida have been reduced but still remain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The West saw a mixed bag of conditions last week. The Pacific NW enjoyed a cooler and wetter week which has been enough to hold the line in most parts but impacts continue to be felt here, especially in regards to water supplies heading into the next water year. Many locations may see, or be close to, their lowest water year precipitation totals unless abnormally wet weather makes an appearance over the coming months.</p>
   <p>In the Intermountain basin and Rocky Mountain states, the situation has worsened as they saw another round of above-normal temperatures with all but Colorado and New Mexico seeing very little, if any, precipitation.</p>
   <p>Extreme drought (D3) has now expanded south and east into all of southern Oregon, and northwest Nevada. The lower limit of this boundary area can be found south of Reno in the Walker Lake and Rivers areas.</p>
   <p>Abnormally dry (D0) conditions have also emerged in east central Alaska in an area roughly defined by Fairbanks in the north, Anchorage to the south, the Denali Park and Reserve on the west and Valdez to the east.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
