<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20011018</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) above-normal rain and snow over the Pacific Northwest from Washington to western Montana, bringing additional short-term drought relief; 2) dry and warm weather over drought areas in New Mexico and western and southern Texas; 3) little rainfall over the dry areas extending from northern Florida to Virginia.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Heavy rains hit windward areas of Maui and the Big Island, but lighter amounts over leeward areas of Oahu and elsewhere failed to end the long-term drought affecting Oahu, Molokai, and parts of the other islands.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast, Great Lakes Region, upper Mississippi Valley, and northern Plains">
   <p>Heavy rains reduced the area of D0 in Minnesota but amounts were not enough to significantly improve the D0 to D1 areas extending from eastern Ohio to New England. Dry weather allowed D0 dryness to expand across northwestern North Dakota, but precipitation caused dryness to diminish slightly in western South Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Generally light to moderate rains resulted in little change to the dryness extending from Virginia southward to Georgia, with D1 drought persisting from central Georgia northward into south-central Virginia. Severe drought (D2) developed in southwestern South Carolina from near Columbia to the Georgia border. This area has recorded cumulative rainfall one foot below normal in the past 52 weeks, resulting in near-record low streamflows. Below-normal rain resulted in a slight expansion northward of the area of D0 (W) dryness that covers much of Floridas northern peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Tennessee Valley area">
   <p>Heavy rains of 4 inches or more upgraded drought in northeast Arkansas from D2 to D1 and removed D0 dryness in western Tennessee and extreme southeastern Missouri. D0 and D1 dryness slightly diminished in Oklahoma, but drought continued in west Texas and southeastern New Mexico. Severe (D2) drought expanded westward into the El Paso area, where rainfall has been only 46% of normal for the past 6 months. Dry weather resulted in D0 dryness advancing slightly northward in south Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation increased over western Washington, with weekly rainfall totals ranging up to several inches over the Cascades and northern Olympic Peninsula. As a result, D1 (moderate) drought improved to D0 (abnormal dryness) over northwest Washington. D1 to D3 drought continued across the rest of the Pacific Northwest, south into California, Nevada, and Utah, and east into Montana and Wyoming. Rain and snow brought some short-term relief to Idaho and Montana, but amounts were not enough to significantly alter the drought depiction. Hot, dry weather caused dryness (D0) to edge southwestward in southern California.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
