<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20051222</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a series of storm systems will move through the Pacific Northwest December 20-24, affecting the coast from central California northward and providing some mountain snows in the Sierra Nevada, Cascade, Bitterroot, Sawtooth, and Teton mountains; 2) a warm-up in the Great Lakes December 22-23 will be replaced by a storm system with snow and rain December 24-25; 3) quiet weather will continue across most of the South through the period; 4) relatively calm winds and little precipitation are expected across Hawaii December 22-29; and 5) relatively warm, dry weather associated with a ridge will dominate the West December 27-31 while cold conditions will dominate the eastern United States during the same period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>No changes were made for the week in Alaska. For Hawaii, a dry week has led to the expansion of D0 across the state, with D1 conditions developing across Kauai and Niihau. The Lihue Airport on Kauai is on pace for its driest December on record. So far, only 0.07 inches have fallen for the month, compared to the previous record of 0.51 inches. Mt. Waialeale, also on Kauai, has only received 1.32 inches of precipitation thus far for December. The previous record-low December total there was 3.07 inches. Meanwhile, the average December precipitation for Mt. Waialeale is more than 45 inches!</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northern and Central Plains">
   <p>The week was generally mild and dry, with temperatures moderating considerably across the Plains from the previous week. No changes were made to the drought areas in the Central Plains. Based on a reassessment of conditions, D0 was added back into a region of northeast Montana and extreme northwest North Dakota.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Tennessee Valley and North Carolina">
   <p>Some precipitation fell during the week across the Tennessee Valley and North Carolina. In Kentucky and central Tennessee, no improvements took place because the month-to-date precipitation has remained below normal in these locations. Meanwhile, slight improvements did occur in the D0 areas of central North Carolina and eastern Tennessee as a result of the weekly precipitation totals. The long-term moderate drought (D1) is still causing hydrological drought impacts for a small area in central North Carolina, however. It is estimated that more than 500,000 people are still under mandatory water restrictions in this part of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>The week was generally dry across most of the Midwest. The exceptions to this were again in the lake-effect snow areas. Areas around Houghton, MI, received 25-29 inches of snow for the week, and the snow depth is up to 36 inches in the Keweenaw Peninsula north of Houghton. The winter has been snowy in places away from the Great Lakes as well. In Iowa, both Cedar Rapids (16.6 inches) and Burlington had their snowiest December 1-14 periods ever, and this period was the second snowiest on record for Dubuque, IA, and Moline, IL. These snows have provided little drought relief, however, as the snow-to-water ratios have been higher than normal. The Illinois Farm Bureaus weekly publication noted that some producers are purchasing drought-resistant varieties, reflecting their concern that the current drought will continue into the 2006 growing season. Levels for most of the Great Lakes continue to remain well below normal. Although most of the Midwest did not have a change in drought status for the week, a little deterioration was noted in the D0 and D1 levels across northern Missouri.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>The main story across the South continues to be the drought area in Texas and adjacent areas of Oklahoma, Arkansas, and Louisiana. Heavy rains early in the week did improve drought conditions near Houston and across Louisiana, and eliminated D0 conditions across parts of Mississippi. Unfortunately, however, conditions continued to deteriorate elsewhere. As a result, an area of Exceptional Drought (D4) was added to northeast Texas, southeast Oklahoma, and southwest Arkansas. Neighboring areas of the D2 and D3 areas were also expanded. In spite of the season, impacts are considerable. Burn bans continue to exist across all of Oklahoma and a large part of Texas, lake levels continue to fall, hay supplies for livestock are very low, and many stock ponds are completely dry. In the Dallas-Fort Worth area, 2005 is currently on pace to end as the driest year since 1956, with a year-to-date precipitation departure of -14.91 inches. In Oklahomas Southeast Climate Division, the 180-day period from June 23 through December 19, 2005, ranks as the driest such period in the 85-year record since 1921. The Division total for the period (9.99 inches) is a departure of 14.65 inches below the normal (41%). In addition, an area of Extreme Drought (D3) was added in central and southern Texas from near Austin to San Antonio to Laredo. Austin has a year-to-date precipitation departure of -12.40 inches (63%), while the departure is -15.70 inches (51%) for San Antonio. The year-to-date precipitation total for Carrizo Springs, a town just north of Laredo, is 9.90 inches (49% of normal). Going back to 1912, no year with a complete record of data has had less than 10 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A strong storm system affected the West Coast late in the week, providing considerable precipitation for the Oregon and California coasts. Although some improvement occurred to the east of the San Joaquin Valley, most of the Valley itself had precipitation totals around one-half inch or less. Precipitation totals for the December 17-19 period totaled 0.56 inches in Fresno, 0.28 inches in Hanford, and 0.01 inches in Bakersfield. As a result of the dry conditions, winter wheat emergence has been slow across the Valley. The week was dry across Arizona. Flagstaff has reported only a trace of snowfall so far this season, and only 2.26 inches of precipitation since the beginning of September. Snowbowl Ski Resort north of Flagstaff remains closed because of the lack of snow. In northwest Montana and northern Idaho, dry conditions have led to an expansion of D0 and D1 conditions. The snow water equivalent is 52-64% of normal for the Water Year for basins in these regions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
