<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030717</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may have an impact on abnormally dry or drought areas during the next 5 days (July 17-21) include: 1) The remnants of former Hurricane Claudette may provide limited drought relief to southwestern Texas and parts of the Southwest. Claudette's moisture will be steered around the sprawling ridge of high pressure centered over the Four Corners region, and will likely enhance the shower activity associated with the Southwestern monsoon (summer rainy season); 2) A sharp but fluctuating temperature boundary will persist along a northwest-to-southeast line across the Plains and Midwest. Cooler air to the north and east will provide favorable conditions for agricultural interests, but hot weather to the south and west will continue to severely stress reproductive summer crops. A series of disturbances will plunge southeastward along the boundary, sparking thunderstorm development. Showers are most likely from the upper Midwest southward into Kansas and Missouri, while mostly dry weather is forecast for the southern Plains; 3) Mostly dry weather and above-normal temperatures are expected across the Great Basin, northern High Plains, northern Rockies, and the Northwest, but beneficial showers are expected in northern New England.</p>
   <p>The 6- to 10-day outlook for July 22-26 calls for the continuation of a sharp temperature gradient across the nation's mid-section. Above-normal temperatures are forecast across the western half of the U.S., while cooler-than-normal weather and near- to above-normal precipitation totals are likely in much of the East. Above-normal rainfall is forecast across southern Texas and may provide some drought relief in the Southwest, but drier-than-normal conditions are expected across the northern and central High Plains, the northern Rockies, and the Northwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>In Hawaii, low reservoir levels on Oahu and western Molokai necessitated a change to moderate and severe drought (D1 and D2), respectively. Despite the resumption of trade wind showers in recent weeks, recovery from varying of dryness and drought (D0 to D2) has been slow from Oahu to the Big Island. Farther north, scattered showers prevented the expansion of abnormal dryness (D0) across east-central Alaska, despite record warmth. On July 9, Tok (91 F) posted a daily-record high, while Fairbanks (85 F) had its warmest day since the summer of 1999. Nevertheless, Fairbanks' July 1-14 rainfall, 0.94 inch, boosted its year-to-date precipitation to 3.06 inches (74 percent of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Weekly rainfall topped 2 inches in a broad band from Iowa to the middle and upper Ohio Valley, while locally heavy showers also dotted the Great Lakes region. As a result of the latter rains, abnormal dryness (D0) was erased from parts of northern Illinois and southeastern Wisconsin. Heavy showers also reduced the amount of abnormal dryness across northern Lower Michigan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Despite scattered showers and below-normal temperatures, there was little change in the overall depiction of dryness across the nation's northern tier from northern New York into Maine. Dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) were more of a long-term concern in New Hampshire and Maine, while short-term precipitation deficits were more apparent farther west.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>An untimely heat wave struck the southern and central Plains, threatening summer crops during a sensitive period of development. High temperatures reached or exceeded 95 F (a critical temperature for many reproductive summer crops) on nearly every day during the first two weeks of July across southeastern Colorado and the western half of Kansas. Although heat was more sporadic elsewhere on the Plains, temperatures reached 100 F at least once during the first half of July as far north as central North Dakota and southeastern Montana.</p>
   <p>Abnormal dryness (D0) was broadly expanded across the central and southern Plains to reflect the effects of recent heat and short-term dryness on agricultural interests. Pueblo, Colorado, posted an all-time-record high temperature of 109 F on July 13, edging the mark of 108 F set on June 29, 1990. A day later, Ashland, Kansas, logged a high of 113 F, tying its monthly record established on July 31, 1922 and 1934. Meanwhile, long-term dryness and drought (D0 to D2) remained intact across much of the northern and central High Plains, resulting in a broad array of conditions across the nation's mid-section at different time scales.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Dry weather and a record-setting heat wave brought gradually worsening drought conditions to much of the West. Agricultural dryness (D0) remained a concern in the Northwest, while much of the Southwest and Intermountain West continued to face problems related to drought-lowered reservoirs and stress on dryland agricultural interests. Among the stations tying all-time-record high temperatures during the recent heat wave were Hanksville, Utah (114 F on July 11), and Grand Junction, Colorado (105 F on July 12 and 13). St. Johns, Arizona, tied its all-time record with a high of 104 F on July 9 (most recently attained from July 2-4, 1923), then surpassed that standard with highs of 105 F on July 10, 12, and 13, and 106 F on July 14. At lower elevations, relief was hard to come by even at night, as shown by the July 15 low temperature of 96 F in Phoenix, Arizona. The highest minimum temperature previously observed in Phoenix was 93 F on July 20, 1989, June 27, 1990, and July 14, 2003. Ironically, just a year ago, from July 10-14, 2002, dozens of all-time record-high temperatures were tied or broken in the West, including highs of 105 F in Grand Junction on July 13 and 14.</p>
   <p>Despite the official onset of the monsoon (summer rainy season) in the Southwest near the Mexican border, showers were widely scattered. In Tucson, Arizona, where average dewpoint temperatures above 54 F from July 11-13 signaled the technical monsoon onset, July 1-14 rainfall totaled 0.54 inch. It was Tucson's fifth-latest monsoon arrival in the last half-century, and latest since July 17, 1997. July-September rainfall typically averages 5.82 inches in Tucson, 48 percent of its normal annual total.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western Gulf Coast">
   <p>Hurricane Claudette made landfall on July 15 near Port O'Connor, Texas, bearing heavy rainfall and maximum sustained winds of at least 80 m.p.h. near the center. Most of the rainfall associated with Claudette's passage across southern Texas fell after the cutoff time for this summary and will be reflected in next week's Drought Monitor. Prior to Claudette's arrival, widespread showers eliminated an area of moderate drought (D1) along and near the Texas coast and brought further reductions in abnormal dryness (D0).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
