<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010816</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Anticipated weather features during the next 10-day period (August 15-24) that may impact areas with abnormal dryness or drought include: 1) a pair of cold fronts should move across the eastern half of the Nation during August 15-19. With an ample supply of moisture, these fronts, plus typical afternoon summer thunderstorm activity, may produce beneficial showers over much of the eastern half of the Nation. The exceptions to this (minimal rainfall) include the eastern Ohio Valley and mid-Atlantic, southern Texas, and the Dakotas. 5-day temperatures should average near to below-normal. 2) In contrast, high pressure (dry and warm) should dominate the West, keeping wildfire activity high. Scattered monsoonal showers should continue in the southern Rockies. 3) The track and intensity of Tropical Depression #4 (Chantal?) east of the Antilles will be monitored for any possible impact on Puerto Rico. The 6 to10-day (August 20-24) outlook calls for: 4) above-normal precipitation for the Southeast, coastal mid-Atlantic and New England, and Pacific Northwest, and below-normal rainfall in the Great Lakes region (normal elsewhere); 5) warmer than normal in the southern and northern thirds of the Plains, upper Midwest, and northern New England, with subnormal temperatures predicted for the southeastern quarter of the Nation and Far West.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Light, scattered showers (daily totals generally less than 0.25 inches) fell on most windward locations of Kauai, Oahu, Maui, and the Big Island, while little or no rain was measured at most leeward portions, maintaining drought conditions across Hawaii. In Puerto Rico, a reassessment of weekly and monthly station data showed abnormal dryness along the south coastal and eastern interior regions of the island, with June-July rainfall totals of 69% and 73% of normal, respectively, during the normally wettest time of the year (May-November).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Plains and Midwest">
   <p>A generally dry week, with subnormal temperatures in western areas and warm weather in eastern sections. Thunderstorms were limited to eastern North Dakota, northern Minnesota, and eastern Wisconsin where 1 to 2 inches of rain alleviated abnormal dryness (D0) in northeastern Wisconsin. Farther south, however, two areas (eastern Nebraska into central Illinois, and central Minnesota into southwestern Wisconsin) have missed significant rains in the Midwest the past several weeks, expanding the area of abnormal dryness in the western and central Corn Belt, and developing a pocket of D1 in eastern Nebraska into western Iowa, and in central Illinois. According to NASS/USDA, 63%, 64%, and 66% of the topsoil moisture is very short or short in Nebraska, Iowa, and Illinois, respectively.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>The combination of meager rainfall (0-0.5 inches) and the first widespread, prolonged hot spell of the summer (weekly departures exceeding +6F, with highs well into the nineties and occasionally topping 100F) expanded abnormal dryness and drought across the central and eastern Great Lakes and western New England. A late week cold front brought relief from the heat, but significant rainfall (2 to 6 inches) occurred in areas farther south and east. These showers were enough to eliminate D0 across New Jersey and eastern Pennsylvania, but lower totals (less than 2 inches) maintained abnormal dryness in Connecticut.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>After last weeks copious rainfall from Tropical Storm Barry, Florida returned to a more typical summertime pattern (widely-scattered thundershowers). As a result, weekly rainfall amounts were much lower (between 0.2 to 1 inch), except for locally heavy downpours (2 to 4 inches) around the Tampa-Sarasota area and in the Panhandle. Although recharge of rivers, lakes, and aquifers generally continued, the pace has slowed, stagnated, or in some instances declined with the sharp drop in precipitation. In north-central Florida, weekly streamflow rates and aquifers, even after Barrys rains, still averaged below normal, thus maintaining D1(W). Although Lake Okeechobees level continues to rise, it was still 2.7 feet below the 1979-1995 average, or about the same level as last August. Accordingly, the D0(W) area was adjusted southward to be consistent with the Drought Monitors depiction a year ago. Farther north, with heavy thunderstorms missing most of South Carolina and south-central North Carolina and weekly temperatures averaging 5F above normal, long-term drought was maintained and short-term dryness developed in eastern South Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Delta">
   <p>The heat and drought eased somewhat as leftover moisture from the remnants of Tropical Storm Barry, plus a cold front passage into northern Texas, lowered temperatures and triggered numerous showers and thunderstorms across the south-central Plains and Delta regions. More than 2 inches of rain fell on the Texas Panhandle, and northwestern, southwestern, and east-central Oklahoma. Even with the recent rain, however, precipitation across most of southwestern Oklahoma was still less than 25% of normal since June 1, with deficits of 4 to 8 inches. Farther east, heavy rains (2 to 5 inches) also drenched most of Arkansas, western sections of Kentucky and Tennessee, and the Missouri Bootheel. Weekly temperatures averaged near to slightly above normal. In contrast, eastern and southern Arkansas, southern Kansas, parts of Oklahoma, and southwestern Texas recorded much lower amounts, maintaining or increasing drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Hot weather (highs in the 90Fs and 100Fs, weekly departures of +6 to +8F) and high-altitude, dry thundershowers sparked hundreds of new wildfires across the Western States (mainly Washington, Oregon, Nevada), with 36 large, active wildfires reported in the West (20 in Nevada affecting over 200,000 acres) as of August 13. Increasing fire danger and new wildfires west of the southern Cascades prompted partial removal of Oregons hydrological drought designation. Widespread drought persisted across the region, and with the Bruneau River dropping to record low levels, D3 was expanded into its headwaters in southwestern Idaho (Owyhee County) and north-central Nevada. The August Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) for Montana also indicated extremely dry conditions in the western and southern thirds of the state, thus increasing severe drought (D2) in those areas. The exception to this was the Marias River basin (south of Alberta) where the SWSI showed somewhat better conditions, so D1 was maintained.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
