<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20001019</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During October 17 - 28, the following potential occurrences could impact dryness- and drought-affected regions: (1) Moderate precipitation in parts of the Mississippi Valley early in the period; (2) Scattered moderate precipitation in the northern and central Rockies during the first half of the period; (3) Episodes of locally heavy precipitation in the Southwest, southern Rockies, and southern half of the Plains; (4) Warm and very dry weather in the Southeast and, to a lesser extent, northern sections of the Plains and Great Lakes region, at least through the first half of the period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Long-term dryness and drought continues to affect leeward parts of all islands in Hawaii. Severe drought (D2), primarily for agricultural and wildfire-related concerns, covers the leeward sides of Maui and the Big Island, and all of Molokai. Abnormally dry conditions also continue along the northern coast of Puerto Rico, where year-to-date rainfall was near 7 inches below normal at San Juan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Another relatively wet week ended D0 conditions in Maine. Most formerly-dry areas recorded at least 1 inch of precipitation in the last 7 days, with 2 to 3 inches measured at many locations.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Generally 1 to 3 inches of precipitation fell on parts of southern and northeastern Texas, Oklahoma, southeastern Kansas, western and northern Missouri, and the northern Great Lakes region. Light precipitation covered most other areas, but little or none was observed in southern Minnesota, South Dakota, Nebraska, eastern and northwestern Iowa, western Kansas, and the central High Plains. During the last 90 days, less than 25% of normal precipitation fell on east-central New Mexico and the northwestern one-third of Texas, including the Panhandle.</p>
   <p>The precipitation pattern prompted improvement from D2 to D1 in sections of Oklahoma and Texas, but allowed D3 to expand into sections of eastern and southern Nebraska and west-central Iowa, where 90-day deficits exceeded 4 inches. In addition, D0 conditions expanded slightly northward in South Dakota and northeastern Montana.</p>
   <p>In part of northern Missouri, ample precipitation has fallen during the past few months, but groundwater analyses indicated that the region has not yet recovered from long-term moisture deficiencies, so D0(W) was introduced because of this concern.</p>
   <p>Farther south, water supplies are unfavorably low across Texas, particularly in southern and western parts of the state. According to the International Boundary and Water Commission, water stores at two reservoirs along the Rio Grande (Amistad and Falcon) were exceptionally meager, amounting to just over 30% and slightly less than 10% of conservation thresholds, respectively. Amistad now contains about 25% less water than at this time last year, and more than half of Falcons reserves have been lost during the same period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South and Southeast">
   <p>Little or no rain fell during the last 7 days in areas to the south and east of the lower Mississippi and Ohio Valleys, allowing dryness to persist or increase. Most areas from the southern Appalachians and extreme western Georgia westward through the lower Mississippi Valley recorded precipitation deficits of at least 1 inch since mid-July, with shortfalls approaching 8 inches in parts of northern and southern Alabama, northwestern Mississippi, and southern Louisiana.</p>
   <p>As a result, exceptional (D4) drought expanded in the central Gulf Coast region, and conditions deteriorated to D3 in eastern Louisiana and southwestern Mississippi. Farther north, D2 and D3 conditions expanded in central Tennessee, and D0 to D1 conditions pushed northward in the extreme southwestern Virginias. Local reports indicated that conditions were also worsening in the western Carolinas and eastern Tennessee, although drought categorizations generally remained the same as last week. This region will be monitored closely for signs of further deterioration.</p>
   <p>In much of Georgia, the Carolinas, and Florida, 90-day rainfall totals were near to above normal despite the dry week, but long-term deficits dating back to May 1998 continued to prompt serious hydrological concerns.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Beneficial precipitation fell on most areas, substantially improving dryness and eliminating the disproportionate wildfire and agricultural concerns that had been affecting much of the region. Tropical moisture from a decaying Pacific Ocean system streamed into southeastern Arizona and southwestern New Mexico, dropping 3 to 5 inches of rain on much of the region. Farther north, totals of 1 to locally 3 inches fell on significant portions of southwestern Colorado, northeastern Utah, western Wyoming, central and southern Idaho, and western Montana. Most other previously-dry areas recorded at least light precipitation.</p>
   <p>As a result, D0 was eradicated in the wetter sections of Arizona and New Mexico, and most other areas from the Rockies westward improved by 1 drought category. Still, D2 covered a fairly extensive area in the northern Rockies, and a small region near the central Utah/Arizona border. According to the National Interagency Fire Center, only the northeastern Rockies and southern California remained in high fire danger as of October 16.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
