<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060413</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>April 12  17 are expected to bring moderate to heavy precipitation in a swath from the Dakotas eastward through the Great Lakes, upper Midwest, Ohio Valley, mid-Atlantic region, and Northeast. Between 1 and 2 inches are expected from the east-central Dakotas eastward through much of the central Appalachians and western New York. Meanwhile, light to moderate precipitation is anticipated in the northern and central Rockies and in parts of central and northern Arizona, and little or none is expected in most of the Southwest, High Plains, central and southern Great Plains, middle and lower Mississippi Valley, Gulf Coast, southern Appalachians, and southern half of the Atlantic Coastal states. Above-normal temperatures are expected over most of the country, with daily highs averaging 9F to 15F above normal from the Southwest, central and southern High Plains, and most of the Great Plains eastward through the mid-Atlantic region.</p>
   <p>The ensuing five days (April 18  22) should be warm and dry in most of the central United States from the eastern Rockies to the central Great Lakes region, Tennessee Valley, and central Gulf Coast. Below-normal precipitation is also anticipated across the Ohio Valley and Northeast, with the odds favoring above-normal amounts only in the far Northwest and across the southern half of the Florida Peninsula. Meanwhile, southeastern Alaska should be cold and dry, with below-normal temperatures also forecast for parts of the Northeast and the Florida Peninsula.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Near- to above-normal mountain snowpack led to the elimination of D0 conditions across east-central parts of the state while low snowpack and a few weeks of consistently below-normal precipitation prompted D0 expansion into the northern Panhandle region. Farther south, 3 to 6 inches of rain last week eliminated D0 conditions in the southernmost reaches of the Panhandle. Elsewhere, no changes were evident from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central Gulf Coast">
   <p>Hot and dry weather, with only scattered locations reporting a few tenths of an inch this past week, led to the northward and eastward expansion of D0AH and D1AH conditions, with moderate drought now extending into much of the Florida Panhandle, and to the introduction of D2AH conditions across southern sections of Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, and adjacent southeastern Texas. Areas from south-central Louisiana eastward through the D1AH area in the Florida Panhandle have received 9 to 12 inches less than normal rainfall since early January, and significant portions of the southern tier of Louisiana north and west of New Orleans are 16 to locally more than 20 inches below normal for the past year.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Widespread moderate to locally heavy precipitation (1 to locally 3 inches) fell on central and northern New England, parts of the central and southern Appalachians, eastern sections of Tennessee and Kentucky, northern Alabama, portions of southwestern Georgia, and sections of north-central and east-central Florida. Moderate precipitation was less widespread across the lower Northeast, the northern half of the mid-Atlantic region, the coastal Carolinas, the southern half and northwesternmost reaches of Georgia, the rest of the Florida Peninsula, and the easternmost fringes of southern Florida. Light precipitation, generally one-half inch or less, fell on other dry areas along the Eastern Seaboard.</p>
   <p>This pattern brought a mixed bag of changes to the dryness and drought conditions in the East. D0 was eliminated in Maine and New Hampshire, and in most of West Virginia, east-central Kentucky, northeastern Tennessee, and parts of the central Florida Peninsula. Dryness was relatively shallow and short-term in nature in these areas before this week, and improvements were based on significant streamflow increases and improved soil moisture. Topsoil moisture also increased through much of the mid-Atlantic, but with continued substantial short-term moisture deficits and a quick decline in streamflows following initial increases caused by runoff, D0 was kept in this region. Also, despite moderate rains in southeastern Tennessee, 90-day precipitation totals only rebounded to between 50 and 70 percent of normal by April 11, 2006, and with continued low reservoir levels, D0 conditions remained in this region as well.</p>
   <p>In contrast, declining streamflows and increasing short-term precipitation deficits led to some D0 expansion into central New York, northwestern Pennsylvania, and east-central Ohio despite some precipitation reports of 0.5 to 0.9 inch in the latter two regions. Farther south, another drier-than-normal week in south-central Virginia and the interior Carolinas led to D1AH expansion into much of central and northern South Carolina, and some D2AH expansion in North Carolina and adjacent Virginia. Less than half of normal precipitation has fallen on most of the D1AH region during the last 90 days, and totals dating back to last April are about a foot below normal for most of the D2AH region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>More than an inch of precipitation fell on a few parts of the region last week. Specifically, totals ranged from 2 to locally 4 inches in central Illinois, and fairly widespread totals of 1 to 2 inches were reported in southeastern Montana, western South Dakota, southeastern Iowa, and west-central Illinois. Light to moderate amounts (0.5 to locally 2.0 inches) dampened parts of southern South Dakota, northwestern Nebraska, southeastern Nebraska and adjacent Kansas, east-central Missouri, northwestern Arkansas and adjacent sections of Missouri and Oklahoma, and a portion of southeastern Kansas. Most other locations recorded a few tenths of an inch last week, but little or none fell on the southern half of the High Plains, most of Texas, part of northeastern Kansas and northwestern Missouri, northern Illinois, and much of southern and eastern Arkansas.</p>
   <p>The resultant depiction of dryness and drought across this broad region did not change much from last week overall, though some adjustments were necessary. Abnormal dryness was taken out of central Illinois, and improvements to D0 were made in southeastern  Iowa and part of west-central Illinois. In addition, increased precipitation for the past several weeks also led to improvements to D0 in the Black Hills and adjacent western South Dakota. Farther south and east, 1-category improvements were also introduced in small parts of southeastern Nebraska, southern parts of last weeks D2H area in north-central Illinois, north-central Kansas, southeastern Kansas, and west-central Arkansas. Furthermore, D3AH conditions were removed from central sections of the Oklahoma and Texas Panhandles, despite the dry week, based on a re-assessment of both the extent and effects of a few episodes of precipitation during the last few months.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, D0AH conditions were introduced in part of southeastern Missouri and the eastern tier of Arkansas while moderate drought expanded into central and north-central Arkansas. Wildfires, low streamflows and reservoir levels, and poor winter wheat crop conditions remain the causes for greatest concern in the central and southern Plains. Farther north, especially through the High Plains, low streamflows and reservoir levels persist in some areas despite recent increases in topsoil moisture brought about by a few weeks of relatively damp weather.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Southwest">
   <p>Another inch or two of precipitation fell on much of western Montana and Idaho, and on smaller areas in southwestern Colorado and east-central Arizona. Amounts were generally less than half an inch in other areas of dryness and drought in the Rockies and Southwest, with little or none reported in much of central and northern Wyoming, eastern Colorado, eastern Utah, southern Arizona, and most of New Mexico.</p>
   <p>This precipitation pattern induced only a few changes in dryness and drought conditions, but some of those made are noteworthy. A recent evaluation by local authorities across the state of Montana led the Drought Monitor to remove D0H conditions from west-central Montana, but despite some recent precipitation, D0H was brought back in to portions of southeastern Montana because of unfavorably low streamflows and snowmelt-induced streamflow outlooks.</p>
   <p>Farther west, D0H was removed entirely from Idaho because of abnormally robust mountain snow water contents and expected significant rises in reservoir levels (along with some possible flooding) as the snowpack melts. However, it should be noted that groundwater, aquifer levels, and some reservoir levels remain unfavorably low in the Big Lost and Little Lost River valleys, and in the Snake River valley from the American Falls Reservoir to Twin Falls. As a result, the Idaho Department of Water Resources still considers these regions to be experiencing drought for their purposes. In addition, Bear Lake in southeastern Idaho is expected to remain at below-normal levels for at least the next few months. During the protracted multi-year drought, streamflows feeding Bear Lake averaged only 5 to10 percent of normal due to loses from the stream channel to the groundwater.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, small areas of improvement were introduced in part of southwestern Colorado (to D0AH) and east-central Arizona (to D2AH) while the consensus of indicators led to the expansion of D2AH conditions through central New Mexico.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
