<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20010118</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Systems predicted to affect the Nations dry or drought areas include: 1) A large storm system bringing significant rain and snow to the eastern third of the country through Sunday, with rainfall amounts forecast to exceed 2 inches from Mississippi to southwestern Virginia and 1 inch from northern Georgia to western North Carolina; 2) A series of Pacific storms accompanied by rain and snow in the Pacific Northwest; 3) a Pacific storm delivering more rain and snow to California on January 24-26 and then rain to Texas, including areas in west Texas experiencing long-term drought.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, D0 dryness worsened to D1 drought across the Big Island, where officials have asked the public for a voluntary 10% reduction in water use. Scattered areas of dryness remained in Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Precipitation amounts remained light from southwestern Pennsylvania southward through North Carolina. Ninety-day precipitation totals have been under 50% of normal for much of the region, and abnormal dryness (D0) continued from southwestern Pennsylvania through West Virginia, with conditions ranging up to D3 (extreme drought) in western North Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Precipitation amounts of 0.5 to 1 inch and melting snow did improve moisture conditions in drought-affected areas of Kansas, Iowa, and Nebraska, leading to the removal of the severe (D2) drought in Nebraska. Above-normal temperatures during the last 2-3 weeks pulled most of the frost out of the ground so that snow melt increased soil moisture reserves by an additional inch in Nebraska. Soil moisture there has increased 3-5 inches since the low point set in September. Small areas of D2 drought lingered in northeast Kansas and western Iowa.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Moderate to exceptional drought persisted across the Florida peninsula, as rainfall amounts stayed under .25 inches. Extreme drought (D3) expanded southward to include Lake Okeechobee, which is fractionally above record low levels for this date. To the north, amounts of .25 to 1.0 inch had no appreciable impact on the hydrologic drought that covers much of the Southeast from southeast Louisiana to Georgia and northward to the Tennessee Valley.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A major Pacific storm brought heavy rain and snow to the West, especially to California. Three-inch rainfall totals were common over coastal California, with snow leaving the equivalent of 2 to 4-inch melted amounts in the Sierra Nevada. The moisture markedly improved moisture conditions across California, but some lingering low soil moisture levels continued over the southern Central Valley. The snows trimmed back but did not eliminate the area of D0 in and near the Sierra, where the seasons cumulative precipitation and snow water content continued to be near or less than 50% of normal. The weeks rain and snow eliminated the area of D0 dryness in central Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
