<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20090611</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (June 11-15), temperatures continue to be below normal over much of the United States.  Departures will range from 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit below normal over the Plains to 9-12 degrees below normal over California.  Temperatures should be a little above normal over Texas and through the Southeast, with temperatures ranging 3-6 degrees Fahrenheit above normal.  An active precipitation pattern will continue to follow the jet stream, with precipitation maxima over portions of Missouri and Kentucky.  Precipitation chances are also greatest over New England, the Central Plains, and into the northern Rocky Mountains.  The Climate Prediction Center 6-10 day forecast (June 16-20) shows temperatures are expected to be below normal over the western half of the United States, New England, and portions of Alaska’s northern coast and Aleutian Islands.  Above-normal temperatures are forecasted over the southern Plains and into the Southeast.  During this time, above-normal precipitation is projected over the High Plains, Rocky Mountains, and into the Pacific Northwest.  The east coast and into Florida also show above-normal chances for precipitation.  Below-normal precipitation is shown over Alaska, Texas, and northern Minnesota during this time frame as well.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>No changes in Alaska for this week.  In Hawaii, impacts to the agriculture interests in the state have prompted degradation over much of the Islands.  On Maui, D1 was expanded over the entire island and D2 was introduced along the western edge.  On the Big Island, a 1-category degradation over the eastern half of the island took place, with D1 conditions introduced.  On Lanai and Molokai, D1 now covers all of both islands.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Gulf Coast and Florida">
   <p>Continuing rains over much of the state have allowed for the removal of all moderate drought from south Florida; just a small pocket of D0 remains along the southwest coast where the rains have lagged behind other areas.  Despite a dry winter and spring, no impacts are being reported at this time, as the last several weeks have brought abundant precipitation. D0 was introduced this week into southern Louisiana as precipitation over the last several months has fallen well below normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>D0 was introduced into Ohio this week.  The new area of D0 has fallen behind in precipitation over the last several months.  This area of Ohio was also very dry at the end of summer and into fall in 2008.  There have been no reported impacts in this region, but conditions could change rapidly as we go into a typically warmer period and water demands increase. D0 was improved over portions of western Iowa and southwestern Minnesota in response to recent rains alleviating concerns in this area.  The D1/D2 regions in Minnesota and Wisconsin did record rain this week, but it was only enough to stave off any further deterioration; no improvements were warranted.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast and Mid-Atlantic, and Carolinas">
   <p>D0 was expanded this week into portions of Massachusetts, Connecticut, and Rhode Island.  D0 was eliminated from Georgia, western North Carolina, and western South Carolina.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>A very active week over portions of the region has allowed for some improvements to areas of D0 that had just been introduced.  In portions of Nebraska, 2 to 3 inch rain totals for the week were common along the Platte River corridor, with some locations reporting hail that wiped out crops over thousands of acres in southeast Nebraska.  D0 was improved in portions of central and eastern Nebraska as well as in the panhandle of the state.  In areas that did not see the heavy rains, D0 was expanded into south central and north central portions of the state. In South Dakota, D0 was improved along the western edge as well as in the eastern portions of the state.  North Dakota had a slight improvement to the D0 from rains over the last week.</p>
   <p>In Oklahoma and Kansas, a dry week prompted the expansion of D0 into southern Kansas and the introduction of D1 in northern Oklahoma.  In Texas this week, it was noted that the most recent rains over the last several months have had little to no impact on the hydrology in the state, with rivers, streams, and reservoirs lagging as some locations have had improvements.  Many changes were made across the state this week, with D0/D1 expanded in the northern panhandle, D2 improved in the southern tip of the state, D2/D3/D4 expanded in south central Texas, and D0 expanded in central Texas. Even in areas where some good rains fell during the spring months, agricultural and hydrological concerns are still having issues related to the long-term dryness in the region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>D0 was improved in Nevada around Lake Tahoe, while D2 was expanded in the area to the north and east of Reno.  Water supplies for irrigation have continued to be lowered from previous forecasts and this will have a direct impact on the region.  A categorical improvement was made over southeast Idaho as indicators on all time scales show this area improving.  D0 was expanded in north central Montana while D0 was also expanded out of Montana into northern portions of Wyoming this week.  Dry conditions over the last few months have led to this change.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
