<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20130718</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>A broad upper-level ridge extended across the contiguous United States during this U.S. Drought Monitor week.  A cold front moving through the ridge brought showers to parts of the northern Plains and Midwest while a closed low retrograded beneath the ridge late in the week, dropping locally heavy rains as it trekked from the Mid-Atlantic to Southern Plains.  Moisture from the low enhanced monsoon showers over the Southwest, while the rest of the West was dry.  Temperatures were above normal except where depressed by frontal showers or the retrograding low.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 6 days (July 17-22), a stationary front draped across the central Plains to Mid-Atlantic may bring up to an inch of rain from eastern Nebraska to the East Coast, Great Lakes, and Gulf of Mexico Coast, with over 2 inches possible along the Mid-Mississippi to Ohio and Tennessee valleys.  Monsoon showers could bring an inch or more of rain to the Four Corners states.  Less than a quarter of an inch of rain is forecast for Oklahoma and adjoining parts of Texas, with most of the West expected to be dry.  Temperatures should be near to above normal, with the warmest anomalies (6-12 degrees above normal) expected in parts of the West.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6-10 day and 8-14 day forecasts (for July 23-31) show the highest likelihood of above-normal precipitation for the Southwest and much of the country east of the Mississippi, with below-normal precipitation from the Northwest to the Central and Southern Plains.  The Northeast may expect cooler-than-normal temperatures with the highest likelihood of above-normal temperatures from the West to Great Plains.  The southern two-thirds of Alaska should be warmer and drier than normal with the north cooler and wetter than normal.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Precipitation was below normal at most of the stations in Hawaii this week, prompting the expansion of D0 to cover the rest of Maui, Molokai, and Lanai.  With sufficient rainfall and above-normal streamflow, Puerto Rico remained free of drought and abnormal dryness on the USDM map.  Alaskan stations were generally drier than normal this week, but with decreased wildfire activity, no change was made to the depiction for Alaska this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>The retrograding upper-level low spread half an inch or more of rain across most of the Southeast, with locally 2 inches or more in parts of the Carolinas and Alabama.  With rainfall deficits eased, streams at normal levels or above, and the absence of any drought impacts, the remaining spots of D0 in Alabama were removed, thus freeing the Southeast of any drought or abnormal dryness on the USDM map.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast to Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>A broad upper-level ridge extended across the contiguous United States during this U.S. Drought Monitor week.  A cold front moving through the ridge brought showers to parts of the northern Plains and Midwest while a closed low retrograded beneath the ridge late in the week, dropping locally heavy rains as it trekked from the Mid-Atlantic to Southern Plains.  Moisture from the low enhanced monsoon showers over the Southwest, while the rest of the West was dry.  Temperatures were above normal except where depressed by frontal showers or the retrograding low.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Lower Mississippi Valley">
   <p>The upper low ended its retrograde motion over the Southern Plains where it dumped several inches of rain over central Oklahoma to north central Texas.  Seven-day rainfall totals exceeded 2 inches at several Oklahoma stations with 4.54 inches being the heaviest report.  Unfortunately, most of the rain fell over areas that were already drought-free, but enough overspread drought areas to cut back the D0-D2 (abnormally dry to severe drought) in the north central counties and D0-D1(abnormally dry to moderate drought) in the south central counties, and eliminate the D4 (exceptional drought) oval in southwestern Oklahoma.  In neighboring Texas, 2-4 inches of rain was widespread in the central to north central counties, with 7+ inches reported in Callahan and Coleman counties and nearly 9 inches falling in Eastland County.  A wider area of 1+ inches stretched to the east and south, with bands of 1+ inches of rain in the panhandle.  As a result, D1-D4 was improved in many areas.  But the beneficial rain did not fall everywhere.</p>
   <p>Drought or abnormal dryness expanded in parts of southwest, south, northeast, and southeast Texas, as well as eastern Oklahoma where soil moisture continued to decline.  Growing rainfall deficits over the last 30-90 days prompted expansion of D0 into Louisiana, Arkansas, and adjoining parts of Mississippi.  Acute precipitation deficits and drying soils led to expansion of D1 and introduction of D2 in Arkansas.  Further to the north, 30-day rainfall deficits, worsening soil moisture, and warming temperatures resulted in D0 expansion in Missouri and Iowa and eastern sections of Kansas and Nebraska, D1 expansion in northeast Kansas, and D2-D3 expansion in western Nebraska.  According to U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) reports, the percent of topsoil short or very short in Arkansas grew from 62 percent statewide July 7 to 68 percent July 14, but the percentage increased rapidly in Missouri (from 23 to 53 percent) and Iowa (12 to 35 percent).  Top soil conditions also worsened in Nebraska, going from 53 percent to 62 percent, and Kansas (68 to 74 percent).   Rains contracted D2 in southwest South Dakota but continued dry conditions expanded D0 and D1 in other sections of the state.  Two to three inches of rain in northern Minnesota shaved the northern edge of the D0-D1 there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Southeastern sections of the West saw improved conditions while northern and western parts had deterioration.  Monsoon showers, enhanced by moisture from the upper low over the southern Plains, dropped several inches of rain over some parts of Colorado, New Mexico, and Arizona.  D3 (extreme drought) was trimmed in extreme southeast Arizona where heavy rains this week gave Douglas an all-time monthly precipitation record for any month of 7.85 inches of rain so far this July.  Improvements were made in New Mexico and Colorado by keeping a balance between above-normal rain in the short term (last 7-30 days) and extreme dryness in the long-term (6-24 months).  D3-D4 was contracted in southwest New Mexico, D3-D4 was trimmed in parts of Colorado and adjacent north central New Mexico, D3 cut in adjoining southwest Nebraska, and D1 pulled back in north central Colorado.  USDA top soil reports showed improvement for New Mexico, which went from 96 percent of the top soil in the state poor to very poor last week to 88 percent July 14, and Colorado (86 percent to 80 percent).  But conditions deteriorated in the Northwest, with Idaho’s percentage rising from 39 to 45 percent top soil short to very short and Oregon going from 54 percent to 66 percent.</p>
   <p>Growing precipitation deficits and worsening soil moisture and pasture and rangeland conditions resulted in the addition of D0 along the east slopes of the Cascades in Washington, expansion of D0 in western Montana and D1 in eastern Oregon, north central Idaho, and western Montana, and D2 in central to eastern Idaho and in the Lake Tahoe region and northward along the California-Nevada state line.  Short-term agricultural impacts were growing, adding to the long-term hydrological impacts of the drought, from the Plains to West, resulting in a relabeling of the impacts indicators (to mostly SL).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
