<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070322</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>From March 21 to March 26, the complex interaction between a nearly stationary front and an upper-level disturbance will produce widespread precipitation.  Significant precipitation, totaling as much as 1 to 3 inches, may fall in the Four Corners states, while even higher totals may occur in Texas and Oklahoma.  Severe thunderstorms will accompany heavy rain across the south-central U.S.  Meanwhile, locally heavy showers and thunderstorms will also develop along the stationary front from the central Plains eastward into the Mid-Atlantic states.  However, unfavorably dry conditions will persist in most areas from the lower Mississippi Valley to the southern Atlantic Coast.  Elsewhere, little or no precipitation will fall across California, the Great Basin, and the northern Plains.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for March 27-31 calls for a strong likelihood of warmer-than-normal weather from the Plains eastward, while near- to below-normal temperatures will prevail in the West.  Wetter-than-normal conditions will affect the central and western U.S., excluding southern California, Texas, and the Four Corners states, while mostly dry weather will prevail in the Atlantic Coast states.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Cold, dry conditions persisted across mainland Alaska, where the depiction of abnormal dryness (D0) was unchanged.  Likewise, no changes were introduced in Puerto Rico, since locally heavy showers were mostly confined to unaffected northern areas.  In Hawaii, however, the coverage of abnormal dryness was reduced in eastern Molokai and parts of northern and eastern Kauai.  During the first 20 days of March, 6.56 inches of rain pelted Lihue, Kauai, boosting its year-to-date total to 9.75 inches (95 percent of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Warm weather and drought conditions were a double-edged sword from the lower Mississippi Valley to the southern Atlantic Coast.  Dry soils favored spring planting and other fieldwork but increased stress on vegetation and boosted irrigation demands.  By March 18, corn planting advanced to 54 percent in Louisiana, compared to the five-year average of 19 percent.  In Texas, 46 percent of the corn was planted, versus the 2002-06 average of 29 percent.  Corn planting reached the halfway mark in Mississippi.  In the Southeast, USDA rated topsoil moisture 32 percent short in Georgia and 82 percent short in Florida.  The portion of pastures rated very poor to poor included 17 percent in Georgia, 19 percent in Mississippi, 44 percent in Texas, and 70 percent in Florida.  Through March 20, year-to-date precipitation totals were less than 40 percent of normal and more than 9 inches below normal in several locations, including Meridian, Mississippi (39 percent of normal and 9.62 inches below normal), and Mobile, Alabama (39 percent and 9.43 inches).  In addition, Southeastern streamflows remained significantly below normal, while the threat of wildfires increased.  In fact, during the first half of March, wildfires charred more than 66,000 acres of vegetation across the South.  In Florida, the average surface elevation of Lake Okeechobee fell to 10.76 feet (by March 20), the lowest level since 2001.  That year, the lake fell to a record-low elevation of 8.97 feet on May 24, shortly before the beginning of southern Floridas rainy season onset.</p>
   <p>General deterioration in the Southeast resulted in an expansion of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2).  In contrast, a late-winter storm affected the Mid-Atlantic States in mid-March, dropping as much as two to three inches of liquid equivalent (rain and melted snow and sleet) across formerly dry (D0) areas stretching from central West Virginia to the Delmarva Peninsula.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>Warmth also expanded across the northern Plains, where Rapid City, South Dakota, posted a March record-tying high of 82F on March 12.  In North Dakota, Bismarck reached 75F nine days earlier than ever before (75F on March 12; previously, 78F on March 21, 1910).  Meanwhile, no significant changes in the drought depiction were observed in the western Great Lakes region, where mostly dry weather prevailed.  Farther south, heavy rain lingered into March 14 across eastern Texas, resulting in some minor additional reductions of dryness (D0) and drought (D1 and D2) along the eastern fringe of the drought-affected area.  At the end of the monitoring period (the night of March 19-20), locally heavy showers and thunderstorms developed in parts of northern Oklahoma and southeastern Kansas.  Some refinements, including a reduction in D0 coverage in southeastern Kansas, were introduced due to that heavy rain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Reminiscent of March 2004, record-setting warmth engulfed the West.  From March 10 to March 20, several monthly record highs and nearly one thousand daily record highs were set or tied.  Among the monthly records was a high of 91F at Utahs Zion National Park on March 17 (previously, 90F on March 20 and 21, 2004).  With a high of 80F on March 12, Reno, Nevada, experienced its earliest 80 warmth on record (previously, 80F on March 14, 1994).  Elsewhere in Nevada, Las Vegas collected five consecutive daily record highs (90, 89, 87, 89, and 91F) from March 13 to March 17; experienced its earliest 90 heat (previously, 90F on March 20, 2004); and just missed its monthly record of 92F, set on March 21, 2004.  In California, Bishop notched seven consecutive daily record highs (83, 85, 84, 82, 84, 84, and 82F) from March 12 to March 18.  Meanwhile in Arizona, Yuma (101F on March 17) logged its earliest reading above 100F (previously, 102F on March 21, 2004).</p>
   <p>Compounding the effect of early-season warmth was continuing dryness.  Downtown Los Angeles, with records going back to 1877, remained on a pace for its driest year (July 1  June 30) on record.  Through March 20, L.A.s season-to-date rainfall stood at just 2.45 inches, or 19 percent of normal.  L.A.s driest season on record, 2001-02, featured 4.42 inches of rain.  Farther inland at Palmdale, California, July 1  March 20 precipitation totaled 0.65 inch, or 10 percent of normal.</p>
   <p>Changes in the Western drought depiction reflected gradual changes associated with steadily worsening water-supply forecasts.  Early-season warmth and premature melting is disruptive to the Western water cycle and forces water managers to make careful decisions regarding competing interestssuch as agricultural, environmental, industrial, municipal, and recreational users.  Abnormally dry (D0) conditions crept northward through the Intermountain region and eastward toward the central and southern Rockies, and correspondingly minor changes in drought coverage were introduced as well.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
