<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20141204</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>The first half of the past week was dominated by an upper-air ridge over the far western contiguous United States (CONUS), and a deep trough over the east-central CONUS. A major storm developed along the Southeast Coast and tracked northeastward just prior to Thanksgiving. This nor’easter brought moderate rain (0.5-2.0 inches) to the Southeast, a mix of rain, sleet, and snow (though mostly rain) along the middle and northern Atlantic coastal plain, and significant amounts of snow across the interior Northeast (up to a foot of snow was reported in the higher terrain of northwest New Jersey and eastern Pennsylvania). By Friday and Saturday, energy diving southward out of British Columbia into the Pacific Northwest and then eastward across the northern Rockies brought heavy mountain snow to these areas. Some precipitation made it as far south as north-central California, but these amounts were generally under an inch (liquid equivalent). Late in the period, light precipitation (0.5-inch or less) fell over central portions of California, and along the far southern coast, though amounts were nowhere near sufficient to offset longer-term precipitation deficits.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>For the upcoming 5-day period (December 4-8), moderate precipitation (1-2 inches) is predicted from eastern sections of the southern Great Plains northeastward to the central Appalachians, while 0.5-1.0 inch amounts of precipitation are forecast across parts of the Four Corners region and northern Rockies. Anywhere from 3-7 inches of precipitation (liquid equivalent) is anticipated for the coastal ranges of the Pacific Northwest (including northwest California), as well as parts of the Sierras.  For the ensuing 5-day period (December 9-13), above-median precipitation is favored for much of the West, southern Plains and Northeast, while modest probabilities for below-median precipitation are predicted for the northern and central Great Plains, and a large portion of the east-central CONUS.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>In Hawaii, several inches of rain fell across northern portions of the Big Island this past week, while monitored streams in the area were running above-average. This prompted the removal of the residual D0 area. The rest of the Hawaiian drought depiction remains unchanged, as water use restrictions remain in place.  Neither the Alaska depiction nor the Puerto Rico depiction was modified this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="California">
   <p>Despite respectable amounts of precipitation falling across the northern half of the state (generally between 0.5-4.0 inches) no changes were rendered to the California drought depiction this week. Though the rainy season is underway, the Water-Year-To-Date (WYTD, since Oct 1) PNP’s range from 5-25 percent of normal over the eastern half of southern California, and 25-75 percent of normal over the western half of southern California, with only a few scattered locales in far northern portions of the state depicting marginal surpluses. The 8-station precipitation index which ranges from Lake Tahoe to Shasta Reservoir is 79 percent of average to date for December 1, while the 5-station precipitation index (which covers the mountains of the San Joaquin River Basin) is only 47 percent of average to date. Snowpack is just starting to form, and is below what is normally expected for December 1, while reservoirs are just starting to receive more water than is being lost, which is later than would normally occur. December 1 marks the start of the wettest time of the year for California. Typically, about one-half of California’s annual precipitation is expected to fall during the December-February season. However, more than this is needed to offset the accumulated deficits.  Finally, stream base flow levels in many areas are still low and indicative of a lack of groundwater response in watersheds so far this cold season. This suggests that groundwater reservoirs still require replenishment.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Mississippi Valley">
   <p>Cold, dry conditions prevailed across much of the region during November. Deficits of 4-6 inches have mounted over the last 90-days across the Arrowhead region of northeast Minnesota. As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded to include the rest of St. Louis, Lake, and Cook Counties, which is also supported by the objective short-term drought blend. No alterations were made to the depiction this week over the central and southern Mississippi Valley.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast and mid-Atlantic regions">
   <p>The nor’easter that affected the Eastern Seaboard early in the period brought widespread precipitation (0.5-2.0 inches, with a few 2-3 inch totals reported) to the mid-Atlantic and Northeast regions. In general, a mix of rain, sleet, and snow was reported across coastal regions (though predominantly rain), and up to a foot of snow in northwest New Jersey and eastern Pennsylvania. As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) was trimmed from portions of eastern Massachusetts, while a 1-category upgrade (from D1 to D0) was rendered to the drought depiction over parts of coastal Connecticut. Abnormal dryness (D0) was also removed from New York City, Long Island, most of New Jersey, and southeast Pennsylvania. In northwest New Jersey, where some D0 was retained, more moisture is needed to replenish depleted groundwater and stream flows. Abnormal dryness was also removed from portions of southeastern Virginia and the extreme southern Delmarva Peninsula due to 2.0-2.5 inches of precipitation received with the nor’easter.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northern and Central Plains">
   <p>Precipitation deficits of 2-4 inches have accumulated in the last 90-days over the eastern halves of the Dakotas, and little if any precipitation was measured during this past week.  Abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded westward from northeast South Dakota to the Missouri River, while moderate drought (D1) was expanded slightly to the southwest into adjacent counties. Abnormal dryness was also expanded westward in south-central North Dakota to the Missouri River, including the counties of Logan, McIntosh and Emmons. In north-central and central Kansas, abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded due to several factors. November precipitation in these areas was about 7 percent of normal, stream flows were in the D2-D3 range, and moderate temperatures in the past week lessened snow/ice cover, leading to increased evaporation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Ohio/Tennessee Valleys">
   <p>No adjustments were made to the drought depiction this week in either region.  In Kentucky, precipitation was below normal in November, which also turned out to be one of the ten coldest Novembers on record. Three-month and 6-month SPI’s, 30-day and 90-day precipitation deficits, and subsoil moisture levels are becoming a concern in western Kentucky. However, a wet October and decent top soil moisture, along with the cold temperatures in November, are probably enough to justify holding off on the introduction of any D0.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Pacific Northwest">
   <p>In north-central Washington (Okanogan County) minor improvements were made to the map based on short and long-term PNP’s (30-, 60-, and 90-days) and SPI’s (3-, 6-, and 9-months). Though it’s still early in the cold season, the far northern Cascades and north-central Washington have adequate SWE’s (74 to 96 percent of median, as of December 3). However, one area that is not faring so well is southwest Oregon, where snowpack is off to a slow start. November precipitation has been generally below normal in this area, and temperatures about 2.5-4.0 degrees F above normal. As a result, snowpack is below normal on individual peaks and almost non-existent on mountain ridges. This area will be reassessed next week, and in the weeks to come.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Rockies">
   <p>The higher terrain of the Upper Colorado River Basin (UCRB) received another round of beneficial snowfall over the past week and basin Snow Water Equivalent (SWE) percent of normal values have recovered over the northern portion of the UCRB from the dry October. The southern basins received slightly less moisture and are still lagging slightly behind where snowpack should be (compared to normal) for this time of year. In eastern Colorado, shorter-term SPI’s are starting to dry out on the northeast plains, but that area had abundant moisture this past growing season and long-term SPI’s are wet. The southeast plains, however, are still in severe drought. No alterations were made this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Moderate precipitation (0.5-2.0 inches) fell across the region in association with the Wednesday nor’easter (day before Thanksgiving). Between 2-3 inches was observed in the eastern Piedmont/Upper Coastal Plain region of North Carolina (resulting in the reduction of coverage of D0), and even higher totals (4-6 inches) were reported in north-central Florida. In east-central Georgia, moderate drought (D1) was expanded slightly southwestward. In Alabama, USGS stream flows fell within the lowest decile of the historical distribution across southern Mobile and southern Baldwin counties abutting the Gulf Coast. Given these stream flows and a cold, dry November, a one-category deterioration was made to the depiction from moderate drought (D1) to severe drought (D2).  In east-central Alabama, little precipitation produced by this latest frontal system (and consideration of Percent of Normal Precipitation (PNP) values out through 90-days) prompted the southwest expansion of the D1 area into Autauga, Montgomery, and Elmore Counties. In far southeastern Alabama, moderate drought (D1) was removed based on 60-day PNP values which are close to normal.  In the northwest portion of the state, no changes were made to the drought depiction, as stream flows and soil moisture values remain adequate.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Plains">
   <p>Most of the region was dry this past week. In Texas, drought impacts are mostly longer-term, and with temperatures generally cooler than normal, conditions are slow to change. One exception is over parts of northeast Texas, which have accumulated significant precipitation deficits (greater than 6 inches) over the last 90-days. This warranted a one-category degradation in the drought depiction, from abnormal dryness (D0) to moderate drought (D1), for the counties of Fannin, Lamar, Red River, and much of Bowie. No alterations were made in Oklahoma this week, though northwest and north-central portions of the state will need to be reassessed next week. In these areas, soil moisture levels have not recovered (and continue to diminish) as they miss out on storms.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southwest">
   <p>Continuing dryness/drought across New Mexico prompted some revisions in this week’s depiction. Abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded in southeast New Mexico across Chaves, De Baca, and Roosevelt Counties. Moderate drought (D1) was expanded in west-central portions of the state (from eastern Cibola County to the Rio Grande Valley), while severe drought (D2) was expanded in northeast New Mexico. In northwest New Mexico, extreme drought (D3) was expanded eastward into more of both San Juan and McKinley Counties.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Anthony Artusa</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
