<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20011004</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 2 weeks that may affect areas experiencing dryness include: 1) above-normal rains over the southern Plains benefitting dry areas in Texas, Oklahoma, and New Mexico; 2) above-normal precipitation from Utah northward to southern Montana, but normal to below-normal rainfall from California to Washington; 3) across the West, temperatures averaging above-normal during October 3-7, but below-normal on October 8-13.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>A cold front crossing the islands dropped 1 to 2 inches of beneficial rain in several areas, but there was not enough moisture to appreciably alter the overall drought depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast, Great Lakes Region, upper Mississippi Valley, and northern Plains">
   <p>Heavy rains from the storm system exiting the eastern U.S. early last week reduced drought across the Northeast, with D0 dryness removed from Michigan and D0/D1 diminished in Pennsylvania. The moisture ended abnormal (D0) dryness in southern New England, and the area of D1 and D2 drought lessened to the north, with D1 drought extending across northern Vermont and New Hampshire into Maine. A small area of D2 drought continued in northern New Hampshire and adjacent Maine. In the northern Plains, lack of rainfall caused abnormal dryness to expand eastward into western portions of the Dakotas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Heavy rains fell along a stalled cold front in southern Florida, but amounts were lighter to the north from the Orlando to Lake City areas, where low aquifer levels and D0(W) persisted. Farther north, a dry week allowed hydrological dryness to expand westward from central Georgia into eastern Alabama, while D1(W) drought re-emerged in eastern Georgia. D0 dryness also expanded northeastward from the Carolinas deeper into southern Virginia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Plains and Tennessee Valley area">
   <p>Dry weather this week resulted in no significant changes to the drought picture, with severe drought (D2) remaining over southwestern Texas and southeastern New Mexico. Dryness (D0) did expand northward into southeastern Missouri, while drought (D1/D2) persisted in northeastern Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Up to 1 inch of rain fell in northern California, western Washington, and parts of Oregon and northern Idaho, but interior temperatures stayed well above normal. Except for some expansion of the drought area in Montana, there was little net change in overall conditions, as moderate to extreme drought persisted across the northwestern quadrant of the country. The 12-month period ending in September was the driest such period in over 100 years of record for many locations in northwest Oregon, including Astoria, Portland, and Eugene. In Nevada, Reno measured the driest water year (October-September) since records began in 1872, with a meager 2.13 inches (28 percent of normal) of precipitation.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
