<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20071101</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather that could affect dry or drought areas over the next 2 weeks includes: 1) below-normal precipitation and above-normal temperatures over the West; 2) a return to below-normal rainfall across the Southeast, except in Florida, which will see up to several inches of rain along the southeast coast from Tropical Storm Noel early in the period. For the longer period, the updated seasonal drought outlook indicates that drought will persist or even expand across the Southeast, Gulf Coast, and the Southwest by the end of January, but conditions will improve in the interior Northwest and northern Rockies. Most of Kentucky and Tennessee should see some improvement.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Heavy rains exceeding 5 inches from Tropical Storm Noel erased D0 dryness in Puerto Rico. Rainfall was light over the Hawaiian drought areas, as well as the D0 area in northern Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Over 4 inches fell on upstate New York east of Lake Ontario. As a result, D1 drought ended near the eastern shores of Lake Ontario, and D0 dryness ended in Pennsylvania, eastern New York, and southern New Hampshire. D1 drought continued in portions of southern New England.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>With rainfall on the light side, there was little change on the Plains, although recent dry weather caused some expansion of D0 in northeastern Texas. Rainfall has been low in several other parts of Texas in the past 2 months, but earlier heavy rains have kept impacts from the dryness to a minimum.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Mid-Atlantic, Ohio and lower Missouri Valleys">
   <p>The major storm system that brought heavy rains to the western portions of the drought affecting the Southeast and Ohio Valley starting around October 22 continued eastward, dropping impressive totals over a large area from the Ohio Valley to the mid-Atlantic region. From October 23 to 27, 4 to 6 inches of rain, with locally higher amounts, drenched the area from North Carolina into eastern Pennsylvania and parts of New Jersey. One to 3 inches fell over the southern Ohio Valley and the Tennessee Valley, and this was on top of the earlier heavy amounts. As a result, the area of drought diminished, with D4 giving way to D3 or better in western Alabama and much of North Carolina, and D3 reduced to D0 to D1 across the mid-Atlantic. D1 and D0 dryness ended over most of western Kentucky and western Tennessee. Although streamflows and soil moisture improved, reservoirs remained critically low in portions of the drought region, including northern Alabama. Due to lower rainfall amounts in Georgia, there was little change in the drought status in that state, with D4 persisting in the north. Long-term rainfall deficits remained a factor in the water supply situation in the Southeast, with year-to-date totals at least 16 inches below normal in much of Alabama, central and eastern Tennessee, northern Georgia, and western North Carolina, and exceeding 20 inches in northern and central Alabama. Short-term dry weather resulted in slight expansion of D0 in central Missouri.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The ending of the Santa Ana winds around Wednesday, October 24, helped fire fighters begin to gain control of the wildfires across southern California. Some light rains fell over central and northern California on October 28-30, with locally heavier amounts in the north and the Sierra. With 30- to 90-day totals above normal, there was some reduction of dryness and drought levels in northern California, and D2 shifted to D1 near San Francisco and north of Lake Tahoe. Recent precipitation also resulted in the reduction of D0 in east-central Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
