<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000907</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather events that may affect some of the nations dry or drought areas include: 1) Locally heavy showers are forecast to continue in the southern Atlantic region, especially in Florida, and may spread westward along the Gulf Coast into eastern Texas; 2) Hot weather will continue to gradually shift westward, bringing late-season heat to the southern Plains and southern Rockies; 3) Scattered showers are possible on the northern and central Plains, but significant rainfall will likely be confined to the western Great Lakes region; and 4) Scattered showers may further reduce long-term moisture deficits in parts of the Southwest, especially in the Four Corners region.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Beneficial, out-of-season showers continued to bring gradual long-term drought relief to leeward sections of the islands. Nevertheless, a pocket of severe drought (D3) persisted on the northwestern portion of the Big Island. In Puerto Rico, generally only light showers fell following last weeks passage of Hurricane Debby. As a result, there was no significant change in the abnormally dry to first-stage drought (D0 to D1) classification for northern parts of the commonwealth.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Very heavy rain (locally in excess of 5 inches) fell in northwestern Lower Michigan, but missed nearby abnormally dry (D0) areas. For the week ending the morning of September 5, generally 0.5 to 1.5 inches of rain dampened the eastern Upper Peninsula of Michigan and the remainder of northern Lower Michigan, bringing little relief from abnormal dryness (D0) and first-stage drought (D1).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Weekly (August 29 - September 4) temperatures averaged as much as 15 degrees F above normal in eastern Kansas for the second consecutive week, accompanied by mostly dry weather. Abnormal dryness (D0 for agriculture and a wildfire threat) expanded to cover the remainder of the central Plains. Gradual drought intensification was noted in many other areas. Following a hot August, an early-September surge of extreme heat produced several monthly record highs. Wichita, Kansas, noted a record-setting 23 days of 100-degree heat in August, then posted a September-record high of 108 degrees F on September 2. Elsewhere on that day, monthly record highs were set or tied in Salina, Kansas (110 degrees F); Lincoln, Nebraska (106 degrees F); and Sioux City, Iowa (103 degrees F). In addition, Iowa (statewide) noted its seventh week of the last eight with below-normal rainfall, allowing for an extension of abnormal dryness (D0) back into roughly the southwestern half of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Heavy rain in the southern Atlantic States contrasted sharply with record-setting heat and continuing dryness from the northwestern half of Alabama westward. For the week ending the morning of September 5, more than 4 inches of rain soaked former extreme to exceptional (D3 to D4) drought areas of north-central Georgia. At least 2 inches of rain fell in the southern Appalachians and adjacent Piedmont areas of Georgia and the Carolinas, resulting in an approximate improvement of one drought classification (e.g. from D3 to D2, or D2 to D1). Less widespread showers provided limited drought relief to areas from easternmost Louisiana to Florida. Meanwhile, an intense, late-summer heat wave set dozens of all-time and monthly temperature records, especially in southern and eastern Texas. As a result, most of the south-central United States experienced an approximate deterioration of one drought classification, and a small area of exceptional drought (D4) was introduced in southwestern Texas. On September 5, all-time-record highs in Texas included 115 degrees F in Del Rio (Laughlin AFB); 112 degrees F in Austin and Hondo; 111 degrees F in Victoria and San Antonio; and 109 degrees F in Corpus Christi. Earlier in the period, on August 29, record highs had been set as far east as the Alabama cities of Tuscaloosa (107 degrees F) and Mobile (105 degrees F). Other locations establishing all-time records included Little Rock, Arkansas (111 degrees F on August 30); Alexandria, Louisiana (109 degrees F on August 31); and Houston, Texas (109 degrees F on September 4). El Dorado, Arkansas, registered twelve consecutive daily-record highs from August 24 - September 4, during which high temperatures averaged 107.3 degrees F. By September 5, streaks of days without measurable rainfall in Texas reached 66 days in Abilene, just shy of its June-August 1970 record of 72 days, and a record-setting 67 days in Dallas-Ft. Worth. Spells without measurable rain reached 37 days in Shreveport, Louisiana, nine days behind the October-November 1921 standard, and 38 days in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, only one day behind the December 1985 - February 1986 record. Farther east, however, Little Rocks record-setting, 27-day (August 5-31) streak without a drop of rain ended with a 0.53-inch total on September 1.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Cooler weather and widespread rainfall brought significant relief to the regions drought areas. The rain aided wildfire containment efforts and boosted topsoil moisture in the Great Basin and Interior Northwest, and eased long-term drought in parts of the Southwest. At least one inch of rain soaked west-central and northwestern Arizona, southern Nevada, and areas east of the Great Salt Lake. Widespread showers also dampened areas from eastern Oregon to the northern Rockies. According to the National Interagency Fire Center, U.S. wildfires consumed about 6.6 million acres through September 5, more than 220 percent of the 10-year average. More than 3.1 million of the acres burned in the northern Rockies and Great Basin.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
