<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20070809</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Hot and dry conditions over much of the United States dominated the weather conditions this past week.  As a dome of high pressure settled in over the Midwest, temperatures were 4-8 degrees Fahrenheit above normal for many locations.  Temperatures were also well above normal through the High Plains and northern Rocky Mountains.  The coolest temperatures were observed over the Southwest and into Texas, where the monsoon season continued.  Precipitation was widely scattered, with the areas north of the dome of high pressure seeing the most significant rains.  Some localized amounts of greater than 5 inches were observed in parts of Wisconsin, Florida, South Dakota and Nebraska.  In general, a few improvements to the drought status of some states took place, but an overall worsening of the drought continued to plague the country.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (August 9-13), temperatures over the United States should continue to be well above normal as a strong ridge of high pressure will be centered over the High Plains.  Temperatures are expected to be 6-9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal during this time, with the greatest anomalies centered on the High Plains and Midwest.  Precipitation during this time will continue to ride over the top of and around the ridge.  Precipitation maxima are expected over the upper Midwest, through the Great Lakes and into New England.  In front of the ridge, precipitation maxima should also be observed over portions of the Mid-Atlantic and south into Florida.  The monsoonal rains should also continue over the Southwest, with Arizona, New Mexico and portions of Colorado and Utah having the potential for the most rain.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlook (August 14-18) is similar to the 5 day outlook in that a ridge of high pressure will dominate conditions over the United States.  Temperatures are expected to be well above normal over much of the country and Alaska too.  Precipitation chances will be slim in the areas dominated by the ridge. The best chances for above-normal precipitation will again be in the areas on the periphery of the ridge.  Areas around the Great Lakes, upper New England and Florida are in the best position to see above-normal rains.  Alaska is also projected to have a good chance of recording above-normal precipitation during this time frame.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Improvements to the D1 status on the Big Island were made this week.  The Kona area is normal to above normal for seasonal precipitation as recent rains over the last month have allowed for the improvement.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The High Plains">
   <p>Heavy rains over portions of South Dakota and Nebraska have allowed for some improvements to the drought status in both states.  In South Dakota, D2 and D1 conditions were improved over much of central and eastern portions of the state.  This was the first significant rain in several weeks, which allowed for the improvements.  D1 conditions were expanded over northeast South Dakota as well as northwest portions of the state.  These areas continue to miss the rains, and the effect of the dryness is becoming a concern.  In Nebraska, D0 was improved in the eastern portion of the state and into portions of central Nebraska as well.  The northeast portion of the state continues to miss out on the precipitation, and D1 and D2 conditions were expanded into extreme northeast Nebraska this week.  D3 was also expanded in western Nebraska where the long-term drought has not let up.  D0 was expanded in North Dakota and a new area of D1 was introduced as well.  The trend of above-normal temperatures and lack of precipitation has allowed for these changes.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest">
   <p>Improvements to the D0 and D1 status over portions of Iowa, Wisconsin and Illinois were made in response to the recent rains bringing these areas some relief.  In Minnesota, drought conditions in the northern portions of the state expanded to the east and west, respectively.  Illinois had a northward expansion of the D0 and D1 conditions in the southern portions of the state.  In Missouri, D0 was expanded in the central portions of the state and a new area of D1 was introduced along the border with Iowa.  In southwest Missouri, D0 and D1 were expanded as well. Worsening conditions in Michigan have warranted expansion of the drought categories.  In the Upper Peninsula, D2 was expanded to the east and a new area of D3 was introduced where precipitation has been less than 25 percent of normal over the last 90 days.  In lower Michigan, D0 filled in the last areas where there was no dryness designation and D1 was expanded north along Lake Michigan and into more of northern Michigan.  In Kentucky, the D2 status was expanded farther to the west as conditions continue to be dry in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid-Atlantic">
   <p>Few changes in the drought status in the region took place this week. With warmer temperatures, the recent improvements were held in check, even with some locations recording rainfall again this week.  Western New York continues to be dry.  D0 and D1 conditions were expanded this week due to the dryness over the last several months.  D0 conditions in Maine and New Hampshire were also shifted farther to the coast, as the rains last week missed the driest regions in general.  D2 conditions in southwest West Virginia were improved.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>The drought improvements due to the rains of June and July have quickly diminished this past week.  With temperatures well over 100 degrees Fahrenheit coupled with another dry week, the drought status over the Southeast expanded in both spatial coverage and intensity.  In Alabama, all drought conditions outside of the southwest portions of the state increased in intensity.  D4 was expanded to the east into Georgia and also in the northwest to include more of Tennessee.  D2 and D3 were expanded to the west to include more of Mississippi.  A new area of D4 was introduced into southwest Georgia and D3 conditions migrated out of Georgia and into the Florida panhandle.  D2 was expanded in South Carolina.  Improvements were made in southeast Georgia and into northeast Florida where consistent rains have made up precipitation deficits.  In southern Florida, improvement to the drought conditions has allowed for the removal of the D2 and a shift of the D0 and D1 conditions to the west.  D0 and D1 were expanded in southwest Florida as conditions continue to be dry.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Several changes to the drought status took place over the last week.  Improvements were made in Arizona, New Mexico, and southwest Colorado.  The rains over the last several weeks have eased drought conditions in these states, allowing for a shift of all categories to the west, and an elimination of D0 in portions of southern Colorado and northern New Mexico.  In Idaho and Montana, conditions continued to deteriorate.  D2 was expanded to include all of Idaho, with a new area of D3 added as well.  Drought status in Montana also worsened, with an expansion of D1 and D2 conditions to the east and a new area of D3 added.  D0 filled in most of the remaining portions of the state that were drought free.  High temperatures coupled with lack of precipitation have taken a toll on the crops in Montana.  In both Idaho and Montana, surface water supplies are at or approaching historic lows.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
