<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100819</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Over the next 5 days (August 19-23), precipitation should be impacting some of the drought areas, as maxima of precipitation are centered over the Gulf Coast and upper Midwest.   The Plains and Mid Atlantic have fairly good chances of precipitation as well.  The monsoon season looks to continue, with widespread precipitation over the southwest.  Temperatures are projected to be above normal for almost the entire United States, with the greatest departures over the High Plains and Ohio River Valley (6-9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal).  Cool temperatures will again take place over the west coast.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (August 24-28) continues to show the best chances for above normal temperatures over the Ohio River Valley and below normal temperatures from Alaska down through the west coast.  Precipitation chances are greatest over the northern High Plains and along the Gulf Coast.  The best chance for below normal precipitation is from Arkansas up through West Virginia and into New England.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>No changes for Alaska or Puerto Rico this week.  In Hawaii, on the island of Kauai, D2 was introduced as pastures and rangelands continue to worsen, causing impacts to the ranching industry there.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="High Plains">
   <p>Coupled with spotty dryness and high temperatures over the last few weeks, D0 was introduced into portions of southeast Nebraska and northeast Kansas.  As several crop tours are making their way through this region, losses are mounting up for both the corn and soybean crops.  Soils have rapidly dried out in the top layers of the profile as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast">
   <p>Dry conditions continued over western Kentucky and into portions of Tennessee.  D1 was expanded in Kentucky while D0 was introduced into much of central Tennessee.  After flooding rains in May, the lack of precipitation and heat has started to impact the area, especially in the agricultural sector.  Rains over portions of central North Carolina and western South Carolina allowed for improvements to the D0 there.  D0 was expanded to the west in eastern North Carolina as well this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southern Plains and Gulf Coast">
   <p>The recent heat coupled with rains in some areas led to improvements for some and degradation for others.  Even with drought indicators fairly dry over the last 6 months, recent precipitation in Louisiana has brought improvements to the drought categories in the state as D3 and D2 were reduced.  Improvements were made to the D0 and D1 in western Mississippi while a shift in D0 was made in eastern Mississippi. Alabama had slight improvements to the D0 in the northwest and D1 in the east.  The D1 in the southern part of the state was also split up and the western lobe stretched farther to the south than in the previous weeks.</p>
   <p>Texas had expansion of D0 in the north and central portions of the state while D0 was eliminated in the panhandle.  In east Texas a general shift of the D0-D2 categories was made to the west, as this area continues to miss out on precipitation and temperatures have been well above normal.  D0 was expanded along the Red River and into much of central and southern Oklahoma. Over the last several weeks, precipitation has been well below normal and temperatures have regularly been at or above 100 degrees Fahrenheit.  Agricultural impacts have developed rapidly and losses are being documented.  In the Oklahoma panhandle, very heavy rains brought relief as a full category improvement was made.  As the impact of this rain is assessed in the coming weeks, further improvements may be needed.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast and Mid Atlantic">
   <p>Locally heavy rains helped to improve conditions in northeast Pennsylvania, where D0 and D1 conditions improved.  D0 was also removed from most of western Pennsylvania as recent rains have diminished the abnormally dry conditions that were there.  D0 was extended into extreme southern New York as well as up the Hudson Valley.  D0 was expanded in Massachusetts and Connecticut, and D1 was also brought up the coast out of New Jersey and into Long Island, Massachusetts and Connecticut.</p>
   <p>Improvements were made in portions of Maryland and Virginia as locally heavy rain brought relief to the D0 and D1 areas.  Up to 4 inches of rain were associated with these isolated thunderstorms.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The monsoon season continues over the southwest, with the rains associated with it helping to improve drought conditions.  In Colorado, the D0 was removed from the San Juan River basin this week and some D1 was removed in northern Arizona.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
