<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20100902</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (September 2-6), tranquil weather will prevail across the majority of the U.S.  A major exception, of course, will be the interaction between Hurricane Earl and a cold front approaching the East.  On the night of September 2-3, Earl will pass near, or just east of, North Carolina’s Outer Banks.  On September 3-4, Earl will graze coastal New England.  Heavy rain and high winds will accompany Earl’s passage along the immediate coast.  In addition, beach erosion will be a major threat along the middle and northern Atlantic Coast.  Farther west, scattered showers in advance of a cold front will stretch from the upper Midwest into the south-central U.S. on September 2.  The following day, showers will advance as far east as the Appalachians before dissipating.  By September 4-5, scattered showers may overspread the Northwest.  The National Weather Service’s 6- to 10-day outlook for September 7-11 calls for cooler-than-normal weather across the northern High Plains and much of the West, while near- to above-normal temperatures will prevail across the remainder of the U.S.  Meanwhile, near- to below-normal rainfall across the majority of the nation will contrast with wetter-than-normal conditions across the nation’s northern tier as far east as the Great Lakes region.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>The drought depiction was unchanged in Hawaii, where drought persisted across the majority of the island chain.  Mandatory water conservation measures remained in effect for Maui and Honolulu Counties.  By the end of August, a wildfire on the Big Island—in the mountains southeast of Waikoloa—was still not fully contained.  The fire had charred nearly 1,400 acres of brush and grass.  Farther north, showers continued to fall across parts of Alaska, where the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) was reduced slightly across the interior and the upper Aleutian Islands.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Mid-Atlantic and the Southeast">
   <p>Only minor changes were introduced in the Southeast.  A small amount of moderate drought (D1) was removed along Florida’s east coast, while some abnormal dryness (D0) was re-introduced in North Carolina.  Farther north, some dryness (D0) was removed from western Virginia, where rainfall locally topped 4 inches.  However, severe drought (D2) remained entrenched in an area stretching from western Maryland into southeastern Virginia.  According to USDA, Virginia led the Mid-Atlantic region with 55 percent of its pastureland rated very poor to poor on August 29, followed by West Virginia with 48 percent and Maryland with 35 percent.  In addition, Virginia’s preliminary 2010 corn yield estimate of 65 bushels per acre, if realized, will be the state’s lowest since 1993 (60 bushels per acre).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Mid-South and the Lower Midwest">
   <p>Late-summer dryness intensified across the Mid-South, resulting in a broad expansion or development of abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1).  According to USDA, Arkansas had the nation’s highest percentage of pastureland rated in very poor to poor condition—62 percent on August 29.  In addition, USDA indicated that 88 percent of Arkansas’ topsoil moisture was rated very short to short.  Although drier-than-normal conditions promoted fieldwork, including corn and rice harvesting, late-developing crops were under increasing levels of stress.  As the end of August approached, 20 to 35 percent of the soybean crop was rated in very poor to poor condition in Arkansas, Kentucky, Mississippi, Missouri, and Tennessee.  Farther north, abnormal dryness (D0) significantly expanded in Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, and Ohio.  More than one-third (36 percent) of Indiana’s pastureland was rated in very poor to poor condition by August 29.  Nearly three-quarters of the topsoil moisture was rated very short to short in both Indiana (73 percent) and Michigan (71 percent).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Heavy rain lingered along the southern New England coast through August 25.  In eastern Massachusetts, the Blue Hill Observatory reported an August 22-25 total of 7.59 inches.  The coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) was reduced in southern New England, but significant rain again bypassed northern Maine.  As a result, moderate drought (D1) was extended northeastward in Maine to the Canadian (New Brunswick) border.  Nearly half (47 percent) of Maine’s pastureland was rated in very poor to poor condition on August 29, according to USDA.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Dry weather continued to plague Texas and neighboring areas.  In fact, USDA indicated that topsoil moisture was 70 percent very short to short in Texas on August 29.  Some moderate drought (D1) was introduced in south-central Texas, while abnormal dryness (D0) was expanded in central and northeastern Texas.  In addition to short-term dryness, August heat played a major role in soil moisture depletion and agricultural deterioration.  Austin (Camp Mabry), Texas, reported its second-hottest August on record (88.7 degrees F, or 4.2 degrees above normal), behind only the 2009 standard of 89.1 degrees F.  Only a trace of rain (2.31 inches below normal) fell during the month in Austin, representing its driest August since 1957.  Elsewhere in Texas, Waco tied an August record with 27 days of triple-digit heat.  Waco, which experienced its hottest August since 1951, also experienced 27 August days with highs of 100 degrees F or greater in 2006.  Farther north, a few other pockets of dryness (D0) were introduced or expanded in locations such as northwestern Kansas and the Dakotas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Few changes occurred in the West, where scattered showers were mostly confined to the Four Corners States and the Northwest.  Through the end of August, Western wildfire activity remained fairly light.  In fact, the nation’s January-August tally of 2.61 million acres burned by wildfires was just under half of the 10-year average of 5.37 million acres.  Furthermore, Alaska accounted for more than 40 percent (1.10 million acres) of the nation’s year-to-date total.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
