<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20110609</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>This week featured a fairly dry pattern with the active storm track located across the northern tier of the contiguous US.   A storm system that began the week out west moved across the northern Great Plains, then across southern Canada.  The trailing cold front, and impulses along it, moved across the eastern half of the contiguous 48 states, although little rainfall accompanied the cold front.  A second storm system moved along a similar track during the latter portions of the weekend and into the early portions of this week.  The two systems combined to generate rainfall across California (1.0 – 5.0 inches), Pacific Northwest (widespread 0.5-1.5 inches with isolated amounts of over 2.5 inches), and across the northern Rockies (0.5 – 3.0 inches).  Significant rains (1.0 – 6.6 inches) also fell across north-central Kansas with isolated areas of rain (0.5 inch – 2.5 inches) across the Mid-West, Lower Great Lakes, and Carolinas.  Portions of western Hawaii received notable rains (0.7 – 6.3 inches) as an upper-level trough remained in place for much of the week.  Outside of those areas, rainfall was generally too light to improve drought conditions.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>June 10 - June 16, 2011 – The atmospheric flow pattern is expected to bring significant precipitation to the northern Great Plains, Great Lakes, and from the Mid-Atlantic states to the Northeast.  Multiple storm systems are forecast to move across these regions, with the most precipitation forecast for the Middle Mississippi River Valley.  Some drought relief is expected across Florida, with the eventual end of the dry season and spreading wildfires.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Great Plains">
   <p>Minor amounts of rain made a dent in the drought across extreme northwestern Texas and northeastern New Mexico (with one station reporting 3.2 inches and surrounding stations reporting about an inch of precipitation.  The rest of Texas and Oklahoma were dry, prompting some expansion of each drought category in those two states.  The hot temperatures (maxima above 100 degrees F many days, meaning anomalies of more than 10 degrees F above normal) and windy conditions continue to extract moisture from the soil.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Rainfall across Puerto Rico was significant so no dryness is depicted.  Rainfall across northwest Hawaii kept drought from expanding and local Farm Service Agency contacts reported that the current depiction matches their observations on the ground.  The drought status across Hawaii remained unchanged, as the western islands received the most rainfall.</p>
   <p>A stormy pattern brought more rains (0.5 – 1.8 inches) across southwestern Alaska.  This prompted a small reduction in the coverage of D0H (abnormal dryness) across southwestern   Alaska.  Dry conditions continued across interior Alaska with less than 0.5 inch of precipitation reported at any station and stream flows declining below drought thresholds, so D0 was introduced across central Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Rockies and Southwest">
   <p>Inputs from the NIDIS: Upper Colorado River Basin Pilot Project continued dryness, so extreme drought (D3) was introduced into the San Luis Valley, avoiding the surrounding higher elevations as the mountains have received closer to average amounts of precipitation for the Water Year.  SPI9 and SPI12 indicate the driest conditions are longer-term but recent (30-day) percent of normal precipitation is indicating less than 5 percent of normal precipitation has fallen during the last month.</p>
   <p>Southeastern Arizona and southwestern New Mexico continued to feel the brunt of the dry conditions with wildfires spreading across eastern Arizona.  The dry conditions across this region prompted an expansion of extreme (D3) and exceptional (D4) drought across this region, all supported by SPI3,6,9 and NLDAS outputs as well as 30-day percent of normal precipitation below 2 percent.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeast and mid-Atlantic">
   <p>The generally dry pattern contributed to the expansion of drought conditions across the Mid-Atlantic.  Abnormal dryness (D0) is now indicated as far north as central New Jersey and as far west as the I-95 corridor in Maryland and Virginia.  Across these regions the 3-month Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI3), 6-month SPI (SPI6), and North American Land Data Assimilation System (NLDAS) Soil Moisture all indicate abnormal dryness.  Most of the contribution to these dry conditions is at the 6-month time frame, with some recent drying associated with higher than normal temperatures.</p>
   <p>Across the Carolinas, continued lack of rainfall led to an expansion of D0 across the central portions of North and South Carolina.  A 1-category degradation was supported by 28-, 14- and 7-day, as well as real-time stream flows (data provided by the US Geological Survey) in the lowest 10th percentile across eastern North Carolina.  NLDAS soil moisture, SPI3, and SPI6 indicate the driest conditions are along the coast while longer term indicators (SPI9, SPI12, and SPI24) depict the driest conditions across central portions of the Carolinas, so a slow expansion of drought is indicated to the west as some precipitation has fallen in the past 3 months.  Across South Carolina, farm operators are seeing crop conditions deteriorate as South Carolina officially entered into incipient drought status on June 2nd, as determined by the State Climate Office.</p>
   <p>Exceptional drought (D4) was introduced across southwestern Georgia and southeastern Alabama.  Statewide topsoil moisture across Georgia was rated at 88 percent very short or short, with 12 percent adequate. Subsoil moisture for the State was 89 percent very short or short, with 11 percent adequate.  NLDAS and SPI for longer than 6 months all indicate Extreme (D3) to Exceptional (D4) drought.  Thirty-day percent of normal precipitation values (from AHPS) are in the lowest 2 percent for the area centered in Sumter County, with the surrounding area at or below 5 percent of normal.  Longer-term dryness was mitigated by some late spring rains across northern Alabama, so the northward expansion of dryness was only minor.</p>
   <p>Drought continued to expand across Florida, with reports from Miami, Fort Lauderdale, and Naples indicating year-to-date precipitation totals running 68 percent, 27 percent, and 33 percent of normal. The Vegetation Drought Response Index for Florida is showing that most of the area is running in Moderate Drought with even interior Palm Beach, and inland Collier Counties running in the Severe Drought range.  Lake Okeechobee is still below the critical line for water shortage, at 3.24 feet below normal for this time of year.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Matthew Rosencrans</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
