<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20080221</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (through February 25), a trio of storms will provide several drought-affected areas with abundant precipitation.  The first low-pressure system will move from the south-central U.S. to the southern Mid-Atlantic coast by February 22, generating a broad swath of frozen precipitation from the southern Plains into the Ohio Valley and Mid-Atlantic states.  Meanwhile, showers and locally severe thunderstorms will sweep across the South.  As the first system begins to depart, a second storm will arrive in the Pacific Coast states on February 21-22.  Unlike the previous system, this storm will weaken after producing widespread rain and snow showers as far east as the Rockies.  Farther west, a third storm will charge ashore along the Pacific Coast during the weekend.  By early next week (February 25), snow will spread from the Rockies into the Midwest.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for February 26 - March 1 calls for near- to above-normal precipitation east of the Mississippi River and across the nation's northern tier.  In contrast, little or no precipitation will fall from California to the Mississippi River, including the Southwest and the central and southern Plains.  Elsewhere, above-normal temperatures in the West will contrast with colder-than-normal weather across much of the eastern two-thirds of the U.S.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Heavy precipitation returned to south-central and southeastern Alaska, but little or no snow fell across the abnormally dry (D0) areas of eastern Alaska.  As a result, the depiction remained unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes Region">
   <p>Another round of heavy snow affected the Great Lakes region, eliminating moderate drought (D1) and reducing the coverage of abnormal dryness (D0) in the areas between Lakes Superior and Michigan.  Lingering abnormal dryness was also eliminated from northern Lower Michigan.  In Wisconsin, Green Bay's July 1 - February 19 snowfall of 73.9 inches represented its highest seasonal total since 1996-97, when 77.0 inches fell.  Even more impressive snowfall totals have been observed in southern Wisconsin (and neighboring areas), where Madison's season-to-date sum of 86.7 inches has already surpassed its former record of 76.1 inches set from July 1, 1978, to June 30, 1979.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Conditions were virtually unchanged across the northern half of the Plains, where mostly dry weather prevailed.  A few minor improvements were noted in Montana due to reassessment of previous weather events.  On the southern Plains, significant changes for the better (reduction of abnormal dryness and moderate drought, or D0 and D1) occurred in Oklahoma (excluding the panhandle) and northern and eastern Texas due to widespread rainfall totals of 1 to 3 inches, with locally higher amounts.  In stark contrast, little or no rain fell across much of southern and western Texas, where a small area of extreme drought (D3) was introduced.  In addition, there was some expansion of moderate to extreme drought (D1 and D2) into southern, western, and central Texas.  Improbably, San Antonio, Texas, followed its wettest January-August period on record (44.61 inches; previously, 38.64 inches in 1992) with its driest September 1 - February 15 period (3.14 inches; previously, 3.17 inches in 1917-18).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeastern and Mid-Atlantic States">
   <p>Widespread precipitation fell across drought-affected areas of the Southeast, resulting in some slight reductions in the coverage and intensity of moderate to exceptional drought (D1 to D4).  Seven-day totals in excess of 2 inches were common from central Alabama and Georgia into the coastal plain of the Carolinas.  In northern Georgia, the surface elevation of Lake Lanier rose to 1052.84 feet by February 19, a little more than 2 feet above the all-time record-low level set in December 2007.  Heavy rain also soaked parts of southern Florida, eliminating abnormal dryness along and near the Atlantic Coast and bringing a slight reduction in the coverage of moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2).  However, the heaviest rain fell well south of southern Florida's Lake Okeechobee and its watershed.  As of February 20, the average surface elevation of Lake Okeechobee stood at 10.10 feet, more than 4 feet below average for this time of year and just 1.28 feet above the all-time record-low level established in July 2007.  Farther west, the areal extent of abnormal dryness (D0) was reduced by heavy rain across southern Arkansas and northern Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>The Western depiction was virtually unchanged this week, as widespread areas receiving more than 1 inch of precipitation were confined to non-drought areas of Arizona.  Spring and summer runoff prospects are generally favorable in many Western basins due to heavy snow from December into February, but reservoir storage remains below average for this time of year in all states except Colorado (near average) and Arizona (above average).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
