<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20081106</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (November 6-10), temperatures are generally expected to be above normal in the West, East, and southern Plains while below-normal readings can be expected in the Rockies and northern Plains states and into northern Minnesota and Wisconsin, where they could use it. The better chance for precipitation over this period is expected in the Pacific Northwest coastal regions and in the northern Plains. Eastern Oklahoma may get a share of the tail end of this precipitation.</p>
   <p>The CPC 6-10 day forecast (November 11-15) calls for better chances of warmer temperatures returning to much of the far West along with a large cooler air mass encroaching over most of the eastern United States, save for Florida and New England. Alaska looks to be cooler than normal as well. As for precipitation, the odds are tilted toward below-normal amounts in Alaska and much of California, Nevada, and western Arizona. Much of the country east of the Mississippi River is potentially looking at above-normal precipitation, with the best chance being situated over the Mid-Atlantic region.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>No changes are noted in the drought depiction this week within Alaska or Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Great Lakes Region and Upper Midwest">
   <p>Most of this region enjoyed a warmer than normal week that didn't feature much in the way of rainfall except in eastern Michigan. Conditions here remain unchanged this week after some modest improvement last week. In general, it hasn't been a good start to the off-season recharge period in these areas. Time of year and lower demand are keeping impacts in check for the most part.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>After some pretty heavy rains for many parts of the region last week, this week saw mostly well above normal temperatures, but didn't see any precipitation from North Dakota all the way down to the Gulf Coast in Texas. Year-to-date deficits are really starting to pile up in the D1-D3 core found in Texas, and this week is marked by some expansion of D0-D1 in Oklahoma and north-central Texas along with growth of the D1-D3 core to the south and west in southern Texas. Streamflows and soil moisture are lagging significantly in south-central Oklahoma and across most of central Texas as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast, Tennessee and Ohio Valleys, and mid-Atlantic Coast">
   <p>For all but parts of the coastal Carolinas and the Northeast, it was a pretty quiet week precipitation-wise. The bigger story has been the return to dryness the past 30-60 days in these regions. As such, the core region of the drought in the Southeast has begun to expand outward again with the movement of the D4 core pushing across extreme northeast Georgia and into extreme southwest North Carolina. The majority of the streamflow readings in this core area are running at, or near, record lows. The cooler temperatures and low-demand season are helping to the degree they can, but some serious winter recharge will be needed before next year's heat and demands surely return. Along the Gulf Coast, an absence of moisture over the past 30-90 days has led to the introduction of D0 in southern Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Over October 31-November 4, two strong systems off the West Coast pushed into northern California, bringing some punch in the form of heavy precipitation (2-5 inches liquid, more in some areas) and cooler air before moving into the Great Basin, where totals fell off. Although it is still early in the wet season, these storms brought significant rain and snow, which were a welcomed sight. That said, longer-term recovery is still needed in both rains and snows this winter in order to recharge soils and surface storage/flows and help aid in the recovery to pasture/rangeland, which took some major hits earlier this year. These can take awhile to bounce back even though we are off to a good start on the young Water Year, which only began a month ago. Thus, the changes to this week's map are found in the reduction of D2 to D1 conditions along the coastal ranges of northern California and into the southern Cascades and much of the Sierra Nevada mountains as well. In general, the lower elevation locations in and around the Sacramento Valley region only saw around 2 inches or less; thus this area stays at D2 this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
