<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030130</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>From January 29 - February 2, wet weather will continue across the northern Rockies and the Northwest, but little or no precipitation is expected south of a line from northern California to the central Rockies. Farther east, mostly dry weather is forecast on the Plains, but some light precipitation, mostly snow, is possible from the upper Mississippi Valley to northern New England, especially in early February. Rain is likely into January 30 across the Southeast, where a generally dry January followed very wet conditions in late 2002. The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for February 3-7 calls for a wetter weather pattern from the Plains to the East Coast, with near- to above-normal precipitation expected. However, the wet pattern will help to erode most of the remaining cold air across the Midwest and East. Meanwhile, much of the West will remain drier than normal, accompanied by below-normal temperatures in most of the Intermountain region and above-normal readings in California.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Isolated, locally heavy showers dampened parts of Hawaii, resulting in little overall change in the abnormal dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1) affecting the entire state.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Weekly rainfall totaled 1 to 2 inches in scattered locations, locally boosting Puerto Rican topsoil moisture reserves and streamflows. However, the majority of the island remained abnormally dry (D0) due to longer-term precipitation deficits.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Streamflows remained low in much of the Southeast, in part due to the effects of long-term precipitation deficits on groundwater reserves. Flows were also disrupted by unusually cold weather and frozen soils. A winter storm brought some snowfall to the Carolinas on January 23, although liquid equivalents were generally one-half inch or less in the areas of abnormal hydrological dryness and moderate drought (D0 and D1).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>Bitterly cold weather (temperatures 8 to 18 degrees F below normal) in the Midwestern and Great Lakes States contrasted with warming conditions on the High Plains. Some snow preceded the arrival of mild air on the northern High Plains, although liquid totals were generally a half-inch or less and provided little change in the drought picture. On January 26, the temperature range of 56 degrees F (high of 56 and low of 0 degrees F) in Great Falls, Montana, was its largest daily range since December 16, 2000, when the high was 40 and low was -21 degrees F). Farther east, the low of -9 degrees F in Indianapolis, Indiana, on January 27 was its lowest reading since a minimum of -10 degrees F on January 17, 1997. Bitterly cold air streaming across the Great Lakes provided localized drought relief in Lower Michigan's snow belt areas, bringing a slight reduction in severe drought (D2). At the same time, severe drought expanded slightly into southeastern Lower Michigan.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Significant precipitation fell from the Pacific Northwest to the northern Rockies, totaling 2 to 5 inches in many coastal and high-elevation locations. The precipitation slightly dented moderate to extreme drought (D1 to D3) in the northern Rockies, but had little effect elsewhere on the Western drought. Pockets of exceptional drought (D4) persisted in the Intermountain West from northern Arizona to southwestern Montana. On January 27, rain spread into valley locations across the Great Basin and Snake River Plain, where Boise, Idaho, netted a daily-record total of 0.72 inch. But overall water-supply prospects remained bleak for the majority of the West, due to the combination of dry soils from long-term drought, mostly below-normal mountain snow packs, and mostly below-normal reservoir levels. Meanwhile in southern California, January 1-27 rainfall totaled only a trace in downtown Los Angeles, nearing the end of only its fourth January without measurable precipitation in more than 125 years (along with 1948, 1972, and 1976). Record warmth (as much as 10 degrees F above normal) brought some early snow melt to the Southwest. Looking at four river basins in Arizona, the average water content of the snow pack fell to 23, 23, 36, and 48 percent of normal on January 28, down from 51, 58, 65, and 74 percent just 15 days earlier. The changes were due to melting snow at lower elevations and a continuation of dry weather at higher elevations.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
