<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20101118</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Precipitation this week fell mainly through the central High Plains and through the Southeast.  This storm also dumped large amounts of snow in and around Minneapolis – St. Paul, with 8 inches falling at MSP airport on Saturday, November 13.  As of Sunday morning, Minnesota State Police responded to 500 automobile accidents and another 600 reports of cars off the road.  Hundreds of people were left without electricity.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Precipitation is expected across the Southeast, up through the Ohio Valley, and into the Northeast and in the northern Plains early in the November 18-22, 2010 time period.  Later in the period, chances of precipitation are highest in the Northwest and along the Pacific Coast. Above normal temperatures will dominate much of the central part of the country from the South and Southeast, through the Midwest and Central Plains, and into much of the Southwest. Below normal temperatures are expected from the Pacific Coast, through the Northwest and into the northern Plains. Hawaii can expect a mostly dry period with the exception of some light windward showers.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing 5 days (November 23-27, 2010), the odds favor cooler-than-normal conditions from the upper Midwest to the Pacific Northwest, as well as for the Southwest.  Warmer-than-normal conditions are expected across the Gulf States and into the Mid-Atlantic.  The odds of above-normal precipitation extend from the Southwest through the Upper Midwest and the Great Lakes.  Odds favor below-normal precipitation in the southern Plains, along the Gulf Coast, and into the Southeast. Odds favor normal to below normal temperatures and normal to below normal precipitation in eastern Alaska. Odds favor above normal temperatures and above normal precipitation in the western part of the state.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Drought conditions remained unchanged across Alaska and Puerto Rico this week.  While little rain fell across Alaska deficits were not sufficient to degrade the existing drought status. Changes in Hawaii are limited to the south end of the Big Island and include elimination of Exceptional Drought (D4) and slight improvement in all other drought categories in that area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Little precipitation fell in the East from the Mid-Atlantic up through the Northeast during this Drought Monitor week, with the exception of central Maine. Combined with the cooler autumn temperatures, no change in drought categories was experienced.</p>
   <p>In the Southeast, Moderate drought expanded in north-central North Carolina into the northern extents of the Tar and Neuse River Basins.  Further degradation in and around the Cape Fear Basin are possible in the near future without some significant precipitation. In Alabama, the central and northern parts of the state saw some beneficial precipitation.  Small improvements in Extreme (D3), Severe (D2), and Moderate (D1) Drought were experienced. Mississippi saw improvements in the D0 to D2 categories, mostly in the center and western parts of the state.  Improvement in drought designation was also experienced in the Panhandle of Florida.  Recent rains generally led to a one category improvement in conditions west of Tallahassee.  In southern Florida, Abnormal Dryness (D0), Moderate (D1) and Severe (D2) Drought expanded along the East Coast and around Lake Okeechobee.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes and Ohio Valley">
   <p>Recent snow eased Moderate Drought (D1) slightly in northern Minnesota.  Severe (D2) and Moderate (D1) Drought and Abnormal Dryness (D0) expanded westward across Illinois and in southern Missouri.  Abnormal Dryness began to be experienced again in southeast Wisconsin.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Abnormal Dryness (D0) and Moderate Drought (D1) continue to be experienced through the Central Plains.  The storm that moved though this area this week did drop beneficial precipitation and conditions improved slightly in Nebraska and Kansas. This storm also brought rain to parts of the Southern Plains with Abnormal Dryness (D0) and Moderate Drought (D1) easing from central Oklahoma through northern Texas.  Moderate Drought (D1) and Abnormal Dryness (D0) increased across central Texas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Precipitation fell in select areas from Oregon, through northern Nevada, across central Utah, and into Colorado and Wyoming.  The precipitation was generally not sufficient to change drought conditions with the exception of the snows across northwest and central Colorado reducing abnormal dryness (D).  In the Southwest, Abnormal Dryness (D0) and Moderate Drought (D1) expanded in eastern Arizona and western New Mexico.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Brewer</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
