<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060105</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Forecast weather that could have an impact on dry or drought areas across the country in the next 2 weeks include: above-normal temperatures and below-normal rainfall across the drought-affected areas of the southern Plains and the Southwest, while generally near normal rain and snow is indicated for the Midwest. The heavy rains should taper off in the West, except for above-normal rains and high-elevation snows continuing in Washington, Oregon, and northern Idaho.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Very little precipitation fell on interior southeastern Alaska, keeping D0 conditions unchanged. Farther south, Hawaii again experienced a drier-than-normal week, with most areas reporting under one-half inch of rain. As a result, D0 and D1AH conditions persisted across the island chain.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, Great Lakes Region, and Upper South">
   <p>This was a wet week over the Midwest and Eastern Seaboard, with over 1 inch of precipitation reducing drought conditions in southern Michigan and parts of Wisconsin. Moderate precipitation chipped away at the extreme drought over northern Illinois, with some pullback of the D3 in northeastern Illinois. Twelve-month precipitation deficits remain over 12 inches across northern Illinois and adjacent Iowa. Over 1 inch of rain scaled back D1 drought in eastern Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky, while D2 drought ended in eastern Kentucky but remained--and even expanded slightly westward--in central Kentucky.</p>
   <p>Although D1 hydrological drought impacts persist in the Raleigh-Durham area of North Carolina, with mandatory conservation efforts affecting nearly 500,000 residents, a reassessment indicated that the drought area is too small for the national scale used in the U.S. Drought Monitor map, so D0H is shown in the affected area. Over an inch of rain removed the western portion of last weeks D0 area in North Carolina.</p>
   <p>Little or no rain fell for the second week in the southern Plains, and temperatures averaged more than 12 degrees F above normal across the Plains. Warm, dry winds contributed to high fire danger and, as of January 4, 24 large fires still blazed across Oklahoma and Texas, with two more in northern Arkansas. Ninety-day rainfall totaled less than half normal across the southern Mississippi Valley, resulting in D2 drought expanding into northeastern Arkansas and southwestern Missouri, while D4 expanded southwestward through the Dallas-Fort Worth area, and the D3 drought in southern Texas joined the D3 in the north. Twelve-month rainfall deficits exceed 20 inches in southeast Oklahoma, northeast Texas, southwest Arkansas, and parts of Louisiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Intermountain West, and West Coast States">
   <p>A series of Pacific storms battered the West Coast, racking up enormous precipitation totals, including several feet of snow in the mountains. Six inches of precipitation or more extended from central California northward through western Oregon and into Washington. Much higher totals fell in some locations, including 22.1 inches in La Porte, California, in the Sierra Nevada. Up to 20 inches fell in Oregon, and 19 inches in Nevada. Ample totals extended into the Intermountain region, including over 4 inches in many locations in Idaho and in western Wyoming. The heavy rain and snow eliminated dryness from Oregon and led to significant drought reduction in Washington and Idaho. The rain also eliminated the D0 in central California.</p>
   <p>In contrast, dryness persisted across the Southwest, leading to expansion of D0 into southern Colorado and western Arizona, as well as D1 expansion across eastern Arizona. Rainfall has been under 40 percent of normal from southeastern California into Texas during the past 60 days, and below-normal snowfall has led to low snow pack in the mountains across the region, including southern Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
