<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040819</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>For the five-day period through August 23, moderate to heavy precipitation (1 to 3 inches) is anticipated in (a) western Montana and adjacent Idaho and Wyoming; (b) most of Colorado and northern and western Kansas; and (c) southwestern Alabama. Light to moderate totals (0.25 to 1.00 inch) are forecast for the Pacific Northwest, the west-central Rockies, northern and central New Mexico, northern Minnesota, the northwestern Great Lakes region, west-central Illinois, and central Georgia. Meanwhile, less than 0.25 inch is expected across the northern half of the Great Plains, the northern High Plains, the southwestern half of Arizona, southwestern Utah, Nevada, California, and central Montana.</p>
   <p>Daily highs should average near or below normal throughout the nations areas of dryness and drought, especially from the north-central states southwestward through most of the Plains, the central Rockies, and the Southwest.</p>
   <p>For the ensuing five days, the odds favor surplus precipitation and below-normal temperatures for most of the dry areas identified on the Drought Monitor, excepting central Georgia, southwestern Alabama, east-central Illinois, eastern Wisconsin, western Texas and adjacent New Mexico, Nevada, California, and eastern Alaska. No distinct tilt of the odds favoring abnormally wet, dry, cold, or warm weather could be discerned for those regions.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Generally 0.7 to 1.1 inches of precipitation brought an end to D0 conditions in central and lower north-central Alaska, and localized totals exceeding 4 inches similarly ended abnormal dryness in parts of the upper Panhandle. In other sections of southern and eastern Alaska, however, dryness persisted or intensified. Only a few tenths of an inch of precipitation fell on the southern tier of the state, and little if any fell in D0 to D1 areas farther to the north. Most notably, this led to a dramatic increase in fire danger across interior southeastern Alaska, according to the Bureau of Land Management, where conditions were reclassified as D1A this week.</p>
   <p>It was another active week for wildfires, according to the National Interagency Coordination Center. An additional half-million acres were scorched during August 1017, bringing the year-to-date total for the state to just under 5 million acres, which is more than 150% of the average acreage consumed across Alaska and the contiguous 48 states combined during January 1August 17 for the previous ten years.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Central and Northern Parts of the Rockies, Intermountain West, and Far West">
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation (0.3 to 0.9 inch) fell on parts of southwestern Montana, central Idaho, southeastern Oregon, the eastern half of Nevada, and north-central and northeastern Colorado. Little or no rain fell on other areas of dryness and drought in the region. For most areas, this led to no change from last weeks classifications, but deterioration was noted in a few areas, particularly where short-term moisture shortages have increased during the past few weeks while significant multi-year precipitation deficits persisted. D1 to D3 conditions expanded northward in central Montana, and D3 conditions pushed into former D2 regions of northwestern Colorado, and parts of southeastern and interior northeastern Utah.</p>
   <p>Surface moisture losses led to increased wildfire activity in many areas. By August 17, over 26,000 acres had been consumed by wildfires since the beginning of the year in northern California, a 150% increase in the year-to-date total from last week. Elsewhere, also by August 17, the Northwest, southern California, the northern Rockies, and the western Great Basin all reported 10% to 33% increases in areas consumed by wildfires since the beginning of the calendar year from totals reported on August 10 by the National Interagency Coordination Center.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeastern Great Plains and Northern Great Lakes">
   <p>Moderate rains of 1 to 2 inches eliminated D0 conditions in far northeastern Minnesota, north-central Wisconsin, and the far western Upper Peninsula of Michigan. However, lesser amounts to the west and east of these regions kept D0 conditions essentially unchanged, and expanding slightly into east-central Wisconsin.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Moderate to heavy rain (1 to locally 6 inches) wiped out abnormal dryness in western Oklahoma, parts of southeast New Mexico, and the central Big Bend area of Texas. In addition, up to 4 inches of rain allowed former D1H to D3H conditions in south-central New Mexico, far western Texas, northeastern New Mexico, and part of south-central South Dakota to improve by one category. Light to moderate rains also induced small areas of improvement in central Nebraska and extreme southern South Dakota, but dryness persisted or intensified in other parts of the central United States. D0 to D2 conditions advanced eastward across the southern tier of Nebraska, spurned primarily by increasing agricultural concerns. Farther north, D0 conditions enveloped most of northeastern Montana, where surface moisture shortages have steadily increased for the past few weeks.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Anywhere from 2 to 9 inches of rain from Tropical Storm Bonnie, Hurricane Charley, and a semi-stationary front brought an end to most D0 conditions in the region. However, pockets of abnormal dryness persisted in southwestern Alabama, which missed most of the weeks precipitation, and in central Georgia, where moisture shortages were considerably larger prior to the wet week than in surrounding areas. Parts of central and east-central Georgia still reported less than normal rainfall for the last 30 days despite the wet week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southern Rockies, Desert Southwest, and Southern California">
   <p>It was a fairly wet week throughout this region, with dry conditions relegated to northwestern New Mexico, northeastern and far western Arizona, and parts of extreme southern California. As a result, D3 conditions expanded slightly into northwestern New Mexico, and D2 conditions were brought into a small area along the extreme southern tier of California and adjacent Arizona.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, 1 to locally 4 inches of rain fell in association with increased monsoonal moisture across much of Arizona, and many areas in far southern Nevada and the adjacent California deserts recorded 0.5 to 2.0 inches of rain. As a result, conditions improved to D1 in a significant part of interior southeastern California and adjacent southern Nevada, and to D2 in a small part of southeasternmost Arizona. However, dryness and drought assessments remained unchanged in most of the area due to the slow start to monsoonal showers and thunderstorm activity during July and early August, and because of the large multi-year moisture shortages in these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
