<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20090521</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>During May 12-18, very wet and stormy conditions prevailed over the eastern half of the country. A slow moving frontal system tracked across the Central States early in the period and the Eastern States later in the period. The heaviest amounts of rain fell from eastern Oklahoma northeastward to the Ohio River Valley, on parts of New York and Pennsylvania, and also across parts of the Southeast. The southern end of the cold front brought some precipitation (up to 2 inches) across central Texas, bringing modest improvement to the region. Late in the period, an area of low pressure aloft and a stationary front brought as much as 5 to 10 inches of rain to northeast Florida, and significant amounts across most of the state. Over the Southwest, little to no precipitation and unseasonably hot temperatures dominated during the period. Weekly average temperatures ranged from 6 to 10 degrees F above normal, with highs in the triple digits as far north as northern California.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (May 21-25) a stationary front and an upper low will bring heavy rains to parts of Florida. This low is forecast to move westward into the Gulf, allowing Florida to dry out while soaking the central Gulf coast by the weekend. A pair of cold fronts will track across the northern tier of states, producing light to moderate rains, with possibly 2-4 inches from Wyoming to South Dakota. In the Four Corners region, scattered showers and storms will move into the area and increase in intensity and coverage.  Warm and dry conditions are forecast for the Pacific Coast States.</p>
   <p>The Climate Prediction Center 6-10 day forecast (May 26-30) calls for above-normal precipitation over the Gulf and Atlantic Coastal States (including Florida), and from western Texas and New Mexico northward through Colorado. Subnormal precipitation is expected across the Northwest, Great Basin, northern Plains and upper Midwest. Warmer than usual weather is forecast for the western third of the Nation, while subnormal readings are predicted for the Central and Southeastern U.S.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Florida">
   <p>After a very dry spring, the south Florida wet season began 9 days early, on May 11. Widespread showers and thunderstorms covered most of the state, bringing at least 1 inch of rain to the drought area. One to two category improvements were made from Fort Myers to Tampa to the I-4 corridor to Palm Coast, where 4 to locally 10 inches of rain fell. South of Lake Okeechobee, 2 to locally 6 inches of rain reduced drought by a category. The KBDI greatly improved, dropping from 600-800 before the onset of precipitation to 100-300 on May 19. Average stream flow values improved accordingly.   Despite the recent wet weather, lower rainfall (1-2 inches) did not significantly mitigate the drought from Lake Okeechobee northward to Brevard County, and D3 remained. As of May 19, Lake Okeechobee was at 10.6 feet (2.64 feet below normal), finally rising after dropping since mid-September 2008.  Heavy rains fell after the 12 UTC May 19 data cutoff, and further improvement will likely be shown next week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>In Kauai, a late-season cold front dropped between 0.25 and 1.00 inch of rain on some spots, but nothing along the southwest (leeward) side. Average stream flows out through 28 days were in the lowest decile. Additionally, a USDA report from the island indicated that pasture conditions were starting to dry out earlier than normal for this time of year, prompting the introduction of D0 throughout Kauai. Elsewhere, light scattered windward showers maintained conditions.</p>
   <p>In Alaska, light showers (less than 0.5 inch of rain) on top of 30- and 90-day observed precipitation deficits at Sitka (3.3/7.0 inches),  Juneau (1.9/3.6 inches), and Yakutat (8.5/21.5 inches) did little to alleviate abnormal dryness throughout the Alaskan Panhandle. The exception was near Ketchikan, where 1-3 inches of rain fell.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Light to moderate rains fell on the upper Midwest, with the heavier amounts (between 1.0 and 1.5 inches) occurring in eastern Wisconsin, the Upper Peninsula of Michigan, and northern Lower Michigan. The rains were enough to alleviate abnormal dryness in those three areas, but further west, larger deficiencies remained. At 30-, 60-, 90-, and 180-days, precipitation was still less than 70 percent of normal. Weekly rainfall amounts were less than 0.5 inches as the 7-, 14-, and 28-day average stream flows remained in the lowest quartile.  The D2 region was shifted southwestward to better depict the driest area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Northeast and Mid-Atlantic, and Carolinas">
   <p>Two to four inches of rain fell across northeast Pennsylvania and southern New York, alleviating most of the D0 in the Northeast. D0(H) remained where lower precipitation amounts were reported (less than an inch), and year-to-date precipitation amounts were 50 to 75 percent of normal.  Average USGS stream flows for latest 7, 14, and 28 days were still in the lower 25th percentile over northwest Pennsylvania and western New York.</p>
   <p>In the Carolinas, another week of moderate to heavy (2-4 inches) rainfall in the drought areas further diminished D0(H) in western and eastern North Carolina, and western South Carolina.  Reports from the Georgia State Climatologist indicated that Lake Lanier was still 6 feet below normal supporting D0(H) in northeast Georgia. In eastern North Carolina and the southern Appalachians, measured precipitation was a foot below normal for the past 12 months, and long-term blends supported the continuation of the drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Although an inch of rain fell on extreme eastern Nebraska, drier conditions to the west expanded the initial D0 area in Nebraska into southeastern South Dakota and north-central Kansas. Year-to-date deficits exceeded 6 inches in this region, although long-term (subsoil) moisture supplies were adequate. Impacts were negligible as the drier top soils allowed producers to make excellent planting progress.  Toward the end of the week, hot weather (highs near 100 degrees F) accompanied the dryness, raising concerns of additional D0 in the western Corn Belt.</p>
   <p>In the southern Plains, a cold front produced scattered showers and thunderstorms, some locally heavy, over southwestern Oklahoma and the eastern two-thirds of Texas, including far southern Texas. In Oklahoma, Roger Mills County finally received decent rains (1.26 inches) after missing out the past few weeks, improving conditions there. The SPI blend products from Texas A&amp;M supported more improvement along the Red River, south-central Texas, and the Big Bend area.  In the Red River region (Donley to Montague counties) 1 to 2 inches of rain provided additional relief from the drought. In south-central Texas (Webb to Gonzales counties), a convective line dropped 1.5 to 3 inches of rain, prompting improvement across the former D4 region.  One to 1.5 inches of rain also eased drought in Starr and Zapata counties (near Laredo).  In the Big Bend area (Pecos, Brewster, and Terrell counties) 1 to 1.5 inches of rain alleviated abnormal dryness there.</p>
   <p>In contrast, a one-category degradation was made in the Texas Panhandle (Parmer to Garza counties) as dry and hot weather occurred during the normally wettest time of the year.  A reassessment of SPI values suggested a westward shift in the core D2-D3 area in north-central Texas (centered over Haskell and Stonewall counties). The worst of the D4 area was centered over Aransas County where the Aransas County airport reported 14 percent of normal precipitation over the past 9 months (3.43 inches versus 25.07 inches normally). Since March 26 of 2009, the airport only measured 0.03 inches of rain, or 0.7 percent of normal!  Since October 1, 2007, a total of 19 months, not counting this May, Aransas County airport has reported only 4 months with at least 50 percent of normal precipitation.</p>
   <p>In New Mexico, continued hot and mostly dry weather further deteriorated conditions. Highs reached the century mark in many locations, and temperatures averaged 4 to 8 degrees F above normal. According to the NRCS, precipitation was well below normal since January across the southern third of the State.  As of May 17, 92 percent of the state's top soil moisture, 62 percent of the total winter wheat, and 65 percent of the pastures and ranges were rated poor or very poor, respectively, by NASS/USDA.  Accordingly, an expansion of D1 and D2 was made in southeastern New Mexico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>An expansion of the D1(A) was made in Arizona, based on short-term blends,  14-,30-, and 60-day precipitation totals, which were 2,5, and 25-50 percent of normal, respectively. The Arizona expansion, which included the area between Phoenix and Flagstaff north to the Colorado River was also based on 90-, 180-, 360-day precipitation deficits (less than 25 percent of normal at 90 days, less than 70 percent of normal at 6 and 12 months).  In eastern Utah (Ferron Creek and Moab), SWSI values near      -2.0 led to an expansion of the D0 area.</p>
   <p>A small reduction of the D1 area in southwestern Idaho was based on the short- and long-term drought blends, and Water Year-To-Date basin average precipitation which stood at 110 percent of normal.  Stream flows are generally near to slightly above normal in this region. The rest of the West received little if any precipitation, but since that is not unusual for this time of the year, no changes were indicated.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Matthew Rosencrans</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>David Miskus</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Anthony Artusa</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
