<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20020103</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Two major winter storms will bring rain and snow to drought areas from the southern Plains to the Southeast, then up the eastern seaboard, during the next 6 days (January 2-7). Precipitation amounts of 1 to 2 inches are expected, with 2-3 inches in the wettest areas. Pacific systems will move across parts of the western U.S. but weaken beneath the upper ridge. Precipitation amounts of less than half an inch expected over most areas, but locally more than an inch in the Sierra Nevada and northern coastal California and coastal Oregon-Washington. Temperatures will average below normal across the southern Plains and Southeast, and above normal across the rest of the Lower 48 States.</p>
   <p>During January 7-12, a dry ridge intensifies over the West with little precipitation, except near normal amounts are expected over Washington, western Oregon, and northern Idaho. Much of the nation east of the Rockies will have below normal precipitation. The northern Plains and mid-Atlantic regions can expect near normal precipitation, with above normal precipitation falling in central Florida to southern Georgia and along the coast from Virginia to Maine. Colder than normal temperatures are expected along the Gulf coast to mid-Atlantic states, while the rest of the Lower 48 States will be warmer than normal.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Puerto Rico">
   <p>One to three inches of rain fell across northern Puerto Rico with locally heavier amounts interior, but considerably drier along the south coast. Near to below normal rainfall occurred at most Hawaiian stations, with more at the favored locations. Consequently, no change has been made to the D0 to D2 areas across southern Puerto Rico and central and eastern Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Another week of light precipitation over most areas from the Appalachians eastward brought no improvement to the drought areas. Mounting deficits over the Southeast, as reflected in 3- and 6-month precipitation percentiles, Palmer Drought Index, objective indicators, and very low to record low streamflows, resulted in expansion of D1 to Georgia-Florida state line, D2 southward in Georgia, and D3 across most of South Carolina into eastern Georgia with a sliver of D3 westward across Georgia.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Dryness or drought areas persisted in most areas with continued light to no precipitation during the week. The D0 and D1 boundaries in central Kansas edged slightly northward to coincide with Palmer Drought Index and soil moisture indicators. A spot of D0 was introduced in southwest Iowa reflecting 90-day precipitation deficits, soil moisture and objective blend indicators. Up to a third of an inch of precipitation in the Texas panhandle prompted the slight contraction of D1 to coincide with the soil moisture indicator.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>One to four inches of precipitation fell across northern and central California, pushing the western D0, D1, and D2 boundaries closer to the Nevada state line. Some of this precipitation making it into west central Nevada nibbled away at the western and southern edges of the D3 there. A snowstorm in southwestern Montana dropped 8-12 inches in valley locations, but the snowfall had low moisture content and gave minimal improvement to mountain snowpack, so no change made to drought depiction there. D2 boundary peeled back slightly in northeast Washington to reflect long-term conditions. But as noted last week, even though near- to well above-normal precipitation fell on most areas during the last 90 days, broad-scale totals in the D1 to D3 areas have not yet been sufficient to ensure substantial reservoir and groundwater recharge when the snowpack melts in spring. Some indicators suggest the stage is being set for drought to develop in Arizona. However, depicting drought in a desert environment is always problematical, and the region is entering its wetter winter season. This area will be closely monitored in the weeks ahead.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
