<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040603</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Ongoing or forecast weather over the next 2 weeks potentially having an impact on dryness or drought areas include: 1) heavy showers and thunderstorms on June 2 over west Texas, Oklahoma, and the Southeast; 2) a tendency toward above-normal rainfall across the drought areas of the Southeast through June 16; 3) the start of the summer rainy season across peninsula Florida, 4) generally above-normal rainfall and below-normal temperatures across the interior Northwest, northern Rockies, and northern Plains through June 16; and 5) widespread showers protruding into western Kansas around June 6.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Precipitation increased in southeastern Alaska, as several locations reported 1 to 3 inches. Although the area of D0 diminished, D0 remained over the Panhandle, where most areas saw less than half of normal rainfall in May.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Another week of storms brought heavy rain and flooding to the Midwest. Rainfall amounts of 2 to 6 inches finally eliminated drought in Minnesota and eastern South Dakota. Heavy rains also reduced abnormal dryness in central North Dakota. But conditions were much drier a short distance to the west. Little rain fell from southwestern North Dakota southward to west Texas, although a few good showers hit western Nebraska. D2 drought expanded slightly westward along the North Dakota-South Dakota boundary, and D2 to D3 drought persisted from southwest South Dakota to western Kansas and into eastern Colorado. Hot, dry weather resulted in D1 drought development in the Texas Panhandle and western Oklahoma. Dodge City, Kansas set a record with a mere 0.25 inches for the entire month of May, beating the previous record of 0.40 inches set way back in 1886 . Preliminary data has Oklahoma recording its driest May, with statewide rainfall averaging just 1.08 inches. The northeast Texas Panhandle recorded no measurable rain for the entire month.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Heavy showers of 2 inches or more eliminated abnormally dry conditions (D0) in western Alabama this past week, with heavy thunderstorms ending dryness in Floridas western Panhandle on June 1. In contrast, warm, dry weather in Georgia and much of South Carolina allowed D1 and D2 drought to persist in both states. The drought even advanced slightly northward into southern North Carolina. In Florida, D0 dryness expanded to cover the entire peninsula as the dearth of rain continued. D1 drought expanded slightly southward in northeastern Florida, and D1 developed in southern Florida. May dryness broke or tied records in parts of the state, as Naples, for example, tied its record for the driest May with 0.64 inches. Vero Beach notched a record with just .09 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>Rain and snow amounts diminished in the northern Rockies compared to the previous week, but heavy rains of up to 4 inches or more struck Washington and Oregon from the Cascades westward, eliminating the D1 drought introduced just last week. Ample rains also shaved some of the D1 and D2 area from south-central Idaho. Additional rains boosted soil moisture in Montana, where USDA rated topsoil moisture at 36% short to very short, which was better than both the 5 and 10-year average for this time of the year. The rains slightly reduced the area of D0/D1/D2/D3 in the northeast and the D3 in central Montana. Monthly rainfall exceeded 7 inches at several high-elevation locations in central and western Montana. In Wyoming, weekly rainfall exceeding 3 inches in several spots in the northwest caused an improvement to D2 near the Tetons. Farther west, however, near-record low streamflows worsened drought levels from D2 to D3 in north-central Wyoming. Dry weather allowed drought to persist across the Southwest.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
