<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040715</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a strong trough should set up over the eastern United States, bringing with it well below-normal temperatures and rains totaling an inch or more into the New England region over the next 5 days ending July 19th; 2) south central Florida could see an inch or more as well over the same period, but the expected totals fall off heading south toward Dade county; 3) precipitation ranging from 1 to 1.5 inches is forecasted for central Colorado, southeastern Wyoming, and over into western and central Nebraska; 4) the monsoon may become much more productive in Arizona over the next 5 days as well with totals of 1 to 1.5 inches possible across the eastern half of the state; 5) looking out at the 6-10 day period ending July 24th, the models keep a strong jet stream over the northern tier of the country with a strong trough in the East and a strong ridge in the West. As a result, rainfall is expected to be above normal along the entire eastern seaboard, eastern New Mexico, and from the northern Plains up into the northern Rockies and Pacific Northwest. Conditions are expected to be drier than normal across much of the Great Basin, most of California and down into northern Arizona; 6) temperatures during this period are expected to be below normal for the Southeast and up into the Mid-Atlantic region while most of the Dakotas, northern Minnesota, and New England can expect warmer than normal temperatures to prevail. In addition, California, the Great Basin and Southwest can also expect above-normal temperatures during the 6-10 day period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Interior and Southeast Alaska were generally warm and dry, leading to no improvement in the abnormally dry (D0) conditions found there and bringing no real relief to the multiple large fires burning there presently. Since June 1, Juneau is 3.3 inches below normal (40% of normal) and Fairbanks in the interior has observed only .35 inches since June 1 (17% of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>As longer-term deficits continue to accumulate in Maine this summer, the abnormally dry (D0) area has pushed slightly down the coast to the west. In addition, recent dryness has led to the emergence of D0 in extreme northeast Pennsylvania, extreme southern New York, and western Massachusetts and Connecticut, where top soils are beginning to dry out. This area missed out on the news-making flood rains that fell just to the south across southeastern Pennsylvania and New Jersey.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>Good rains last week in northern Minnesota have led to the removal of moderate drought (D1) there. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions have eroded somewhat on the northern fringe as well. After a very dry June (7th driest with 1.55 inches) in International Falls, they received more than 2 inches last week alone. The Duluth area also welcomed the rain after its 6th driest June on record.</p>
   <p>Lingering dryness has now resulted in the addition of an abnormally dry (D0) pocket in south central Missouri where recent dryness (the last 30-60 days) has been amplified as the heat returns and year-to-date totals are below normal as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>While rains over the past 30-60 days have led to some improvement in abnormally dry (D0) conditions in South Carolina, recent dryness on top of longer-term dryness and a return to warmth in North Carolina have led to an expansion of D0 into the midsection of the state. The Chapel Hill area has reported below-normal rainfall for every month this year and Greensboro is down more than 10 inches (56% of normal) on the year as well. At this time, there are no major reports of impacts, but the situation bears watching as we head into the hottest time of summer.</p>
   <p>Farther south, the dryness continues in southern Florida as the abnormally dry (D0) area has pushed a bit north and west into the Everglades and points west of Lake Okeechobee. Lake Okeechobee continues to see its level decline in July, when normally it begins to rise during June.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Western States">
   <p>Most of the West saw a relatively quiet week on the precipitation front, leading to no changes across much of the region. So far, the monsoon has been generally sluggish and a little late in coming to Arizona as well. While Arizona and others in the Southwest wait for the monsoon to kick into gear, one area that has seen some changes (for better or worse) recently is New Mexico. The monsoon rains have led to some improvement in extreme eastern New Mexico where abnormally dry (D0) has been pushed to the west, but other areas of the state are still mired in long-term drought, which is now being compounded by short-term dryness as well. As a result, parts of northwestern New Mexico have deteriorated, with an expansion of severe drought (D2) and extreme drought (D3) being noted in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
