<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040212</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a storm system expected to move across the southern United States February 12-16 may clip some drought and dryness areas of New Mexico, Texas, Oklahoma, and Arkansas before moving into the southeastern U.S.; 2) most of the continental U.S. experiencing dryness and drought will, however, remain mild and mostly dry during the entire period; and 3) temperatures and precipitation are expected to be above normal across most of Alaska during the period, including the abnormally dry regions of the state.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Conditions remained abnormally dry across parts of Alaska during the past week. Because of low precipitation totals and low snowpack conditions since October 1, D0 was expanded to include more of the central region of the state. No changes were made for the week for Hawaii.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes">
   <p>A third winter storm in two weeks brought another round of heavy snow to eastern Nebraska, southeast South Dakota, western Iowa, northwestern Missouri, and northeastern Kansas. Totals reached 12 inches in south-central Nebraska, which had been missed by the two previous storms. There were slight improvements made to the drought classification in south-central Nebraska and in southeast South Dakota as a result of this storm. Omahas snow depth reached a record 26 inches for February, just shy of the all-time record of 27 inches in March 1960. Farther north, in Michigans Upper Peninsula, Houghton had its string of consecutive days with measurable snow snapped at 33, one short of the record set during 1998-99. During this recent streak, 110 inches of snow fell on the city.</p>
   <p>Heavier rains also fell during the week in the abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) areas in southeast Oklahoma, northeast Texas, and southwestern Arkansas. However, long-term precipitation deficits remain in the region, and no changes were made to the classifications. Dry conditions also continued across the Texas Panhandle, and Lake Meredith on the Canadian River north of Amarillo set a record low lake level going back to 1967.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Southwest, and Far West">
   <p>Improving hydrological conditions led to improvements in the drought classifications in a couple of locations across the West. In southwestern Montana, improved SWSI values, reservoir storage, and precipitation totals in the Madison and Gallatin River Basins indicate that the exceptional (D4) drought classification can move to extreme (D3). In Oregon, plentiful precipitation and basin snow water contents since the beginning of the Water Year have allowed one-category improvements to the D3, D2, D1, and D0 areas across the eastern half of the state, with similar improvements in bordering sections of Nevada, Idaho and Washington. In the Owyhee Basin in southwest Idaho, the snow water content has reached 135% of normal for this time of year, and is 102% of the April 1 peak when the snow water content is generally at its maximum for the season. Meanwhile, snow water contents increased more than 10% during the week across a number of basins in Arizona and New Mexico, but significant short-term and long-term deficits remain in these states. No changes were made in the drought classifications in these two states.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
