<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040401</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>A pair of slow-moving storm systems will produce widespread precipitation during the next few days. In the East, a nearly stationary storm systemcut-off from the steering flow of the jet streamis forecast to dump 1 to 3 inches of precipitation from the central Appalachians to southern New England. Some locally higher totals are possible in the latter region, including portions of the Northeastern area of abnormal dryness. Farther south, however, dry weather will return to the Southeast. Meanwhile, a complex storm system will evolve across the Plains and the West. Much-needed rain may develop on the Montana High Plains on April 1, and spread across the remainder of the Plains on April 2-3. During the weekend, the focus for heavy precipitation will shift to Texas and the southern Rockies, where storm totals may reach 2 to 4 inches. Elsewhere in the West, disorganized rain and snow showers are not expected to provide significant drought relief. Storm-total rainfall may locally exceed 1 inch on the parched northern and central High Plains, but dry weather will prevail into early next week across the upper Midwest.</p>
   <p>The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for April 6-10 calls for generally cool, wet weather on the central and southern High Plains and across the South from Texas to the southern Atlantic States. Elsewhere, near- to below-normal precipitation and cool conditions are expected in the Northeast, while most of the West will experience a continuation of warm, mostly dry weather.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Negligible precipitation fell in the Alaskan areas of abnormal dryness (D0). Therefore, there were no changes in the depiction, which continued to reflect below-average snow packs and precipitation shortfalls since October 1, 2003.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Only light precipitation fell in the Northeastern area of abnormal dryness (D0), which stretched from east-central New York to the New England coast. Warm weather (as much as 8 degrees F above normal) and below-normal weekly precipitation justified a slight northward expansion of the dry area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>The gradient between drought (D1 to D3) on the High Plains and relatively wet conditions on the east-central Plains sharpened during the week ending March 29. On the High Plains, the combination of dry weather and temperatures as much as 15 degrees F above normal maintained stress on pastures and winter wheat. In Colorado, USDA/NASS reported as of March 28 that pastures and rangeland rated 58 percent very poor to poor, a slight improvement from last year at this time (77 percent very poor to poor) but significantly worse than the five-year average of 36 percent. Meanwhile, the percentage of winter wheat rated very poor to poor included 61 percent in Colorado, 30 percent in Texas, and 28 percent in both Kansas and Nebraska.</p>
   <p>One area that did receive much-needed precipitation (as much as 1 to 3 inches) was the upper Midwest. In fact, heavy rainfall combined with melting snow to produce lowland flooding in parts of eastern North Dakota and northwestern Minnesota, where abnormal dryness (D0) was removed. By the evening of March 30, the Red River at East Grand Forks, Minnesota, climbed 10 feet above flood stage. There were also some modest reductions in dryness (D0) and moderate to severe drought (D1 to D2) across parts of eastern South Dakota, southern Minnesota, northern Iowa, and western Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>The area of long-term, hydrological drought centered on northwestern Missouri also received substantial precipitation (1 to 2 inches), resulting in a reduction from severe to moderate drought (D2 to D1). Although surfaces conditions, such as pasture conditions and streamflows, are in relatively good shape in this area, there are still serious groundwater shortages and long-term precipitation deficits.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Abnormal dryness (D0) expanded across the Southeast, bridging westward to near the mouth of the Mississippi River and edging northward and eastward farther into the Carolinas. Rain associated with a slow-moving cold front moved into the western half of the dry area on the night of March 29-30, providing rainfall locally in excess of one inch to parts of northeastern Alabama and northwestern Georgia.</p>
   <p>The USDAs National Agricultural Statistics Service released information for the week ending March 28 highlighting some of the concerns related to dryness. In central Georgia, many corn producers are awaiting rain before planting and dry conditions are hurting all of the fall/winter crops. Farmers have been irrigating crops where possible. Farther west, reports from west-central Georgia indicate that wheat does not look good and some producers are starting to water the wheat. The same USDA/NASS report noted that Georgias soil moisture was rated 75 percent very short to short.</p>
   <p>According to the U.S. Geological Survey, the percentage of river gauges reporting flows in the lowest one-tenth of historical values for March 30 were as follows: Alabama and South Carolina, 75 percent; Georgia, 73 percent; North Carolina, 54 percent; and Mississippi, 43 percent. For the period October 1, 2003 - March 29, 2004, a nearly six-month stretch, precipitation departures from normal and percent of normal values were as follows: Charlotte, North Carolina, -13.40 inches and 48 percent of normal; Greenville-Spartanburg, South Carolina, -12.71 inches and 56 percent; and Atlanta, Georgia, -11.24 inches and 62 percent.</p>
   <p>Farther west, there were no changes reported in other abnormally dry (D0) pockets. The largest dry area, centered on southeastern Oklahoma, received as much as one inch of rain from March 25-29, temporarily curbing the threat of additional wildfire activity. According to the National Interagency Fire Center, there were more than two dozen large wildfires (100 acres or greater) reported in recent days across Arkansas and eastern Oklahoma, although all of the fires were fully contained by March 26.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A few days of cooler conditions and scattered rain and snow showers were followed by a return to dry weather and record warmth. Despite the briefly cooler weather, March 23-29 temperatures still averaged 2 to 8 degrees F above normal across the northern half of the West and more than 10 degrees F above normal in parts of the Southwest. By March 29, record warmth was back in full force, with more than 50 daily-record highs reported from Washington southward into California and Arizona. March 29 also featured another wave of monthly record highs, including 78 degrees F in Seattle, Washington, and 94 degrees F in Bakersfield, California. Bakersfield also extended records for the greatest number of March days with high temperatures of 90 degrees F or greater (3; previously, 1 day in 2003 and earlier years) and 80 degrees F or greater (17; previously, 16 days in 1934). On March 30, another parade of records included March-record highs in Montana locations such as Havre (79 degrees F), Great Falls (78 degrees F), and Cut Bank (77 degrees F). Since the spell of record warmth began on March 7, there have been more than 1,000 daily-record highs and several dozen monthly record highs set or tied across the western half of the United States.</p>
   <p>Dryness or drought (D0 to D4) continued to affect nearly all of the West east of the Cascades and Sierra Nevada. Areas experiencing extreme to exceptional drought (D3 to D4) stretched from parts of central and western Montana southward through the Great Basin and the Intermountain region into northern Arizona and much of New Mexico. Water-supply concerns supported some incremental worsening of drought conditions in parts of the Intermountain West and Southwest. In addition, below-normal seasonal precipitation justified some expansion of abnormal dryness (D0) across southern California. In San Diego, nine-month (July 2003 - March 2004) precipitation totaled 4.58 inches (47 percent of normal). San Diegos rainfall since the beginning of 1999 stood at 37.58 inches (62 percent of normal). Farther east, south-central Arizona remained one of the least-affected areas by drought, in part due to recent widespread precipitation. Nevertheless, Tucson reported only 3.54 inches of rain (63 percent of normal) from October 2003 - March 2004, and netted 51.36 inches (77 percent) from January 1999 - March 2004.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
