<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000601</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 2 weeks, showers in the first week are forecast ahead of a second week with much above-normal temperatures and below-normal rainfall. As a result, no major changes are expected except in Missouri, where the 5-day rainfall forecast indicates 2 inches or more in southern Missouri.</p>
   <p>Above-normal rains are forecast during June 6-10 across the Southeast, providing some hope that the drought conditions there could improve. Increased diurnal showers are forecast in Florida as well, also providing hope that drought conditions could improve.</p>
   <p>Increased rainfall in Montana should prevent further expansion of the drought. Increased rainfall over New Mexico should offer some drought relief during the first week of the forecast period, with 1 to 2 inches forecast during May 31 to June 5. Later drier weather will offset some of the benefits.</p>
   <p>For Hawaii, no significant changes are expected in the next 2 weeks. In Puerto Rico, increasing tropical showers should gradually reduce the dryness.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Torrential rains fell over eastern Puerto Rico May 29-30, but most of the rain missed the north coast area, so abnormal dryness due to lingering rainfall deficits since the start of the year continued along the coast. Little rain fell in Hawaii, allowing D1 and D2 drought to persist in the leeward areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Widespread rains swept across the Midwest on May 25-26, further easing drought conditions. One to 2-inch totals were common, with 3 inches or more in central Missouri. The moisture improved topsoil moisture across the region. In Iowa, USDA reported that the slow, soaking showers were exactly what was needed to further crop and pasture growth for most areas of the state. Nevertheless, high temperatures reduced some of the benefits of the rains, especially in Nebraska, and subsoil moisture supplies remained below normal for much of the western Corn Belt due to the lingering effects of the dry fall and winter. Precipitation since October 1 has totaled 6 to 8 inches below normal from southeast Nebraska eastward through central and southern Iowa and southward into the northern third of Missouri and, as a consequence, severe (D2) drought persisted in most of this area. The recent moisture reduced the area of D3 (extreme) drought in southeastern Nebraska and northwestern Missouri. A second area of severe drought (D2) persisted in southeastern interior Missouri, where 6-inch rainfall deficits since October remain. USDA topsoil ratings for Missouri improved from 77 to 47 percent short to very short in the past week. The rains reduced the D2 (severe) drought area in Illinois, confining it to the west-central area, but D1 (first-level) drought extended in a narrow band through central Illinois into western Indiana.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="South-Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>Rains improved moisture conditions in Arkansas, Tennessee, and northeastern South Carolina, but lighter showers and high temperatures caused drought to expand elsewhere over the Southeast, with extreme drought (D3) extending from Georgia into adjacent parts of South Carolina and southward deep into Florida. Extreme drought also covered the Gulf Coast from the Florida Panhandle to southeast Louisiana, with hot, dry weather raising the drought category to the highest possible rating of D4 in portions of southeastern Louisiana. As of May 27, New Orleans' Audubon Park had reported only 5.80 inches of rain since January 1, compared with a normal of 23.74 inches. In Georgia, the corn and soybean crops were rated 43 percent poor or very poor. Both Georgia and Alabama reported cotton condition 37 percent poor to very poor. In Texas, showers brought some minor relief to lingering dry areas in the east, but hot weather with little or no rain caused extreme (D3) drought to edge northward in the southwestern part of the state. Some rain fell from the Panhandle southward to the Lubbock area, but high temperatures offset much of the benefits. Farther north, heavy rains did eliminate dryness from Oklahoma and much of Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Above-normal temperatures and scanty rains caused D1 drought to expand northward in central Montana to the Canadian border. In north-central Montana, precipitation totals from April 1 to May 27 totaled as little as one-third inch, which is 13 percent of normal. Rangeland conditions quickly deteriorated in the past week, with 46 percent rated poor to very poor across the state. Winter wheat was rated 55 percent poor or very poor. Abnormally high temperatures also caused drought to expand northward in the Southwest, with severe drought (D2) expanding to cover most of the southern two-thirds of New Mexico and extreme drought (D3) expanding northward from southwest Texas deep into southeastern New Mexico. Extreme fire danger continued over large areas of Arizona and New Mexico.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
