<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20090319</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Texas, North Carolina and Virginia received beneficial rainfall this week, with some areas greening up just in time for St. Patrick's Day.  Colorado's Front Range and Florida are among the regions that experienced worsening drought conditions.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>Early in the next drought monitoring period, a front is forecast to push its way through the southern Plains and off the east coast.  Moisture from the Gulf of Mexico could produce some precipitation from the central United States into the northeast.  Over the weekend a system will move onshore in the West.  Coastal regions are projected to receive heavy rainfall with snow at higher elevations.  Orographically enhanced precipitation will fall on the western slopes of the mountains from the Sierra Nevada to the Rocky Mountains.  Early next week, the eastern states will have a strong ridge following the weekend cold front that could prevent much rainfall.  In the longer range overall, the six to ten day forecast calls for above average temperatures throughout the Plains states from North Dakota to western Tennessee, and below normal temperatures over all of Alaska and the southern tip of Florida.  For the same period, precipitation is projected to be below normal in northwest Alaska, the Intermountain region and Southwest, and East Coast.  Above normal precipitation for the six to ten day period is expected in the Pacific Northwest and central states.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Rainfall over the last two weeks on the Big Island has improved drought in the southern area.  The severe and moderate drought regions have reduced in extent this week.  Alaska and Puerto Rico had no change this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Southeastern Pennsylvania, northern Maryland and northern Delaware are still dry after one of the driest Februarys on record in the region.  For the last 90 days, locations in this area have measured about half of normal precipitation, with deficits of four to six inches.  Abnormally dry, or D0, was introduced.  In southwestern Virginia, the extent of moderate drought was reduced due to significant rainfall.  The steady, multi-day rainfall event was welcome and brought 1.5 to 3.5 inches of precipitation across this area.  In southern Virginia and North Carolina, drought conditions improved this week, also reflecting a four-day rainfall event that increased streamflow and raised groundwater levels.  Two to three inches fell in central North Carolina into Virginia, as abnormally dry conditions improved to near normal.  Western North Carolina also experienced improvement in the region of moderate drought, and the D1 region was scaled back.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Drought relief finally came in the form of significant rainfall to areas of eastern, central, and northern Texas into Oklahoma.  One-category improvements were made in a swath from west of San Antonio to southeastern Oklahoma.  Weekly precipitation totals of three to five inches were common throughout this region.  In the Big Bend, moderate drought was reduced to abnormally dry conditions (D0) in Presidio and western Brewster counties, with over an inch of rainfall this week.  In eastern Texas, wet conditions also prevailed east of Interstate 45, expanding the area of D0.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Florida's drought conditions continue to degrade and a lack of rainfall pushed the east coastal counties into the severe category from Kennedy Space Center to West Palm Beach.  On the west coast north of Naples, another dry week caused a one-category deterioration to moderate, or D1 conditions.  The Suwanee and Santa Fe river basins in the north have had consistently low streamflow.  In combination with little or no precipitation, this region fell into moderate drought as well.  The central coast of Louisiana continues to experience a deficit of precipitation over the last 90 days, and moderate drought was introduced.  The southwest counties of the state locally received two inches or more of precipitation, bringing a one-category improvement there.  Rainfall amounts as heavy as four to six inches locally fell this week in central Alabama and east into Georgia, but this was primarily in the drought-free region so no change was made in these states.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>In California, an expansion of moderate drought (D1) was introduced in eastern Fresno and Tulare counties over the Sierra Nevada crest, due to lack of precipitation over recent weeks and low reservoir storage.  Colorado's Front Range continues to experience dry conditions.  Pueblo has received just .08 inch of precipitation since January 1, and Colorado Springs has measured .26 inch in the same period.  As a result, moderate drought conditions are depicted on the map.  The area along the Yellowstone River in Montana, between Miles City and Sidney, has been abnormally dry this winter.  The last major winter storm to reach this region was in mid-October, and there is little snow cover on the ground.  D0 was introduced in Prairie, Dawson and Richland counties.  Abnormally dry conditions have also expanded in central Montana due to low winter precipitation and no snow cover.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Laura Edwards</name>
   <affiliation>Western Regional Climate Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
