<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030821</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period (through August 30) which may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought include: Over the next 5 days (August 21-25): 1) A cold front should descend across the Great Lakes and bring some precipitation to portions of the Great Lakes region; 2) monsoonal rains are expected to persist across portions of the Southwest. For the 6-10 day period (August 26-30) expect warmer than average temperatures across much of the U.S. from the Intermountain West to the Great Lakes and Southeast. Below average temperatures are expected across New England. Above average precipitation is forecast along a large portion of the western U.S./Canadian border and from Arizona to the Texas Gulf Coast. Below average precipitation is expected to persist across the central and interior Rockies as well as across much of the eastern U.S. Brisk trade winds are forecast across much of Hawaii early in the period and are expected to diminish later in the period. Associated precipitation should not be significant. Showers and above normal temperatures are forecast across much of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>There was no change in the D1 to D2 drought over Hawaii and the D0 dryness in southeastern Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central and Southern Plains">
   <p>A band of heavy thunderstorms with hail occurred across parts of south central Nebraska and north central Kansas at the end of the Drought Monitor period. But the rain came too late for farmers in some southern and central Nebraska counties, where corn was chopped for silage. Water deliveries from Harlan County Reservoir, in south central Nebraska, have been shut down, the first time in history that this has happened, and some streams were at record low levels. Although there were a few reports of 1 to 2 inch rains, no change was made to the drought depiction in this area due to the severe long-term impacts. Another band of 1-inch rains prompted the contraction of D0 and D1 in central Texas. Elsewhere, very little significant rain occurred. The continued dryness and very hot temperatures resulted in the expansion of the D1-D2-D3 areas in Missouri and adjoining areas of Iowa, Nebraska, and Kansas, and the encroachment of D2 into the western Oklahoma panhandle where most farm ponds are completely dry with the rest down. USDA reported that nearly half (46%) of the corn and soybean crops in Kansas were rated in poor to very poor condition, with Missouri seeing a jump this week to 51% of the corn crops in this condition. Some streams and many ponds in northwest Missouri were dried up. A band of D3 was added to the Nebraska panhandle, where low water supplies resulted in the shutdown of irrigation, and to south central Kansas, where the Palmer Crop Moisture Index reached severely dry levels.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes to Northern Plains Region">
   <p>Much of the Great Lakes to northern Great Plains region received no rainfall during this Drought Monitor period. Temperatures persistently in the 90s and 100s combined with the bone dry weather to result in significant expansion of D0A and D0AH. D0 was expanded into areas of north central Illinois which were experiencing growing crop stress. The D1 areas in southern Minnesota and southwest Wisconsin were combined and expanded, and the D1 and D2 boundaries in central South Dakota were edged eastward.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>It was dry over Maine during this Drought Monitor period, with only a few tenths of an inch of rain reported. The rainfall of the past few weeks has done little to replenish the long-term deficits ... the statewide precipitation rank for August 2002-July 2003 was seventh driest out of the last 109 years. The D0H area was left intact to reflect long-term dryness and state reports of low ground water levels.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Scattered showers and thunderstorms brought 1 to 2 inch rains to parts of Arizona, New Mexico, Nevada, Colorado, and Wyoming. The D2 and D3 were contracted in southern Arizona where the heavy rains were most widespread. However, conditions across the West generally were dry during the period. Nearly four dozen wildfires continued to burn across a large part of Montana and Idaho. Streams and reservoirs in parts of eastern Idaho are the lowest they have been since the 1930s, with some basins showing the lowest 3-year average flows on record. D2 and D3 were expanded in western Idaho, D4 expanded in eastern Idaho, and the H line over Montana and Wyoming was expanded into Idaho, to reflect these conditions.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Candace Tankersley</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Heim</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
