<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20030306</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>The forecast for March 5 - 10 calls for heavy precipitation (above 0.75 inch) in the D0H and D1H areas of both New England and the Southeast, with 1.5 to 3.5 inches anticipated in eastern South Carolina and southern Georgia. Farther west, totals should exceed 0.5 inch in most of Washington, the Oregon Cascades, northeastern Oregon, northern and central Idaho, central and western Montana, and northwestern Wyoming, with very heavy precipitation (3 to locally 7 inches) anticipated in orographically-favored parts of the Olympic Mountains, the western slopes of the Washington Cascades, and the eastern Idaho Panhandle. Meanwhile, light to moderage precipitation is expected in the northern Plains and northern Great Lakes region, and little or none is expected in other areas currently experiencing dryness or drought.</p>
   <p>The 6-10 day outlook (March 11 - 15) favors continued heavy precipitation along the northern half of the West Coast, in eastern Washington, over the northern Idaho Panhandle, and in extreme northwestern Montana. The odds also favor above-normal precipitation across the south-central and southeastern Great Lakes region. In contrast, below-normal precipitation appears more likely in the Southeast, the Plains, most of the Rockies, the Southwest, the central and eastern Great Basin, and southeastern Idaho.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Less than 0.5 inch of precipitation fell on the D0 area introduced in western Alaska last week, leaving the D0 conditions intact.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Hawaii">
   <p>Dryness returned to much of Hawaii this week, with most locations reporting 0.5 inch of precipitation or less. Scattered higher totals were measured on parts of Kauai, northern and eastern Oahu, southeastern Maui, and parts of the Big Island, but weekly totals above 1.5 inches were relegated to east-central and northeastern portions of the Big Island, where normals are higher than in most other parts of the state. As a result, drought classifications were unchanged from last week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Scattered moderate precipitation (locally approaching 1 inch) fell on most of Maine, Vermont, and New Hampshire last week. Accumulated precipitation deficits now exceed an inch for the last 90 days across much of Maine and the northern and central sections of New Hampshire and Vermont. Furthermore, 24-month totals are 5 to 7 inches below normal in northern sections of the latter 2 states, and 10 to 15 inches below normal across most of Maine away from the immediate Atlantic coast. A colder-than-normal winter has helped the situation, allowing fallen snow to remain in place than would normally be expected, but continued long-term precipitation deficits led to the introduction of D0H into the northern halves of Vermont and New Hampshire, and into lower Maine, while D1H was expanded to cover most of northern and west-central Maine.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Another relatively dry week, featuring rainfall totals below 0.5 inch through southwestern, central, and northern parts of the region, allowed 4-week precipitation totals to decline to 33% to 50% of normal. In addition, 8-week totals were generally between 45% and 75% of normal, which is reflected by markedly below-normal streamflows at several sites. These facts led to the expansion of D0AH into central and north-central parts of Puerto Rico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>The 7-day period ending Tuesday morning featured little or no precipitation throughout the areas of dryness and drought from the Plains eastward through the Mississippi Valley and Great Lakes region, with totals exceeding one-quarter inch restricted to scattered sites across eastern Kansas, central and southwestern Missouri, Michigan's Upper Peninsula, northern Wisconsin, southernmost South Dakota, northernmost Nebraska, and southeastern sections of both Wyoming and Colorado.</p>
   <p>As a result, dryness and drought categorizations generally remained intact, but a few areas deteriorated which were near category cusps last week. D4AH expanded eastward from Wyoming into northern parts of the Nebraska Panhandle, where less than 40% of normal precipitation has fallen since October 2002.</p>
   <p>D3AH expanded into southeastern Nebraska, and D1AH to D2AH conditions also expanded in areas adjacent to the new D3AH region. Farther north, D1AH conditions enveloped southeastern North Dakota and northwestern Minnesota, and both D0AH and D1AH expanded northward in eastern Montana.</p>
   <p>December 2002 - February 2003 was the driest winter in 108 years of record for the state of Michigan, and the second driest such period for Minnesota and Wisconsin. In addition, smaller areas of record winter dryness were identified in northwestern Illinois, east-central Iowa, north-central Wisconsin, and north-central Minnesota. In the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan and in northwestern Illinois, the 6 months through February 2003 were the driest such period in 108 years of record, as were the last 12 full months in southwestern Nebraska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Far West">
   <p>Heavy precipitation fell on the Southwest and, to a lesser extent, parts of the central Rockies for the second time in three weeks. At least an inch of precipitation fell on central and east-central Arizona, across southwestern Utah and adjacent locales, and in southwestern Colorado and adjacent areas. Amounts of 3 to locally over 6 inches were reported in some of the higher elevations of central Arizona.</p>
   <p>Most other parts of the region recorded 0.3 to 1.0 inch with isolated heavier amounts, but totals below one-quarter inch were reported in the northern and western Great Basin, southern and far northern Idaho, central and eastern Washington, central and southeastern Oregon, central and southwestern sections of both Montana and Wyoming, and the southern Rockies.</p>
   <p>The heavy precipitation in the Southwest led to 1-category improvements in drought classification for a broad section of central and eastern Arizona, southern Nevada, and part of southern California. Farther north, however, the week's precipitation didn't substantially improve conditions, and deterioration occurred in some areas that missed most of the precipitation. D3H expanded into parts of northwestern Nevada and southeastern Oregon, with adjacent D2H areas stretching a bit farther west than last week. Mountainous parts of these areas continued to report snowpack water content near or slightly below half of normal for early March. Farther north, D2H and D3H expanded northward along the Front Range of the Rockies in Montana, where long-term moisture shortages have been exacerbated by a water year (beginning October 2002) featuring only 60% to 80% of normal precipitation to date.</p>
   <p>The 1-year period extending through February 2003 was the third driest such period in 108 years of records for the state of Colorado despite that fact that wetter than normal conditions were observed for the last half of this period, according to preliminary statistics from the National Climatic Data Center. Elsewhere, this was the seventh driest such period in 108 years for Nevada, and the ninth driest for both Oregon and Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Moderate to heavy precipitation fell on much of the D0H area in southern Georgia and the Carolinas, with amounts generally ranging from 1 to 3 inches in central North Carolina, 0.5 to 2.0 inches in South Carolina, and 1.5 to locally 6.0 inches in southern Georgia. However, despite the abundant rainfall, which even led to localized flooding, groundwater levels at many locations have climbed only modestly above the record lows that were in place before the year 2000, and 60-month precipitation remains below the 5 percentile threshold for most of the region. Therefore, the D0H area went unaltered this week.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
