<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040408</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather developments that may have an impact on dry or drought areas in the next 2 weeks include: 1) a change in the weather pattern that should offer relief to dry areas in the Southeast, with a series of lows during April 8-13 bringing widespread rain to the region, with amounts ranging from 1 to 2 inches and higher; 2) more rain for Colorado and New Mexico on Thursday-Sunday, April 8-11, amounts generally ranging from 0.5 to 1.0 inches or more; 3) above-normal precipitation for the northern Plains, northern Rockies, and Great Basin during April 15-21, with below-normal temperatures.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Although above-normal precipitation ranging from 0.05 to 0.25 inches fell over the areas of abnormal dryness (D0), there was no significant change to the depiction, as deficits dating back to last autumn continued.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northeast">
   <p>Heavy rain or snow ended D0 dryness in New England and upstate New York. Much of New England saw 2 to 3 inches of precipitation on April 1-5.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Upper Midwest">
   <p>Negligible precipitation this period resulted in no change to the D0 to D2 drought depiction in the upper Midwest and the D2 to D3 depiction in western and central Nebraska and western Kansas. In contrast, the same slow-moving storm system that affected the Southwestern states dropped 1 to 3 inches of rain on western Texas, ending D0 dryness on the Plains. The Trans-Pecos region of Texas also saw a general 1-category improvement. Dry weather led to slight expansion of the D0 area in southeastern Oklahoma and into northern Arkansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South">
   <p>Abnormal dryness (D0) persisted across the Southeast, as rainfall amounts this past week ranged from 0 to around 0.5 inches. Continuing short-term dryness led to D0 expansion northward and eastward in North Carolina and westward in Louisiana and southern Mississippi and northward into central Alabama. Persistent short-term dryness led to a new area of D0 in southeastern Florida centered in Broward County.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Heavy rain and high elevation snows extended from Arizona into New Mexico during April 2-5. Precipitation amounts of 1 to 2 inches were common, with some locations reporting 3 inches or more. Heaviest amounts covered portions of central and eastern New Mexico, where this was one of the most significant precipitation events in recent years. Albuquerque set a 24-hour precipitation record with 2.29 inches on April 3-4, eclipsing a record dating back to 1893. The rain and snow had its greatest impact in New Mexico, removing the D4 areas and generally improving drought status by one category, with a 2-category improvement in parts of the east. Much of the state remained at some level of drought because of continued long-term precipitation deficits as high as 20 inches. D3 drought extended across southwestern and south-central New Mexico and remained over northern Arizona and much of central Arizona. D2 drought covered much of central New Mexico and parts of central Arizona. Conditions improved to D0 in far eastern New Mexico except in the northeast. Long-term deficits remained near D4 levels of severity in parts of New Mexico and Arizona, including near Los Alamos, New Mexico, where the 3-year precipitation deficit exceeded 20 inches, but these areas were not large enough to depict on the national Drought Monitor map. Totals exceeding 2 inches in parts of central Arizona caused the D3 and D2 areas to recede northward due to short-term moisture improvements, but the rainfall did little to ease water shortage concerns. Roosevelt Lake, east of Phoenix, for example, was only 35 percent full as of April 7. One to two-inch totals caused some retreat of the D1 in southwestern Colorado. The general totals of 0.5 to 1 inch over the state eased the wildfire threat, although the impact on long-term drought was minor. Severe to extreme drought persisted over the Colorado plains, where the winter wheat crop was rated at 61 percent poor to very poor. Rain or snow amounts tended to be light farther north in the Great Basin and northern Rockies, resulting in little change to the drought depiction, and even some slight expansion of drought in Idaho and Utah.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
