<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060119</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>For the next 5-day period (January 18-23): 1) The main long-wave features continue to be a trough settled in over the West and Plains and ridging over the Southeast. Temperatures will remain well above normal for the eastern two-thirds of the United States. The Mid-Atlantic region is showing the most significant positive temperature anomalies. 2) The Pacific Northwest continues to be the part of the country with the most active weather pattern. A series of systems will continue the wet pattern observed in this region for the last month. 3) In the South and Southeast, there is a chance that the precipitation pattern will remain active. Good rains are expected over much of the Gulf Coast states.</p>
   <p>In the extended period, 6-10 days out (January 24-28): 1) Zonal flow will dominate the weather pattern over the United States. Models are showing a low-amplitude trough centered over the west/central portion of the country. 2) Temperatures are looking to be well above normal, centered over the Great Lakes region . The entire eastern half of the United States is showing a fairly good chance of observing temperatures above normal. In the Southeast and Alaska, temperatures are forecast to be below normal during this same time frame. 3) The precipitation pattern over the central United States should continue to be dry along with the northern third of Alaska and the southern tip of Florida. Areas that are showing a better chance of receiving above-normal precipitation are the Pacific Northwest and the southern tip of Alaska as well as in the South up through the Mid-Atlantic states.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>Persistent dry weather across parts of Alaska has led to expansion of D0 to the west and south because of below-average snowpack and only 50-70% of their normal precipitation since October 1, 2005.</p>
   <p>Modest precipitation across parts of the Big Island this week is helping to somewhat alleviate dry conditions, but the D0 remains in place. Conditions remain unchanged this week across the rest of Hawaii, with a drier pattern continuing.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Lower Mississippi Valley and Southeast">
   <p>Heavy rains late in the period have led to a slight improvement of D0 and D1 across extreme western Tennessee, eastern Arkansas, northern Mississippi, and north central Louisiana. These rains missed out on southern Louisiana and southern Mississippi, which has allowed D1 to move back into the New Orleans area and eastward toward the Alabama border.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Seasonality issues and long-term indicators have overcome any recent gains in northern Illinois, where D3 has pushed east, once again gaining a foothold all the way to Lake Michigan and the Chicago area. Precipitation values at 30-, 60-, and 90-day time frames are all below normal, in contrast to a few sites that have benefited from modest wetness over the past two weeks. Precipitation rankings for the12-month period show values in the 1 st and 5 th percentiles for climate divisions in northern Illinois.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southwest">
   <p>Yet another dry week has led to more expansion of drought in Arizona and New Mexico. The D2 has expanded eastward out of Arizona and into southwestern New Mexico. This region continues to see low streamflows, very little precipitation (and little snowpack), and warm weather. Most of this region is below 50% of normal for precipitation since October 1. In fact, most of central Arizona is below 25% for the water year, with some areas around Phoenix coming in at around 5% of normal over this time period (-2.75). According to the NWS, they havent seen any precipitation since October 18 (91 days and counting) in Phoenix (at the airport), which is currently the 7 th driest such streak on record (going back to 1895).</p>
   <p>Northern New Mexico and southern Colorado continue to miss out on the wet stuff as well. Mountain snowpacks in many basins are running below 50% of normal, with many locations at, or near, record lows with regard to snow water equivalent in north central New Mexico and extreme south central Colorado. As a result, D1 has expanded in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Northwest and Northern Rockies">
   <p>The favorable storm pattern continued last week across this region, resulting in more improvement and pushing D0 to the south in the northern Idaho Panhandle and extreme northwestern Montana. The D0 also continues to recede to the east in central Washington. Precipitation totals in this region over the past month are running more than 200% of normal.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>Abnormally warm weather over the past 30 days, coupled with high winds, has led to a substantial drying out in the central Plains, encompassing Nebraska and Kansas. North Platte, NE, has seen only 1.81 of precipitation (46% of normal) since September 1, 2005. Many locations are running at 50-70% of normal since October 1, 2005. This has led to a slight expansion of D1, which joins up with Iowa. A slight expansion of D0 is noted this week in northeastern Nebraska. A movement of the impacts line to the west marks a westward push of AH conditions due to the recent warm and dry conditions. A large fire (approximately 5,600 acres) broke out in central Nebraska near Halsey at the Nebraska National Forest, the first major wildfire outbreak since March 1999, when 72,000 acres burned in the same region.</p>
   <p>Farther south, the D0 in Texas has also expanded to cover all of the western region of the state. In the north central region, D4 has continued its slow expansion to the west and south. Towards the Gulf Coast, D0 has pushed all the way to the Gulf Coast around Houston as recent dryness and long-term deficits overtake the rains they saw during the tropical season.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Brian Fuchs</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
