<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20081224</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <intro>
   <p>Three storm systems affected the western United States during the last 7 days, dropping widespread moderate to heavy precipitation on much of the country's dry areas from the Rockies westward to the Pacific Coast. Remnants from 2 of these systems re-strengthened as they tracked through the central and eastern states, dropping moderate precipitation on parts of the dry regions in the Southeast, Ohio Valley, and upper Midwest as well. However, substantial precipitation evaded most of the Plains, Florida, Alaska, and Hawaii.</p>
  </intro>
  <forecast>
   <p>More moderate to heavy precipitation is expected across the dry area in the interior eastern United States, where 1.5 to 3.5 inches of precipitation are forecast during December 24 - 28, 2008. Moderate amounts are expected to the south and east of the Appalachians, and across southeastern Louisiana. Totals are forecast to be much lower farther east and south, with only a few tenths of an inch expected in northeastern North Carolina, and little or none along the Florida Peninsula. Moderate to heavy precipitation (0.5 to 2.0 inches) is also forecast for central and eastern sections of the dry area in and near the Great Lakes region, with lesser amounts expected in eastern Minnesota, northwestern Wisconsin, and the Upper Peninsula of Michigan. The dry areas in the Plains from Texas to North Dakota and Montana are expected to remain dry, with amounts exceeding 0.5 inch restricted to eastern Oklahoma. Farther west, more beneficial precipitation is anticipated from the Rockies westward to the Pacific Ocean, with amounts below 0.25 inch restricted to the deserts. More than an inch is expected in coastal areas and typically-wetter higher elevations, with 2 to 6 inches predicted in central Arizona, the mountains of southwestern California, the Sierra Nevada, the southern Cascades, and northwestern California. Around the cusp of the new year (December 29, 2008 through January 2, 2009), odds favor above-normal precipitation in the Great Lakes region, the northern Plains, and the western states from northwestern Colorado northward through Montana and westward to the central California coast. Meanwhile, drier than normal conditions are favored in the Southwest, the southern Rockies, the central and southern Plains, peninsular Florida, and the southern half of the D0 area in northwestern Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Precipitation totals were relatively low across Hawaii in the wake of last week's heavy rainfall and flooding, but former D0 to D1 conditions improved in Kauai and Oahu as drought impacts continued to ease. Little or no precipitation was again observed in northwestern Alaska, where D0 conditions persisted.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Moderate to locally heavy precipitation fell on all but the west-central and southernmost sections of the dry region extending from the Ohio Valley southward into Alabama and Georgia, on central and southern portions of the dry region in the Great Lakes states and upper Midwest, and across northeastern North Carolina. The largest amounts (2 to 4 inches) were recorded across southwestern Pennsylvania and at scattered locations in eastern Tennessee and the northern reaches of Georgia and Alabama. As a result, abnormal dryness (D0) was pulled out of southwestern Pennsylvania and adjacent sections of Ohio and West Virginia, where 60-day precipitation totals climbed above normal. In addition, D3 and D4 conditions were reduced in part of northern Georgia, and both D0 and D1 conditions were trimmed back in parts of the Upper Peninsula of Michigan, where lake-effect snowfall has been abundant for the past several weeks. Meanwhile, little or no precipitation fell on the Florida Peninsula, southeastern Louisiana, and northern Wisconsin, where D0 to D1 conditions remained unchanged. These regions received less than half of normal precipitation during the last 2 months.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains">
   <p>It was a dry week for the already-dry areas in the Plains. Precipitation totaled between one-quarter and one-half of an inch in south-central North Dakota, but elsewhere, only scattered locations in south-central Montana, southeastern Wyoming, and the eastern sections of Colorado, Oklahoma, and Texas recorded over 0.1 inch. Dryness and drought classifications remained unchanged in most areas, although D0 expanded to cover most of Oklahoma and more of northeastern Texas, including the greater Dallas and Fort Worth metropolitan area. For the last 60 days, only 5 to 25 percent of normal precipitation fell on most of the dry region across Oklahoma and Texas, and amounts ranged from 4 to 8 inches below normal across the eastern tier of this area.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Significant precipitation fell on a large proportion of the dry area covering much of the United States from the Rockies westward. Totals ranged from 2 to locally 8 inches across western Oregon, northwestern and southwestern California, the Sierra Nevada, central Arizona, and a few small areas in northwestern Arizona, southwestern and north-central Utah, western Colorado, central and southeastern Idaho, and western Wyoming. Amounts below 0.25 inch were restricted to central Washington, parts of southeastern Oregon and southwestern Idaho, all but northwesternmost Montana, most of Wyoming, northwestern Colorado, western and northeastern Utah, most of Nevada, part of the California valleys and the northern desert region, northeastern Arizona, and northwestern New Mexico. The abundant precipitation led to improvements in the assessed drought severity across north-central and far northeastern California (D3 to D2), southern California to the east and south of Los Angeles (D2 to D1), east-central sections of the California desert (D1 to D0), and a small part of central Idaho (D1 to D0). In addition, D0 conditions were removed from southwestern Washington, all but the southern tier of western Oregon, and west-central Arizona. However, despite the wet week, precipitation totals for the calendar year remained under half of normal across most of Nevada, adjacent sections of northeastern California and southern Oregon, central Washington and adjacent northern Oregon, and scattered smaller areas.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
