<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040311</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Light to moderate precipitation is expected through most current areas of dryness and drought during March 11 - 15, 2004, with totals expected to range from 0.1 to 0.5 inch. A few areas should get somewhat larger amounts, specifically part of east-central New York (0.50 to 0.75 inch), northern portions of the D0 area along the Texas Gulf coast (0.5 to 1.0 inch), central and eastern portions of the Big Bend (0.5 to 1.0 inch), southeastern Oklahoma and adjacent Texas (0.75 to 1.25 inches), northwestern Missouri (0.5 to 1.0 inch), and a swath covering southeastern North Dakota, northern Minnesota, and western Wisconsin (0.5 to 1.0 inch). In contrast, little or no precipitation is forecast for the Great Basin, the west-central Rockies, and the western half of Arizona. Above-normal temperatures are forecast for this period in New England and from the Front Range to the West Coast, with significantly cooler-than-normal conditions restricted to western Texas and eastern New Mexico.</p>
   <p>The ensuing 5 days (March 16 - 20) are expected to be wetter than normal in the Pacific Northwest, northern Intermountain West, northern Plains, upper Mississippi Valley, western Great Lakes region, and New England while the odds favor drier-than-normal conditions through the southwestern half of Texas, the southern Rockies, the desert Southwest, and central and western portions of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Less than 0.5 inch of precipitation fell on the D0 region in Alaska. However, a re-assessment of conditions based on global soil moisture models and percent of normal mountain snowpack led to some reduction in the extent of abnormal dryness. Very little precipitation has fallen on some parts of the area since the beginning of December 2003. During this period, only 0.02 to 0.80 inch of precipitation was measured at Unalakleet, Tanana, and Bettles, AK, which represents only 2% to 25% of normal for the period.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="New England">
   <p>Less than 0.5 inch of precipitation fell last week, perpetuating a pattern of consistently below-normal precipitation dating back at least to the beginning of the calendar year. Since January 1, 2004, both Boston, MA and Portland, ME have received 5 to 6 inches less than normal precipitation, or about one-third of normal. Farther west, Utica, NY has measured 40% of normal, or about 4.5 inches less than is typical. As a result, D0AH conditions were introduced in a significant portion of New England including southern Maine, the central and southern sections of New Hampshire and Vermont, adjacent New York, and much of central and northern Massachusetts. Subtle but consistent dryness has affected the northern portions of this region for a long time, with Portland, ME recording almost 16 inches less than normal precipitation since the beginning of 2002.</p>
   <p>For the time being, snow cover and melting snow are providing moisture for the soil, masking potential impacts from the recent precipitation deficits. However, if drier-than-normal conditions continue once the snowpack is depleted, soil moisture content would decline rapidly, possibly affecting the beginning of the growing season, which is still about 2 months away.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Upper Mississippi Valley, and Western Great Lakes">
   <p>Moderate to heavy precipitation doused the eastern tier of the areas affected by dryness and drought, with weekly totals of an inch or more fairly widespread from the Texas Panhandle northeastward through the western Great Lakes region. The heaviest precipitation was observed in last weeks D0 areas in central Kansas and southwestern Oklahoma, where 3 to locally 5 inches were reported.</p>
   <p>The precipitation brought an end to abnormal dryness across most of southern Oklahoma, the southeastern Texas Panhandle, most of central and northeastern Kansas, southeastern Nebraska, much of Iowa, and central Wisconsin. Just west of these areas, former D1 to D2 conditions improved by 1 category in a swath from the central Texas Panhandle northeastward through southeastern Minnesota and west-central Wisconsin. Unfortunately, only small parts of last weeks D3 areas improved. Specifically, D2 now covers the central Oklahoma Panhandle, small sections of adjacent Texas and Kansas, and interior northwestern Missouri.</p>
   <p>In the latter region, a small-scale but serious drought has been entrenched for at least a couple of years. Recently, soils and smaller bodies of water have been replenished from time to time, as they were by last weeks 1 to 2 inches of precipitation which instigated the 1-category improvement depicted in this weeks Drought Monitor. However, long-term precipitation totals remain far below normal, and serious hydrologic impacts continue to affect the region. The Missouri Drought Assessment Committee has maintained the region in conservation phase which is the most severe classification in their 3-tiered system. Since the beginning of 2002, both St. Joseph, MO and Kansas City, MO are more than 20 inches below normal, which corresponds to just over 70% of normal precipitation for the &gt;2-year period.</p>
   <p>Across the northern Great Plains and most of the High Plains, light to locally moderate precipitation fell on the southern half of the region while little or none was observed farther north. As a result, D0 to D3 conditions remained unchanged in most of these regions, though some deterioration was identified in central Nebraska (to D2), southeastern North Dakota (to D1), and northeastern Minnesota (to D1).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Interior West">
   <p>Scattered areas, primarily in the higher elevations, reported more than an inch of precipitation for the week, but only a few areas could claim any tangible improvement as a result. The heaviest totals were observed in the higher elevations of central Arizona, where 2 to 3 inches of precipitation fell. This moisture brought improvement to D0 into a small area in central Arizona, but most of the state received only light precipitation, resulting in drought persistence or intensification. This week, D1 conditions overspread southwestern Arizona, and D3 expanded into central parts of the state just north of the higher elevations that received relatively heavy precipitation. The Salt River Project, which manages water supplies for much of the Phoenix, AZ area, has decided to maintain the 33% water allocation   reduction, initially implemented at the beginning of 2003, to the end of 2004. This marks only the second time that allocation reductions continued through two full years since the Salt River Project was initiated in 1902. Currently, the Salt and Verde reservoir systems are holding only about 42% of capacity.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere, isolated areas of improvement were assessed in small parts of southwestern Montana (to D3), east-central Idaho (to D2), and south-central Colorado (to D2) while a drop to D2 conditions was noted in a small section of southern Wyoming near the Colorado border. Drought Conditions remained unchanged elsewhere.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Richard Tinker</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NWS, NCEP, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
