<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050203</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 5 days (February 3-7), only light precipitation will fall across the West, primarily late in the period across the Great Basin, the Rockies, and the Pacific Northwest. Meanwhile, a surge of sharply colder air will arrive across the northern Plains and the Northwest during the weekend (February 5-6), preceded and accompanied by snow showers. Cold air will overspread the remainder of the Plains and West early next week. Farther east, a slow-moving storm system will drift across the Southeast on February 3-4, producing locally heavy rain showers in the southern Atlantic region and significant snow and ice accumulations in the piedmont region of western North Carolina and southwestern Virginia. Dry weather will return to the Southeast following the storms passage. The NWS 6- to 10-day outlook for February 8-12 calls for above-normal temperatures across the eastern half of the U.S., while colder-than-normal weather will prevail in much of the West. Above-normal precipitation is likely in the Four Corners region and from the central and southern Plains eastward to the Appalachians, while drier-than-normal conditions will be confined to northern California, the Northwest, and the southern Atlantic region.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>Mild, mostly dry weather prevailed across the northern Plains and upper Midwest, resulting in little or no change to the depiction of dryness (D0) and moderate to exceptional drought (D1 to D4). There was a slight expansion of severe drought (D2) on the Montana High Plains, where exceptionally warm, windy weather during the second half of January eliminated winter wheats protective snow cover and reduced soil moisture reserves. Cut Bank, MT, which typically receives 12.51 inches of precipitation annually, netted just 7.65 inches (61 percent of normal) during 2004. Interestingly, it was Cut Banks second-wettest year among the last five (2000-04), exceeded only by the 2002 total of 12.16 inches that was skewed by a very wet June (4.85 inches). In January 2005, Cut Bank endured a temperature swing of 97F (from -35F on January 15 to 62F on January 23), wind gusts to 35 m.p.h. or higher on nine consecutive days (January 16-24), and a peak gust to 67 m.p.h. (on January 17). In addition, Cut Banks January precipitation totaled just 0.02 inch (5 percent of normal).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast">
   <p>Rain, freezing rain, sleet, and snow affected the southern Atlantic States on January 29-30. However, only light rain showers fell in southern Florida, where abnormal dryness (D0) expanded slightly to cover the remainder of the peninsula south of Lake Okeechobee. January rainfall totals in southern Florida were as low as 0.25 inch (9 percent of normal) on Marathon Key and 0.45 inch (20 percent) in Ft. Myers. South Floridas fire danger, represented by the Keetch-Byram Drought Index (KBDI), remained high in late January, according to the Florida Division of Forestry, averaging greater than 500 (on a scale of 0 to 800) in Martin, Palm Beach, Broward, Collier, and Lee Counties. KBDI values locally higher than 650 were noted in Palm Beach, Broward, and Collier Counties. High values of the KBDI are an indication that conditions are favorable for the occurrence and spread of wildfires.</p>
   <p>Farther north along the southern Atlantic Coast, late-January storminess slightly dented precipitation deficits. Nevertheless, January rainfall was less than 30 percent of normal in locations such as Wilmington, North Carolina (1.32 inches), and North Myrtle Beach, South Carolina (0.78 inch). This section of the Atlantic Coast as far north as the Carolinas will continue to be monitored for possible introduction of abnormal dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Moderate drought (D1) was introduced across the interior Northwest, stretching from the eastern slopes of the Cascades across northern Oregon, eastern Washington, and northern Idaho. Severe drought (D2) expanded slightly in the Bitterroot Range and adjacent areas in western Montana. In the Northwest, record warmth continued to reduce snow packs, while generally dry weather allowed season-to-date precipitation totals to fall farther behind normal. From October 2004 - January 2005, river basin-average precipitation ranged from 54 to 87 percent of normal in the Northwest, including Washington, Oregon, Montana, northern and central Idaho, and northern Wyoming. In those areas, the water equivalent of the high-elevation snow pack was substantially lower due to some of the precipitation falling as rain and recent melting of snow. On February 2, snow-water equivalents ranged from just 12 to 32 percent of average in the Cascades of Washington and northern Oregon.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere in the West, a re-analysis of earlier precipitation led to a slight reduction in coverage of severe to extreme drought (D2 to D3) in southeastern Oregon and northwestern Nevada. Meanwhile, more wet weather (1 to 2 inches of liquid equivalent) in southern Nevada, southwestern Utah, and northwestern Arizona led to some further erosion of abnormal dryness (D0) and moderate drought (D1).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Brad Rippey</name>
   <affiliation>U.S. Department of Agriculture</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
