<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20061122</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>From November 24 to November 28, precipitation is expected to occur mainly in the Northwest and along the mid-Atlantic coast.  The remainder of the country should stay mostly dry with a slight chance of precipitation in the middle of the country near the end of the period.  Maximum temperatures are expected to be above average in the eastern two-thirds of the country, and below average in the western third.  Minimum temperatures are expected to be above average throughout most of the country except for Montana and the Dakotas, where they are expected to be below average.</p>
   <p>From November 29 to December 3, precipitation is expected to be above average in the Northwest, Northern Plains, Great Lakes region, Northeast, and mid-Atlantic region.  Below-average precipitation is expected in the Central and Southern Plains.  Temperatures are expected to be above average from Arizona northeastward into New England.  Below-average temperatures are expected in Alaska, the Northwest, and Montana.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Summary">
   <p>Recent precipitation in the Southeast led to a reduction in areas of dryness.  The D1 along the Florida western coast was reduced in area.  Improvements in Montana from recent precipitation are reflected in this weeks map.  In Oklahoma, D4 was introduced, and D3 expanded, in the northern area of drought in response to continued dryness and poor agricultural conditions.  In Texas the two areas of D3 were expanded.  The northern area was extended northward into the Red River Basin, and the southern area was extended eastward.  D0 was introduced into the Central Valley of California; it is very early in the wet season, but this area is abnormally dry.</p>
   <p>Although the drought intensities were not changed or introduced on this weeks map, areas that are being closely monitored for changes include southern California, where dryness is increasing; Minnesota, where dryness is increasing in the southern part of the state; and in the Texas Panhandle, where precipitation events have been very localized.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Ned Guttman</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
   <name>Liz Love-Brotak</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, NESDIS, NCEI</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
