<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041014</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) the slow-moving upper low in the Ohio Valley has brought beneficial showers to this region October 12-13; 2) a clipper-like system will pass through the Great Lakes region October 15-16, bringing the potential for light snow accumulations as well as perhaps the first lake-effect snow event, with the highest accumulations possible in the higher elevations of Michigans Upper Peninsula; 3) a system coming out of the Plains October 16-17 could bring potentially heavy rains to the Ohio and mid-Mississippi Valleys October 17-18; 4) a broad trough will dominate most of the nation October 19-23, with below-normal temperatures in the western United States and above-normal temperatures in the eastern U.S.; and 5) precipitation is likely to be above normal for the northern-tier states with this pattern October 19-23, with below-normal precipitation in the Southwest.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Moderate drought (D1) continues on the island of Hawaii and abnormal dryness (D0) continues on Maui, but no changes were made to these areas for the week. Also, no changes were made to the long-term dryness across part of Alaska.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Central States">
   <p>What a difference a week makes! A slow-moving storm system combined with Tropical Storm Matthew to produce heavy precipitation across the Lower Mississippi Valley this past week. Weekly rainfall totals averaged more than 6 inches statewide in Louisiana, and totals greater than 6 inches were also common across north-central, central, and southeastern Arkansas. In northeast Arkansas, Jonesboro received a daily record 1.57 inches of rain on October 11, but still remains at only 57 percent of normal since September 1. As a result, D0 has been removed from all of Louisiana and western Mississippi, and most of Arkansas and eastern Oklahoma. Heavier rains also moved through south-central Missouri and southeast Kansas, reducing the D1 and D0 conditions there as well. Pockets of moderate drought (D1) remain in southwest and southeast Missouri in the areas that did not receive as much precipitation during the week. Northern areas of this region, stretching into southern Illinois and Indiana, did not receive much rainfall for the week, and D0 conditions remained unchanged. This was also true of the D0 area stretching from western Iowa into eastern Kansas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Great Lakes and Great Plains">
   <p>Some rains fell during the past week across the abnormally dry (D0) and moderate drought (D1) areas in Michigan and Wisconsin, but not enough for the current situation to improve. In fact, areas to the northwest and southeast remained dry, and the streamflow levels have fallen in these areas. As a result, moderate drought (D1) was expanded across eastern Michigan and D0 was expanded slightly across both the western Upper Peninsula and in southeastern Michigan. Most of the drought and dryness regions across the Plains remained dry during the past week, and no changes were made in these areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Most of the western United States was dry this past week, with above-normal temperature departures. The exception to this was in New Mexico. Significant rain, and hail, moved through the central portions of the state. As a result, drought conditions have improved to the moderate drought (D1) category in this region. There was also improvement from D3 to D2 in the states far west-central section. Meanwhile, an evaluation of conditions and long-term precipitation totals revealed that the northwest part of New Mexico continues to struggle with drought conditions, and extreme drought (D3) was expanded across this region. In Idaho, a similar evaluation of the water year revealed that the Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) values for the Big Lost, Little Lost, and Bear River Basins were -4.0 each. The exceptional drought (D4) area was expanded to cover both the Big and Little Lost River Basins. No other changes were made in the West.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
