<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040205</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Conditions expected over the next 2 weeks that could influence ongoing dry areas include: 1) the central Plains and Midwest are bracing for yet another major winter storm that is slowly churning out of the southern Rockies and into the Plains (2/4-5) bringing with it the potential for 6-10 inches of snow to areas of Kansas, Nebraska and Iowa. The third major storm in as many weeks has left many locations in the region approaching snow depth records; 2) after the storm passes and moves up and out of the Midwest and into the Northeast, high pressure should dominate over the next 5 days (2/5-10) and another surge of Arctic air, coupled with the snow pack, will serve to keep temperatures bitterly cold. The push of cold air is expected to reach as far south as Texas, Louisiana and Mississippi where temperatures will be 8-12 degrees (or more) below-normal; 3) in the 6-10 day period (2/10-14) and 8-14 day period (2/12-18), precipitation is expected to be below-normal for virtually all of the northern half of the country. One area that could benefit from the current storm and other systems over the next two weeks is southern Oklahoma, northeastern Texas, Arkansas and Louisiana where above-normal precipitation is expected over this time frame.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska and Hawaii">
   <p>There are no new changes to report for Alaska or Hawaii this week.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes Region">
   <p>A second major winter storm in as many weeks tracked over a nearly identical path blanketing parts of eastern Nebraska, Iowa, northeastern Kansas and northwestern Missouri with 6-10 inches (or more) of snow. The storm then pushed into the Great Lakes region dumping over a foot of snow in parts of southeastern Minnesota and western Wisconsin where liquid equivalents generally measured out at between .75 to 1.0 inch, or more, in most locales. For the most part, the snow fell right where it was needed resulting in a one category improvement along its path from northwest Missouri up into Minnesota and Wisconsin where extreme drought (D3) has been eliminated. Long-term deficits and the timing of the year preclude any further improvement at this time as severe drought (D2) remains in these parts. These good snows will need to be followed up by ample spring rains to put a major dent in the ongoing drought.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Southwest, and Far West">
   <p>All in all, it was a quiet week for most of the drought affected areas in the West. Yet again, northern and western Idaho continued to benefit from good precipitation. For the first time in a long time there, totals are above-average for both the water year (Oct. 1-to-date) and the past 12 months. While no major changes have occurred here, the gradient is tight between the improvement seen in western Idaho and the persistent long-term drought seen in the eastern and southern regions of the state. In recent weeks, slight improvement has been noted in Idaho with a gradual pushing of moderate hydrological drought (D1 H) to the east and south. While many basins have increased their snow water equivalent measures, they have just stayed at, or a little above, normal as the peak season for snow pack begins to approach.</p>
   <p>To the south in Arizona, water deliveries will be cut again for the second consecutive year by the Salt River Project (SRP). Last year was the first such year this was done in 50 years. The SRP anticipates delivering only two-thirds of its normal allotment. Due to other sources of water though, no immediate shortages or restrictions are anticipated for the metro Phoenix area. Changes in this weeks map reflect this by showing a movement of moderate (D1 H) and severe (D2 H) drought slightly southward into the south central regions of the state.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
