<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20040219</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) the long-wave pattern across North America favors a stormy pattern to develop across the southwestern United States into the central and southern Plains and continue through the period; 2) with the first storm system affecting the California coast and pushing inland around February 22; 3) meanwhile, a storm system will bring some snow to Colorado February 19, and then move across the central Plains and into the Great Lakes February 20-21; 4) a ridge will remain over Alaska during the period, keeping above-normal temperatures across the state; and 5) above-normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation are expected for the Pacific Northwest, northern Rockies, and northern Plains.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>Unlike the West, Alaska saw temperatures 13-23F above normal last week. Heavier precipitation fell across the Alaskan Panhandle, but relatively little precipitation was recorded elsewhere. Abnormally dry conditions still exist for much of the central part of the state. In Hawaii, the past week was generally dry, and abnormally dry conditions still exist on parts of Hawaii and Molokai.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Mississippi Valley, and Great Lakes">
   <p>The past week was much quieter for all states bordering the western Great Lakes and within the northern and central Plains. A strong storm system did bring blizzard conditions to eastern Montana and North Dakota February 10-11. Otherwise, very little snow fell in the abnormally dry or drought areas and the temperatures moderated considerably from the previous several weeks. For Omaha, NE, the just-ended cold wave (January 26-February 15) was the 9th coldest for that period in 134 years of data. For Lincoln, NE, the same period was also the 9th coldest in 118 years of data. The average high in Lincoln during these 21 days was 20.2F. In comparison, the average high for the same 21 days during 1987 was 53.3F.</p>
   <p>A couple of systems did move across the southern United States during the past week, clipping a few abnormally dry and drought areas in New Mexico, Texas, Oklahoma, and Arkansas. The heaviest precipitation, however, remained farther south. Only limited improvement was seen in northeast Texas and to the severe drought (D2) area east of Lubbock in western Texas. For Lubbock, February precipitation totals have only provided 0.12 inches thus far. Meanwhile, the winters dryness continues to deteriorate conditions across the Plains of western Oklahoma, western Kansas, and eastern Colorado. As a result, D1 and D2 conditions pushed slightly eastward across the Panhandle of Oklahoma and southwestern Kansas, and D1 conditions were expanded to cover all of the Plains in northeastern Colorado.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies, Southwest, and Far West">
   <p>Although it was a colder than normal week for most of the West, only New Mexico saw increases in some of its snow cover totals during the past week. A storm system brought one foot or more of snow to the mountain areas around Taos, with lesser amounts as the storm moved to the east. Unfortunately, western New Mexico missed the snowfall associated with this storm. Given the quietness of the past week in the West, no changes have been made to the drought classifications across this region.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
