<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20060511</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 5-day period (May 11 - May 15) that may affect areas of dryness or drought include: 1) a building ridge in the West could mean a quieter pattern is in store for those west of the Mississippi. On the other side, a deep trough in the Midwest and East moves the conveyer belt of moisture eastward out of the Plains and brings with it the potential for unsettled weather and good rains (the heaviest amounts expected in the Great Lakes and Northeast) across virtually all of the eastern United States, except for southern Florida, which could be left high and dry again; 2) as you would expect with this pattern, significantly warmer-than-normal temperatures are expected in the West (west of the Rockies) and below-normal temperatures are forecasted for the eastern half (points east of the Missouri River) of the country.</p>
   <p>The 6- to 10-day (May 16-20) outlook from the Climate Prediction Center calls for the likelihood of the following: 1) this period continues to show an amplification of the ridge building in the West and migrating a bit eastward to cover the central part of the country, leading to a greater likelihood of above-normal temperatures in the West and below-normal readings in the East; 2) precipitation is expected to be below normal across most of the West, northern and central Plains, and into the Midwest over this same time frame. Above-normal precipitation is more likely across much of the Eastern Seaboard (including Florida) and also in the Texas Panhandle region into extreme eastern New Mexico; 3) ridging in northwestern Canada should lead to conditions across most of Alaska being above normal in terms of temperature, with below-normal precipitation expected across the southern half of the state, including the Alexander Archipelago.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Alaska">
   <p>Another round of heavy rains in the Alexander Archipelago has led to more improvement there, resulting in more reduction of abnormally dry conditions found there. The persistent dry pattern in the north remains across eastern Alaska, where the D0 has expanded slightly north and east of last weeks depiction.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>Although parts of New England saw some light precipitation last week, most of the Northeast saw little or no precipitation in what has been a dry spring thus far. Year-to-date totals are beginning to lag behind as well. This has led to an expansion of abnormally dry (D0) conditions across more of the region. West Virginia, Maryland, Pennsylvania, and southern New York have all been placed under this D0 area. Totals on the year are generally running 50-75% of normal. The dryness is quite pronounced over the past 60 days, with 2 to 6 inch deficits having accrued (25-50% of normal). New Jersey officials just declared a drought watch this week, citing dry spring conditions that have led to falling stream and ground water levels, particularly in the north.</p>
   <p>Farther south in the Mid-Atlantic region, some decent rains fell across the coastal plains of the Carolinas (2 to 4 inches or more), resulting in a modest retreat of the D0 and D1 on its eastern edge. However, longer-term deficits (25-50% of normal since January 1) are common in these same areas; moving inland, streamflows are at, or near, record low levels for this time of year across the Carolinas and Virginia as well.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Gulf Coast States">
   <p>Another dry week in southern Florida has led to the northward expansion of moderate drought (D1) out of the Lower Peninsula and into central Florida in and around the Orlando area, which continues to add on to its record dry start to the year. Most locations have only seen 25-50% of normal rains (6 to 9 inch deficits) on the year. This dryness has exacerbated the fire season there and has led to more than 2,400 fires (54,000 acres burned) for the year to date. Another bout of rains this week in the Florida Panhandle has led to the removal of moderate drought (D1) there.</p>
   <p>Along the rest of the Gulf Coast, beneficial rains continued to cut into the long-term deficits across southern Mississippi and Alabama, allowing for a slight easing of D0 conditions. Heavier rains in northern Louisiana also led to continued improvement, and an even larger area of non-drought is depicted there. The short-term relief is welcomed, but it hasnt been nearly enough to erase the dryness (25-50% of normal) that dates back to last fall.</p>
   <p>Many parts of Texas continue to feast on recent rains, leading to an incredible short-term turnaround from where they were just a month ago. Even the northern reaches of the core region of D3 and D4 in the south shared in the rains this past week, with a large area in and around San Antonio reporting anywhere from 2 to 5 inches or more. This, coupled with rains over the past 30 days and above-normal year-to-date totals (130-150% of normal or more), has led to notable improvements on this weeks map. The core areas of drought in the south (D1-D4) have all been pushed south, tightening the gradient between the haves and the have-nots in central and southern Texas. Not all have shared in these recent rains, though. Southern coastal areas continue to be blocked off from the moisture, and this had led to a slight expansion of D3 and D4 east and north along the Gulf Coast. Many points within the D4 area along the southern Texas Gulf Coast have seen less than 15% of their normal annual rains to date. For the Corpus Christi area, only the .80 inches recorded between January 1 and May 9, 2002, is drier than the .89 inches (11 % of normal) they have recorded through May 9 of this year (records here go back to 1887). This same degree of dryness is also found for many locations along the Lower Rio Grande Valley.</p>
   <p>In central Texas, where the heavy rains have fallen over the past month, it has led to a reduction of D1 and D2 drought and an erosion of the abnormally dry (D0) conditions found there. This holds true for both northern and western Texas as well where 1-category improvements continue to eat away at the drought in these regions. For many locations around San Antonio, the monthly totals received thus far have already made May the wettest month recorded since November of 2004, a string of 17 months. This follows right on the heels of the driest May-through-April 12-month period on record. Improvement is also noted in northern Texas along the border with Oklahoma and into the southern reaches of the Panhandle. The area has seen a general retreat of moderate (D1) and severe (D2) drought, leaving behind abnormally dry (D0) conditions and a readjustment of the Hydrological (H) Impact line in northern Texas. All of these recent rains are helping to ease the early pressure that was being put on local water supplies, but long-term deficits remain and will take time to recover fully, assuming that the rains continue.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Great Lakes">
   <p>Once again, Kansas, Oklahoma, southwestern Missouri, and northern Arkansas shared in the heavy rains that have persisted over the central and southern Plains over the past few weeks. Improvements are noted this week across much of this region, with a removal of severe drought (D2) and large cuts in the moderate drought (D1) across eastern Oklahoma, western Arkansas, and southwestern Missouri. Eastern Nebraska and eastern Kansas also saw a removal of abnormally dry conditions (D0) after the last series of rains brought annual totals above normal.  All of the short-term wetness has led to the entire region being under the Hydrological Impact (H) designation, given the short-term surplus and continued long-term dryness. The rains across eastern Missouri have also brought year-to-date totals up to normal levels, resulting in a reduction and removal of abnormally dry (D0) in some parts.</p>
   <p>Farther north, the High Plains continue to dry out. In particular, the Dakotas cant seem to shake the dryness on both the short- and long-term scales. Abnormally dry (D0) conditions have migrated more to the north and east in North Dakota this week in order to reflect this.</p>
   <p>In the Great Lakes region, dryness continues to persist in northern Wisconsin and northern Michigan, including the Upper Peninsula. Abnormally dry conditions (D0) and moderate drought (D1) continue to slowly advance to the east, and D0 has even shifted southward out of the U.P. and into northern Michigan. In Ohio, the dryness continues as well, especially in northern and eastern parts of the state where D0 has expanded westward and moderate drought (D1) has been introduced this week after a dry start to the spring has left many locales in northern Ohio around 50% of normal over the past 90 days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A bleak ending to the snow season has become a reality in the Southwest, where things actually never got going in the first place this past winter. Conditions continue to deteriorate over New Mexico and Arizona, with a large expansion of extreme drought (D3) across eastern New Mexico and central Arizona being depicted. Water Year-to-date precipitation totals are at or below 50% of normal across both states. The very beneficial prior water year has proven to be a much-needed buffer for them as water supplies (smaller bodies) were recharged quite nicely, which should help them cope with this recent winter drought until the monsoon season arrives later this summer.</p>
   <p>Farther north, persistent dryness has once again turned to moderate drought (D1) in northern Wyoming and southern Montana. Water Year snow water equivalent readings for basins from Yellowstone over to the Bighorn region are running at just 45-65% of normal as of May 8. The expansion of D1 stretches from northeast Wyoming westward and up into southern Montana.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Mark Svoboda</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
