<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000224</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 10 days (through March 4), a series of storm systems will continue to march across the Central States, dragging a series of trailing cold fronts through the region. Occasional showers and thunderstorms may provide drought relief from northeastern Texas to the Delta, while lighter amounts of precipitation will reach the Southeast. Dry weather is expected across Peninsular Florida, where additional areas may require an abnormally dry (D0) designation or experience drought intensification.</p>
   <p>A very active storm track during the next 10 days will provide locally heavy precipitation and additional drought relief to areas from the southeastern Plains to the Ohio Valley and much of the lower Midwest. Lighter precipitation is forecast across the western Corn Belt. Unfavorably dry conditions are forecast to persist, however, on the southern High Plains, where there are increasing concerns about a lack of soil moisture for winter grains and soon-to-be-planted summer crops. Meanwhile, wetness may aggravate lowland flooding in the Ohio Valley.</p>
   <p>A stormy pattern will continue during the next 10 days across most of the region. The most significant precipitation will fall from northern and central California eastward to the Wasatch Range, although locally heavy amounts are possible as far north as the Pacific Northwest. Although some additional precipitation is expected as far south as southern California and northern Arizona, the southern portions of Arizona and New Mexico are not expected to see appreciable relief from first-stage drought (agricultural and wildfire concerns).</p>
   <p>The primary storm track is expected to remain well north of Hawaii, resulting in little change in the agricultural drought affecting the aforementioned areas.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Hawaii's pattern of mostly dry weather with near- to below-normal temperatures continued for a fourth consecutive week. As a result, there has been little or no improvement in long-term agricultural drought (D1) during the last month across much of Molokai, Lanai, southwestern Maui, and western portions of the Big Island.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains and Midwest">
   <p>A major storm system crossed the region on February 18, capping a very wet period in the Ohio Valley. During the last 10 days, rainfall ranged from 2 to 7 inches in much of the Ohio and middle Mississippi Valleys, resulting in drought reduction or elimination. Varying degrees of drought linger both north and south of the Ohio Valley, with a pocket of severe drought (D2) in an area centered on northeastern Indiana. Farther west, a larger area of severe drought (D2) remains intact across the western Corn Belt (eastern Nebraska, western Iowa, southeastern South Dakota, and southwestern Minnesota), despite recent, generally light precipitation, including some rainfall on February 23.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South-Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>During the last 10 days, several low-pressure systems passed north of the region, resulting in episodes of showery precipitation and occasional severe weather. Significant precipitation largely bypassed the south-central U.S., however, leaving a large core area of severe drought (D2) intact across the central one-third of Texas, much of Louisiana, and into western and northern Mississippi. In addition, temperatures in the D2 area averaged at least 10 degrees F above normal, contributing to additional evaporative losses. Although temperatures were also well above normal in the Southeast, rainfall generally ranged from 1 to 2 inches, with locally higher totals, across first-stage to severe drought areas (D1 and D2) in western Florida and southern Georgia. Significant rainfall (1 to 4 inches) was also observed in drought areas (mostly D1) of the southern Appalachians and Tennessee Valley.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>Continuing a six-week trend, storm systems have been moving ashore across northern and central California. The water equivalent of the high-elevation Sierra Nevada snow pack is approaching normal following the abysmal start to the wet season through early January. The most significant moisture of the season spread into southern California on February 21 and 23. Farther east, however, soil moisture remained limited and high-elevation snow packs continued to lag normal across the Southwest, particularly in Arizona and New Mexico, despite limited improvement in recent days. Although first-stage drought (D1) remains a problem for dryland agriculture and has increased the risk of wildfires in southern portions of Arizona and New Mexico, the Southwest's hydrological situation is not yet a significant concern.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
