<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000406</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>April 5 - 10 should bring moderate rainfall to parts of Tennessee and the southern Appalachians. However, most other areas are expected to measure less than half an inch, with totals below 0.25 inch anticipated along the southern and western tiers of the region. The ensuing 5 days (April 11 - 15) are forecast to be wetter than normal from the lower central Plains southeastward into the northwestern lower Mississippi Valley, but near- or below-normal precipitation is anticipated elsewhere, especially near the Atlantic Seaboard and in the southwestern half of Texas. In many of these areas, unseasonable warmth is also anticipated, additionally stressing many of the drought regions.</p>
   <p>Substantial rains (over 1 inch) could benefit the southeastern half of the Great Lakes region, the northeastern Corn Belt, and much of Indiana and western Ohio during April 5 - 10. At least 0.25 inch is anticipated in most of the other dry areas, which should not allow for either marked improvement nor deterioration. During April 11 - 15, unseasonable warmth is expected in areas south and west of central Illinois, and surplus rains should be limited to the southwestern fringes of the region, keeping drought conditions intact.</p>
   <p>April 5 - 10 could bring some much-needed rains (over 0.25 inch) to parts of western Texas, but seasonably-typical dryness should prevail farther west, and abnormally warm weather is expected throughout the region. Temperatures are expected to return to near normal during the ensuing 5 days (April 11 - 15), but unfavorably dry weather is expected to persist.</p>
   <p>A wetter weather pattern may be setting up for the state of Hawaii, though substantial reductions in long-term rainfall deficits are unlikely in the near future. Meanwhile, Puerto Rico is transitioning towards its wetter time of year (summer and autumn), so a substantial increase in rainfall during the next few months will be needed for the region to avoid deteriorating dryness.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, Puerto Rico, and Guam">
   <p>Substantial rains covered large sections of Hawaii during March 29 - April 4, with scattered totals of 4 to 6 inches reported. These rains were sufficient to eliminate last week's D0 conditions in eastern parts of the Big Island and windward sections of both Kauai and Oahu. Meanwhile, locally moderate rains in Puerto Rico were not sufficient to eliminate D0 conditions along the northern tier of the island. San Juan, PR recorded about 4.4 inches of rain since January 1, which is approximately 3.4 inches below normal. In Guam, about 3 inches of surplus rainfall were recorded since the start of February. However, late winter and early spring are typically dry compared to other times of the year (particularly autumn), and rainfall totals since August 1999 remained more than 15 inches below normal (about 75% of normal) through early April.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Plains, Midwest, and Central Appalachians">
   <p>Drought conditions remained unchanged or worsened in most of these areas during March 29 - April 4. Most locations from the eastern Corn Belt and the central Great Lakes region westward to the High Plains and northward to near the Canadian border recorded lass than 0.2 inch of precipitation in the last 7 days, with totals of 0.6 to 2.0 inches restricted to the eastern fringes of the region. As a result, D1 conditions expanded northward through the southern Great Lakes region, and D2 conditions became more widespread across the Corn Belt and the lower northern Great Plains. As March ended, NASS reported that a majority of Nebraska was experiencing short or very short moisture in both topsoil (53%) and subsoil (72%).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and Western States">
   <p>Seasonably-increasing normals and evaporation rates prompted the expansion of D0 conditions into part of interior western Montana despite locally moderate precipitation. Some of this area received little more than half of normal precipitation for the October through March period. Farther south, D0 to D2 conditions remained unchanged in Arizona and New Mexico.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The South-Central and Southeastern States">
   <p>A wet week along the northern tier of this region abetted significant drought relief. At least 3 inches of rain fell during the 7-day period ending April 4 on most locations from far eastern Texas northeastward through the southern Appalachians, with 5 to locally 9 inches dousing a broad swath encompassing northern Louisiana, southeastern Arkansas, central and northern Mississippi, northern Alabama, and adjacent sections of Tennessee and Georgia. In addition, 3 to 6 inches of rain fell on part of upper southern Georgia, and highly localized but intense thunderstorms dropped as much as a foot of rain on areas near and just west of Daytona Beach, FL. Because of these rains, D2 (severe drought) conditions were reduced to D1 (first-stage drought) in central Mississippi, upper south-central Georgia, and part of east-central Florida while D1 conditions improved to D0 (abnormally dry) in the northern lower Mississippi Valley, eastern Tennessee, and parts of the southern Appalachians. Also, D0 and D1 conditions improved in and just south of the Texas Panhandle.</p>
   <p>Across most of central and upper southwestern Florida, however, subnormal rainfall and seasonally-increasing evaporation rates induced deterioration to D2 conditions. As of March 31, short or very short topsoil and subsoil moisture covered about 90% of the state, according to the National Agricultural Statistics Service (NASS). Farther north, persistent subnormal rains for the last several weeks allowed D1 conditions to develop in part of northern Arkansas while D0 conditions expanded slightly into southwest Oklahoma and areas near the Mississippi/Ohio Rivers' confluence.</p>
   <p>From the beginning of the calendar year through April 5, nearly 590,000 acres had been consumed by wildfires nationally, 50% more than the average for the same periods in 1996-1999, according to the National Interagency Coordination Center. Of this year's acreage consumed to date, almost 90% was located across the southern tier of states.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
