<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20041202</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather conditions potentially having an impact on the areas of dryness or drought over the next 2 weeks include: 1) little precipitation but continued cold weather across the interior West during the first week of December contrasting with unseasonable mildness over the Upper Midwest; 2) a storm bringing heavy rain and snow to the Midwest on December 6-7 followed by much colder weather in the Plains states; 3) generally low temperatures and below-normal precipitation for the West and High Plains during the next 2 weeks</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii and Alaska">
   <p>In Alaska, the D0 persisted in the eastern interior basin as generally light precipitation fell. In contrast, up to several inches of rain in windward areas of Maui and the Big Island reduced the D0 area on the latter island and eliminated D0 on Maui. Locally dry conditions, however, persisted over western Maui.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The East">
   <p>One to two inches or more of soaking rains ended dryness in northern New England and upstate New York. To the south, amounts ranging up to 1 inch or more eliminated the D0 area in southern South Carolina, although scattered rainfall deficits persisted near the coast, where monthly rainfall totaled less than 1 inch. Although November was unusually dry in southern Florida, with Miami recording only 0.34 inches of rain, the extent or severity of the moisture deficits did not yet warrant development of D0 dryness.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Great Plains">
   <p>Precipitation ranging from 0.5 to over 1 inch brought some dryness relief to the Great Lakes region. The moisture, some of which fell as snow, eliminated the D1 drought areas in southeastern Wisconsin and eastern Michigan and the D0 area in the Upper Peninsula of Michigan, while reducing the D0 area in southern Michigan. Although snow fell across northern Kansas, southern Nebraska, and southwestern Iowa, the moisture was not enough to end the D0 dryness there. Precipitation was mostly light over the D1 and D2 drought area extending from western North Dakota into northwestern Kansas, resulting in no change in the drought intensity. November was quite dry across the Upper Midwest, with International Falls, Minnesota picking up only 0.31 inches of precipitation.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The West">
   <p>A storm tracked across the region during November 27-28, bringing snow from California eastward to the Rockies. Four to 11 inches of snow covered Reno, Nevada, and up to 1 to 2 feet fell in Utah. Snowbird in Utahs Wasatch range measured a 63-inch snow depth at an elevation of 9600 feet on December 1, an weekly increase of 20 inches. Cheyenne, Wyoming notched a daily record snowfall of 9.7 inches on the 28 th. As a result of the recent snows and the improved streamflows, drought improved by one category to D2 in much of eastern Utah, while the D1 area continued to shrink in southern and central Utah. D1 also receded in east-central Nevada, where the river basin snowpack reached nearly 350 percent of normal. The area of D3 also diminished in western and southern Nevada, while D1 and D0 retreated slightly in western Colorado. The area of D3 decreased in southwestern Wyoming. D2 drought retracted slightly in northwestern Arizona. Although increased snows in the mountains of south-central Montana contributed to some reduction of the D3 area, November was generally a dry month in the state, and overall snowpack continued below normal. Great Falls measured just 0.16 inches of precipitation for the month. Cold weather settled over the West on the 29 th and 30th, and subzero temperatures were common across Colorado and Wyoming.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Douglas Le Comte</name>
   <affiliation>NOAA, CPC</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
