<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20050317</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>Weather features to watch in the next 10-day period that may affect areas experiencing dryness or drought across the country include: 1) a storm system has brought beneficial precipitation to the new D0 areas along the Gulf Coast March 15-16, and will continue to bring precipitation to Florida March 17; 2) a winter storm moving across the northern United States has led to dust storm warnings for the Columbia River Basin in Washington March 16, and will bring heavy snows to the northern Rockies, northern Plains and Great Lakes March 17-19; 3) precipitation will return to the West Coast March 18-21, while another system will bring precipitation to the Gulf Coast and Southeast during the same time period; 4) above-normal precipitation remains a possibility for both the West Coast and the Southeast for the March 22-26 period.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Puerto Rico">
   <p>Continued dryness across Puerto Rico has led to the introduction of Moderate Drought (D1) to the southern and southeastern parts of the island. Reservoir and streamflow levels have fallen in the affected areas, and the number of brushfires has increased significantly in some locations.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Midwest and Plains">
   <p>The past week was generally dry across all the Midwest and Plains. The Alberta Clipper that carried strong winds into the region March 10-11 only provided light amounts of snow for the D0 areas in Minnesota and South Dakota. No changes were made to the drought or dryness areas in this region.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Rockies and The West">
   <p>In the Pacific Northwest, the past week again featured above-normal temperatures and below-normal precipitation. Some light precipitation did occur across the Rockies in Montana, Wyoming, and Colorado. In response to the developing drought event, Governor Christine Gregoire of Washington announced a statewide drought emergency on March 10, setting in motion a variety of activities and resources to help the state cope with the impending impacts. In Idaho, the exceptional drought (D4) category was expanded to cover more of the Bear Lake area, the Snake River Plain, and the Big and Little Lost River Basins. The D3 areas along both the Lower and Upper Snake River Plain and across central Idaho were also expanded. Projected streamflows into the summer months along the lower Snake River are estimated to be approximately 30 percent of normal. In Montana, deteriorating conditions led to expansion of the D3 in the central and western parts of the state. Surface Water Supply Index (SWSI) values are in the extremely dry category for the majority of river basins in these areas. Deteriorating conditions also led to an expansion of D2 into central Oregon, as well as expansion to the D2, D1, and D0 areas around the Klamath Basin in southern Oregon and northern California. As a result of the conditions in this region, Governor Ted Kulongoski of Oregon announced a state of drought emergency for Klamath County, making state and federal aid available for farmers and ranchers if water supplies are limited this summer. Meanwhile, in New Mexico, a major snowstorm March 14-15 provided beneficial moisture to the northern, central, and eastern parts of the state. The area of extreme drought (D3) in north-central New Mexico was improved to D2. Long-term precipitation deficits remain in this region, with three-year deficits of 12-20 inches for the Las Vegas, Santa Fe, and Los Alamos areas.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="The Southeast and Texas">
   <p>For the most part, the past week continued to be dry across the Southeast and the D0 areas in Texas. Because of increasing precipitation deficits since last fall, and additional indicators such as low streamflow levels, D0 was introduced into two areas: southern Mississippi and southeast Alabama. Beneficial precipitation moved into these two new D0 areas on Tuesday, March 15, but after the morning deadline. Meanwhile, heavier rains did fall across parts of southern Florida early in the week. West Palm Beach set a daily record with a rainfall total of 3.15 inches on March 9, and totals greater than 1.50 inches were common in this region. Some heavier rains also fell in northeastern North Carolina, although the weekly total was only 0.41 inches in Elizabeth City, so the abnormally dry area in the Carolinas was not changed.</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Michael Hayes</name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
