<Results>
 <week>
  <date>20000713</date>
  <disclaimer>The discussion in the Looking Ahead section is simply a description of what the official national guidance from the National Weather Service (NWS) National Centers for Environmental Prediction is depicting for current areas of dryness and drought. The NWS forecast products utilized include the HPC 5-day QPF and 5-day Mean Temperature progs, the 6-10 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, and the 8-14 Day Outlooks of Temperature and Precipitation Probability, valid as of late Wednesday afternoon of the USDM release week. The NWS forecast web page used for this section is: https://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/forecasts/.</disclaimer>  <forecast>
   <p>During the next 2 weeks, several potential weather features could impact current drought areas, including: 1) Frequent thunderstorms and heavy rainfall for at least the next several days in the Southeast, especially the eastern portions of the dry area; 2) Hot and dry conditions in much of the central and southern Plains which could last through the period, especially in Texas; 3) Average to above-average monsoon thunderstorm activity in the Southwest; and 4) Increasing rainfall in the southern two-thirds of Alaska.</p>
  </forecast>
  <region name="Hawaii, Alaska, and Puerto Rico">
   <p>Another week with scattered light rainfall kept abnormal dryness across most of the southern half of Alaska, where a few locations reported 4+ inches less rain than normal during April 1 - July 10.</p>
   <p>In Hawaii, moderate windward rainfall that began in June continued through last week, easing former D0 conditions. However, only light, scattered leeward rainfall was reported, keeping D1 to D3 conditions unchanged.</p>
   <p>D0 conditions persisted over northern and western Puerto Rico. At San Juan, less than 14 inches of rain fell during the last 218 days (December 7 - July 11), compared to a normal of almost 25 inches.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Midwest">
   <p>Copious rainfall caused drought conditions to continue eroding in most of the central United States. Most dryness- and drought-impacted areas from central Nebraska and north-central Kansas eastward received at least an inch of rain in the last 7 days, with more than 3 inches recorded in parts of central and eastern Nebraska. As a result, severe drought (D2) was reduced to first-stage drought (D1) in western Iowa and eastern Nebraska; abnormal dryness (D0) eased in central Iowa; and conditions improved to abnormally dry (D0) in southeastern Nebraska. In addition, moderate rains improved conditions to D1 in part of northwest Kansas.</p>
   <p>Despite generally improving conditions, there were a few areas that missed the bulk of last week's rainfall. Hot and relatively dry weather kept extreme drought (D3) intact across southwestern Nebraska, and allowed D1 conditions to expand into most of northeastern Colorado and northwestern Iowa. As last week ended, substantial proportions of many Nebraska crops remained in poor or very poor condition, including oats (42%), sorghum (23%), and corn (20%), according to the National Agricultural Statistics Service. Furthermore, much of several states' pastures and rangelands were in poor or very poor condition, including Nebraska (57%), Colorado (36%), and Missouri (28%).</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Southeastern States">
   <p>A drought of historic proportions continued affecting many areas. Only southern Louisiana and southern Florida reported widespread 7-day rainfall totals approaching or exceeding an inch. This allowed D0 conditions in southern Florida to ease for the time being, but drought intensification was noted across the rest of the Southeast. Exceptional drought (D4) expanded into most of central and southwestern Georgia and southern Alabama, and the D0 to D3 conditions observed from northern Georgia and central Alabama northwestward toward the Ohio and Mississippi Rivers' confluence represented a one-category deterioration for most locations. Rainfall totals 7 or more inches below normal for the last 90 days were reported from central Georgia westward into central and eastern Alabama.</p>
   <p>As a result, streamflows in the Southeast dropped to precipitously low levels, and crop conditions declined markedly in many regions. In Alabama, about 30% of cotton and 62% of peanuts were in poor or very poor condition, an increase of 21% from the prior week's peanut crop condition. Georgia reported 32% of cotton and 26% of peanuts in poor or very poor condition while 19% of Louisiana rice was similarly rated. In addition, large proportions of several states' pastures were in poor or very poor conditions, including Georgia (55%), South Carolina (48%), and Alabama (48%). For the 5 southeastern most states (AL, GA, FL, MS, SC) as a unit, 76% of streamflow sites reporting to the U. S. Geological Survey (USGS) were within the lowest 10% of their historical observations for July 12, and 36% established new daily record lows.</p>
   <p>Farther west, hot and dry weather allowed D0 conditions to increase in coverage across central and southeastern Texas. Much of this region recorded 1 to locally 4 inches less rainfall than normal over the last 30 days.</p>
  </region>
  <region name="Western States">
   <p>Patchy areas from the far southern Rockies and High Plains northward through eastern Idaho and Montana received 0.2 to locally 2.0 inches of rain during the last 7 days, but these were generally too light and spotty to provide any widespread, substantial relief. In fact, continued heat and dryness caused D1 conditions to expand into parts of central Idaho, southwestern Colorado, and southeastern Utah. Moderate rains were a bit more widespread in the eastern half of Montana and southern sections of Arizona and New Mexico, but only a small section of northeastern Montana improved by one category (D1 to D0 or D0 to nothing).</p>
  </region>
  <author>
   <name>Staff </name>
   <affiliation>National Drought Mitigation Center</affiliation>
  </author>
 </week>
</Results>
